<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-IDENT-1162" status="released">
    <persName>
        <forename>Anne</forename>
        <forename>Jane</forename>
        <choice>
            <seg><surname notBefore="1839" notAfter="1858">Douglas</surname></seg>
            <seg><surname notBefore="1858" notAfter="1898">Cupples</surname></seg>
        </choice>
    </persName>
    
    <note type="dates"><date>1839–98</date></note>
    <sex value="F"/>
    <note type="biography">
        <p>Scottish author. Second daughter of Archibald Douglas. Married George Cupples in 1858. Wrote children’s books. Lived in New Zealand from 1891.</p></note>
    <note type="further">
            <p><hi rend="bold">Further Information:</hi></p> 
            <p>Anne Jane Cupples (1839-1898) was a writer and the wife of Scottish writer and dog breeder George Cupples. Charles Darwin praised her writing, energy and role as populariser of science and champion of good feeling towards animals. In November 1870, Anne Cupples asked Darwin to write in support of a Government pension for her husband. In 1870 Darwin wrote to Alexander Strahan to back an application for financial support that Cupples had submitted. In November [1872] Anne Cupples provided Darwin with accounts of the expressions of dogs that howl to music. In 1877 Darwin wrote to the Literary Fund in support of Cupples’ work and to confirm her need.</p> 
            <p><hi rend="bold">Additional Gender Resources:</hi></p> 
            <p><ref target="http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/women-and-science" type="hyperlink">http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/women-and-science</ref></p> 
            <p><ref target="http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/womens-scientific-participation" type="hyperlink">http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/womens-scientific-participation</ref></p> 
            <p><ref target="http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/gender-and-scientific-participation" type="hyperlink">http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/gender-and-scientific-participation</ref></p> 
            <p><ref target="http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/scientists-wives" type="hyperlink">http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/scientists-wives</ref></p>   
            <p><hi rend="bold">Primary Sources:</hi></p> 
            <p><hi rend="bold">Letters:</hi></p> 
            <p>Darwin Correspondence Database, http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/entry-7053</p> 
            <p>Darwin Correspondence Database, http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/entry-8611</p> 
            <p>Darwin Correspondence Database, http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/entry-10764f</p> 
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cupples’ books:</hi></p> 
            <p>Cupples, Anne Jane. <hi rend="italic">Our Sailmaker’s Yarn</hi>. By Mrs. G. Cupples; and other stories of the sea, by popular authors. Edinburgh : W. P. Nimmo, Hay, &amp; Mitchell, 1889.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, Anne Jane. <hi rend="italic">Little Miss Matty: a tale of the sea</hi>. London: Hodder &amp; Stoughton, 1886.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, Anne Jane.<hi rend="italic">A Knitting-Book of Counterpanes: toilet-covers, pin-cushions, and other articles of fancy work.</hi> Edinburgh : Johnstone, Hunter &amp; Co., 1871.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, Anne Jane. <hi rend="italic">Vea and her Cousins; or, Kind words awaken kind echoes. A tale for the young.</hi> London : T. Nelson &amp; Sons, 1872.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, Anne Jane.<hi rend="italic">A Book about House Work. A convenient manual for mistresses and maids, etc.</hi> London: Simpkin, 1877.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, Anne Jane. <hi rend="italic">Terrapin Island; or, Adventures with the “Gleam."</hi> Edinburgh; London: Gall &amp; Inglis, [1876].</p> 
            <p>Cupples, George, Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Tappy’s chicks: and other links between nature and human nature</hi>. London: Strahan &amp; Co., Publishers, 1872.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, George, Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Singular creatures, and how they were found: being stories and studies from the domestic zoölogy of a Scotch parish</hi>. Boston, Mass.: Lee and Shepard, 1872.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, George, Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Shadows on the screen, or, an evening with the children</hi>. London: T. Nelson &amp; Sons, 1883.</p> 
            <p>Cupples, George. <hi rend="italic">Scotch deer-hounds and their masters</hi>, edited by Mrs George Cupples. Edinburgh and London, W. Blackwood and Sons, 1894.</p>
    </note>
    <note type="sources">
        <p><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Modern English biography</hi></ref>.</p>
    </note>
    <note type="volume">16,17,18,19,20,21,23,25,WSL,26,30</note>
    <note type="keywords">
        <term type="name">Cupples, George</term>
        <term type="l">Writer</term>
    </note>
</person>