<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8114">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   21 December 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5293</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8114 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8114.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8114.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 56</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 56</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1871-12-21">21 Dec 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on <hi rend="italic">Die Kalkschwämme</hi> [1872].</p> 
            <p>A Franciscan prior, Padre Buona-Grazia, agrees with human descent.</p>
            <p>His trip to Dalmatia.</p> 
<p>German reception of <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Mentions current work.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die Kalkschwamme</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Buona-Grazia</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Franciscan prior</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Dalmatia</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1872</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00231_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00231_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="56:1r" xml:id="i231">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00231.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00231_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00231.dzi" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="56:1v" xml:id="i232">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00232.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00232_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00232.dzi" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="56:2r" xml:id="i233">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00233.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00233_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00233.dzi" width="3885px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="56:2v" xml:id="i234">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00234.jpg" width="3940px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00234_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3940px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00234.dzi" width="3940px" height="6386px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>21. Dec 1871</date>
                    <salute>Mein theurer, hochverehrter Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ehe das Jahr 1871 zu Ende geht—das Jahr, in welchem der “Descent of man” erschien!—muss ich Ihnen nothwendig noch einen herzlichen Gruss, und einen besten Glückwunsch für das folgende Jahr schicken. Möge Ihnen 1872 frische Gesundheit und neue Kraft zu neuen bahn brechenden Werken schicken! Ich habe mich in diesem Jahre <hi rend="underline">jeden Tag</hi> mit Ihnen viel beschäftigt, da meine “Monographie der Kalkschwae” die mich fast ausschliesslich beherrscht hat, den “<hi rend="underline">Darwinismus</hi>” und namentlich die beiden Fundamental-Probleme der <hi rend="underline">Erblichkeit</hi> und <hi rend="underline">Veränderlichkeit</hi> überall zur Basis hat.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich habe versucht, die ganze Frage jetzt einmal nicht synthetisch—wie bisher—sondern <hi rend="underline">analytisch</hi> zu behandeln, und im Einzelnen durch Unmassen von Thatsachen den gemeinsamen Ursprung aller Arten einer Gruppe zu beweisen. Die Spongien, und vorzüglich die Calcispongien sind die “most Darwinistic animals” unter allen Wesen, welche ich kenne, und die Erscheinungen der Vererbung und Anpassung lassen sich leichter verfolgen und im einzelnen sicher erkennen, als es sonst wohl möglich ist.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Da das Buch von 60 Tafeln begleitet ist, wird es erst im Sommer oder Herbst des nächsten Jahres erscheinen. Jetzt wird daran schon eifrig gedruckt. Ich hoffe dass es Ihnen viel Freude machen wird.</p>
<p>Das Material für diese Spongien-Arbeit habe ich grösstentheils selbst in Norwegen und Dalmatia gesaelt, vorzüglich auf der Insel <hi rend="underline">Lesina</hi> (im südlichen Dalmatia) wo ich im Frühling einen wundervollen Monat in einem <hi rend="underline">Franciscaner Kloster</hi>(!) verlebt habe.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Nun hören Sie! Der Prior dieses Klosters, Padre Buona-Grazia, ist ein begeisteter Darwinist! Ein Verehrer und Kenner von Goethes Werken und Darwins “Origin of Species”!<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Ehe noch mein Fuss die Insel betreten hatte, ehe noch unsere Barke gelandet war, stand schon der Prior am Ufer und rief mir entgegen: “Nicht wahr, Herr Professor, <hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi> hat Recht, und wir stammen <hi rend="underline">Alle</hi> von einem und demselben <hi rend="underline">Catarrhinen-Affen</hi> ab!! So ist gewiss noch niemals ein Naturforscher in einem <hi rend="underline">Katholischen Kloster</hi> aufgenommen worden.—</p>
<p>Leider haben später die Jesuiten von der Haeresie des Padre gehört und ihn in Rom beim Papste verklagt: “er habe affengläubige Ketzer im Kloster aufgenoen und dasselbe entheiligt”. Der arme Prior sollte ausgetrieben und womöglich eingekerkert werden. Da er jedoch eine sehr beliebte und geachtete Persönlichkeit und zugleich der unentbehrliche Schullehrer der Insel ist, wird man wohl nicht wagen, ihm zu Leibe zu gehen.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Ist diese Geschichte nicht kostbar? Meine Reise in Dalmatien (Ragusa etc) und Montenegro war auch sonst sehr interessant. Auch ein Stück Türkei (bei Skutari) habe ich besucht.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Die Spongien Ausbeute war sehr reich.</p>
<p>Von dem <hi rend="underline">colossalen</hi> Erfolge, den Ihr Werk “Descent of man and sexual selection” auch bei uns in Deutschland gehabt hat, haben Sie sicher bereits gehört. Fast jede Zeitschrift hat das Buch besprochen, die meisten allerdings ohne jeden Verstand!<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Wie lange wird es dauern, ehe die Menschen die <hi rend="underline">einfachsten</hi> Dinge begreifen lernen! Wie sehr ich mich über das Buch im Ganzen und in allem Einzeln gefreut habe, brauche ich Ihnen nicht erst zu sagen.</p>
<p>Mir geht es gut. Nur habe ich jetzt <hi rend="underline">zu Viel</hi> zu thun! Ausser dem Schreiben und Drucken der Spongien auch noch die III. Aufl. der “Schöpfungsgeschichte”<ref target="#foot.f9"/>— und dann—<hi rend="underline">leider</hi>—die <hi rend="underline">Geschäfte</hi> als <hi rend="underline">Decan</hi> (Dean) unserer philosoph. Facultaet (ein schreckliches Amt)—</p>
<p>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen und den besten Wünschen für das neue Jahr 1872 | Ihr treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>21 December 1871</date>
                    <salute>My dear, most esteemed friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Before the year 1871 draws to a close—the year that saw the appearance of the “Descent of Man”!—I absolutely must send you my cordial greetings and my best wishes for the year to come. May 1872 bring you fresh health and new strength for yet more pioneering work! <hi rend="underline">Every day</hi> this year I have been preoccupied with you, since my “Monographie der Kalkschwämme”, which has dominated my attention almost exclusively, is based on “<hi rend="underline">Darwinism</hi>” throughout, in particular on the two fundamental problems of <hi rend="underline">heritability</hi> and <hi rend="underline">variability</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Now, for a change, I have tried to treat the entire question not synthetically—as before—but <hi rend="underline">analytically</hi>, and to demonstrate the common origin of all species of a group in detail through a vast quantity of facts. Sponges, and particularly the Calcispongiae, are the “most Darwinistic animals” of all beings that I know of, and in this group the phenomena of inheritance and adaptation can be more easily traced and more clearly recognised in detail than is commonly the case.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> As the book is accompanied by 60 plates, it will only appear in the summer or autumn of next year. At the moment it is already in press. I hope that you will be very pleased with it.</p>
<p>The material for this work on sponges I have for the most part collected myself in Norway and in Dalmatia, mainly on the island of <hi rend="underline">Lesina</hi> (in southern Dalmatia), where I spent a wonderful month in a <hi rend="underline">Franciscan monastery</hi>(!) last spring.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Now listen to this! The prior of that monastery, Father Buona Grazia, is an enthusiastic Darwinist! An admirer of and expert on Goethe’s work and on Darwin’s “Origin of Species”!<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Before my foot had touched the island, before our bark had landed, the prior was already standing at the shore and crying out to me: “<hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi> is right, isn’t he, professor, and we are <hi rend="underline">all</hi> of us descended from one and the same <hi rend="underline">catarrhine monkey</hi>!! Surely a scientist has never yet been received in this manner in a <hi rend="underline">Catholic monastery</hi>.—</p>
<p>Unfortunately the Jesuits later heard about the father’s heresy and reported him to the pope in Rome: “he has received ape-believing heretics in the monastery and thus desecrated it”. The poor prior ought to be expelled and possibly incarcerated. Since, however, he is a very popular and respected personality, and also the indispensable schoolmaster of the island, I’m sure they won’t dare attack him.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Isn’t this story priceless? My travels in Dalmatia (Ragusa etc) and Montenegro were very interesting also in other respects. I even visited a part of Turkey (near Scutari).<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The yield of sponges was very rich.</p>
<p>You have certainly already heard of the <hi rend="underline">colossal</hi> success that your work “Descent of man and sexual selection” has had with us in Germany. Almost every journal here has reviewed it, albeit without any understanding!<ref target="#foot.f8"/> How long will it be, I wonder, before people begin to grasp the <hi rend="underline">simplest</hi> things! How delighted I was about the book as a whole and in every detail I need hardly mention.</p>
<p>I am well. Only I now have <hi rend="underline">too Much</hi> to do! Apart from writing and publishing the sponges, there is the III ed. of the “Schöpfungsgeschichte”<ref target="#foot.f9"/>—and then—<hi rend="underline">unfortunately</hi>—the <hi rend="underline">duties</hi> as <hi rend="underline">decan</hi> (dean) of our philosophical faculty (a dreadful office)—</p>
<p>With my most cordial greetings and the best wishes for the new year 1872 | Yours most faithfully | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> was published in February 1871. Haeckel’s monograph on calcareous sponges (Haeckel 1872a) was published in December 1872 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8669.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 10 December 1872</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haeckel relied on embryology in his classification of sponges. He emphasised the similarity of the early embryonic stages of the entire group, and noted similarities in development to other groups. He argued that divergent forms of development only occurred after what he termed the ‘Gastrula’ (gut-forming) stage and concluded that this was extraordinarily important for the general phylogeny of the animal kingdom (Haeckel 1872a, 1: 333–4). Haeckel inferred that a hypothetical ancestor, ‘Gastraea’, was the progenitor of most major divisions of the animal kingdom and created a genealogical tree in which he gave phylogenetic equivalents of developmental stages (for example, Gastraea corresponds to Gastrula; Haeckel 1872a, 1: 465). For more on the significance of Haeckel 1872a, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Di Gregorio 2005</ref>, pp. 203–17, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">S. J. Gould 1977</ref>, pp. 170–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lesina was the Italian name for the Croatian city of Hvar on the island of the same name in the Adriatic Sea off the Dalmatian coast. The Franciscan church and monastery were built in the fifteenth century (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bonagracija Marojević</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Marojević was head of the state school (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Velnić 1969</ref>). Marojević had written to Haeckel on 7 July 1871, telling him about his censure by the Vatican (Archiv, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref> Haus, Friedrich Schiller Universität, Jena).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Ragusa was the Italian name for the city of Dubrovnik (Croatia). The region (now country) of Montenegro was technically part of the Ottoman Empire until 1878, although its independence had been recognised by the Ottomans since 1799. Scutari is now the Albanian city of Shkodër (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">For the German reviews of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> in CD’s collection of reviews, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix V.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Haeckel refers to the third edition of his book of lectures on the natural history of creation, <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Haeckel 1872b).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>