<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12559">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. H. Schneider<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   2 April 1880</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10640</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12559 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12559.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12559.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="28">28</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 59</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 59</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4227.xml">Schneider, G. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1880-04-02">2 Apr 1880</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes studies with Ernst Haeckel</p>
            <p>and research on psychology of lower animals.</p> 
<p>Sends book [<hi rend="italic">Der thierische Wille</hi> (1880)] and describes his views on the subject.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Der thierische Wille</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2048">Haeckel, E. P. A.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Schneider, G. H. 1880</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-11-14" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-02-22" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2019-03-11" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-06-04" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2019-06-04" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00243_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00243_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="59:1r" xml:id="i243">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00243.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00243_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00243.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:1v" xml:id="i244">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00244.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00244_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00244.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:2r" xml:id="i245">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00245.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00245_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00245.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:2v" xml:id="i246">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00246.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00246_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00246.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:3r" xml:id="i247">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00247.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00247_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00247.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:3v" xml:id="i248">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00248.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00248_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00248.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:4r" xml:id="i249">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00249.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00249_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00249.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="59:4v" xml:id="i250">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00250.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00250_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00250.dzi" width="4009px" height="6539px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Leipzig,</placeName>
                    <date>d. 2. April 1880.</date>
                    <salute>Hochzuverehrender | Hochgeehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Als ich im Jahre 1870 in Jena Naturwissenschaften, insbesondere Zoologie bei Herrn Professor Haeckel<ref target="#foot.f2"/> studirte, erweckte die Descendenz- und Selectionstheorie ein ungemeines Interesse in mir. Ich sah sofort, dass diese Entwickelungsprinzipien für die psychischen Erscheinungen mindestens dieselbe Bedeutung haben müssten als für die morphologischen und beschloss sofort dem Studium der psychischen Phänomene vom Standpuncte der Descendenz- und Selectionstheorie aus mein Leben zu widmen.</p>
<p>Mein lebhaftes Interesse insbesondere für das von Ihnen entdeckte allgewaltige Lebensprinzip der natürlichen Auswahl im Kampfe ums Dasein gewann mir das Wohlwollen und die Sympathie des grossen Jenenser Zoologen, der nun meine Bestrebungen allseitig freundlichst unterstützte. Leider haben mich Nahrungssorgen jahrelang vielfach von meinen Arbeiten abgehalten. Nachdem ich nun aber fünf Jahre in Neapel gelebt und theils in dem Aquarium der zoologischen Station, theils in meinem kleinen Privataquarium Beobachtungen über die Willensäusserungen der niederen Thiere gemacht und mehrere kleinere Arbeiten theils als Broschüren, theils in wissenschaftlichen und populären Journalen veröffentlicht habe, bin ich nun endlich so glücklich Ihnen ein Exemplar meiner ersten grösseren Arbeit: “Der thierische Wille” ergebenst einschicken zu können.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Damit ich einen Verleger dafür gewinnen konnte, musste ich freilich den Stoff zum grössten Theile in populärer Form bringen und die allgemeinen Erörterungen, in welchen der wissenschaftliche Werth liegt, auf ein geringes Maass beschränken. Beurtheilen Sie also gütigst das Buch mit Nachsicht.</p>
                    <p>Ich denke, ich habe das Problem des thierischen Willens <hi rend="underline">ganz in</hi> <hi rend="underline">Ihrem Sinne aufgefasst</hi>, indem ich, gestützt auf Ihre grossartigen und klassischen Untersuchungen, alle instinctiven Triebe wie alles zweckbewusste Wollen, resp. die Entstehung und Entwickelung desselben aus der Selection und aus successiven und simultanen Associationen erkläre.</p>
                    <p>Das Material über thierische Willensäusserungen habe ich systematisch geordnet, die Gewohnheiten zum Nahrungserwerb, zum Schutze, zur Begattung und zur Pflege der Nachkommenschaft zusammengestellt und sie nach ihrer psychologischen Werthigkeit eingetheilt:</p>
<p>1; in solche, welche auf Grund eines subjectiven oder durch unmittelbare Berührung hervorgerufenen objectiven Zustandes (Bewegungen auf Grund von <hi rend="underline">Empfindungstrieben</hi>) erfolgen, 2, in solche, welche durch Wahrnehmungen der Objecte aus der Entfernung beruhen (<hi rend="underline">Wahrnehmungstriebe</hi>) und 3, in solche, die auf einfachen Reproductionen der Wahrnehmungen oder auf Vorstellungsverbindungen beruhen (<hi rend="underline">Vorstellungs- und Gedankentriebe</hi>); und von diesen Erkenntnisstrieben habe ich noch zwei allein auf Bewegungsassociationen beruhende Hilfstriebe (Folgetrieb und Associationstrieb) unterschieden.</p>
<p>Um eine scharfe Grenze zwischen rein physiologischen und rein psychologischen Vorgängen zu haben, habe ich das Gebiet der Reflexe ganz in die Physiologie verwiesen und als reine Reflexe nur diejenigen Bewegungen bezeichnet, mit denen gar keine Bewusstseinserscheinungen, auch keine einfachen Empfindungen (d.h. das <hi rend="underline">Bewusstwerden</hi> einer Nervenerregung) verbunden und die also rein physiologischer Natur sind; denn dadurch, dass man bisher so mannigfache Bewegungen, die eine ganz verschiedene psychologische Werthigkeit haben, als Reflexe bezeichnet hat, ist die Unklarheit sehr begünstigt worden.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">Alles Triebleben, aller Instinct wie alles zweckbewusste Wollen beruht nach meiner Darlegung darauf, dass sich im Laufe der genetischen Entwickelung ganz bestimmte zweckmässige (d.h. der Arterhaltung günstige) Beziehungen zwischen gewissen Erkenntnissacten und bestimmten Gefühlen und Trieben ausbilden, so dass, wenn ein gewisser Erkenntnissact entsteht, durch dessen Associationsbeziehung auch der entsprechende Trieb hervorgerufen wird, so dass also z. B. eine bestimmte Wahrnehmung einen zweckentsprechenden Trieb und die zweckmässige Bewegung nothwendig zur Folge hat, auch wenn ein Bewusstsein des Zweckes fehlt</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Auf diese Weise finden zunächst <hi rend="underline">alle</hi> Instincte ihre naturgemässe Erklärung aus der Descendenz- und Selectionstheorie. Aber auch die zweckbewussten Willensäusserungen, welche sich aus den instinctiven entwickeln, sind damit auf ihre Ursachen zurückgeführt.</p>
                    <p>Die ersten Associationsbeziehungen zwischen Erkenntnissacten und zweckentsprechenden Trieben sind solche zwischen Empfindungen und Empfindungstrieben z. B. zwischen dem Bewusstwerden einer angenehmen Berührung mit einem Nahrungskörper und dem Trieb zum Einschliessen desselben, oder zwischen dem Bewusstwerden einer unangenehmen Berührung und dem Trieb zur Contraction des ganzen Körpers etc.</p>
                    <p>Die Frage nach der ersten Entstehung solcher zweckmässiger Beziehungen fällt mit der Frage nach der Entstehung der ersten Organismen zusammen.</p>
                    <p>Wird nun mit einem Empfindungstriebe die <hi rend="underline">Wahrnehmung</hi> des Objectes associirt, wird z. B. mit dem Nahrungsgenusse und dem Fresstriebe, der ja auf einer unmittelbaren Berührung beruht, etwa die Gesichtswahrnehmung des Nährkörpers (sobald ein Sehorgan entwickelt ist) associirt, so vermag dann auch diese Wahrnehmung allein schon einen Trieb zum Fressen resp. zum Annähern an das Object zu erwecken; und so gehen die Wahrnehmungstriebe auf Grund von Associationen aus den Empfindungstrieben hervor. etc. etc.</p>
                    <p>Ich bilde mir ein mit dieser Arbeit ebenfalls einen nicht unwichtigen Beitrag zur Ausbauung ihres grossen Gedankens über die Entwickelung der Organismen, welcher Gedanke sicher die ganze zukünftige Philosophie beherrschen wird, geliefert zu haben.</p>
                    <p>Die specielle Entwickelung und Differenzirung der einzelnen Thiergewohnheiten (mit den Stammbäumen) werde ich in einem besonderen Buche bringen und diesem eine grössere Arbeit über den menschlichen Willen, sowie eine solche über die thierische und menschliche Erkenntniss folgen lassen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Erlauben Sie mir, Hochgeehrtester Herr Darwin, gütigst an diese Mittheilungen eine Bitte anschliessen zu dürfen?</p>
                    <p>Da ich, wie gesagt, nur durch Ihre epochemachenden grossartigen Werke zu meinen Arbeiten angeregt worden bin und der Überzeugung lebe das Willensproblem ganz in Ihrem Geiste aufgefasst zu haben, so würde ich mich unendlich glücklich schätzen, wenn ich erfahren könnte, <hi rend="underline">wie gerade Sie über meine Arbeit denken</hi>, wie Sie dieselbe beurtheilen; und durch eine auch noch so kurze Mittheilung würden Sie mich zu unendlichem Danke verpflichten.</p>
<p>Hoffentlich haben Sie mein Buch: “Der thierische Wille” sowie auch die früher an Sie abgeschickte kleine Schrift gegen Prof. Jaegers vermeintlicher Entdeckung der Seele von mir erhalten.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Genehmigen Sie, Hochgeehrtester Herr, den Ausdruck der wärmsten Verehrung, mit der ich bin | Ihr | ganz ergebenster | G. H. Schneider</p>
                    <p>(Weststrasse 80 II in Leipzig)</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Jäger’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Leipzig,</placeName>
                    <date>2 April 1880.</date>
                    <salute>Most estimable | Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In 1870, when I was studying natural sciences in Jena, in particular zoology with Professor Haeckel,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> the theory of descent and selection awakened an extraordinary interest in me. I saw at once that the principles of evolution must have at least the same significance for psychological phenomena as for morphological ones, and I resolved immediately to dedicate my life to the study of psychological phenomena from the point of view of the theory of descent and selection.</p>
                    <p>My lively interest especially in the all-powerful principle of life that you discovered, that of natural selection in the struggle for existence, won me the favour and sympathy of the great Jena zoologist, who now most kindly supports my efforts in every respect. Unfortunately the cares of life have for many years interfered with my work in numerous ways. Now, however, after having lived in Naples for five years, and having made observations of volition among lower animals, partly in the aquarium of the zoological station, partly in my small private aquarium, and having published several smaller works sometimes as pamphlets, sometimes in scientific and in popular journals, I am finally in the fortunate position to be able humbly to send you a copy of my first bigger work: “Der thierische Wille”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In order to be able to get a publisher for it, I admittedly had to put the major portion of the material into a popular form and to restrict the general argument, in which lies its scientific merit, to a small part. Therefore kindly judge this book with forbearance.</p>
                    <p>I think I have interpreted the problem of the animal will <hi rend="underline">entirely within your conceptual framework</hi>, by explaining, based on your magnificent and classical investigations, all instinctive drives like all conscious desires, or rather, the origin and development of these, in terms of selection and of successive and simultaneous associations.</p>
                    <p>I have systematically arranged the material on expressions of will in animals, compiling habits of feeding, protection, mating and care of offspring, and classified them according to their psychological significance:</p>
                    <p>1; into those that occur on the basis of a subjective state or an objective state caused by direct contact (movement due to <hi rend="underline">sensory drives</hi>), 2, into those based on the perception of objects at a distance (<hi rend="underline">perceptual drives</hi>) and 3, into those based on simple reproductions of a perception or in conjunction with ideas (<hi rend="underline">representational and ideational drives</hi>); and from these cognitive drives I distinguished a further two auxiliary drives that are based purely on associations of movement (following drive and social drive).</p>
                    <p>In order to have a clear boundary between purely physiological and purely psychological processes, I have relegated the area of reflexes entirely to physiology, and designated as pure reflexes only those movements with which no phenomena of consciousness at all, not even simple sensations (i.e. <hi rend="underline">becoming conscious of</hi> a nerve impulse) are associated, and thus are purely physiological; since the designation of a variety of movements having completely different psychological significance as reflexes, which has been the case until now, has engendered much confusion.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">All instinctual life, all instinct like all goal-directed desire depends, according to my exposition, on the fact that, in the course of developmental evolution quite specific purposive (i.e. favourable to species preservation) relations develop between certain cognitive acts and certain sensations and drives, so that when a particular cognitive act occurs, a corresponding drive will be triggered through that associative relation; thus e.g. a specific perception necessarily elicits a corresponding drive and the corresponding motion, even if there is no consciousness of the goal.</hi></p>
                    <p>In this way <hi rend="underline">all</hi> instincts initially have a natural explanation in the theory of descent and selection. However, purposive expressions of the will, which evolve from instinctual ones, can thus also be traced back to their causes.</p>
                    <p>The first associative connections between cognitive acts and corresponding drives are those between sensations and sensory drives, e.g. between the awareness of a pleasant contact with an item of food and the drive to incorporate it, or between the awareness of an unpleasant touch and the drive to contract the entire body etc.</p>
                    <p>The question concerning the initial formation of such purposive connections coincides with the question of the emergence of the first organisms.</p>
                    <p>If, now, the <hi rend="underline">perception</hi> of an object is associated with the sensory drive, if, e.g., the enjoyment of food and the drive to eat, based on direct contact, is associated with, for instance, the visual perception of a food object (once a visual organ has evolved), then this perception alone can arouse a drive to eat or rather to approach the object; thus the perceptive drives develop from the sensory drives on the basis of associations. etc. etc.</p>
                    <p>I like to think that with this work I have also made a not unimportant contribution to the expansion of your great idea about the evolution of organisms, an idea that surely will dominate all future philosophy.</p>
                    <p>I will devote a separate book to the special evolution and differentiation of individual animal habits (together with genealogies), and this will be followed by a larger work on the human will, as well as one on animal and human cognition.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Would you kindly allow me, most esteemed Mr Darwin, to add a request to this message?</p>
                    <p>Since, as I said, I was only inspired to undertake my work because of your epochal, magnificent works, and since I am firmly persuaded of having approached the problem of volition entirely in your spirit, I would consider myself infinitely fortunate if I had the opportunity to learn <hi rend="underline">what you of all people think of my work</hi>, how you judge it; and for any communication, however brief, I would be forever indebted to you.</p>
<p>I hope you have received my book: “Der thierische Wille” as well as the previously sent small work countering Prof. Jaeger’s supposed discovery of the soul.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Accept, most esteemed Sir, the expression of my warmest regards, with which I remain | Yours | wholly devoted | G. H. Schneider <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">(Weststrasse 80 II in Leipzig)</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
                        
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 159–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Ernst Haeckel</ref> was professor of zoology at Jena. Schneider studied philosophy at Jena but attended Haeckel’s lectures (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11018.xml">Lucidi 2009</ref>, p. 21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Schneider was a teacher at the German school in Naples. ‘The cares of life’ is probably an allusion to his conflict with the director of the Zoological Station at Naples, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml">Anton Dohrn</ref>, who had refused to grant him a place at the German table, ostensibly because of his lack of qualifications (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11013.xml">Groeben ed. 1985</ref>, p. 298). CD’s copy of <hi rend="italic">Der thierische Wille</hi> (Animal will; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11014.xml">Schneider [1880]</ref>) is in the Darwin Library–Down. In his introduction to the book, Schneider laid out his case against Dohrn and the funding practices of the station (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. vii–xv).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The only follow-up book to appear was <hi rend="italic">Der menschliche Wille</hi> (Human will; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11015.xml">Schneider 1882</ref>). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD’s copy of <hi rend="italic">Jäger’s vermeintliche Entdeckung der Seele: eine Widerlegung</hi> (Jäger’s supposed discovery of the soul: a refutation; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11016.xml">Schneider 1879</ref>) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml">Gustav Jäger</ref> had published an article in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>, ‘Die Entdeckung der Seele’ (The discovery of the soul; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11017.xml">Jäger 1878</ref>), in which he equated the specific smells emanating from an animal with its soul, and further, postulated that each individual possessed a unique odour.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>