<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4082">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Armand de Quatrefages<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   [28 March] – 11 April 1863<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10341</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4082 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4082.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4082.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 175: 3</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>175: 3</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3892.xml">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1863-03-28" notAfter="1863-04-11">[28 Mar] – 11 Apr 1863 </date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Continues to support, in debates at the Société d’Anthropologie, the view that variability of animals and anatomical modifications are produced by environment. Wishes to use CD’s niata cattle example from <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> [2d ed., pp. 145–6].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_839">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">causation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Societe d’Anthropologie</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Monsieur et cher confrère</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Comme je vous le disais je crois dans ma derniere lettre je soutiens en ce moment à la Société d’Anthropologie une lutte assez vive en faveur de la variabilité des espèces animales.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Un de mes confrères m’a défié de citer <hi rend="underline">une seule espèce</hi> chez qui l’action des milieux eut produit des modifications <hi rend="underline">anatomiques</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Il ne compte pour rien celles qui se rattachent à la peau, au tissu cellulaire … Je vais repondre 〈    〉 en insistant sur l’histoire du cheval.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Mais on ne s’arrêtera pas là et je voudrais placer sous les yeux de ces disciples de S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Thomas un fait bien concluant<ref target="#foot.f6"/>  </p>
<p>J’ai songé aux <hi rend="underline">bœufs-dogues</hi> que vous nous avez fait connaitre, aux bœufs Nãta ou Niata.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Vous en avez dites vous (Journ. of Research … ) une tête à Londres.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Pourriez vous en faire prendre une photographie et me l’envoyer?<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Serait-il encore mieux possible d’en obtenir un moule pour les collections du Museum?<ref target="#foot.f10"/> a-t-elle été publiée quelque part?<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Si elle ne l’a pas été et que vous ou quelqu’un en Angleterre avez l’intention de le faire, je n’ai pas besoin de vous dire qu’aucune publication detaillée n’aura lieu en France et que je me bornerai à montrer soit le dessin soit le moule pour l’instruction de mes auditeurs et la conversion (si possible est) de mes contradicteurs.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Pardon Monsieur et cher confrere de ce que mes demandes peuvent avoir d’indiscret et recevez de nouveau l’expression de mon bien affecteux dévouement | De Quatrefages <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">11 Avril 63</p>
<p>J’ai vu M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Martins 〈    〉 en ce moment à Paris pour la réunion des délégués des facultés de Province.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Je lui ai donné toutes les instructions, que mon habitude de ces petits details pouvaient me sugérer, pour que votre collection fut aussi bien faite que possible.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Je l’ai trouvé rempli d’excellentes intentions. Il a pris votre adresse et vous enverra directement les objets par le chemin de fer<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>J’ai eu aussi ces jours derniers un veritable plaisir a causer longuement avec le D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Carpenter. ses travaux sur les Comatules m’ont très vivement interessé.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Merci de tout ce que vous me dites d’aimable 〈a〉u sujet de mes Métamorphoses<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir and dear colleague,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>As I think I told you in my last letter, I am engaged at present in a rather lively battle at the Société d’Anthropologie on behalf of the variability of animal species.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> One of my colleagues has challenged me to cite a <hi rend="underline">single species</hi> in which the action of the environment has produced <hi rend="underline">anatomical</hi> modifications.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He does not take into account those which concern the skin, the cellular tissue … I am about to reply 〈    〉 by insisting on the history of the horse.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> But this will not be the end of it, and I should like to produce before the eyes of these disciples of St Thomas one decisive fact.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I have considered the <hi rend="underline">pug</hi>-<hi rend="underline">cattle</hi> which you brought to our attention, the Nãta or Niata cattle.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> You say (Journ. of Research … ) that you have the head of one in London.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Could you have a photograph of it taken and sent to me?<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Even better—would it be possible to have a cast made for the museum collections?<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Has it been published anywhere?<ref target="#foot.f11"/> If it has not and either you or somebody else in England intends to do so, it goes without saying that no detailed publication will be produced in France, and I will restrict myself to showing either the drawing or the cast for the instruction of my students and the conversion (if it be possible) of my opponents.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Forgive me Sir and dear colleague for any indiscretion in my questions and please accept again the expression of my affectionate devotion | De Quatrefages <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>11 April 63</p>
<p>I saw M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Martins who is at present in Paris for the meeting of the delegates of the provincial faculties.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I gave him all the guidance that my experience of these small details could suggest,<ref target="#foot.f14"/> so that your collection should be as well arranged as possible. I found him full of excellent intentions. He took your address and will send you the objects directly by train.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>A few days ago I also had the great pleasure of talking at length to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Carpenter; I have found his work on Comatulae of very great interest.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Thank you for all the kind things you said about my Métamorphoses.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.11, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the originalFrench, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.11, pp. 275–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The date range is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, 27 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4066.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 25 March 1863</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">André Sanson</ref>, and to a meeting of the Société d’Anthropologie held on 19 March 1863 (<hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 159). For Quatrefages’s responses to Sanson of 16 April and 16 July, see <hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 213–23, and nn. 5 and 12, below. For Sanson’s responses to Quatrefages of 7 May and 16 July, see <hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 254–68, 374–5, and 380–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Quatrefages described the modification of breeds of horses through environmental influences at a meeting of the Société d’Anthropologie on 16 April 1863, citing the descent of the English racehorse from Arab stock as an example (<hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 215–19). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to the biblical narrative of the apostle Thomas’s refusal to believe in the resurrection of Jesus Christ without direct experience (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Niata: ‘An abnormally small variety of cattle, found in South America’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). Quatrefages refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 145–6, where CD observed that the niata cattle ‘appear externally to hold nearly the same relation to other cattle, which bull or pug dogs do to other dogs.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 146. CD presented a skull of this breed from the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> collections to the Royal College of Surgeons of London in 1840 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francisco Javier Muñiz, 26 February 1847</ref>, n. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD sent photographs of the niata skull in May (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4166A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, 14 May [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 19 May [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Quatrefages was professor of the natural history of man at the Muséum d’Histoire Naturelle in Paris (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>); apparently, no cast of the skull was sent (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4166A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, 14 May [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 19 May [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The skull is described in Owen [1853], 2: no. 3832; CD had also discussed it in his manuscript draft of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 89–91, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4094F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, [14 April 1863]</ref>). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 177.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Quatrefages displayed the photographs at a meeting of the Société d’Anthropologie on 2 July 1863 (<hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 350–2). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 19 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Frédéric Martins</ref> was professor of botany at the Faculté de Montpellier (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2033.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire universel des contemporains</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Quatrefages completed his own research on silkworms between 1857 and 1859 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6463.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Quatrefages 1859</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Martins had agreed to send CD a collection of varieties of the common silkworm (<hi rend="italic">Bombyx mori</hi>) at different stages in their life cycle; however, the collection was apparently never sent (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, 27 March [1863]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Benjamin Carpenter</ref> had travelled to Paris for recreational purposes during his Easter vacation as registrar of London University (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carpenter 1888</ref>, p. 84; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). However, he soon became involved in the heated discussions that followed the discovery on 28 March 1863 of a fossilised human jaw at Moulin-Quignon in the Somme valley, discussions in which Quatrefages also played a leading role. See Carpenter’s report of the discovery in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 18 April 1863, p. 523; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Grayson 1983</ref>, pp. 213–17, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7949.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Van Riper 1993</ref>, pp. 134–39. Carpenter published his work on the echinoderm <hi rend="italic">Comatula</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1269.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carpenter 1865</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, 27 March [1863]</ref>. The reference is to <hi rend="italic">Métamorphoses de l’homme et des animaux</hi> (Quatrefages 1862), of which there is an lightly annotated copy in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 691).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>