<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1205">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Jean Louis Rodolphe Agassiz   22 October 1848</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3070</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1205 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1205.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1205.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark"> Shrewsbury OC 23 1848</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Houghton Library, Harvard University (MS Am 1419: 274)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_180.xml">Harvard Houghton</repository>
                    <collection>L. Agassiz Correspondence etc.</collection>
                    <idno>MS Am 1419: 274</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Shrewsbury Down letterhead</placeName>
                <date when="1848-10-22">22 Oct 1848</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml">Agassiz, J. L. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks LA and sends thanks to A. A. Gould for specimens. Describes principal findings of his research on cirripedes. Is obliged for information Joseph Leidy gave about cirripede eyes. Describes anatomical features and chief aspects of growth. Describes discovery of parasitic males and a species parasitic upon other cirripedes.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough | Kent<ref target="#foot.f1"/></placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 22. 1848</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Although I have not yet received the Box with the Cirripedia, I cannot wait longer to send you &amp; D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gould my most cordial thanks for your great kindness.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I hope that you will give my especial acknowledgments to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gould for the very great assistance, which the named specimens will afford me. I have been particularly gratified in receiving specimens from yourself, in as much as, when doubting whether to undertake a monograph of the class, or to confine myself to their anatomy, your sentence that “a monograph on the Cirripedia was a pressing desideratum in Zoology”<ref target="#foot.f3"/> much helped to decide me.— In your letter to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lowell<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (to whom I also beg you to present my respectful thanks) you say you sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> like to hear what results I have arrived at; as far as the limits of a letter go, it will give me <hi rend="underline">real</hi> pleasure to do so.— I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be glad if you would not mention my present results, partly because I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> like to have the satisfaction of publishing myself what few new points I have found out, &amp; partly because one is more free to alter ones own views, when they are confined to one’s own breast.—</p>
<p>The Cirripedia are true Crustacea with no affinities to other classes; M. St. Ange<ref target="#foot.f5"/> curiously mistook a strong epithelium for an inner sort of stomach, &amp; hence the affinity with the Annelides disappears. The Cirripedia are either a sub-class equal to the Siphonostomous &amp; Maxillated classes &amp;c or to all these classes together; this I cannot decide yet.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> All cirripedes (except one forming an abnormal order) in their first larval stage, have 3 pair of legs &amp; two pair of antennæ in process of formation within cases, &amp; one eye: in the last stage, all have six legs, two compound, <hi rend="underline">not</hi> pedunculated, most singular eyes &amp; a pair of prehensile antennæ. In this stage they are pupæ, <hi rend="underline">for they have no mouth</hi>. In assuming the mature form, the compound eyes are moulted, &amp; by the act of moulting (by a process which I cannot explain without diagrams) the cirripede assumes the position which it always holds, which is at right angles to that which the pupa assumed when first attached. I am particularly obliged for the information about D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Leidy. I know the black spots which he alludes to, but I had not discovered that they were eyes,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> though I thought them like eyes. I will attend to this. I have long been aware that the Cirripedia are exquisitely sensitive of light or rather shadows. Cirripedes have olfactory &amp; auditory organs; the nerves proceeding from the <hi rend="underline">infra</hi> œsoph. ganglion.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>The means by which Cirripedes are attached is one of the most remarkable parts of their Natural History:<ref target="#foot.f9"/> a portion of the <hi rend="underline">ovarian</hi> cæca, becomes modified &amp; glandular &amp; secretes a cement, which is poured out by 2 ducts opening at the penultimate segment of the antennæ of the pupa, &amp; fixing them <hi rend="underline">permanently</hi> to the support. Afterwards the cement in some families is poured out by symmetrical orifices round the base of shell or peduncle, or in a single line, when the cirripede is attached to a coralline.— When the pupa moults, the whole of its envelopes are moulted, except the cemented antennæ: hence by care (&amp; extreme care is requisite) the antennæ of the pupa can be demonstrated in the exact centre of the base of the largest Balanus or Anatifera.—</p>
<p>Strange as it may appear, this curious means of attachment is the only character absolutely universal in the Cirri<hi rend="underline">pedia</hi>, (some Cirri<hi rend="underline">pedia</hi> are <hi rend="underline">apodal</hi> <ref target="#foot.f10"/> ).— I have made out, I believe with certainty from dissection &amp; not from analogies the homologies of the cirripedia<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The shell, including the peduncle of the Pedunculata, consists of the 3 anterior segments of the head, so enlarged as to receive the whole rest of body, which consists of 14 segments in the larva &amp; in some abnormal cirripedia (the cirri answer to the 5 pair of ambulatory legs &amp; the outer pied-machoire of the higher crustacea), the 4 posterior abdominal segments being always aborted.—</p>
<p>The great majority of cirripedes are bisexual,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> but it seems that they can fecundate each other, for I have scrupulously examined a Balanus, which had had its penis cut off &amp; was imperforate, but in which the ova were impregnated.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I have one genus, in which the sexes are distinct, the male (sometimes two of them) being parasitic &amp; permanently attached within the so-called sack of the female.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> There is, however, one much stranger case, but of the accuracy of which I am positive after repeated dissections: the normal form is bisexual, but the male organs are small, though perfect &amp; containing zoosperms, to make up for this, some of the pupæ, become attached to the orifice of the sack of the hermaphrodite, undergo a <hi rend="underline">retrograde</hi> metamorphosis, never acquire a mouth or stomach, &amp; are filled with testes, &amp; ultimately the whole animal consists of a great sperm-receptacle full of zoosperms.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> As soon as these are discharged, these embryonic “supplemental males” die &amp; are soon succeeded by another set: I have counted 10 of these supplemental males on one hermaphrodite. You will laugh at this account, but I assure you I would not presume to tell you anything, of which I was not <hi rend="underline">sure</hi>, from repeated examinations of specimens taken at different periods &amp; from different countries.—</p>
<p>The most remarkable individual cirripede, which I have seen is <hi rend="underline">naked</hi>, apodal, with a <hi rend="underline">suctorial</hi> mouth, &amp; parasitic in a double way within another cirripede.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/> I hope I have not wearied you much with these details: I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be proud if anything I could say, would interest you.—</p>
<p>With sincere respect &amp; my cordial thanks for your &amp; D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Goulds kindness— Pray believe me | Yours faithfully &amp; obliged | C. Darwin</p>
<p>I do not suppose I shall finish my Monograph for two or three years— my health allows me to work very little</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.7 your] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘you’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.8 Zoology] ‘oo’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.11 mention] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘to’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.14 they are] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.3 the affinity] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.6 pair of antennæ 2.7] ‘pair of’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.7 within] ‘with’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.7 last] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘second’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.11 without diagrams)] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘)’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">2.12 that] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">2.15 them] ‘m’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘ir’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">2.16 the Cirripedia] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘they’; ‘Cirripedia’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">3.1 one] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">3.3 by 2 ducts opening] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi>; ‘2’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">3.5 families] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘genera’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">3.7 envelopes] ‘en’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">4.2 (some] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘for’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">4.3 from dissection &amp; not from analogies] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">4.6 which consists] ‘which’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi>; ‘consists’ <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘consisting’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">4.6 &amp; in some abnormal cirripedia 4.7] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">5.3 were] ‘w’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">5.5 &amp; permanently attached] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">5.7 the orifice] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">5.13 these embryonic] ‘these’ <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘this’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25">5.13 males” die] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘male” dies’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n26">8.1 Monograph] ‘M’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘m’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD was actually in Shrewsbury from 10 to 25 October, his last visit before the death of his father (‘Journal’; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix I).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1200.xml" resp="#automat">letter to A. A. Gould, 3 September [1848]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1139.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. E. Gray, 18 December 1847</ref>, n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Amory Lowell</ref>, who, as trustee of the Lowell Institute, Boston, invited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>, upon the recommendation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, to deliver a course of public lectures at the institute in 1846. The great popularity of these lectures, on the ‘Plan of Creation in the Animal Kingdom’, was the main reason Agassiz decided to remain in the United States (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4977.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lurie 1960</ref>, pp. 116–33).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3191.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gaspard Joseph Martin-Saint-Ange</ref>. CD repeated this point in <hi rend="italic">Living</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cirripedia</hi> (1851) and frequently referred to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5274.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Martin-Saint-Ange 1835</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>9–20, CD discussed the taxonomic rank of cirripedes, stating his belief that they should be considered as a subclass of the class Crustacea and describing the various relations that cirripedes hold to other divisions of Crustacea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2873.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Leidy</ref> had recently announced his discovery of eyes in a mature <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi> (Leidy 1848). CD mentioned this in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>49.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>15, 52, and <hi rend="italic">Living</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cirripedia</hi> (1854): 95, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD often repeated this statement (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>37). The anatomical correspondence between what he took to be the cement glands and the ovarian tubes suggested to him a homology between the two systems. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>151–2, CD speculated ‘that Cirripedes were once separated by scarcely sensible intervals from some other, now unknown, Crustaceans … with their oviducts opening at or near their second pair of antennæ’, and suggested how the ovaria could have been transformed into a cementing apparatus. This view was challenged in 1859 by August Krohn (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4503.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Krohn 1859</ref>) (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2931.xml" resp="#automat">letter from CD to Charles Lyell, 28 [September 1860]</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 2: 345, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 2931).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The name ‘cirripede’ is derived from the Latin for ‘curl’ (‘cirrus’) and for ‘foot’ (‘pes, ped-’) and ‘refers to the appearance of the legs, which can be protruded like a curled lock of hair from between the valves’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). CD had a single specimen of what he took to be an aberrant cirripede completely lacking feet. He named the specimen <hi rend="italic">Proteolepas bivincta</hi> and, using the feet as the character on which he based his orders, made it the sole member of the order Apoda.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 6 October [1848]</ref>, n. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1167.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. S. Henslow, [1 April 1848]</ref>, n. 6, for CD’s use of the term ‘bisexual’ to mean hermaphrodite.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">This is probably the ‘fortunate chance’ that enabled CD to show that hermaphrodites fertilise each other and to which he referred in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 45, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 101.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><hi rend="italic">Ibla cumingii</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>183–203), first mentioned in <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1167.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. S. Henslow, [1 April 1848]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">The genus <hi rend="italic">Scalpellum</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1174.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 10 May 1848</ref>, n. 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><hi rend="italic">Proteolepas bivincta</hi> (see n. 10, above).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>