<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1004">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   [3 October 1846]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">50</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1004 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1004.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1004.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp &amp; C</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 161</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 120 &amp; DAR 146: 161</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 3: 348</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.50)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>50</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1846-10-03">[3 Oct 1846]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses A. C. Ramsay’s article ["On the denudation of South Wales", <hi rend="italic">Mem. Geol. Surv. G. B.</hi> 1 (1846)]. Mentions his own paper ["Volcanic phenomena in South America", <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 53–86]. Emphasises that sedimentary deposits are not ordinarily preserved.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Mem. Geol. Surv. G. B.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Wales, South</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Ramsay, A. C. 1846</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Down]</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been much interested with Ramsay;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> but have no particular suggestions to offer: I agree with all your remarks made the other day.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> My final impression is, that the only argument against him, is to tell him to read &amp; reread the Principles, &amp; if not then convinced to send him to Pluto.— Not but what he has well read the Principles! &amp; largely profited thereby.— I know not how carefully you have read this paper, but I think you did not mention to me, that he <hi rend="underline">does</hi> p. 327 believe that the main part of his great denudation was effected during a vast (almost gratuitously assumed) slow <hi rend="underline">Tertiary</hi> subsidence &amp; subsequent <hi rend="underline">Tertiary</hi> oscillating slow elevation.— So our high-cliff argument is inapplicable. He seems to think his great subsidence only <hi rend="underline">favourable</hi> for <hi rend="underline">great</hi> denudation, I believe, from the general nature of the off-shores sea’s bottoms, that it is almost necessary: do look at two pages p. 25 of my S. American Vol. on this subject, when out next week.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The foundation of his views viz of one great sudden upheaval,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> strikes me as threefold.— 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. to account for the great dislocations; this strikes me as the odder, as he admits that a little northwards, there were many &amp; some violent dislocations at many periods during the accumulation of the palæozoic series.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> If you argue against him allude to the cool assumption that petty forces are conflicting:<ref target="#foot.f6"/> look at Volcanos; look at recurrent similar earthquakes at same spots; look at <hi rend="underline">repeatedly</hi> injected intrusive masses. In my paper on Volc. Phæn. in Geolog. Transact, I have argued (&amp; Lonsdale thought well of the argument, in favour, as he remarked, of your original doctrine) that if Hopkins views are correct, viz that mountain-chains are subordinate consequences to changes of level in mass, then, as we have evidence of such horizontal movements in mass having been slow, the formation of mountain chains (differing from volcanos only in matter being <hi rend="doubleUnderline">in</hi>jected instead of <hi rend="doubleUnderline">e</hi>jected) must have been slow.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Secondly, Ramsay has been influenced, I think, by his alpine insects: but he is wrong in thinking that there is any necessary connection of Tropics &amp; large insects; videlicet Galapagos. Arch. under the Equator. <hi rend="underline">Small</hi> insects swarm in all parts of Tropics, though accompanied generally with large ones.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Thirdly, he appears influenced by the absence of newer deposits on the old area, blinded by the supposed necessity of sediment accumulating somewhere near (as no doubt is true) &amp; being <hi rend="underline">preserved</hi>;—an example, as I think, of the common error, on which I wrote to you about. The <hi rend="underline">preservation</hi> of sedimentary deposits being, as I do not doubt, the exception, <hi rend="underline">when they are accumulated</hi> <hi rend="underline">during periods of elevation or of stationary level</hi>; &amp; therefore the preservation of newer deposits would not be probable, according to your view that Ramsay’s great palæozoic masses were denuded, whilst <hi rend="underline">slowly rising</hi> — Do pray look at end of II. Chapt at what <hi rend="underline">little</hi> I have said on this subject in my S. American volume.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I do not think you can safely argue that <hi rend="underline">whole</hi> surface was probably denuded at the same time to the level of the lateral patches of Magnesian conglomerate.—</p>
<p>The latter part of paper strikes me as good, but obvious. I shall send him my S. American Vol. for it is curious on how many similar points we enter, &amp; I <hi rend="underline">modestly</hi> hope it may be a half oz: weight towards his conversion to better views. If he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. but reject his great sudden elevations, how sound &amp; good he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be.— I doubt whether this letter will be worth the reading.</p>
<p>Ever your’s | C. D.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 is,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.6 p. 327] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi>; ‘327’ <hi rend="italic">above interl del</hi> ‘319, 321,’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.6 believe that] ‘that’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.7 main part of his] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.8 gratuitously] ‘ly’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.8 slow <hi rend="italic">Tertiary</hi>] ‘slow’ <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘su’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">1.8 subsequent] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">1.9 slow elevation] ‘slow’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">1.9 our] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">1.9 is] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">1.10 for <hi rend="italic">great</hi> denudation,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">1.10 the general] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">1.11 the off-shores] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">1.12 two pages 1.13] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">2.1 viz of one great sudden upheaval,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">2.2 the odder] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">2.6 similar] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">2.11 having been] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘being’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">2.13 have been] ‘have’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi>; ‘en’ <hi rend="italic">added to</hi> ‘be’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">3.2 there is] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">3.3 the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">3.4 ones] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘—’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">4.2 blinded] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘overlooking,’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">4.2 supposed] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘ne’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25">4.3 the common error, on 4.4] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n26">4.4 on] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘ab’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n27">4.4 which] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n28">4.4 being] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> <hi rend="italic">caret</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n29">4.4 , as I do not doubt, the 4.5] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n30">4.6 the preservation … be] <hi rend="italic">interl after</hi> <hi rend="italic">del</hi> ‘not being’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n31">4.8 what] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘I’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n32">5.1 at the same time 5.2] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n33">5.4 sudden] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n34">6.1 Ever] ‘E’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘e’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay</ref>, who was employed by the Geological Survey. CD’s comments apply to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1846</ref>, a copy of which is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had made a trip to London with Emma which he recorded in his Account Book (Down House MS) on 30 September.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1846</ref> dealt with evidence for marine denudation revealed by the work of the Geological Survey in Wales. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 25–6, CD had argued that the cliffs on St Helena were formed by subsidence of sloping volcanic strata, allowing the ocean to cut away at successively higher levels of the slope while depositing detritus underwater. Ramsay considered slow subsidence an important aid to the process though not a necessary one (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1846</ref>, pp. 326–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Ramsay (1846, pp. 314–17) believed that the convoluted strata appearing over much of South Wales had been produced by a single great catastrophe occurring near the end of the Carboniferous.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Ramsay (1846, p. 314) had noted pre-Carboniferous disturbances in North Wales.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Ramsay (1846, p. 317) argued that in view of the enormous lateral pressure required to fold strata thousands of feet thick, no such result ‘could have obtained from the conflicting action of petty forces working at various times’. Lyell was apparently considering Ramsay’s argument in connection with revisions for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5009.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1847</ref>. Lyell did not follow CD’s suggestions however, adding only a footnote to his volume commenting on the short time-span allowed by Ramsay (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5009.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1847</ref>, p. 168 n.).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">As assistant-secretary of the Geological Society, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2989.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Lonsdale</ref> oversaw the refereeing of CD’s paper. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2989.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Lonsdale</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-412.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[15 May 1838]</ref>, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> June 1838], and [8 March 1839]. CD had cited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref> (1838) in his discussion of the slow elevation of mountain chains (‘On the connexion of certain volcanic phenomena in South America’, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 76–80).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Ramsay had cited the conclusion of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_651.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter Bellinger Brodie</ref> (1845), that the small size of most fossil insects in British Secondary strata indicated a cool or temperate climate. This conclusion seemed to contradict the tropical character of many Secondary fossils, but Ramsay argued that Brodie’s insects constituted evidence for the continued existence of a temperate highland region existing side by side with tropical lowlands throughout the Secondary period. Thus, the extensive denudation which eroded the once massive formations of South Wales had not occurred until the Tertiary (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1846</ref>, pp. 324–5). The presumed thickness of these formations had, of course, been part of Ramsay’s argument that only a great catastrophe could have folded them.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, pp. 135–9. Here CD argued that substantial sedimentary deposits were not likely to accumulate in periods of elevation because of the denuding action of the breakers. He used this argument to account for the absence of fossiliferous Tertiary strata on the west coast of South America. He used it again in the <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (pp. 172–3, 290–2) as a partial explanation of the absence of transitional forms in the fossil record.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>