<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-447">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Emma Wedgwood   [30 November 1838]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5182</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-447 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-447.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-447.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 204: 152</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 152</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Wedgwood, Emma</persName>
                <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                <date when="1838-11-30">[30 Nov 1838]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has accepted the Hensleigh Wedgwoods’ invitation to go to London with them; can look at houses with CD. She wishes to avoid extravagance; asks him to choose three or four for her to see.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Wedgwood, Hensleigh’s family</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">London</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">inviting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                    <date>Friday.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I like your unsentimental shaped paper very much so I hope you will stick to it. It holds so much. I really &amp; solemnly think you are quite right about houses &amp; so let us cast off the suburbs &amp; what is more Susan thinks so too &amp; you know what a wise woman she is. I read her what you said on that subject which I did not think was infringing on your wish of keeping your letters to myself. Dear good Susan has undertaken to get all the household linen which will be a great weight off our minds. She came over by the coach yesterday &amp; we are enjoying her visit thoroughly. She brings a very good account of Caroline &amp; will stay till Monday. The Hensleighs have asked me to go up with them for a week to look at houses with you. I think you thought of this plan yourself once, but I then thought it would be a bustle &amp; not much use. Whether it will be of much use now I don’t know, but I am sure I shall like it of all things so I am a coming. The only thing I shall not like will be if it cheats me out of one of your visits here but you must not let it do that because we shall be in a bustle all the time I am at Notting Hill so that it will not do instead of a walk round Birth hill. I really think it will help matters if you fix upon 3 or 4 of the most likely houses for me to take a look at with you. Susan is all for Tavistock Sqr. but I am afraid that will be too extravagant. I want to be strictly incog so don’t say that I am coming to those dreadful blabs Erasmus &amp; Robert for I don’t mean to go after any of my friends: So they need not know it till they see me at Notting Hill. I am very glad Roberts affair is so well got over. I do believe he has suffered a great deal with this unlucky affair. I want you to ask Robert whether he is going strait to Liverpool about the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>because if so it would be very convenient by way of an escort home for me, but you must only find out from curiosity &amp; not tell him your reason. &amp; he may be going round by Oxford or elsewhere.</p>
<p>My dear Charley shall I really see you the end of next week. It will be very pleasant I do think. I will send your note to Frank. I am afraid poor Cavington will hate the sight of me. I have great hopes that with the excellent character you can give him he will get a situation &amp; I am sure Frank will do all he can for him. The great Solomon thinks he knows of a man servant for you &amp; if he approves nothing more can be desired. I have the offer of a housemaid whom I like in some respects. I see you want a real good scolding about getting your work done so you must think what a dreadful rage I shall be in if you are not at leisure the week after next to go a galivanting with me in the flies &amp; omnibusses. It is very unlucky your having such a quantity of work on your hands. I quite approve of your plan of furnishing a bit of the house first &amp; getting into it how we can &amp; then furnishing at our leisure. I think it would be quite insulting to take the house in Bedford Place just opposite the Horneritas.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>There were several things in your last letter that pleased me uncommonly. I was a good deal flattered too by Thomas’s approbation, but your own flattery I like best though I don’t think you a very impartial judge. I feel sometimes inclined to say to you “I am very glad you think so” when I have said nothing in a very dignified way as if I thought your opinion quite a just one &amp; no more than my due. Caroline says in a note to me that she can wish me no greater happiness than to meet with the same constant sympathy &amp; affection she does &amp; then it will not signify where I live as she finds. That is a wonderful marriage I say for the hundredth time, but I think I kn〈ow〉 one that will turn out quite as happy, though I don’t quite approve of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell’s attempting to foment domestic dissention so early in the day as this. I don’t expect that you will be quite so lively at the D<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>on Sunday, he will know better than to talk in that frivolous unfeeling way upon such a solemn subject. I believe I shall take your advice about Lyells book especially as I begin to think he has such a bad heart. I shall do my errands in London now instead of going to Liverpool. I think you will be glad to see me my dear Charles so I will give you my blessing &amp; wish you Good bye.</p>
<p>The Temperance Festival succeeded very well in spite of the weather which was as bad as possible. The room was fuller than it could hold &amp; a Temperance song to the tune of “Auld lang syne” was sold for a halfpenny each Said to be composed by Miss Wedgwood of Camp Hill<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but not thought to be genuine. We are going to walk to Camp Hill this morning with Susan.</p>
<p>Goodbye once more write to me soon like a dear old soul. yours Emma W.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2392.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Horner</ref>s and five unmarried daughters lived at Lower Bedford Place. ‘Horneritas’ is obviously a play on ‘Señoritas’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Emma’s aunt, Sarah Elizabeth (Sarah) Wedgwood, was a strong advocate of temperance (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wedgwood 1980</ref>, p. 235). Camp Hill, on Maer heath, was her residence.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>