<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9756">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Arnold Dodel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   13 December 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16747</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9756 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9756.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9756.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">1p (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 194</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 194</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1342.xml">Dodel-Port, Arnold</persName>
                <placeName>Zurich</placeName>
                <date when="1874-12-13">13 Dec 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Describes his university lectures on evolution and their publication in a book [<hi rend="italic">Die neuere Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (1875)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die neuere Schopfungsgeschichte</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Dodel-Port, Arnold 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-02-18" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-02-18" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-02-18" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00877_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00877_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="194:1r" xml:id="i877">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00877.jpg" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00877_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00877.dzi" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="194:1v" xml:id="i878">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00878.jpg" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00878_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00878.dzi" width="5390px" height="7458px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Zürich,</placeName>
                    <date>13. Decbr. 1874</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Herrn Charles Darwin in Down, Beckenham Kent—England.</seg>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Sie erhalten mitlaufend ein Exemplar meiner “Neuern Schöpfungsgeschichte”, welche nichts Anderes enthält, als die erweiterten Vorlesungen über Ihre Abstammungs- u. Zuchtwahltheorie, so wie ich sie seit 4 Jahren am eidgenössischen Polytechnikum u. an der Universität in Zürich zu halten gewohnt bin.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich schmeichle mir, der erste Docent unserer schweizerischen Republik gewesen zu sein, der es wagte, an einer unserer vier Hochschulen eine Semester-Vorlesung über die neuere Schöpfungs-Geschichte zu halten. Ich las im Sommer 1871 zum ersten Mal über Ihre Theorie u zwar vor 21 Zuhörern verschiedener Fakultäten; im Winter 1872/73 vor circa 80–100 Personen, in den Wintern 1873/74 und 1874/75 vor c<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>. 60–80 regelmässigen Hörern. Ich habe nicht unterlassen, rückhaltlos u furchtlos, offen u. scharf die Lehre vorzutragen u. die Consequenzen anzudeuten, welche sie naturgemäss für die wissenschaftlich-socialen u. religiösen Bestrebungen der Gegenwart haben muss. Der Lohn war die Genugthuung, einen grossen Kreis junger Leute für Ihre Theorie ins Interesse hineingezogen zu haben, aber auch bittere Anfeindungen mancherlei Art.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> durch letztere wurde ich veranlasst, meine Vorlesungen <hi rend="underline">so schnell wie möglich</hi> zu publiciren. Es ist meines Wissens diese “Neuere Schöpf.-Gesch.” die erste Darstellung Ihrer Theorie von Seite eines Botanikers auf unserem Continent. Man wird manche werthvolle Arbeit von anerkannten Botanikern gehörig berücksichtigt finden. Unsere Disciplin ist sehr geeignet, Beweismaterial aller Art für die Descendenz-Theorie zu liefern. Vielleicht finden Sie manchen Punkt in meinem Buche angedeutet, den Sie später bei allfälligen neuen Auflagen Ihrer Werke mitberücksichtigen können.</p>
<p>Ich hoffe, mein Buch wird zum Mindesten von ebenso vielen strebsamen Leuten gelesen, als dasjenige eines andere Botanikers (Wigand), der sich ablehnend gegen die Abstammungs- u. Zuchtwahltheorie verhält.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ich fahre fort, im Interesse unserer freisinnigen Sache zu dociren u. zu schreiben, zu forschen u. zu prüfen.</p>
<p>Möge dieser erste Versuch nicht umsonst gemacht worden sein!</p>
<p>Ich habe die Ehre, Sie meiner ausgezeichnetsten Hochachtung u. tiefsten Verehrung zu versichern.</p>
<p>Ihr ergebenster | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Arnold Dodel, | Docent a/d. Universität.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Zürich,</placeName>
                    <date>13. Decbr. 1874</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">To Mr Charles Darwin in Down, Beckenham Kent----England</seg>
                    <salute>Most highly honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>By the same post as this you receive a copy of my “Neuere Schöpfungsgeschichte”, which contains nothing other than an expanded version of my lectures on your theory of descent and of selection, as I have given them in the past few years at the federal polytechnic and at the university in Zurich.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I flatter myself to have been the first university teacher of our Swiss republic who dared give a regular course of lectures on the new history of creation at one of our four institutes of higher education. In the summer of 1871 I lectured on your theory for the first time, in fact to an audience of 21 listeners from various faculties; in the winter of 1872/73, to circa 80–100 people, in the winter of 1873/74 and 1874/75 before ca. 60–80 regular listeners. I left nothing out and presented your theory without reservations or fear, frankly and strongly, and I pointed out the implications it must necessarily have for the scientific, social, and religious endeavours of the present day. My reward was the satisfaction of having won a great circle of young people for your theory, but also bitter animosities of all sorts.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> the latter induced me to publish my lectures <hi rend="underline">as speedily as possible</hi>. To my knowledge this “Neuere Schöpf.-Gesch.” is the first account of your theory by a botanist on our continent. A number of valuable works by established botanists have been given due consideration. Our discipline is well suited to provide evidence of all kinds for the theory of descent. Perhaps you will find a number of points in my book which you could later take into consideration in the various new editions of your works.</p>
<p>I hope that my book will be read by at least as many assiduous people as that of another botanist (Wigand) who has taken a disapproving stance against your theory of descent and selection.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I shall continue to teach and write, to research and to examine, in the interest of our liberal-minded task. May this first attempt not have been undertaken in vain! I have the honour of assuring you of my highest respect and of my deepest veneration. Your most devoted | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Arnold Dodel, | teacher at the university.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">There is a lightly annotated copy of Dodel’s <hi rend="italic">Die neuere Schöpfungsgeschichte nach dem gegenwärtigen Stande der Naturwissenschaften</hi> (New history of creation according to the present state of science; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2076.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dodel 1875</ref>) in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 203–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In 1874, eleven students of Zürich University signed a formal complaint, criticising Dodel’s lectures on the Darwinian theory on scientific and moral grounds. A petition in defence of Dodel, signed by another thirty-nine students, led to proceedings against him being abandoned. The situation was however not permanently defused, and when asked to assess Dodel for his promotion in 1879, the rector’s office of Zürich University refused to comment. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2374.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Erziehungsrate des Kantons Zürich ed. 1938</ref>, p. 698 n.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Albert Wigand</ref> criticised CD’s theory in his work <hi rend="italic">Der Darwinismus und die Naturforschung Newtons und Cuviers</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8760.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wigand 1874–7</ref>). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Albert Wigand, 11 March 1874</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>