<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11029">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Oscar Comettant<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   1 July 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16486</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11029 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11029.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11029.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Duplicated circular</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 216</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 216</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1028.xml">Comettant, Oscar</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1877-07-01">1 July 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Circular letter advertising Ernest Lavigne’s scheme to educate wealthy foreign children in Paris.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2831">Lavigne, Ernest</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Paris</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">education</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-02" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="rclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name>. Corrections entered by Sam Evans.</change>
        <change when="2016-11-02" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name>. Corrections entered by Sam Evans.</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00903_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00903_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="216:1r" xml:id="i903">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00903.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00903_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00903.dzi" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="216:1v" xml:id="i904">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00904.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00904_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00904.dzi" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="216:2r" xml:id="i905">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00905.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00905_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00905.dzi" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="216:2v" xml:id="i906">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00906.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00906_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00906.dzi" width="5501px" height="7482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Institut Musical | 64, rue Neuve-des-Petits-Champs</hi> Paris,</placeName>
                    <date>1 juillet 1877</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je viens, en qualité de collègue, comme ayant pris part au dernier congrès des amèricanistes à Nancy,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> apporter le fait suivant à votre connaissance.</p>
<p>Mon gendre, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne, ancien èlève de l’ècole normale supèrieure, membre de l’universitè de France, homme de lettres et traducteur de Lucréce,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> a rèsolu de prendre chez lui six jeunes ètrangers (chiffre maximum) pour leur donner l’instruction universitaire les preparer au baccalaurèat et les rendre aptes à suivre les diffèrentes facultès de mèdicine, de droit, ou à embrasser tout autre carrière scientifique ou d’art.</p>
<p>Cette instruction génèrale faite en vue d’obtenir les diplomes de l’université de France, ne devra pas empècher l’étude particulière de la langue maternelle des jeunes étrangers et de l’histoire de leur pays. A cet effet, des maitres nationaux leur seront donnés.</p>
<p>Ces jeunes gens trouveront chez M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. et M<hi rend="superscript">me</hi>. Ernest Lavigne, dans leur maison située dans un des plus beaux quartiers et des plus aèrés de Paris, les soins affectueux et delicats de la famille avec un paternelle surveillance.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ils vivront comme les enfants de la maison: chacun aura sa chambre particulière comfortablement meublée et ils jouirent tous de cette sage liberté qui laisse à l’esprit son essor et rend le travail fructueux en le faisant agréable.</p>
<p>Sous la direction d’un maitre expèrimenté tel que M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne, il n’est pas tèmèraire d’assurer que les jeunes gens placès sous sa direction obtiendront leurs diplomes dans un temps relativement court.</p>
<p>Je n’entierai point dans le détail des ètudes qui suivront les les èlèves de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne: le programme des ètudes classiques est suffisamment connu. Mais il me parait utile d’insister sur un point important que devront grandement apprècier, suivant moi, les familles.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne jugeant justement qu’une èducation reste incomplète si l’élève en même temps qu’il reçoit l’instruction proprement dite, n’èlève pas son esprit par d’utiles récrèations, entend que les jeunes gens qui lui seront confiés suivront le mouvement de la littèrature actuelle les progrès qui se rattachent aux Beaux Arts et à l’industrie   En consèquence, au moins <hi rend="underline">deux fois</hi> par mois, les èlèves de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne seront conduits dans les principaux théatres de Paris, dans les concerts de choix, aux expositions de peinture, aux expositions industrielles, <hi rend="underline">etc.</hi> de telle sorte qu’il ne resteront ètrangers à rien de ce qui peut alimenter sainement l’intelligence et fortifier l’imagination.</p>
<p>Entre tous les jeunes gens, ceux qui se trouvent momentanèment èloignés de leurs parents ont plus particulièrement besoin de nobles distractions. L’education du beau privilège exclusif des enfants èlevès dans leur famille, les pensionnaires de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne la recevront à Paris, sans qu’il encoute aux parents aucun surcroit de depense.</p>
<p>En effet, nul supplèment ne viendra se joindre au prix invariable de la pension pour les thèatres, les concerts, les visites aux expositions, aux musèes, en un mot pour aucun des divertissements aux quels M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne croira pouvoir conduire ses èlèves, pas plus que pour les soins à donner en cas de maladie, par le médecin attachè à la maison.</p>
<p>Le prix de la pension est de 5,000 francs par an, payables par semestre d’avance.</p>
<p>Telle est en peu de mots, monsieur et honorè collègue, l’exposé du plan d’èducation particulière adoptè par M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne. Il m’a paru qu’il était de nature à intèresser les familles étrangères et je prends la liberté de vous recommander mon gendre.</p>
<p>Comme homme de science, ses ètudes brillantes entre toutes et ses titres universitaires le recommandent suffisamment; aussi est-ce bien plutot pour me porter garant des soins intelligents et affectueux dont seront entourés les èlèves chez mon fils et ma fille, qui, en père de famille, je m’adresse aux pères de famille.</p>
<p>Permettez-moi de vous prier de communiquer les présentes explications aux personnes qui seraient dans l’intention d’envoyer leurs enfants à Paris pour y faire une éducation sèrieuse et obtenir leurs diplomes.</p>
<p>Je vous serais reconnaissant, Monsieur et honoré collègue, si vous trouviez le temps de m’accuser rèception de cette lettre, et je vous prie de recevoir à l’avance tous mes remerciements pour ce que vous voudrez bien faire en faveur de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne.</p>
<p>Avec mes salutations les plus distinguèes | Oscar Comettant | homme de lettres, Directeur de l’institut musical<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">64, rue Neuve des Petits champs, Paris.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Institut Musical | 64, rue Neuve-des-Petits-Champs</hi> Paris,</placeName>
                    <date>1 July 1877</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I write to you in the capacity of a colleague, having taken part in the latest congress of Americanists at Nancy,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> to bring to your attention the following fact.</p>
<p>My son-in-law, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne, former pupil of the École normale supérieure, member of the university of France, man of letters and translator of Lucretius,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> has decided to take into his home six young foreigners (maximum number) in order to give them university-level instruction, prepare them for the school-leaving certificate, and fit them to pursue the various studies of medicine, law, or to take up any other scientific or artistic career.</p>
<p>This general instruction, made with a view to obtaining the diplomas of the university of France, ought not to prevent the particular study of the native language of the young foreigners and of the history of their country. To this effect, teachers of their own nationality will be provided for them.</p>
<p>These young people will find at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. and M<hi rend="superscript">me</hi>. Ernest Lavigne’s, in their house situated in one of the most beautiful districts in Paris and with the freshest air,  the affectionate and delicate care of a family with a fatherly supervision.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> They will live like children of the family: each will have his own room, comfortably furnished, and they will all enjoy that wise liberty that lets the spirit rise and makes work fruitful by making it agreeable.</p>
<p>Under the direction of an experienced master like M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne, it is not reckless to assure you that the young people placed under his direction will obtain their diplomas in a relatively short time.</p>
<p>I will not enter at all into the details of the studies that the pupils of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne will follow: the syllabus of classical studies is well known. However, it seems worthwhile to insist on one important point that families, I think, will greatly appreciate.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne, judging correctly that an education is incomplete if the student, at the same time as he receives instruction properly so called, does not elevate his spirit with useful amusements, intends that the young people entrusted to his care should follow the movement of current literature, the progresses that relate to the fine arts and industry.  As a result, at least <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> a month, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne’s pupils will be taken to the principal theatres of Paris, to the best concerts, to exhibitions of paintings, to industrial exhibitions, <hi rend="underline">etc.</hi>, so that they will not be strangers to anything that could healthily nourish the intelligence and invigorate the imagination.</p>
<p>Of all young people, those who find themselves momentarily far from their parents have more particular need of high-minded entertainments. The education that is the exclusive and noble privilege of children brought up at home, the boarders at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne’s will receive in Paris, without any additional expense on the part of the parents.</p>
<p>Indeed, there will be no addition to the fixed rate for boarders for theatres, concerts, visits to exhibitions, to museums, in a word, for any of the diversions to which M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne believes he can take his pupils, any more than there will be for the care to be given in case of illness, by the doctor attached to the house.</p>
<p>The cost of boarding is 5,000 francs a year, payable six months in advance.</p>
<p>Such is, in a few words, sir and honoured colleague, the statement of the particular plan of education adopted by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lavigne. It seems to me to be the sort of thing that would interest foreign families and I take the liberty of recommending my son-in-law to you.</p>
<p>As a man of science, his brilliant studies above all and his university qualifications sufficiently recommend him; also it is rather for me to give a guarantee of the intelligent and affectionate care with which pupils will be surrounded at the home of my son and daughter, I who, the father of a family, address myself to fathers of families.</p>
<p>Allow me to beg you to communicate these details to persons who intend to send their children to Paris to undertake a genuine education and obtain their diplomas.</p>
<p>I would be grateful to you, Sir and honoured colleague, if you found the time to acknowledge receipt of this letter, and please accept in advance my thanks for anything you might be willing to do in favour of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ernest Lavigne.</p>
<p>With my best regards | Oscar Comettant | man of letters, director of the Musical Institute<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">64, rue Neuve des Petits champs, Paris.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The first international congress of Americanists took place at Nancy, France, in 1875 (<hi rend="italic">Compte-rendu du Congrès international des Américanistes</hi>, vol. 1). The congress brought together experts on the ethnology, linguistics, geography, history, archaeology, and sociology of the Americas.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See Lucretius 1870.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernest Lavigne’s</ref> wife was Comettant’s daughter, Ernestine Clara. The location of their home is unknown.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>