<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5133">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Bartholomew James Sulivan   27 June 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10818</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5133 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5133.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5133.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 286</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 286</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml">Sulivan, B. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                <date when="1866-06-27">27 June 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on his health.</p>
            <p>Discusses a surveying expedition under Richard Charles Mayne on which his son will be Second Lieutenant; hopes to arrange for them to excavate some bones in the Falklands.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, good or improving</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3246">Mayne, R. C.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4615">Sulivan, J. Y. F.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Falklands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                    <date>June 27/66</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am indeed glad to get such a cheering letter from you—and to hear that you have such a prospect of restored health.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Up to three months ago I was in hopes I was getting better, for I had lost all the pains in joints &amp;c. and my pulse and general circulation was stronger;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but either from my head not being able to stand this—or because the complaint was making more progress, I became very unwell with head symptoms—such as pain in the frontal region if I stoop or cough or on the least thing trying my head; &amp; though for some time time I have been regularly under the best doctor here I get little—if any—better. I believe it is entirely caused by congestion of all the small vessels of the brain.</p>
<p>about three months since my eldest boy came home promoted—having got the annual surveying promotion from the surveying ship in Mediterranean:<ref target="#foot.f3"/> he had suffered from Rheumatism—and was advised to try the hot air baths of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Barter at Blarney—Co. Cork—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>He came back in six weeks well &amp; strong: &amp; the Doctor assured him that they would do my head great good— Finding him still very confident about it after sending him particulars of my case, and as I get no better here I think of going over there with my wife and eldest daughter next week.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I shall also escape the bother I have with the work of my house because some builders here think nothing of breaking contracts &amp; delaying work they have pledged themselves to do, and it is with difficulty I have been able to get common exertions made to finish it though promised me by 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of August, &amp; not likely to be ready by 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of October.</p>
<p>And now having tried your patience with personal matters, I must tell you that my boy is going out as 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Lieut with Mayne,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> and that I have been looking forward to interesting Mayne &amp; his Naturalist in a further search for “<hi rend="underline">my bones</hi>”,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> having been giving my boy full particulars, &amp; I meant to urge it on Richards (Hydrographer), also—who was my second Lieut. &amp; with me cutting them out.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> So with the aid of First Lord I have no doubt it will be easily managed<ref target="#foot.f9"/>   If I were well I should enjoy going with them and being landed at Falklands, for the summer, after a months good work at the “diggings”—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I look forward to going on Board Nassau at Portsmouth &amp; pointing every thing out to Mayne. His vessel is a very long unhandy vessel for Gallegos, &amp; I should not like to take her in there in such a tide &amp; intricate channel, but there is a nice safe anchorage just outside; inside a good bank, &amp; so thoroughly sheltered, &amp; this removes all objection on that score. They could pitch a tent on the far shore of the River opposite the bones, &amp; in three or four days load all their boats twice over, with a good party—but to get the bones out carefully there would be work for a month—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>The Nassau is not going out for the survey of Straits of M. Her chief object is the better survey of the Smythe &amp; Baker channels, &amp; the best anchorages on them;<ref target="#foot.f12"/> which is much wanted now that many large steamers go that way. at the same time she will make larger plans of some of the Harbours in the Straits. In one, through one channel in not being surveyed, a French screw line of battle ship was nearly lost and had to go back leaking to Rio Janeiro.</p>
<p>She will also complete the sounding of Possession Bay, &amp; the best positions for anchoring outside the narrows; this was left very unfinished.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>I have seen published lists of the FitzRoy subscription.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I had one sent me but cannot now lay my hand on it— It was through that, that I knew of your handsome contribution to it.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> I have heard twice from M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. FitzRoy:<ref target="#foot.f16"/> but do not know what has been done with the testimonial fund. I suppose you saw that his Son was promoted into a death vacancy soon after going out in Commodores ship last year to Africa, so he has a good start—being a Commander about 26,—as times go.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>My second boy went out in a new surveying ship to N America, under Hope; and on his arrival had a Lieuts commission given him in a death vacancy, which had afterwards to <hi rend="underline">be cancelled</hi> because his ship did not get on the station <hi rend="underline">till two hours after the death.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f18"/> I was not sorry as his elder brother was not then promoted.</p>
<p>all my party are well. my wife joins me in kind regards to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Darwin &amp; your daughters—<ref target="#foot.f19"/> Believe me my dear Darwin | Yours most sincerely | B J Sulivan</p>
<p>I will take care to have written particulars prepared if I am not able myself to see Mayne &amp; the Naturalist. Hooker<ref target="#foot.f20"/> should ask Richards to further it &amp; I will write also. B J S</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter from CD to Sulivan has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Sulivan had suffered health problems in 1864, and had resigned his position as chief naval officer in the Marine Department at the Board of Trade in 1865 because of his continued ill health (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4831.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 8 May [1865]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Young Falkland Sulivan</ref> had served as sub-lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="italic">Firefly</hi>, stationed in the Mediterranean, from November 1864; he was promoted to the rank of lieutenant in January 1866 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Navy list</hi></ref>). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4831.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 8 May [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The physician <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Barter</ref> ran a hydrotherapy establishment in Blarney, County Cork, Ireland, offering hot-air baths and Turkish baths (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Sulivan refers to his wife, Sophia, and to their eldest daughter, Sophia Henrietta. Sulivan did undergo treatment by Barter (see Sulivan ed. 1896, p. 391).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Young Falkland Sulivan</ref> served as lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="italic">Nassau</hi> from 1866 to 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Navy list</hi></ref>); the vessel surveyed the Straits of Magellan from 1866 to 1869 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cunningham 1871</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Charles Mayne</ref> was the commander of the <hi rend="italic">Nassau</hi> during the survey expedition (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5089.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 13 May 1866</ref> and n. 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The naturalist on HMS <hi rend="italic">Nassau</hi> was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1159.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Oliver Cunningham</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4996.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 4 February 1866</ref> and n. 4). In January 1845, while commanding HMS <hi rend="italic">Philomel</hi>, Sulivan had discovered the fossil bones of mammals at the base of a cliff along the Río Gallegos in Patagonia (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, letters from B. J. Sulivan, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-730.xml" resp="#automat">13 January – 12 February 1845</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-886.xml" resp="#automat">4 July 1845</ref>). Six casks of bones were collected and sent to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref>, who described several of the findings (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-984.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Richard Owen, 21 [June 1846]</ref>; <hi rend="italic">Report of the 16th meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science held at Southampton in 1846</hi>, Transactions of the sections, p. 66, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6084.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Owen 1853</ref>). For CD’s interest in the findings, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-864.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [4 June 1845]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-923.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to C. G. Ehrenberg, 29 October [1845]</ref>. For Sulivan’s interest in returning to the site, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Richard Owen, 28 April [1850]</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3836.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Arthur Mellersh, 30 November [1862]</ref>. Sulivan’s discovery is discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_903.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Brinkman 2003</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3995.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Henry Richards</ref> was lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="italic">Philomel</hi> (Sulivan ed. 1896, p. 56); he became hydrographer to the Admiralty in 1863 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Modern English biography</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The first lord of the Admiralty was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4306.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Adolphus Seymour Seymour</ref>, twelfth duke of Somerset (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Sulivan had surveyed the Falkland Islands from 1837 to 1839, and lived there from 1848 to 1851 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The search for the fossils took place in December 1867 and May 1868. The ship’s naturalist, Cunningham, reported that the strata were rapidly disintegrating, and that few specimens of any size or value were found, except for one fossil cranium of a large quadruped, later identified by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> as a new genus of mammal allied to <hi rend="italic">Anoplotherium</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cunningham 1871</ref>, pp. 279–82, 469–73).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The Smyth Channel is north of the western end of the Strait of Magellan, between the Archipiélago de la Reina Adelaida and the Península de Muñoz Gamero. The Baker Channel is at the southern end of the Golfo de Penas. (<hi rend="italic">Times atlas.</hi>)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Possession Bay is on the north side of Bahía de Lomas, at the eastern entrance to the Strait of Magellan (Mapa de Chile, 1: 3.000.000. Instituto Geográfico Militar, Santiago, 1975). HMS <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> had visited Possession Bay on 24 January 1834 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref>, Appendix).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> commanded HMS <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> during the 1831 to 1836 voyage on which Sulivan was second lieutenant and CD naturalist and companion to FitzRoy (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1). FitzRoy committed suicide on 30 April 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13). A testimonial fund was set up for his family (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Shaw, 3 October 1865</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">CD had subscribed £100 to the FitzRoy testimonial fund (CD’s Classed account books (Down House MS), 4 October 1865).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maria Isabella FitzRoy</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5660.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert O’Brien FitzRoy</ref> had served as flag lieutenant of HMS <hi rend="italic">Bristol</hi>, stationed on the west coast of Africa, from 7 October 1865, and became commander of the vessel on 1 February 1866; the commodore of the vessel was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5946.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geoffrey Thomas Phipps Hornby</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Navy list</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4618.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Edward Sulivan</ref> was sub-lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="italic">Gannet</hi> from July 1865; from December 1866, he was lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="italic">Duncan</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Navy list</hi></ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5943.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Hope</ref> was navy commander-in-chief in North America and the West Indies (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Sulivan refers to Emma, Henrietta Emma, and Elizabeth Darwin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>