<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2449">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. R. Wallace   6 April 1859</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14947</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2449 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2449.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2449.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 202</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Marchant (1916) 1: 136;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 118</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 279</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">The British Library (Add MS 46434)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Add MS 46434</collection>
                    <idno/>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1859-04-06">6 Apr 1859</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>First part of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> MS is with Murray;</p> 
            <p>CD hopes he has noticed ARW’s work fairly.</p> 
<p>ARW is right in thinking that CD was led to believe that selection was the principle of change from studying domesticated productions and that after reading Malthus he "saw at once how to apply this principle". Geographical distribution and geological relations of extinct and recent inhabitants of S. America first led him to the subject, "Especially case of Galapagos Islds". Hooker and Lubbock are full converts and Huxley now believes in species mutation. "We shall live to see all the <hi rend="italic">younger</hi> men converts."</p> 
            <p>Praises ARW’s work and spirit.</p>
            <p>CD had actually written a letter to ARW stating he would not publish before him but was persuaded by Lyell and Hooker to allow them to act "as they thought fair &amp; honourably".</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3149">Malthus, T. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3463">Murray, John (b)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">extinction</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>April 6 /59</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wallace</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I this morning received your pleasant &amp; friendly note of Nov. 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. <ref target="#foot.f1"/> The first part of my M.S is in Murray’s hands to see if he likes to publish it. There is no preface, but a short Introduction, which must be read by everyone, who reads my Book. The second Paragraph in the Introduction, I have had copied <hi rend="underline">verbatim</hi> from my foul copy, &amp; you will, I hope, think that I have fairly noticed your paper in Linn. Transacts—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You must remember that I am now publishing only an Abstract &amp; I give no references.— I shall of course allude to your paper on Distribution; &amp; I have added that I know from correspondence that your explanation of your law is the same as that which I offer.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You are right, that I came to conclusion that Selection was the principle of change from study of domesticated productions; &amp; then reading Malthus I saw at once how to apply this principle.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Geographical Distrib. &amp; Geological relations of extinct to recent inhabitants of S. America first led me to subject. Especially case of Galapagos Isl<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi>.—</p>
<p>I hope to go to press in early part of next month.— It will be small volume of about 500 pages or so.— I will of course send you a copy. I forget whether I told you that Hooker, who is our best British Botanist &amp; perhaps best in World, is a <hi rend="underline">full</hi> convert, &amp; is now going immediately to publish his confession of Faith; &amp; I expect daily to see the proof-sheets.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Huxley is changed &amp; believes in mutation of species: whether a <hi rend="underline">convert</hi> to us, I do not quite know.— We shall live to see all the <hi rend="underline">younger</hi> men converts. My neighbour &amp; excellent naturalist J. Lubbock is enthusiastic convert.</p>
<p>I see by Nat. Hist notices that you are doing great work in the Archipelago;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> &amp; most heartily do I sympathise with you. For God sake take care of your health. There have been few such noble labourers in the cause of Natural Science as you are.</p>
<p>Farewell, with every good wish | Yours sincerely | C. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. | You cannot tell how I admire your spirit, in the manner in which you have taken all that was done about publishing our papers. I had actually written a letter to you, stating that I would <hi rend="underline">not</hi> publish anything before you had published. I had not sent that letter to the Post, when I received one from Lyell &amp; Hooker, <hi rend="underline">urging</hi> me to send some M.S. to them, &amp; allow them to act as they thought fair &amp; honourably to both of us. &amp; I did so.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 paper] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘papers’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.13 inhabitants of S. America] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">5.3 had published.] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘did.’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">5.4 to the Post,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">5.6 &amp; I did so—] <hi rend="italic">added</hi>; ‘&amp;’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘—’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Wallace’s letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Apparently CD enclosed a copy of the relevant paragraph in his letter. The text in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 1–2, reads: <quote> My work is now nearly finished; but as it will take me two or three more years to complete it, and as my health is far from strong, I have been urged to publish this Abstract. I have more especially been induced to do this, as Mr. Wallace, who is now studying the natural history of the Malay archipelago, has arrived at almost exactly the same general conclusions that I have on the origin of species. Last year he sent to me a memoir on this subject, with a request that I would forward it to Sir <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, who sent it to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>, and it is published in the third volume of the Journal of that Society. Sir C. Lyell and Dr. Hooker, who both knew of my work—the latter having read my sketch of 1844—honoured me by thinking it advisable to publish, with Mr. Wallace’s excellent memoir, some brief extracts from my manuscripts.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 355, CD stated: ‘This view of the relation of species in one region to those in another, does not differ much (by substituting the word variety for species) from that lately advanced in an ingenious paper by Mr. Wallace, in which he concludes, that “every species has come into existence coincident both in space and time with a pre-existing closely allied species.”’ CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1855</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Malthus 1826</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Hooker 1859 was the first scientific work to discuss CD’s theories at length.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Several of Wallace’s letters to his natural history agent <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Stevens</ref> were published in the <hi rend="italic">Zoologist</hi> and in the Proceedings of the Entomological Society during 1858 and 1859. Many of his specimens, particularly his entomological and ornithological specimens, were exhibited at meetings of the Zoological Society and the Entomological Society and reported in their printed proceedings and in <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See the correspondence between CD, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> in June 1858.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>