<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10391">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   14 February [1876]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6712</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10391 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10391.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10391.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Thiselton-Dyer, W.T., Letters from Charles Darwin 1873–81: 22a)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Thiselton-Dyer, W. T. letters: 22a</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent" subtype="personGrp">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1876-02-14">14 Feb [1876]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Asks for identification of a <hi rend="italic">Cineraria</hi> which is self-sterile.</p>  
<p>Fritz Müller’s letter on <hi rend="italic">Cecropia</hi> [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">10384</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">10384</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Cineraria</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cecropia</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Feb 14. 1875</date>
                    <salute>Dear Dyer</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Will you be so kind as to tell me the name of the common greenhouse vars of Cinerarea such as the enclosed.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> They have thick stems which I think cannot be called woody. I want to know because they offer one of those curious cases of a plant absolutely sterile with its own pollen, but fertile with that on any other plant of the same or another variety.</p>
<p>Secondly—I have a great straggling bush 7 or 8 feet high of an unnamed sp of Pleroma from Kew. It bears large &amp; really handsome purple flowers. Shall I return it; but if so I think it must be cut back. I enclose seeds of which if as is probable of no value may be thrown away.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Thirdly: I hope that you &amp; Hooker will read the second paragraph of a letter by Fritz Müller in next Nature about the little excrescences in Cecropia closely like those on the tips of the leaflets of the Bulls horn Acacia described by Belt. Müller speaks of them as containing albumen but Frank at present finds not much of this but on the other hand an abundance of oil globules.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> This production of food for the protective ants seems to me extremely curious, and Frank wishes to trace the developement &amp; nature of these bodies. Would you therefore ask Hooker to get one of the bull’s horn acacias propogated for us. I have written to Müller to ask for seeds of the Cecropia; but if you can find time after you have read Müller letter, will you look at any Cecropias in your houses, to see whether you can find anything of the kind that he describes; and if so have a plant propagated for us.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I must tell you an odd coincidence. I mistook in Müllers letter and read Ceropegia &amp; so went &amp; looked at my <hi rend="underline">C. stephanotis</hi> and lo &amp; behold at the place where the petiole joins the leaf I found five or 6 little conical bodies something like the excrescences on Cecropia but of a black colour.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Believe me dear Dyer | Yrs sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S I received an uncommonly nice note from R. Lankester about Linnean Soc. affair.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I continue my fathers letter with, I am ashamed to say, one more request; pray forgive me for troubling you in this way. I enclose the papers in which D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker was so good as to send me some grass seeds, would you kindly let me have their names written on them clearly— I have failed to make them out with Steudel.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Also would you let me know how morphologically to describe the awn of Stipa compared with that eg of Avena? I send one as a reminder— The twisting research has turned out v interesting I think &amp; I have all but finished my paper &amp; drawings—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I was delighted at the collapse of the blackballers &amp; at Lankesters triumphant entry<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Yours sincerely | Francis Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">4.1 Ch. … affair.— 5.2] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10394.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Thomas Moore to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 15 February 1876</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref>, the amanuensis, evidently wrote 1875 in error.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Florist’s cineraria (<hi rend="italic">Pericallis</hi> x <hi rend="italic">hybrida</hi>) is a hybrid of endemic species from the Canary Islands, <hi rend="italic">P. cruenta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P. lanata</hi>, and possibly other species. The genus name <hi rend="italic">Cineraria</hi> is now mostly restricted to South African species (Cron <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. 2006).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Pleroma</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Tibouchina</hi>, a neotropical plant genus of the family Melastomataceae. An entry in the <hi rend="italic">Inwards book</hi> (Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew) for 21 February 1876 records the receipt of seeds of <hi rend="italic">Pleroma</hi> from CD; the receipt of a plant of <hi rend="italic">Pleroma</hi> is recorded on 3 March 1876.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Müller’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10324.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to CD of 25 December 1875</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23) was printed in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 17 February 1876, pp. 304–5. Müller had enclosed specimens of the small white bodies (now known as Müllerian bodies) found on the cushion-like structure (now called the trichilium) at the base of the petiole of leaves of <hi rend="italic">Cecropia</hi> (the embauba or trumpet-tree). Francis was evidently studying their nutrient composition. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> had sent CD a specimen of bull-horn acacia in 1874 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10384.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, [9 February 1876]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">An entry in the <hi rend="italic">Outwards book</hi> (Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew) for 17 February 1876 records the dispatch to CD of <hi rend="italic">Acacia cornigera</hi> (bull-horn acacia) and <hi rend="italic">Cecropia peltata</hi> (the embauba or trumpet-tree).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Ceropegia stephanotis</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Stephanotis floribunda</hi> (stephanotis or Madagascar jasmine).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester’s</ref> letter to CD has not been found. Lankester had been elected a member of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 3 February 1876; CD and Francis had made a trip to London in order that they could attend the meeting and vote for Lankester (<hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London</hi> (1875–6), p. iii; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, [4 February 1876]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Hooker had sent Francis grass seeds from India (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10215.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 23 October 1875</ref>). There is an annotated copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4552.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Gottlieb Steudel’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Nomenclator botanicus</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Steudel 1841</ref>) in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 788–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Francis was studying the ability of some awned seeds to bury themselves in the ground; most of his research was based on observation of seeds of <hi rend="italic">Stipa pennata</hi> (feather grass). <hi rend="italic">Avena</hi> is the genus of oats; Francis used <hi rend="italic">A. elatior</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Arrhenatherum elatius</hi>, false oat grass) in his experiments. His paper ‘On the hygroscopic mechanism by which certain seeds are enabled to bury themselves in the ground’ appeared in <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Linnean Society</hi> in June 1876 (F. Darwin 1876c).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">When Thiselton-Dyer first proposed Lankester for membership in the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> in 1875, Lankester was blackballed by several members because the Council had proposed remission of his fees. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 2 December 1875</ref>. See also n. 7, above.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>