<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7911">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From V. O. Kovalevsky   19 August [1871]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17791</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7911 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7911.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7911.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 66</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 66</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2751.xml">Kovalevsky, V. O.</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1871-08-19">19 Aug [1871]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>A. J. Gaudry is one of few supporters of Darwinism in Paris.</p>
            <p>The climate is so hostile that Kovalevsky must mitigate his views so as not to irritate the French.</p> 
<p>Working on <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium</hi>, which he believes is intermediate between <hi rend="italic">Palaeotherium</hi> and the horse.</p> 
            <p>His brother-in-law has been arrested.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Anchitherium</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">horse</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Palaeotherium</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">French</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1829">Gaudry, A. J.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Kovalevsky, V. O.’s brother-in-law</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Paris</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">intermediate forms, gradation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">arrested</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris | 18. Boulevard St. Michel</placeName>
                    <date>19 Aug.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>What a long time I had no news from You and feel that it is all by my own fault. Your last letter to Berlin<ref target="#foot.f2"/> came together with another, from Paris, stating the arrest of my brother in law, my wife was so alarmed at the position of her sister left alone, that we took the same evening the train to Paris and from that time are staying here trying to do something through our Embassy; I have seen the man nearest to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thiers M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barthelemy St. Hilaire and hope to obtain a decree of banishment.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Happily I have not quite lost my time in Paris, and through the kindness of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gervais<ref target="#foot.f4"/> did get access to all the collections of the Paris Museums. In the cellars of the Laboratoire d’Anatomie Comparée I found a large quantity of chests with fossils from Sansan, collected by Lartet, and seeing among them many bones of Anchiterium resolved to study this genus nearer than it was done by Blainville.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> By and by the quantity of bones found in different places grew very large, a block of stone proved to contain the whole head (quite unknow till now) and gradually I came to the idea of publishing a monography of Anchiterium as a first essay in Palaeontology.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gervais gave the permission to publish the description of all they have and I am now very busy comparing bones of Palaeoth. Hipparion and horse with my Anchiterium.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have the animal nearly complete, as good as a living one and a head though crushed but with a full dentition: six molars in each jaw, the seventh coming into place, and three permanent premolars in both jaws quite formed and ready to push the milk premolars out. I think it is the most precious head any collection can boast, fancy only 40 molars beautifully preserved in one head; I have exposed the 12 permanent premolars by breaking the outer wall of both jaws. The animal is very curious presenting a mixed type of horse and Palaeoterium; the head is quite Palaeotherian, the extremities, the carpus and tarsus are hippoid but still with Palaeoterian affinities, so the large metacarpal (the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.) is hippoid in his upper part and quite Palaeotherian in the lower, the articular surface for the phalangi beeing quite the same as in Palaeotherium with the middle ridge extending over only one half of the lower articular head and not on the whole as in Hipparion and horse.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Notwithstanding all this the French are dead against You and I must really mitigate my <hi rend="underline">Darwinisme</hi> not to irritate them.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Still you have here a great friend of Your views, this is M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gaudry but even he dares not to do it openly as “le Darwinisme est en mauvaise odeur au Jardin des Plantes”.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> But even M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gaudry is opposed to my views of making from the Anchiterium a transitional type between Palaeotherium and horse, saying that one has quite an omnivorous the other a ruminant dentition, but I hope that a series of milk teeth in the happiest state (worn down so as to present the two crescents characteristic for ruminants) will help us over this difficulty.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Before going to print I shall certainly see You an take Your opinion on the matter.</p>
<p>But my letter is getting to long, I hope to have some lines from You, my best compliments to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Darwin and the ladies<ref target="#foot.f12"/> | Your truly | W. Kowalevsky</p>
<p>Have You read Kupfer’s “Verwandschaft zwischen Ascidien und Wirbelthiere” in the second number of the Archiv für Mikroskopische Anatomie for 1870, it will greatly interest You.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to the arrest of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5986.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Victor Jaclard</ref> (see n. 3, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-7796.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to V. O. Kovalevsky, 2 June [1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Jaclard was a member of the socialist government of the Paris Commune and was arrested in June 1871 after the commune fell to the national government. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7583.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 14 March 1871</ref>. Jaclard’s partner, Anna Korvin-Krukovskaya, was a sister of Kovalevsky’s wife, Sofia Vasilyevna Kovalevskaya. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6859.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Adolphe Thiers</ref> was the leader of the French national government; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6053.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jules Barthélemy-Saint-Hilaire</ref> had helped bring him to power. Kovalevsky helped Jaclard and Korvin-Krukovskaya escape to Switzerland, where they were formally married, and then to Russia. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DBF</hi></ref>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delfau 1971</ref>, p. 75; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koblitz 1983</ref>, pp. 108–9.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paul Gervais</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The fossils of <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium</hi>, a three-toed, browsing member of the horse family, had been discovered at Sansan by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2819.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Lartet</ref> after the publication of Henri Blainville’s classification of fossil vertebrates (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_687.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Blainville 1841–55</ref>; see preface to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4482.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">V. O. Kovalevsky 1872</ref>). Lartet had adopted the name <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium aurelianense</hi> in place of <hi rend="italic">Palaeotherium aurelianense</hi> by 1868 (Université de Toulouse, <hi rend="italic">Edouard et Louis Lartet, pionniers des études préhistoriques</hi>, Carnets autographes d’Eduard, 1: Notes de travail ‘Elephas bombifrons’, www.biu-toulouse.fr/num150/lartet/ (accessed 24 September 2010); see this site for a comprehensive collection of Lartet’s personal papers). The Laboratoire d’anatomie comparée was part of the Muséum d’histoire naturelle, Paris.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Kovalevsky refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4482.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">V. O. Kovalevsky 1872</ref>. Kovalevsky was one of the first to interpret fossils according to Darwinian theories of evolution (see n. 11, below); he published eight monographs on the paleontology of ungulates showing their adaptation to their environment (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vucinich 1988</ref>, pp. 62–8; see also S. J. Gould ed. 1980).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Palaeotherium</hi>, an Eocene branch of the family Equidae, and <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium</hi>, a younger branch of the same family, were both browsing horses; the Hipparion group, which includes modern <hi rend="italic">Equus</hi>, is younger still, and comprises grazing horses. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">MacFadden 1992</ref>, p. 99.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Palaeotherium</hi> had three distinct toes; in <hi rend="italic">Hipparion</hi> the middle toe had developed into a hoof.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For the reception of Darwinism in France, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stebbins 1988</ref>, especially pp. 136–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Kovalevsky refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1829.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Albert Gaudry</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Le Darwinisme est en mauvaise odeur au Jardin des Plantes</hi>: Darwinism is extremely unpopular in the botanic garden. The Muséum d’histoire naturelle was in the botanic garden in Paris.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Gaudry is associated, along with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, with the theory that <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hipparion</hi> represent intermediate chronological stages in a simple lineal descent from <hi rend="italic">Palaeotherium</hi>, which had toes, to <hi rend="italic">Equus</hi>, which has hooves. In his most recent work on the fossil animals and geology of Attica, however, Gaudry, while recognising the similarities between <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hipparion</hi>, had not proposed any relationship between them; he classed <hi rend="italic">Anchitherium</hi> as a descendant of a line beginning with <hi rend="italic">Palaeotherium</hi>, and placed <hi rend="italic">Equus</hi> on a separate line of descent beginning with <hi rend="italic">Hipparion</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2748.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gaudry 1862–7</ref>, 1: 350–3). Kovalevsky recognised that the different forms had a common ancestor, but suggested that they had evolved separately at different periods, adapting through natural selection to different habitats, with resultant changes in dentition as well as the development of hooves (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4482.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">V. O. Kovalevsky 1872</ref>). For the history of evolution in equids see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">MacFadden 1992</ref>, especially pp. 28–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Kovalevsky refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> and her daughters, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref> and Elizabeth Darwin. Kovalevsky wrote a Russian lower-case cursive ‘t’ (which resembles a Roman lower-case cursive ‘m’) in the word ‘to’ in ‘compliments to’, so that in the manuscript the word looks like ‘mo’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Kovalevsky refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6095.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Wilhelm Kupffer</ref> and to his work on the relationship between ascidians and vertebrates (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4521.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kupffer 1870</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>