<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1909F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">To E. W. V. Harcourt   24 June [1856]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">21939</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1909F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1909F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1909F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt> 
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="endorsement" subtype="letter">1856.</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Bodleian Libraries, Oxford (MS. Harcourt dep. adds. 346, fols. 255–7)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_48.xml">Bodleian</repository>
                        <collection>Harcourt</collection>
                        <idno>MS. Harcourt dep. adds. 346, fols. 255–7</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                    <placeName>Down</placeName>
                    <date when="1856-06-24">24 June [1856]</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2102.xml">Harcourt, E. W. V.</persName>
                </correspAction>

            </correspDesc>
           <abstract>
                <p>Thanks EWVH for his offer but he is not likely to go to London soon to visit John Leadbeater, the bird dealer; he could take a rock pigeon for comparison, but other skins he would have compare at the British Museum.</p>
                <p>Would be obliged if EWVH could investigate domestic species in Egypt, especially a type of dog depicted in ancient monuments; and he is particularly interested in tumbler pigeons.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-01-21" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2019-03-01" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2019-07-22" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2020-05-05" status="sup-footnoted">Footnoted by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2021-06-09" status="sup-reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
            <change when="2021-08-24" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                        <date>June 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                        <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>I am very much obliged for your note &amp; will certainly take advantage of your offer &amp; visit M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Leadbeater, but I am not likely to go to London for some weeks.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I can take a Rock Pigeon for comparison; but for the swallows (&amp; perhaps a few other Birds) I could only compare them by taking them to the British Museum. Will you entrust them to me? I will pledge myself to take them back the same or next day: in this case, I fear, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have to trouble you to send me a line addressed to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Leadbeater, instructing him to give me the skins.—</p>
                        <p>I am particularly obliged for your kind offer of assistance in case you are compelled to go to Ægypt. On the most ancient monuments there is figured a greyhound-like Dog, but with longer pointed ears, &amp; an extraordinary <hi rend="underline">very</hi> short &amp; very much curled tail: Nott &amp; Gliddon in their curious Book assert that exactly the same variety now exists in N. Africa; &amp; I am very curious to hear whether this is really so, for it would be a truly wonderful instance of permanence in a variety, &amp; I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be very much obliged if you would make enquiries: I can hardly credit this statement of these not very accurate authors.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                        <p>The subject, which I am chiefly intent on, in regard to variation, is the Domestic Pigeon.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Skins are on their road to me sent by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Murray from Persia,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; I hope to get all the breeds from India &amp; China. Any assistance of this nature would be invaluable; but I know it is <hi rend="underline">much</hi> too troublesome to expect you yourself to skin birds for me, &amp; I fear there is little chance of your being able to find anyone who could skin; but if this were possible, &amp; you could hear of any breeds of Pigeon, believed to have been long kept in Ægypt, I would gratefully, with your permission, repay you for their purchase &amp; skinning. The Birds sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be adult   A Tumbler would be particularly valuable, &amp; I hope to get Tumblers from all quarters of the world.— Any observations on any of the domestic animals, as Ducks, Poultry, <hi rend="underline">Rabbits</hi> (the skeletons of which I am collecting with great pains),<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Dogs, or Cats, would be very interesting to me.—</p>
                        <p>I am sure you will see that I have taken your most kind offer in the most literal &amp; freest manner. With my very sincere thanks | I beg leave to remain | Dear Sir | Yours very faithfully | Charles Darwin</p>
                        <p>My hand is so tired with writing that I fear this note will be even less legible than at the best of times.—</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
               <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.6 to send] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘with’</note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.2 from Persia,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                   <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.8 The Birds … adult] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                   <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.10 (the] ‘t’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘whi’</note>
            </div> 
                
            </div>          

                      

                      

            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">Harcourt’s letter has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2851.xml">John Leadbeater</ref> was a taxidermist and bird dealer in London. CD next visited London on 14 August 1856 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6, Appendix II). CD wanted to compare Harcourt’s Madeiran bird specimens with others (see this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1900F.xml">letter to E. W. V. Harcourt, 12 June [1856]</ref>).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD cited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3562.xml">Josiah Clark Nott</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1891.xml">George Robbins Gliddon</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Types of mankind</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5913.xml">Nott and Gliddon 1854</ref>, p. 393) on the ancient Egyptian dog in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 17.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, pp. 20–8, and <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 131–224.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD cited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3460.xml">Charles Augustus Murray</ref>, a diplomat, for sending him pigeon skins from Persia in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, p. 20.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f5">Tumblers are a variety of domestic pigeons bred for their ability to tumble or roll over backwards in flight; several different types of tumbler were bred in Europe, Persia (Iran), and India. On rabbits’ skeletons, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1895.xml">letter to W. D. Fox, 8 [June 1856]</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            </div>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>