<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9035F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From V. O. Kovalevsky<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   30 August 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21159</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9035F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9035F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9035F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">V. O. Kovalevsky 1873–4, pp. [ii–iii]</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">V. O. Kovalevsky 1873–4, pp. [ii–iii]</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2751.xml">Kovalevsky, V. O.</persName>
                <date when="1873-08-30">30 Aug 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Talks of his attempts to describe the course of descent for a part of the animal kingdom, and thanks CD for his help and support.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Der fruchtbringende Einfluss Ihrer geistvollen Ideen auf alle Zweige der Naturwissenschaften musste selbstverständlich am meisten in der Palaeontologie und Geologie Anklang finden, denn eben in den Erdschichten, welche die erloschenen “Ringe der grossen Kette” bergen, müssen wir die positiven, unzweideutigen Belege für die von Ihnen begründete Descendenztheorie suchen. Ich habe versucht, gestützt auf genaue anatomische Grundlagen, den Gang dieser Descendenz für einen Theil des Thierreichs darzustellen, und darf wohl sagen, dass dieser Entwickelungsgang für einige der Haupttypen unserer noch heute existirenden Land-Säugethiere sich so klar darstellen lässt, dass man über die Richtigkeit der Abstammungstheorie schwerlich noch in Zweifel bleiben kann. Es gereicht mir zur grössten Freude, diesen Versuch Ihnen widmen zu dürfen, nicht weil ich ihn einer solchen Zueignung für besonders würdig erachte, sondern weil mir dadurch Gelegenheit geboten wird, die tiefe Verehrung, welche ich Ihnen persönlich zolle, auszudrücken.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Seit dem Anfange meiner Studien sind Sie für mich immer der beste Lehrer und der wärmste Freund gewesen; Sie haben stets allen meinen Arbeiten Ihr volles Interesse geschenkt und mir während meines längeren Aufenthalts in England alle Wege des Studiums geebnet.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Manche Sammlungen und Bibliotheken wurden mir durch Ihre Fürsprache zugänglich, die mir sonst vielleicht verschlossen geblieben wären, Ihr Name und Ihre Freundschaft waren für mich stets die beste Empfehlung, welche mir alle Pforten öffneten.</p>
<p>Die weitere Entwickelung und Ausbreitung der von Ihnen niedergelegten Grundsätze, ihre thatsächliche Begründung durch klare, unzweideutige Beispiele muss unvermeidlich dazu beitragen, die palaeontologische Wissenschaft in neue Bahnen zu lenken und ich sehe mit Zuversicht einer nahen Zukunft entgegen, wo die Abstammung aller Geschöpfe sich so einfach und klar darstellen lässt, wie die Abstammung der Gruppe, mit der ich hier beschäftigt war. Mehrere von diesen Abstammungslinien lassen sich schon jetzt, obwohl noch in unklaren Umrissen skizziren, und ich darf wohl hoffen, dass es mir in der Zukunft vergönnt wird, manche von diesen Fragen in der gastfreundlichen Einsiedlerschaft zu <hi rend="underline">Down</hi> gemeinschaftlich mit Ihnen zu besprechen, wie es auch bei einigen der hier behandelten der Fall war.</p>
<p>In treuer Ergebenheit | Ihr | W. Kowalevsky. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">München, den 30. August 1873.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The productive influence of your inspired ideas on all branches of science obviously had to gain the most favourable reception in palaeontology and geology, for it is precisely in the strata of the earth, which conceal the obscured “links of the great chain”, that we must look for positive, unambiguous evidence in favour of the theory of descent founded by you. I have attempted, supported by precise anatomical foundations, to represent the course of this descent for a part of the animal kingdom, and I believe I may claim that for some of the main types of our terrestrial mammals still in existence, this development can be described with such clarity that there can hardly remain any doubt about the truth of the theory of descent. It gives me the greatest pleasure to be allowed to dedicate this attempt to you, not so much because I deem it especially worthy of such a dedication, but rather because it gives me an opportunity to express the deep regard that I have for you personally.<ref target="#foot_trans.f2"/> From the beginning of my studies you have always been the best teacher and the warmest friend to me; you always bestowed your fullest attention on all my works, and during my extended stay in England, you smoothed the way for all my studies.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Many collections and libraries were accessible through your recommendation that would otherwise perhaps have remained closed to me. Your name and your friendship were always the best recommendation for me, which opened all doors to me.</p>
<p>The further development and dissemination of the principles laid down by you, their factual foundation through clear, unequivocal examples, must inevitably lead to palaeontological science taking new directions, and I anticipate with confidence a near future when the descent of all creatures can be portrayed in so simple and so clear a manner as the descent of the group dealt with here. A number of these lines of descent can already be sketched, though only in rough outlines, and I may well hope that I will yet have the opportunity to discuss some of these issues with you in the hospitable seclusion of <hi rend="underline">Down</hi>, as was the case with some of the problems considered here.</p>
<p>In true devotion | Yours | W. Kowalevsky. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Munich, 30. August 1873.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 361–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">This dedicatory letter appears before the foreword to Kovalevsky’s monograph on <hi rend="italic">Anthracotherium</hi> (V. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kovalevsky 1873–4</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 17 May 1873</ref> and n. 3, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to V. O. Kovalevsky, 21 May 1873</ref>). CD’s annotated copy of the first two parts of the monograph is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f2">This dedicatory letter appears before the forword to Kovalevsky’s monograph on <hi rend="italic">Anthracotherium</hi> (V. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kovalevsky 1873–4</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 17 May 1873</ref> and n. 3, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to V. O. Kovalevsky, 21 May 1873</ref>). CD’s annotated copy of the first two parts of the monograph is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In 1872, Kovalevsky had been in England from mid-June until mid-October (Gaisinovich ed. 1988, pp. 180, 210–12).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>