<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10513">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From F. B. Zincke   23 [May 1876]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11156</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10513 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10513.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10513.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 184: 10</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>184: 10</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5299.xml">Zincke, F. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Ipswich</placeName>
                <date when="1876-05-23">23 [May 1876]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On communication noises used by domestic poultry.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">poultry</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Wherstead Vicarage. Ipswich.</placeName>
                    <date>23 〈May〉</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Language of domestic poultry—</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Since I read y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. works I have taken much interest in the habits &amp; variations of domestic poultry</p>
<p>I have an aviary in which I used years ago to keep small birds. Some weeks ago I placed in this a cock &amp; two hens. I soon found that the cock wished the hens to take possession of the box I had placed on the ground for the hens to lay in. For this purpose 〈he〉 w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. frequently get into the 〈bo〉x, &amp; when in w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. invite the hens to enter. This he did by uttering the same sounds as those with which the hen summons her chickens. The sound is something like “up, up, up, cup, cup, up, cup”.</p>
<p>No sooner however had a hen entered than he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. come out of the box, &amp;, standing in front of it, change his utterance to the hushing utterance of the hen when she warns her brood &amp; calls them to lie still beneath her wings. This utterance w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be some〈thing〉 like ya-a-a-ah ya-a-〈  〉<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Here is a change of “word”—〈    〉 with an understood purpose, &amp; so understood by the hens to which the words were addressed. I may also observe that the call of the poultrywomen to the fowls in a poultry yard to come to be fed, “cup, cup, cup” seems to be taken from the language of the birds themselves—for it is the call of the hen to the chickens to come to her for something she has to give them.</p>
<p>〈    〉 to variation of plumage— 〈five〉 or six years ago. I placed 〈in〉 my yard some game, 〈Do〉rking, Cochin China, Bramah putra, &amp; creve-cœur hens, with only Creve Cœur cocks.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Among all these there was not a white feather, &amp; all the cocks were raven black. From the first about 10 per cent of all the chickens came either pure white—or white with with several detached black feathers, or, in some instances with black &amp; yellow feathers on a generally white ground. I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. thus have got a breed of something like tor〈toise〉 shells. All these kinds had 〈    〉 <hi rend="underline">legs</hi> like the creve cœur fa〈ther〉</p>
<p>I also found that a small per centage of these half, or quarter bred creve cœurs came marked in a very similar manner to the golden Hamburgh<ref target="#foot.f4"/>—&amp; it was in order that I might get a strain of these that I shut up in the old aviary the cock, of whose language I have been giving you a specimen, &amp; the two hens—</p>
<p>I am yrs very faithfully | F. Barham Zincke.</p>
<p>P.S. And when the cock goes into the 〈bo〉x, &amp; turns about in it, &amp; 〈pre〉pares it for the hen, has 〈he〉 not <hi rend="underline">sympathy</hi> with her <hi rend="doubleUnderline">prospective</hi> wants? &amp; when does this, &amp; invites her to enter, &amp;, when she has entered, tries to keep her within the box, does he not <hi rend="underline">reason</hi>?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year and month are established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10515F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to F. B. Zincke, 26 May [1876]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 55, CD had considered bird communication with respect to songbirds, and wrote: <quote>The sounds uttered by birds offer in several respects the nearest analogy to language, for all the members of the same species utter the same instinctive cries expressive of their emotions; and all the kinds that have the power of singing exert this power instinctively; but the actual song, and even the call-notes, are learnt from their parents or foster-parents.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had discussed fowls in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 1: 236–89, noting that they all seemed to have diverged from a single type (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 236). Most breeders, however, claimed that fowl breeds were ancient and that the kinds bred true even in colour (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 242). Dorking and Cochin were breeds of fowl; crève-coeur were a subbreed of the crested or Polish breed; ‘Brahma Pootras’ were a recent breed formed by a cross and were similar to Cochins (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 237, 241, 258). In order to support his claim that all breeds were descended from a single species, CD had noted that the offspring of several crosses exhibited signs of reversion (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 255).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD described the Hamburgh breed of fowl in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 1: 238–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 46, CD had stated that all animals possessed some power of reasoning.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>