<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5210">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   10 September [1866]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3559</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5210 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5210.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5210.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 234</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 59;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 290, 306</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (92)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>92</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1866-09-10">10 Sept [1866]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>L. Agassiz’s evidence [for glaciation of America] is very weak.</p> 
<p>Thanks AG for arranging for American edition of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>, but doubts that the book will be successful.</p>  
<p>Has found no differences in pollen of <hi rend="italic">Rhamnus</hi> so cannot conjecture whether it is dimorphic.</p>  
<p>The common oxlip of England is certainly a hybrid between the primrose and the cowslip whereas <hi rend="italic">Primula elatior</hi> is a good species.</p> 
            <p>Reports experiments on the relative vigour of seedlings from cross- and self-fertilised plants.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cowslip</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">oxlip, common</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">primrose</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Primula elatior</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Rhamnus</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_43">Agassiz, J. L. R.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down. | Bromley. | Kent. S.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Sep 10</date>
                    <salute>My dear Gray</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Perhaps you will remember when one of my boys was terribly ill you sent him some stamps which he looked at, &amp; then after a long silence there came out the words “He is awfully kind”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> He never said a truer thing. In the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> place your note about Agassiz has interested &amp; amused me much;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> for the day before I had been reading the Atlantic Monthly &amp; the copy of a letter from M<hi rend="superscript">me</hi>. Agassiz to Lyell &amp; one from him all about the Amazonian glacier.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> We were both lost in astonishment at the nonsense which Agassiz writes &amp; I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not resist sending to Lyell a copy of part of your note, for his pre-determined wish partly explains what he fancies he observed. The evidence advanced by him is so weak that I do not think it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be admitted for the former existence of glaciers even in a temperate region.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>With respect to the Origin, you speak of reading the sheets, but Murray promised me to send you a bound copy.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> After all as there is no chance of a new edition perhaps it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be as well to let the Appletons have the sheets if they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> make any use of them; though on the other hand it is hardly worth while taking trouble about giving a few of the additions.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>With respect to my next book “on domestic animals” I am in perplexity, though most grateful to you for the capital bargain which you have made with Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Ticknor.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> My perplexity is this that I really have no idea whether it will be in the least degree popular; I am sure some chapters are curious, but then many others enter into far too minute details for the general reader: hence I do not quite like Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Ticknor to agree to publish until they have seen some of the sheets. And here comes the difficulty; there are about 42 wood-cuts &amp; it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> save great expence if metal copies were procured of these, &amp; to do this Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Ticknor w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have to make up their minds soon &amp; enter into some arrangement with Murray, as I think I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not ask Murray, who publishes at his own risk, to give copies; <hi rend="underline">though as far as I am concerned I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> willingly do so.</hi> I feel pretty sure that I shall not even begin to print till the beginning of next year.</p>
<p>Many thanks for the specimens of the Rhamnus; my son &amp; self have both looked at the pollen of both forms but alas! can make out no difference.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> The difference seems confined to the pistil &amp; to the peduncles. We cannot even conjecture whether this species is reciprocally dimorphic like Primula or is merely tending to become dioecious.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> This is a great disappointment to us &amp; the nature of the two forms c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> only be made out by experiment or by observing their seed-production in their natural state.</p>
<p>I suppose this species c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not be purchased in your nursery gardens—</p>
<p>In my last letter I asked you whether you knew of any striking cases of endemic or naturalized plants which never flowered or which never seeded; if at no time I get an answer I shall understand that you know of no cases like the Acorus or horse-radish in Europe.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>The only point which I have made out this summer which c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> possibly interest you is that the Common Oxlip found every where more or less commonly in England, is certainly a hybrid between the primrose &amp; cowslip; whilst the P. elatior found only in the Eastern Counties (<hi rend="underline">Jacq</hi>.) is a perfectly distinct &amp; good species; hardly distinguishable from the common oxlip except by the length of the seed-capsule relatively to the calyx. This seems to me rather a horrid fact for all systematic botanists.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I have just begun a large course of experiments on the germination of the seed &amp; on the growth of the young plants when raised from a pistil fertilized by pollen from the same flower, &amp; from pollen from a distinct plant of the same or of some other variety.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I have not made sufficient experiments to judge certainly, but in some cases the difference in the growth of the young plants is highly remarkable.</p>
<p>I have taken every kind of precaution in getting seed from the same plant, in germinating the seed on my own chimney-piece, in planting the seedlings in the same flower pot, &amp; under this similar treatment I have seen the young seedlings from the crossed seed exactly twice as tall as the seedlings from the self-fertilized seed; both seeds having germinated on same day. If I can establish this fact (but perhaps it will all go to the dogs) in some 50 cases, with plants of different orders, I think it will be very important, for then we shall positively know why the structure of every flower permits, or favours, or necessitates an occasional cross with a distinct individual.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> But all this is rather cooking my hare before I have caught it. But somehow it is a great pleasure to me to tell you what I am about.</p>
<p>Believe me my dear Gray | ever yours most truly | &amp; with cordial thanks | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.7 Agassiz] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand above del</hi> ‘he’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.8 fancies] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand above del</hi> ‘thinks’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.4 like Primula] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">9.3 young] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">9.5 both … day.] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">10.1 &amp; with cordial thanks] <hi rend="italic">added in CD’s hand</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 27 August 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">When <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin</ref> was recovering from scarlet fever, Gray had sent a selection of American postage stamps for his collection (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">10–20 June [1862]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3667.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">28 July [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 27 August 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Elizabeth Cabot Cary Agassiz’s letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> has not been found. It is likely that she enclosed a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz’s</ref> article from the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> (J. L. R. Agassiz 1866a), which Lyell then passed on to CD along with her letter. Lyell’s letter to CD has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5208.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to Charles Lyell, 8 [–9] September [1866]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For the portion of Gray’s 27 August 1866 letter that CD copied and sent to Lyell, see the postscript to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5208.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 8[–9] September [1866]</ref>. On the reasoning behind Agassiz’s theory, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5208.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 8[–9] September [1866]</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 27 August 1866</ref>. CD had asked his publisher, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">John Murray</ref>, to send copies of the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> to a number of people (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5155.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 15 July [1866]</ref> and n. 3). Gray’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD’s American publisher, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. Appleton &amp; Co</ref>., printed from stereotypes. Since CD had made major revisions (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. xi–xii), Appleton’s would have had to recast most of the book. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 18 July 1866</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>; Gray had told CD that he thought he could make an arrangement with the Boston firm <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4752.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ticknor &amp; Fields</ref> to publish it (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 27 August 1866</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Gray had enclosed specimens of the flowers of <hi rend="italic">Rhamnus lanceolatus</hi> with his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5184.xml">letter of 7 August 1866</ref>. In CD’s notes on <hi rend="italic">R. lanceolatus</hi> (DAR 109: A42 and 44), a table of pollen-grain sizes indicates a slight difference between those of long-styled and those of short-styled forms. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 295–6, CD noted a ratio of 10 to 9 in the diameter of pollen-grains in the two forms. CD’s son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Erasmus Darwin</ref> had observed a difference in the size of the pollen-grains of the two male forms of a related species, <hi rend="italic">R. cathartica</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5128.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. E. Darwin, 20 June [1866]</ref> and n. 5, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 295). William’s notes on the <hi rend="italic">R. lanceolatus</hi> specimens received from Gray, dated 28 August 1866, are in DAR 186: 43.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 295–6, CD noted that the pistil of the short-styled form of <hi rend="italic">Rhamnus lanceolatus</hi> was half to two-thirds the length of that of the long-styled form. Moreover, he noted the slightly larger size of pollen-grains in the long-styled form. He suggested that <hi rend="italic">R. lanceolatus</hi> was a hermaphrodite plant that was becoming dioecious. In earlier work on various dimorphic species of <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>, CD had shown that heteromorphic unions resulted in complete fertility whereas homomorphic unions were incompletely fertile (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, p. 91). CD later referred to this phenomenon as reciprocal dimorphism (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>, p. 191).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The letter to Gray requesting information on plants which never flowered or seeded has not been found. <hi rend="italic">Acorus calamus</hi> (sweet flag) is a perennial herb propagated by rhizome division; horseradish (<hi rend="italic">Armoracia rusticana</hi>) is propagated by pieces of root. CD’s question about <hi rend="italic">Acorus</hi> and horseradish was related to his work on sterility from the excessive development of the organs of growth or vegetation; he refers to the sterility of the two plants, and others, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 170.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In crosses of long-styled primrose (<hi rend="italic">Primula vulgaris</hi>) with pollen of short-styled <hi rend="italic">P. elatior</hi>, CD found only minimal fertility, compared with the high rate of fertility he had recorded in earlier experiments using pollen from the common oxlip (now <hi rend="italic">P. veris</hi> x <hi rend="italic">vulgaris</hi>) with <hi rend="italic">P. vulgaris.</hi> CD’s interpretation of the results emphasised the necessity of going beyond structural criteria in classifying species (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Specific difference in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, pp. 449–51). CD’s notes for his crossing experiments made in 1866 with the common oxlip and <hi rend="italic">P. elatior</hi> (which he called the Bardfield oxlip), are in DAR 108: 8–10; the bulk of CD’s notes on <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> are in DAR 108–11. CD’s discussion of the common oxlip and <hi rend="italic">P. elatior</hi> is in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 55–73.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">This work marked a departure from many of CD’s previous crossing experiments, which were designed to assess the regulation of cross-fertility and self-fertility by variation in flower structure. Earlier experiments had focused on the number of seeds produced in controlled crosses while the new work concerned the relative growth of plants raised from such seeds (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Allan 1977</ref>, pp. 250–1). CD later published the results of these and further experiments in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>; see especially pp. 285–311.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 303, CD concluded that seedlings from a cross between distinct plants were generally superior in height, weight, and constitutional vigour to those that were self-pollinated.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>