<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6605">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. F. Claus<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   6 February 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16447</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6605 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6605.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6605.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 177</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 177</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_955.xml">Claus, C. F.</persName>
                <placeName>Marburg</placeName>
                <date when="1869-02-06">6 Feb 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Pleased by CD’s good opinion and offer to provide material. Discusses work he would do on cirripedes.</p>
            <p>Moritz Wagner’s views on migration of species;</p>
            <p>his doubts about Fritz Müller’s views on developmental stages of Crustacea.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cirripedes</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Crustacea</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4916">Wagner, M. F.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-05-04" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00700_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00700_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="177:1r" xml:id="i700">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00700.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00700_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00700.dzi" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="177:1v" xml:id="i701">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00701.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00701_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00701.dzi" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="177:2r" xml:id="i702">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00702.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00702_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00702.dzi" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="177:2v" xml:id="i703">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00703.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00703_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00703.dzi" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="177:3r" xml:id="i704">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00704.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00704_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00704.dzi" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="177:3v" xml:id="i705">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00705.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00705_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00705.dzi" width="3799px" height="6290px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Marburg</placeName>
                    <date>d 6/II 1869</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Sie haben mir durch Ihre gütigen Zeilen eine ebenso grosse Freude als Ehre erwiesen, und weiss ich in der That kaum, wie ich mich für das in Aussicht gestellte Untersuchungsmaterial dankbar beweisen kann.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich hoffe durch eine möglichst sorgfältige und gewissenhafte Prüfung jener so interessanten und wichtigen Objecte mich Ihrer grossen Güte und Ihres Vertrauens einigermassen würdig zu zeigen. Ich werde die bezeichneten Gegenstände mit dem grössten Danke acceptiren. Da ich bislang nur die Larven und Puppen von Lepadiden untersuchen könnte, so würde ich Ihnen auch besonders verpflichtet sein, wenn Sie mir vielleicht die Gelegenheit verschaffen könnten, die Puppen von Balanus zu examiniren; ich sollte denken, die Post würde ein solch’ kleines Kästchen, welches ich Sie bitten würde, an das Königliche zoologische Institut zu adressiren, leicht annehmen und beförderen—</p>
<p>In einer kleinen Notiz, die ich neben mehreren Arbeiten mir erlaubt habe an Sie in Kreuzband abzusenden, habe ich schon 1862 den Versuch gemacht, den <hi rend="underline">Cirripedienleib</hi> auf den der <hi rend="underline">Copepoden</hi> morphologisch zurückzuführen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Meine neueren Studien der Larven, Puppen und jungen in Puppen eingeschlossenen Cirripedien, haben hoffe ich meine damalige Zurückführung ziemlich sicher gestellt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Die Organe in den Hörnern der Larve sind jedenfalls Sinnesorgane und mit Fäden ausgestattet den Sinnesfäden (Leydigschen Organen) niederer Crustaceen vergleichbar, sie sind offenbar dasselbe, was Sie als Gehörorgane in der Puppe dargelegt haben, deren <hi rend="underline">Stirnecken</hi> den Stirnhörnern der Larve entsprechen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Die feinere Bestimmung dieser Organe ist leider nur an frischen Puppen möglich, ich konnte leider nur Spiritusexemplare untersuchen.</p>
<p>Bezüglich der Schrift von Wagner<ref target="#foot.f6"/> dürfte wohl auch hervorzuheben sein, dass die allmähligen tellurischen und klimatischen Veränderungen als Ursache der Veränderungen in den Lebensbedingungen und Wechselbeziehungen der Organismen viel zu gering geschätzt worden sind. Die Migration mag besonders in Betracht kommen zur Erklärung der räumlich neben einander enstehenden geographischen Varietäten, die letztern dagegen zur Erklärung der <hi rend="underline">zeitlich</hi> aufeinanderfolgenden Abänderungen. Im letzteren Falle ist die Migration secundär und Folge nicht wie Wagner glaubt primäre Ursache. Auch haben Sie, sollte ich denken, durch die Darlegung der 2 erdachten Beispiele, insbesondere der langbeinigen schnellern und kurzer beinigen Wolfrasse sehr wahrscheinlich gemacht, dass auch ohne so strenge Isolierung, wie sie Hochgebirge, Ströme und Meere bedingen, Varietäten räumlich neben einander hervorgehn können. Das hat Wagner nicht widerlegt, sondern nur seine Behauptung einfach entgegengehalten—.</p>
<p>Es gereicht mir zur besondern Ehre, Ihnen, hochverehrter Herr, meine Photographie beilegen zu dürfen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Ich würde mich glücklich schätzen, die Ihrige mit Ihrer eigenhändigen Namensunterschrift zu besitzen und in meinem zoologischen Album an die Spitze der Naturforscher stellen zu können, die durch ihre Arbeiten in die Entwicklung der Wissenschaft gewaltig eingreifend, umgestaltend und aufbauend gewirkt haben.</p>
<p>Dass <hi rend="underline">R Leuckart</hi> <ref target="#foot.f8"/> einen Ruf nach Leipzig erhalten und angenommen hat, wird Ihnen wohl noch nicht bekannt sein.</p>
<p>Mit ausgezeichter Hochachtung und Verehrung unterzeichne ich als Ihr ergebenster | C Claus</p>
<p>P.S. In der kleinen Schrift “über die Copepodenfauna Nizza’s im Sinne Darwin’s habe ich die Bemerkungen Fr. Müller’s über die zwei Männchen von Tanaïs d. (Riecher und Packer) in ihrem Werthe in Zweifel gezogen.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Ich darf mir wohl erlauben, Ihnen uber die <hi rend="underline">Naupliuslarven</hi> der Garneelen meine Zweifel nicht vorzuenthalten. Fr. Müller hat nicht bewiesen, weder dass die sog. <hi rend="underline">Naupliuslarven</hi> aus den Eiern von <hi rend="underline">Peneus</hi> hervorgingen noch dass die Zoëastadien nach Abstreifung der Haut aus den Naupliuslarven sich entwickelten. Das neben einander Vorkommen der Naupliusformen und Zoestadien berechtigt nicht zu dem Schlusse, dass diese die jüngeren Stadien der letzteren sein, <hi rend="underline">was noch zu beweisen ist</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Es mag vollkommen wahr sein, aber die <hi rend="underline">Sicherheit</hi> fehlt. Meine Zweifel aber sind nunmehr geradezu angeregt durch die <hi rend="underline">Grösse</hi> der Eier von einer nicht näher bestimmten Peneus art. Ein so grosses Ei lässt auf die vollkommenere Ausbildung des Embryos und der ausschlüpfenden Larve schliessen—</p>
<p>In etwa <hi rend="underline">vier</hi> Wochen fangen die Ferien an und ich habe dann <hi rend="underline">sechs</hi> Wochen freie Zeit, um mich ausschlieslich der Cirripedienarbeit widmen zu können. Sollten Sie indessen, hochverehrter Herr, bis dahin nicht wohl Zeit haben, mir das Material zuzusenden, so würde ich auch bis in den Sommer warten können, ich möchte um keinen Preis Ihre kostbare Zeit im unrechten Augenblick in Anspruch nehmen. Ihr | C Claus</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName>Marburg</placeName>
       <date>6/II 1869</date>
        <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>With your kind lines you have given me as much pleasure as honour, and indeed I scarcely know how I can show my gratitude for the research material you promised me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I hope, through the most careful and conscientious examination possible of these very interesting and important subjects, to prove myself in some way worthy of your great kindness and of your trust. I will accept the specimens referred to with my deepest gratitude. As I have hitherto been able to analyse only the larvae and pupae of Lepadidae, I would also be particularly obliged to you if you could possibly provide me with an opportunity of examining the pupae of Balanus; I should think that the postal service would easily accept and deliver such a little box which I would ask you to address to the Königliche Zoologische Institut—</p>  
            <p>In a small note that I have permitted myself to send to you under wrapper, along with a number of other works, I have already in  1862 made an attempt to trace back the morphology of the <hi rend="underline">cirripede body</hi> to that of <hi rend="underline">copepods</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> My more recent studies of the larvae, pupae and young cirripedes that are still enclosed in their pupae have, so I hope, largely borne out this earlier analysis.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The organs in the horns of the larva are in any case sensory organs and equipped with hairs comparable to the sensory hairs (Leydig organs) of lower crustaceans; they are obviously identical with what you presented as the acoustic organs of the pupa, whose <hi rend="underline">sternal edges</hi> correspond to the sternal horns of the larva.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Unfortunately, a finer determination of these organs can only be carried out on fresh pupae, and regrettably I was only able to examine spirit specimens.</p> 
            <p>Regarding Wagner’s pamphlet,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> surely it should also be emphasised that gradual tellurian and climatic changes have been greatly underestimated as a cause of change in the conditions of existence and the interactions among organisms. Migration may be of importance especially in accounting for geographical varieties that develop side by side, the latter, on the other hand, in accounting for <hi rend="underline">chronologically</hi> successive variations. In the latter case migration is secondary and an effect, not, as Wagner believes, a primary cause. Furthermore you have, I should have thought, with your account of the 2 imaginary examples, particularly that of the long-legged, faster, and shorter-legged wolves, made it very probable that even without such strict isolation as is produced by mountains, streams and oceans, variations can develop side by side in the same area. This Wagner has not refuted, but merely contrasted it with his own assertion—. </p>
       
            <p>I feel it a special honour, esteemed Sir, to be able to enclose my photograph.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I would consider myself fortunate to own one of you, signed by your own hand, and to be able to insert it in my zoological album at the summit of naturalists who through their work have had a powerfully radical, transforming and constructive impact on the development of science.</p> 
            <p>I expect you have not yet heard that <hi rend="underline">R </hi><hi rend="underline">Leuckart</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/> has been offered and accepted a position at the University of Leipzig.</p> 
        <p>With the greatest respect and veneration I remain your most devoted | C.  Claus</p> 
            <p>P.S. In a pamphlet “A Darwinian account of the copepod fauna of Nice” I questioned the value of Fr. Müller’s remarks on the two male forms of Tanais d. (smellers and graspers).<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Surely I may be allowed not to withhold from you my doubts about the <hi rend="underline">nauplius larvae</hi> of the prawn. Fr. Müller has neither proven that the so-called <hi rend="underline">nauplius larvae</hi> develop from the eggs of <hi rend="underline">Peneus</hi> nor that the zoea stage develops from nauplius larvae after the skin has been shed. The simultaneous occurrence of the forms of nauplius and the stages of zoea does not warrant the conclusion that the former are the earlier stages of the latter, <hi rend="underline">which still remains to be </hi><hi rend="underline">shown</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p> 
        <p>It may be perfectly true, but the <hi rend="underline">certainty</hi> is missing. And my doubts are  now aroused by the <hi rend="underline">size</hi> of the eggs of a species of Peneus as yet not  precisely identified. From an egg of this size one may infer a fuller  development of both embryo and hatching larva—</p> 
        <p>In about <hi rend="underline">four</hi> weeks the holidays will begin and I shall have <hi rend="underline">six</hi>  weeks to apply myself exclusively to the study of cirripedes. In the  meantime, should you, esteemed Sir, not have the time to send me the  material until then, I can well wait until summer, for I should not at any  price want to take up your time at the wrong moment. Yours | C. Claus.</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 67–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had offered to send some specimens of barnacles. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to C. F. Claus, 28 January 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Claus refers to his paper on the morphological relations between copepods and other crustacean groups, including cirripedes (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1435.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claus 1862</ref>; for the section on cirripedes, see pp. 161–2). CD’s copy of the paper has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">With his letter of 24 January 1869, Claus had enclosed an offprint of his article on the cypris-like larvae of cirripedes and their transformation into sedentary adults (Claus 1868b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Claus refers to CD’s description of acoustic organs in the final pre-adult stage (cypris) of <hi rend="italic">Lepas australis</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, p. 15). For more on CD’s view of the homologies of the naupliar, cyprid, and adult horns and antennae, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5843.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newman 1993</ref>, pp. 372–4. In modern terminology, the ‘Leydig organ’ is the organ found near the oesophagus of sharks and other members of the subclass Elasmobranchii, and is associated with the immune system. Claus probably refers to an organ described by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2917.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Franz von Leydig</ref> in a monograph on <hi rend="italic">Daphnia</hi> as an analogue of the green gland in decapods (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4740.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leydig 1860</ref>, pp. 25–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Claus refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moritz Wagner</ref> and Wagner 1868a or 1868b. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6575.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C. F. Claus, 24 January 1869</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The photograph has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rudolf Leuckart</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Claus refers to his study, <hi rend="italic">Die Copepoden-Fauna von Nizza. Ein Beitrag zur Charakteristik der Formen und deren Abänderungen ‘im Sinne Darwin’s’</hi> (The copepod fauna of Nice. A contribution on the diagnosis of its form and its modification ‘in the Darwinian sense’; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1438.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claus 1866</ref>). In <hi rend="italic">Für Darwin</hi> (F. Müller 1864a, pp. 13–16; Dallas trans. 1869, pp. 20–4), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> had described two forms of male in <hi rend="italic">Tanais dubius</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Chondrochelia dubia</hi>). Claus questioned whether one might be the sexually mature form of the other, as was the case with the amphipod <hi rend="italic">Phronima</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1438.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claus 1866</ref>, pp. 1 and 2). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 50, CD had noted Müller’s discovery of the two forms of male; the passage remained unchanged in subsequent editions. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 328–9, CD cited Müller at greater length on <hi rend="italic">Tanais.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Müller had suggested that <hi rend="italic">Penaeus</hi> emerged from the egg in its nauplius state in a paper, ‘Die Verwandlung der Garneelen’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5655.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1863</ref>, p. 8), that appeared in English as ‘On the metamorphoses of the prawns’ (F. Müller 1864b, p. 104). Müller’s observation was only confirmed much later (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4387.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kishinouye 1900</ref>), but Claus evidently accepted Müller’s account when he made his own observations on development in the genus (see Claus 1876, pp. 10–13).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>