<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4817">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Herbert Spencer   22 April 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14571</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4817 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4817.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4817.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Duncan (1908): 117</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 13</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 225</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 225</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml">Spencer, Herbert</persName>
                <placeName>London, Kensington Gardens Square, 88</placeName>
                <date when="1865-04-22">22 Apr 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Wonders whether CD might contribute, if possible, an occasional letter to the <hi rend="italic">Reader</hi> to help in their effort to establish the journal.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Reader</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>88, Kensington Garden’s Sq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>.</placeName>
                    <date>22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. Ap<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. 1865</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>We are getting our staff of the <hi rend="underline">Reader</hi> into better working order; and are proposing forthwith to use all the means available for making a more decided impression, and establishing our position.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Profs Huxley and Tyndall, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. J. S. Mill<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and myself, have severally agreed to write a few leading articles by way of giving the intended tone and direction.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Among other means of making the public aware of the character of the <hi rend="underline">Reader</hi>, we propose to obtain, so far as possible, occasional brief letters from the leading men of science, announcing such interesting novelties as admit of being understood by the general public, and are of fit nature to be quoted from our columns. I have a letter from Sir John Herschel consenting to aid us in this way. Sir Charles Lyell, too, has promised the like aid.</p>
<p>Can you in like manner give us, occasionally, the valuable help of your name?</p>
<p>I am aware that your health is so precarious that you are obliged to be very economical of your energies—a fact which I greatly regret. And I am fully impressed with the fact, that it would be wrong to ask you to undertake any other labours than those important ones which occupy you. The favor we ask, however, does not involve such a waste of labour in any appreciable degree. A letter of <hi rend="underline">a dozen lines</hi> would suffice the purpose of giving us the weight of your name; and making it apparent that you joined in the effort to establish a scientific journal, and an organ of progressive opinion.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> We are all just now making considerable sacrifices to do this; and feel the necessity of concentrating all possible means of insuring that success which we have not yet quite achieved.</p>
<p>very sincerely yours | Herbert Spencer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The <hi rend="italic">Reader: a Review of Literature, Science, and Art</hi> was a weekly paper, founded in 1863, that provided a forum for reviews of literary and scientific works. Its audience was ‘upper-middle-class, highly educated, politically liberal, and philosophically radical’ (Sullivan ed. 1984, p. 346). Spencer was instrumental in re-launching the paper with new proprietors and increased scientific content in November 1864, after both he and CD had become shareholders (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4674.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, 19 November [1864]</ref> and n. 4, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7381.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer 1904</ref>, 1: 118–19). The paper had been faltering since <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley’s</ref> article on science and church policy in the issue of 31 December 1864 offended many of the Christian-Socialist supporters of the paper and led some of the proprietors and editors to withdraw (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4734.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. D. Hooker, 1 January 1865</ref> and n. 14, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4745.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Huxley, 15 January 1865</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1979.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1994–7</ref>, 1: 331–2, 343, and Barton 1998, p. 440). For CD’s opinion of the <hi rend="italic">Reader</hi>, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4734.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. D. Hooker, 1 January 1865</ref>, n. 14, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4742.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 7 January [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Spencer refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Tyndall</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3327.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Stuart Mill</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">On the intended character of the <hi rend="italic">Reader</hi> and its connection with Huxley, Spencer, Tyndall, and other members of the X Club, see Barton 1998, pp. 433 and 439.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">No correspondence from CD appears in the 1865 issues of the <hi rend="italic">Reader.</hi> For CD’s support for the <hi rend="italic">Reader</hi>, see n. 1, above.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>