<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2427">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From T. H. Huxley   [9–12 March 1859]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3382A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2427 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2427.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2427.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">Amem 4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 166: 288</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 288</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1859-03-09" notAfter="1859-03-12">[9–12 Mar 1859]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Serial homologies in the Mollusca. Gives instances of repetition of homological parts in Radiata.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Mollusca</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">homology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
<p>1) Serial homologies are without doubt far less readily traceable in the <hi rend="underline">Mollusca</hi> than in the <hi rend="underline">Annulosa</hi> just because their body is never divided into true segments—corresponding with those observable in the <hi rend="underline">Vertebrata</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Annulosa</hi> <ref target="#foot.f2"/> However I should say that the pedal ganglia are the serial homologues of the cerebral ganglia—</p>
<p>The arms of the <hi rend="underline">Cephalopoda</hi> afford another case which is much more genuine than it looks inasmuch as their original paired successive arrangement on each side of the foot is disguised by subsequent modifications The chambers of the Nautilus shell are serial homologues—so are the paired branchiæ of the <hi rend="underline">Eolidæ</hi> — so are the multitudinous eyes of <hi rend="underline">Pecten</hi> —; so are (perhaps) the palps and gills of <hi rend="underline">Lamellibranchiata</hi> —indeed, on second thoughts, I would knock out the perhaps.</p>
<p>The valves of the shell of <hi rend="underline">Chiton</hi> afford another case—and if one were very hard up perhaps the palettes of <hi rend="underline">Teredo</hi> might be said to be the serial homologues of the proper shell valves—</p>
<p>2. The multiplication of suckers on the Dibranchiate Cephalopod arm—the multiplication of the tentacles in the <hi rend="underline">Nautilus</hi>.: the multiplication of branchiæ in the Nudibranchs.; of Eyes in the Pectens might all be brought forward as cases of irrelative or vegetative (which is as you say a bad word) repetition—but there are very few good instances of anything of the sort among Mollusks that I can recollect</p>
<p>3. The <hi rend="underline">Echini</hi> would afford capital examples of the indefinite repetition of homological whorls of homological parts— For the shell, consists of a great number of superimposed circles each of which consists of five sets of homologous parts each set containing those homologous pieces twice or more repeated.</p>
<p>As to the Encrinites the stem is a series of homologous joints—the calyx is a series of whorls of homologous parts &amp; the arms are series of homologous joints but I do not know that you can say that the elements of the stem are homologous with those of the calyx or with those of the arms</p>
<p>The rays of <hi rend="underline">Asteriadæ</hi> can hardly be called unimportant parts as they contain portions of the all the organs of the body— In the <hi rend="underline">Medusidæ</hi> again the number of reproductive organs in a whorl is often very great— But the strongest cases against your view are afforded by the <hi rend="underline">Calycophoridæ</hi> (<hi rend="underline">Diphydæ</hi>) and <hi rend="underline">Physophoridæ</hi> here you may have an organism a yard long with regularly repeated homologous organs in great number—thus  [DIAGRAM HERE] generative organs Gen. org leaf like appendages Float stomachs &amp; tentacles St. &amp; T propelling organs</p>
<p>Now these organs have just the same primitive relation to one another as the modified leaves which compose the different whorls of a flower. They are not in whorls however but are on one side of a stem—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>To tell you the truth I learnt the meaning of ‘homology’ from studying these creatures and my hair stands on end at even the hint that there are no serial homologies among them—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>What do you say to a <hi rend="underline">Tænia</hi> too? He is a Cuvierian Radiate</p>
<p>Again the segments of <hi rend="underline">Nodosaria</hi> or other chambered Foraminifer are serial homologues n’est ce pas?</p>
<p>How about the successive pinnæ of <hi rend="underline">Pennatula</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated on the assumption that Huxley composed this memorandum during the period between the letters to T. H. Huxley, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">8 March [1859]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2430.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">13 [March 1859]</ref>. Huxley may also have sent CD a letter at the same time, but this has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD adopted Huxley’s explanation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 438.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD discussed serial homologies in the animal and plant kingdoms in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 435–9, but did not mention any supposed parallels between the Radiata and plants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Huxley had used the concept of homologous organs of Medusae to great effect in his first published paper (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3991.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1849</ref>). See also L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 163.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>