<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3469">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. D. Hooker   [10 March 1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">4202</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3469 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3469.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3469.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 152: 16–19</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Huxley (1918) 2: 40</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 10: 104</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 101: 20–2; Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (probably JDH/2/1/2)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>101: 20–2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Kew</placeName>
                <date when="1862-03-10">[10 Mar 1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Returns Asa Gray’s letter. Disappointed with Gray. Comments on America. British–American relations.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1957">Gray, Asa</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-09-22" status="exportToCUDL">Exported to CUDL by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00041_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00041_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="20r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00041.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00041_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00041.dzi" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="20v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00042.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00042_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00042.dzi" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="21r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00043.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00043_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00043.dzi" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="21v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00044.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00044_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00044.dzi" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i5" n="22r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00045.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00045_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00045.dzi" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i6" n="22v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00046.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00046_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00101-000-00046.dzi" width="3105px" height="5551px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Kew</placeName>
                    <date>Monday</date>
                    <salute>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I return Grays letter with many thanks. I need not say that he is quite wrong in thinking I “care for none of these things,” but I told you before why I ceased to write to him about them, &amp; am very glad I did so—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> he writes to you &amp; to Boott &amp; did to me as an angry man—visibly—&amp; there is no use arguing with such.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I confess moreover to be miserably disappointed in him as with the North generally. I did think that there were some at any rate who would have preserved a calm &amp; dignified bearing, let their feelings be ever so much outraged; but the Boston dinner &amp; Gray’s letters have put all that out of the question;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> his whole letters are steeped in the most inordinate self esteem as a Yankee. he can allow of no difference of opinion, is blind to everything, &amp; what is worse brags like the greatest bullies amongst them. It is the total want of self-respect that I so deeply deplore in Gray.— I mean of course in his capacity as Citizen—for I have the same high opinion of him as a man as ever—</p>
<p>What folly he talks of 2 such nations as England &amp; America ever being on the best terms— What is there in the whole history of the human race to quote for such a state of things as “<hi rend="underline">best of terms</hi>” between two nations of the same blood &amp; bone, &amp; with the same aims &amp; prospects. Nothing but the power of despising us, or we them, ever can or ever will bring one of us to look amicably on the other. It is not in the bounds of possibility that two nations so powerful, so ambitious, so <hi rend="underline">like</hi> should love one another, &amp; it will be bad day for one or both when they do. A Gray knows no more of the philosophy of the “struggle for life” than the Bp of Oxford does.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> You might as well talk of High X loving low X,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> God knows they are each powerful enough, &amp;c <hi rend="underline">like</hi> enough to form one body religious with a common aim &amp; object—, <hi rend="underline">if</hi> they would sink differences &amp; agree <hi rend="underline">each to be</hi> <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>, or one to be everything &amp; the other nothing.</p>
<p>It always amuses me to hear political noodles regret that we as a nation are <hi rend="underline">hated</hi> abroad, God forbid we should be any thing else (till the Millenium comes)— so sure as we are loved we shall be done for— Fancy your credit as a Naturalist if Houghton loved you as one or Owen! or Sedgwick! you must be reduced to a nonentity first.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Rival nations may fear &amp; hate—never love &amp; Gray must be utterly demented not to know that.</p>
<p>Poor Grays account of apology for the Boston dinner is a very lame one &amp; it is lamentable to see him try to cloak it—by sneering allusions to our “members of Parliament.”— How lame too the attempt to put all on the shoulders of a few cunning fellows on both sides the water—. as if the general feeling here in favor of giving Jonathan<ref target="#foot.f8"/> a licking were not spontaneous &amp; heartfelt—(right or wrong I do not say)— I can quite see that the poor fellow is most hurt at the loss of your cordial sympathy &amp; there is an uneasy state of mind running through his letter. Again many thanks for it, I was most anxious to see it.</p>
<p>I find nothing so good as Alcohol &amp; water to preserve plants in for after dissection—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> it hardens enough &amp; not too much, leaves tissues tolerably transparent, &amp; quite clean. Vinegar will preserve pollen masses if I remember right but renders other tissues far too soft. Other fluids are apt to clog or discolor, as far as my experience goes.</p>
<p>Olivers lecture went off very well   he will have a capital paper in next Review—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> would you care to see it before publication?</p>
<p>I send you a capital letter of Bates, which please return as I have not answered it.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Lubbock spent a day here last week &amp; I am as much charmed as you are with him. We hope he will bring Mrs L. to Kew, I like her so much<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I hope much to get down to you at Easter week, if you can take me in: but my Father’s health is so uncertain that I cannot be sure of my movements.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> This an examination week at Chelsea for Asst Surgeons Army.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Ever yours affec | J D Hooker</p>
<p>P.S. Reading over this I fear you will think my politics very Mephistophelean—</p>
<p>I am curious to hear of your trimorphous Primula— I suspect it will prove a very complicated case.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>King S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Leicester March 5 My Dear Sir</p>
<p>I have not been quick to answer your last not only because most of my writing time is just now taken up by my book of Travels<ref target="#foot.f16"/> but because your letter was so full of new observations on the most difficult of all Nat. Hist. subjects that it required long consideration.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I hope you will attend to mine only when you have nothing else to do. The view you propound of the origin of species—by the nat. Selection of varieties which always occur as a universal condition of reproduction, in organic species, independent of the direct action of external conditions; is simple &amp; grand. As you say it recommends itself by its simplicity &amp; clearness &amp; is amply sufficient to explain the origin of species. But what if the real state of things is not so simple as this? Are there not some phenomena in species which seem to show that local conditions &amp; use &amp; disuse have some direct effect on individuals the effect being propagated to the offspring &amp; so complicating the question of the origin of species. Whilst I was travelling I used to attribute like many others the production of distinct local varieties or races to the direct action of the local conditions &amp; when I found such coming in contact with their supposed parents without intermarrying or reverting, I supposed the cause was the gradual &amp; slow change in their constitutions which had brought them to a point when they were incapable of going back. But since I read M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin’s book I believe that Nat. Sel. has effected this change operating both on structure &amp; functions. But still the belief is strong that Climatal &amp; other causes have some slight effect; so slight however, that of themselves they are unable to produce a race. Your letter shows me plainly that the effect must be yet slighter. I think the strongest case of the inability of local conditions acting directly to produce a race is that of the two races of man inhabiting the Tropics of America &amp; Africa. All facts go to show that the American race must have lived in Brazil many thousands of years yet there is no approach to the negro. Yet the effect of exposure to the sun is to blacken the skin. For the nomade tribes of Amazon Indians are darker coloured than the agricultural &amp; the families of chiefs in Africa are lighter col<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. than the rest of the tribe &amp;c &amp;c. My studies of those curious mimetic butterflies gave me convincing proof that local physical conditions do not directly produce a race for there I see a species exhibiting nearly a dozen varieties in one limited spot &amp; 4 or 5 of them as it were in the act of being selected &amp; segregated; the motive for such a process being also quite plain to detect.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>A little more in corroboration of your views.— On testing them by my case of the mimetic butterflies I find they hold good. There is really no proof that the variable species originally sported in a different manner in one locality from what it did in another. Inappreciable variations or very small variations similar in all the localities &amp; Nat. Sel. <hi rend="underline">drawing them out</hi> as it were would be sufficient to explain the whole case. The elimination of intermediate vars. formerly, &amp; of the occasional offspring of cross marriages between the divergent selected forms in one limited district must have been &amp; must be now very stringent &amp; perpetually acting; probably however there is a <hi rend="underline">moral</hi> barrier preventing frequent intermarriages although there is not a <hi rend="underline">geographical</hi> one; in other words the selected &amp; now somewhat widely divergent vars. refuse to intermarry.</p>
<p>Now for a few cases which seem to show that the modifications induced by direct action, are propagated. A few sheep have been imported into the Amazons region from Portugal. The wool nearly all falls off &amp; the young at about 2 or 3 months old (when alone I have noticed them) have a thin coat of straight wool more like hair than wool. I know this is an imperfect observation. I did not notice that <hi rend="underline">hair</hi> or a tendency to hair was produced in the lifetime of a sheep &amp; I did not see lambs when first born, to prove that they have this modified coating at their birth. The sheep are only kept by twos &amp; threes as pets &amp; have not been in the country for many generations so that I do not think selection artificial or Natural has operated.</p>
<p>Dogs become lopeared in consequence of the relaxation of muscles from disuse   puppies are born lop-eared.</p>
<p>Mr Darwin’s case of tame Ducks having less developed wing bones from disuse seems to come under this head<ref target="#foot.f19"/> but unconscious or Nat. Sel. may have come into play here. For when ducks were first tamed strong flyers would less readily submit than weak ones &amp; so forth.</p>
<p>The general blindness of animals in deep caverns seems to be partly owing to direct effect of external cond. on individuals leading to disuse of the organs &amp; collapse of muscles &amp; nerves reproduced in offspring. But this belongs to the same class of facts as those cases which show a general similarity in some features amongst widely different species of animals &amp; plants living under the same conditions; such as fleshiness of plants on sea coast brassy tints of beetles ditto &amp; some similar cases which I observed in S. America such as transparency of wings in Heliconia butterflies living near either tropic; very suffused colouring on E. of Andes under the equator &amp;c.</p>
<p>Some part of this general similarity is owing to Nat. Sel. adapting one sp. to another in external dress; but I think there are some cases where this explanation is inapplicable. It is curious in the case of negro that the colour produced by direct action should be also the one selected as most suitable by nature. Of course the whole argument depends on this question which you put &amp; which I thank you for having placed so vividly before me. Are the peculiarities induced in the lifetime of an organism transmitted to its offspring? We may allow several generations for the operation. I cannot think of any facts giving affirmation to this question except the poor ones given in this letter. Even if they prove it they would not show that a race &amp; new species could be produced by direct action; Nat. Sel. is always acting &amp; would act of course on the offspring of these species</p>
<p>I am much obliged to you for recalling me to order in the matter of forgetting the thousands of generations &amp; millions of individuals extinguished without offspring in the case of insect species. I really was not giving the full force to that.</p>
<p>I have not fully answered your letter but will finish another time. Would you oblige me by getting from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bentham the names of the following trees— I think M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Spruce may have sent them under these same native names<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p> 
              <table rend="centre">
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Tapiribá</cell>
                      <cell rend="width05"/>
                      <cell rend="centre width05"/>
                      <cell rend="left">a stone-fruit tree (very acid— com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Acutitiribá</cell>
                      <cell rend="width05"/>
                      <cell rend="centre width05">—</cell>
                      <cell rend="left">round yellow mealy fruit</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Jabuti-puhé</cell>
                      <cell rend="width05"/>
                      <cell rend="centre width05">—</cell>
                      <cell rend="left">anonaceæ? delicious wild fruit</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Massarandúba</cell>
                      <cell rend="width05"/>
                      <cell rend="centre width05">—</cell>
                      <cell rend="left">cow tree</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Umarí or Marí</cell>
                      <cell rows="2" rend="width05"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">}</hi></cell>
                      <cell rend="centre width05"/>
                      <cell rend="left">two similar fruits</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="centre">and Uixí</cell>
                      <cell rend="centre width05"/>
                      <cell rend="left">Upper Amazon</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Pamá</cell>
                      <cell rend="width05"/>
                      <cell rend="centre width05"/>
                      <cell rend="left">wild stone fruit flavour of cherry</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                      <cell rend="left">Sucu-úba</cell>
                      <cell rend="width05"/>
                      <cell rend="centre width05"/>
                      <cell rend="left">of Santarem<ref target="#foot.f21"/></cell>
                  </row>                 
              </table>

<p>Please give my kind regards to your family  </p>
<p>Yours sincerely | H W Bates</p>
<p>I shall send tomorrow a small box per post with a specimen of leaves that have a fine woolly substance on their under surface to get information from you on its nature.— a certain ant (Polyrhachis bispinosa) collects this material &amp; makes large nests of it   after being elaborated by them it is collected &amp; used as tinder &amp; sold in all shops on the Amazons. Latreille gave an interesting account of the ant &amp; its work but no one up to present time has explained the matter.<ref target="#foot.f22"/> | Yrs | H W B</p>
<p>Will you please give me the reference to your remarks on colours of plants &amp; fur of artic animals not being dependent on climate. I must quote you in my book where I have given similar generalization<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>6.1 Olivers … publication? 6.2] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 I send … it. 7.2] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 Lubbock … much 8.2] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>9.1 I hope … in:] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.1 P.S.... Mephistophelean—] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘Photograph’<ref target="#foot.f24"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil, circled pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Above last paragraph</hi>: ‘Remember Lythrum’<ref target="#foot.f25"/> <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the relationship to the letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3468.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">7 March [1862]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">14 March [1862]</ref>. The only Monday between these dates fell on 10 March 1862.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3451.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 18 February 1862</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3395.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [19 January 1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Boott, 27 January 1862</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 31 December 1861</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Hooker refers to the dinner held in honour of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5132.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Wilkes</ref> in Boston in November 1861 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3404.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 22 January [1862]</ref>, n. 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The bishop of Oxford, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5128.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Wilberforce</ref>, was well-known for his outspoken opposition to natural selection (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, and this volume, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3426.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Kingsley, 31 January 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to High and Low Church Anglicans.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2165.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Haughton</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref>, and Adam Sedgwick had all written hostile reviews of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix VII).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Jonathan: ‘a generic name for the people of the United States, and also for a representative United States citizen’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD had asked Hooker about methods for preserving plant specimens in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3468.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 7 March [1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref> had delivered a lecture entitled ‘On the distribution of northern plants’ at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7845.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Institution of Great Britain</ref> on 7 March 1862 (Oliver 1862a). In an article published in the April issue of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>, Oliver challenged the proposal made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oswald Heer</ref> (Heer 1861a, pp. 213–20) and others that the geographical distribution of plants could be explained by postulating a continental link between Europe and America during the Miocene period, the so-called ‘Atlantis’ hypothesis (Oliver 1862b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Walter Bates</ref>. See enclosure.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Hooker refers to John and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3021.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ellen Frances Lubbock</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Jackson Hooker</ref> had been seriously ill since the summer of 1861 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_117.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Allan 1967</ref>, pp. 207, 208).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Hooker refers to examinations for admission to the Army Medical Service, held at Chelsea Hospital in March 1862. Hooker served for many years as a scientific examiner for medical officers in the armed services (L. Huxley ed. 1918, 1: 387); he was examiner for the paper on natural history, held on 11 March 1862 (<hi rend="italic">Statistical, Sanitary, and Medical Reports</hi> 1860, p. 488).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3468.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 7 March [1862]</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_447.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bates 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">For Hooker’s <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to H. W. Bates of 2 February 1862</ref>, see the enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3480.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [23 March 1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Bates displayed his collection of Amazonian mimetic butterflies to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 16 January 1862 (<hi rend="italic">Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London (Botany)</hi> 6 (1862): lviii). His paper on the butterflies (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>), read before the society on 21 November 1861, was published in the society’s <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> in November 1862 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raphael 1970</ref>, p. 76).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">The botanist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4507.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Spruce</ref> had been collecting plants in South America since 1849; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref> received, named, and distributed the plants Spruce sent back to England (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). Hooker, in his reply to Bates of 18 March 1862, informed him that Bentham had not kept a record of Spruce’s native names, but had reclassified the specimens according to their natural orders (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bates 1892</ref>, pp. lv–lvi).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">Bates described several of these fruits in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_447.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bates 1863</ref>, 2: 216–18.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4596.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Latreille 1802</ref>, pp. 133–7. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2824.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pierre André Latreille</ref> referred to this ant as <hi rend="italic">Formica bispinosa</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">Hooker had reported in his <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Bates of 2 February 1862</ref> that he had long denied ‘that tropical heat or light <hi rend="italic">produces</hi> the bright colouring of plants, or that arctic climates <hi rend="italic">produce</hi> woolly covering’ (see the enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3480.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [23 March 1862]</ref>). In his reply to Bates of 18 March 1862, Hooker stated: ‘I do not think I have anywhere published any notices of colours of plants in relation to climate, but I will see and let you know’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bates 1892</ref>, p. lvii). In his discussion of the independence of colour and climate (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_447.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bates 1863</ref>, 1: 19–22), Bates did not cite any work of Hooker’s, but did refer to CD’s similar conclusions (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3377.xml" resp="#automat">letter from H. W. Bates, 6 January 1862</ref> and nn. 5–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">Hooker apparently enclosed a photograph of himself in this letter (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 14 March [1862]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">Hooker had repeated his promise to send CD specimens of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum</hi> in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3465.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 3 March 1862</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 14 March [1862]</ref> and n. 13.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>