<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11690F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [12 September 1878]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21516</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11690F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11690F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11690F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 44</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 44</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="high">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>6 Queen Anne St, London</placeName>
                <date when="1878-09-11">[12 Sept 1878]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>He has been working hard at Kew for two days.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-03-08" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2017-06-14" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2017-06-20">Responded to review <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-07" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2017-08-07" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>    
    <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>6 Queen Anne S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Here are some tubes Hawksley sent to see whether they wd do, they look pretty good tho’ the walls are thick. They draw them out over flame &amp; have to guess the right moment to stop pulling so it is impossible to get any size accurately except by making a lot &amp; picking some out. The sample quills are strung on a bit of red strap with the tubes<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have had 2 days hard work at Kew, very successfully, Lynch the head foreman gathers the leaves &amp; brings them in to me all with the names marked.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It would be an endless job for me to hunt out where each plant is &amp; I should think he is trustworthy   I have impressed on him the awful consequences of mistakes   I frightened him so by asking whether he was sure that 2 plants were rightly named that he took them to the Herbarium &amp; they were right. I have been rather horrified at finding out mistakes in the number of stomata given in my books, I was led to look at the stomata myself by seeing how badly they suited Sachs theory.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> One Broussonettia was given as having all its stomata above &amp; I found it was an ordinary tree-leaf wetting perfectly above &amp; hairy underneath, &amp; I found very few st above &amp; lots on the undersurface.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> <hi rend="underline">Vicia sativa</hi> was given as no stomata above, &amp; as the bloom is only on the upper side I looked at stomata &amp; found far more above than below.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I sent the plant to the Herbarium to make sure. Some mistake may be misprints such as the under side stoma being put in upper side column, or wrong figure &amp;c. Or the Germans &amp; I may be looking at different plants. I have done 3 or 4 sp of primula &amp; they suit Sachs theory well</p>
<p>P. marginata has most bloom above &amp; stomata <hi rend="superscript">16 above/1 below</hi></p>
<p>P. capitata exactly vice versâ in both bloom &amp; stomata. The meal of primulæ must be very bad protection as it washes off on dipping the leaf in water.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I am not sure it wouldn’t pay better to only count stomata myself but it is so awfully slow compared to using other peoples observations.</p>
                    <p>Horace was here to dinner on Tuesday &amp; went on to Cambr same night &amp; comes he tomorrow to see W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> off   H. seemed very well &amp; jolly. Uncle Ras is pretty well.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I dont see much of him, I leave here 7·45 am &amp; get back 6·45 pm. Hooker was away when I called. Dyers have gone<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I am glad to here ubbadubba<ref target="#foot.f10"/> is jolly | Yrs affec | F D</p>
<p>After all I will send glass tubes separate from this letter</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The day and month are established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11690.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, 12 September [1878]</ref>, and by the reference to the departure of the Thiselton-Dyers (see n. 9, below); the year is established by <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>, p. 99, where Francis wrote that he did the work described in this letter in 1878.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD and Francis used clear and blackened glass tubes, and quills, to enclose the tips of cotyledons of plants while observing the effects of light on the lower parts; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, pp. 470 and 478. Hawksley: possibly <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Paton Hawksley</ref>, a surgical-instrument maker in London who patented clinical thermometers in 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9675.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Woodcroft 1871</ref>, p. 450).  </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3058.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Irwin Lynch</ref> was helping Francis with his work at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, on stomata on leaves, which was part of his and CD’s investigations of bloom on plants; CD did not publish on bloom, but see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Julius von Sachs thought that bloom protected the stomata of plants from water (Sachs 1868b, p. 178; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>, p. 99).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Broussonetia</hi> is the genus of paper mulberries. Francis listed <hi rend="italic">Broussonettia</hi> (sic) <hi rend="italic">papyrifera</hi> as having no bloom on its leaves and stomata only on the undersides in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>, p. 104; for his source, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weiss 1865</ref>, p. 133.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Vicia sativa</hi> is common vetch. Francis listed it as having more stomata on the undersides than the upper sides of its leaves, and bloom only on the upper surface, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>, p. 109. Francis listed four sources for his original determination of the number and position of stomata in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>, p. 102: <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9710.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Czech 1865</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9708.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kareltschikoff 1866</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9709.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Morren 1863</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weiss 1865</ref>. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9710.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Czech 1865</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9709.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Morren 1863</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weiss 1865</ref> did not mention <hi rend="italic">Vicia</hi>, while <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9708.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kareltschikoff 1866</ref>, p. 272, said it had more stomata on the undersides than the upper sides of its leaves. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Darwin 1886</ref>, p. 114. <hi rend="italic">Primula marginata</hi> is the silver-edged primrose; <hi rend="italic">P. capitata</hi> is the round-headed Himalayan primrose.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Francis was staying with his uncle <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Erasmus Alvey Darwin</ref> in London, where his brothers Horace and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Erasmus Darwin</ref> had visited him. William and his wife Sara were on their way to visit Sara’s relatives in Boston, Massachussetts (<ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Emma Darwin to W. E. Darwin, 17 September [1878]</ref> (DAR 219.1: 115)); they sailed on 14 September (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> was director of the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Turner Thiselton-Dyer</ref> was the assistant director. Thistleton-Dyer’s wife, Harriet Anne, was Hooker’s daughter. The Thiselton-Dyers left for a month-long tour of Switzerland on 12 September 1878 at 6:45 in the morning (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Turner Thiselton-Dyer’s</ref> diary, Archives, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bernard Darwin</ref>, Francis’s son.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>