<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2175">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Hugh Falconer   23 November 1857</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13304</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2175 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2175.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2175.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">1p, encl 2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 6: 490</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 144: 20</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 20</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1857-11-23">23 Nov 1857</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1585.xml">Falconer, Hugh</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Can HF ask Col. E. Dickie [probably Col. Edward John Dickey] enclosed questions about Indian horses? [Questions relate to striped markings on the Kutch breed of horses.]</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1315">Dickey, E. J.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">India</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Kutch</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 23rd</date>
                    <salute>My dear Falconer</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>You told me that you thought you could obtain information for me about the colours and markings of some Indian horses, from the very best authority, namely Col. E. Dickie.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> If you could interest him to oblige me with answers to the following questions, it would be conferring a very great kindness on me. I have put the questions in full, though I do not suppose he could answer all; but if he would take the trouble to answer some of them, I should feel extremely much obliged to him, and to you for aiding me in getting information on a point on which I am very curious</p>
<p>My dear Falconer | Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>Would you be so kind as to send off my queries pretty soon, as time is precious.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>[Enclosure]</p>
<p>1. Major Gwatkin in a letter published by Col. Hamilton Smith, speaking of the Kutch or Kahleawar breed of horses, says “Kutch is the country where the mares are bred; the sire is an Arab. They are generally greys or light duns, and almost invariably have the zebra-marks on the arms and thighs with list down the back.”<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am very anxious to know what are the colours of the pure Kutch mares; for it seems very surprising that the offspring, begotten by Arab sires, which I believe are never dun, should be <hi rend="underline">generally</hi> dun or grey and have a dorsal stripe and transverse zebra-like marks on the legs. These latter characteristics, I hear, are generally lost in the Scandinavian duns, when crossed with any other colour.</p>
<p>2. In the Kutch or Kahleawar duns (whether or not a crossed breed), are the zebra-like leg-markings, and dorsal stripe very generally present? Does a transverse shoulder stripe, like that on the ass, ever occur? Is such shoulder stripe ever double, as sometimes, though very rarely, is the case with the ass.</p>
<p>3. Am I to understand from Major Gwatkin that the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Grey</hi> Kutch horses have a dorsal stripe and zebra-like marks on the legs: I have never heard of this before.</p>
<p>4. Are any Kutch horses cream-coloured; and have such the dorsal, or shoulder, or leg stripes?</p>
<p>5. Chesnut horses often have a dorsal stripe: in India have they ever a shoulder or leg stripes?</p>
<p>6. Is the dun or other colour when accompanied by the above stripes, strongly inherited, when such coloured horses are crossed with others.</p>
<p>7. Are all the horses, whatever their colour may be, <hi rend="underline">when striped</hi>, small and built like cobs.</p>
<p>8. What is the colour of the Dun or Cream or other colour, when accompanied by stripes <hi rend="underline">in the foal</hi>, before first hair is shed? Are the stripes at this early age more or less conspicuous?<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>C. Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> Down, | Nov. 22nd 1857.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1315.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward John Dickey</ref> was the superintendent of the stud department of the Bengal Army from 1853.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The copyist recorded that Falconer had written on the original: ‘Wrote to Dr. Bruist Bombay 13 Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>, enclosing copy of the queries, as the best chance of having them well answered.’ <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_715.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Buist</ref> was the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Bombay Times</hi> and an authority on India (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The letter from ‘<hi rend="italic">Major Gwatkin, Superintendent of the Hon. East India</hi> <hi rend="italic">Company’s Stud in Northern India</hi>’, received too late to be included in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7253.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. H. Smith 1843</ref>, was extracted in the ‘Advertisement from the publisher’ placed at the beginning of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Hamilton Smith’s</ref> volume. The passage quoted comes from p. xi, and is marked in CD’s copy of the work in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In the manuscript of his species book, CD relied upon Smith’s work for information on Indian horses (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 329–30). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 58–9, CD discussed the striped horses of India but did not mention either Dickey or Buist (see nn. 1 and 2, above).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>