<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11183">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C.-F. Reinwald<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   13 October 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10484</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11183 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11183.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11183.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 107</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 107</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3970.xml">Reinwald, C.-F.</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1877-10-13">13 Oct 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Pleased CD is satisfied with translation of <hi rend="italic">Cross and self-fertilisation</hi>.</p>  
<p>Sends £20 royalties for <hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi> (700 sold).</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cross and self-fertilisation</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">French</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>13 Oct. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Nous avons eu l’honneur de recevoir votre aimable lettre du 7 Oct. et nous voyons avec plaisir que la traduction et l’exécution typographique de votre ouvrage “Cross and Self fertilization” a repondu à votre attente, et que vous en êtes satisfait.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Nous sommes entièrement à votre disposition pour d’autres exemplaires que vous desireriez envoyer à des personnes de votre choix.</p>
<p>Nous avons l’avantage de vous remettre avec cette lettre un cheque de £20.— pour le Percentage au droit d’auteur pour notre traduction des <hi rend="underline">Insectivorous Plants</hi>, dont nous croyons être près de 700 Exemplaires de vente a l’heure qu’il est.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Nous espérons bien dans quelque temps pouvoir également vous envoyer le Percentage pour le nouveau Volume de Cross- and Self-fertilization, mais les circonstances politiques actuelles ne font nullement avantageuses pour nos affaires de librairie, de manière que nous ne pourrons rien préciser à l’égard du temps qu’il faudra pour vendre 700 Expl.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Quant aux <hi rend="underline">Climbing Plants</hi>, ce petit volume, ne se vend, comme bien vous le pensez, qu’avec lenteur, et la nouvelle édition des <hi rend="underline">Emotions</hi> est naturellement dans le même cas.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Vous avez eu la bonté de nous envoyer un exemplaire de votre dernier ouvrage</p>
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">The different forms of flowers.</hi></p>
<p rend="left">Ce volume contient 15 gravures sur bois et si nous pensions à faire traduire ce volume en français il faudrait avant tout acheter ces clichés à M. Murray, auquel nous allons écrire pour en connaître le prix.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Quoique nous ayons le plus grand envie de faire traduire également ce nouveau volume en français, les complications actuelles de notre gouvernment et des chambres nous forcent de différer cette publication jusqu’à un moment plus tranquille, en nous occupant en attendent de la recherche d’un bon traducteur.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Nous ne perdons pas de vue ce dernier point et nous espérons pouvoir vous donner bientot des nouvelles à cet égard.</p>
<p>Veuillez agréer en attendant, cher Monsieur, l’expression de mes sentiments les plus distingués | C Reinwald &amp; C<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To Charles Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi>, Down Beckenham | Kent</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>13 Oct. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>We have had the honour of receiving your kind letter of 7 Oct. and we are pleased to see that the translation and typesetting of your work “Cross and Self fertilization” has met your expectations, and that you are satisfied.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> We are entirely at your disposal to provide other copies that you might want to send to anyone you choose.</p>
<p>We take the opportunity of sending with this letter a cheque for £20.— for the percentage of author’s rights for our translation of <hi rend="underline">Insectivorous Plants</hi>, of which we believe there are close to 700 copies sold up to this time.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> We also hope to be able to send you within a short time the percentage for the new volume of Cross- and Self-fertilization, but current political circumstances are in no way favourable for our bookselling trade, so that we will never be able to tell how long it would take to sell 700 copies.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>As for <hi rend="underline">Climbing Plants</hi>, this little volume only sells rather slowly, as you expected, and the new edition of <hi rend="underline">Emotions</hi> is naturally in the same situation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>You have kindly sent us a copy of your last work</p>
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">The different forms of flowers.</hi></p>
<p rend="left">This volume has 15 woodcuts and should we consider having it translated into French, it would be necessary first of all to buy these clichés from Mr Murray, to whom we are going to write to find out their price.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Although we have the greatest desire to have this new volume translated into French, the current problems of our government and the chambers forces us to postpone this publication until a quieter time, while busying ourselves in the meantime with the search for a good translator.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> We are not losing sight of this last point and we hope to be able to give you news on this soon.</p>
<p>In the meantime please accept, dear sir, the asurance of my highest consideration | C Reinwald &amp; C<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To Charles Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi>, Down Beckenham | Kent</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter has not been found. Reinwald’s firm had published <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Édouard Heckel’s</ref> French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (Heckel trans. 1877).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edmond Barbier’s</ref> French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (Barbier trans. 1877) had been published in May 1877 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10955.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C.-F. Reinwald, 9 May 1877</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In May 1877, a constitutional crisis arose in France when the republicans and royalists in the Chamber of Deputies clashed over the position of the church within French society; the conservative president dissolved the republican cabinet and appointed a royalist government to oversee elections (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10038.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. L. Fuller 2012</ref>, p.23). A general election to the Chamber of Deputies of the Third Republic was scheduled for 14 and 28 October 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10039.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fortescue 2000</ref>, p. 34).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi></ref> (R. Gordon trans. 1877) and a second French edition, revised and corrected, of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> (Pozzi and Benoît trans. 1877) had been published in 1877.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD’s publisher, John Murray, usually allowed foreign publishers the use of the clichés of the illustrations of CD’s works in return for a small fee (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Eduard Koch?, 6 February 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Édouard Heckel</ref> (see n. 2, above) translated <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>; it was published in 1878 (Heckel trans. 1878).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>