<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-667F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To William Kemp   7 April [1843]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21365</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-667F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-667F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-667F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Cambridge University Library (MS Add. 10252/14) (gift of Ruth Cramond and David Cramond)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>MS Add. 10252/</collection>
                    <idno>14</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1843-04-07">7 Apr [1843]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2657.xml">Kemp, William</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD will sent seeds to specialists for identification.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>April 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Owing to my change of residence your communication has been slow in arriving here.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am much obliged for it, as it promises to be very wonderful.— I will today send one or two of the seeds to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Robert Brown (confessedly the first Botanist in Europe) &amp; find out whether he knows them or their family; &amp; I will send the remainder to Professor Lindley with a request to have them planted at the Horticultural Garden of London &amp; taken care of.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Let me urge on you to watch your plants &amp; if they do not prosper to vary their treatment. I think you do not know whether they inhabited a cold or hot, a wet or dry climate. As any plant dies, I earnestly recommend you to dry it between paper most carefully even if it has only the germinal leaves, &amp; preserve if they flower some in Spirits of Wine &amp; I will get (if you choose) the best botanists to examine them.— Should the Plants turn out known ones, your case no doubt is deserving of record, but sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> they turn out unknown species your case would be magnificent.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Daubeny of Oxford is attending to the subject of germination of old seeds, but he unfortunately has just started for Spain.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> With respect to your paper for Taylor’s Journal, I will do as you please, but if it were my own nothing sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> induce me to publish it, till the seeds had fully grown &amp; had been examined by Botanists with <hi rend="underline">known</hi> names.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In present state some of the Public w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> say he has been imposed upon by seeds having been placed there, as a joke; &amp; others w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> say, no doubt they are some common British Plants. It is well to make every paper to tell with its whole effect <hi rend="underline">at once.</hi> If the seeds turn into unknown plants, <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi> you w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> prefer your Paper being read before the Geological Society; sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> you prefer this, I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> (when the plants have been examined) with pleasure transmit it to the Soc.— In that case the latter part of the Paper, if you will allow me to suggest it, had better be a little simplified:— If you follow my advice, &amp; retain your paper till the plants have flowered or have died &amp; have been examined—Could you not in the 〈in〉terval reexamine the situation &amp; try to get more or hunt for shells or bones &amp;c in the gravel.—</p>
<p>I will wait till I hear from you again.— I will inform you if M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown has anything particular to say about the seeds. &amp; on the ultimate fate of those seeds, which I send to the Horticultural Gardens.—</p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very faithfully | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.9 dry it] <hi rend="italic">caret before ‘it’</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.9 between paper] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.10 &amp; preserve … Wine] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.14 Spain.—] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Oxford.—’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.16 publish it,] ‘it,’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.19 some common] ‘some’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">1.22 transmit it] ‘it’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.2 , which] <hi rend="italic">added</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-699.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from William Kemp, 2 October 1843</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD moved to Down House in Down, Kent, on 14 September 1842 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, Appendix II). Kemp’s letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Kemp had found seeds in a sand pit near Melrose, Scotland; see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-699.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from William Kemp, 2 October 1843</ref>. CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-668.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lindley, 8 [April 1843]</ref>). CD’s letter to Robert Brown has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Kemp wished to argue that the seeds had been deposited in the sand thousands of years previously when the pit would have been a river bank or lake shore (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-668.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lindley, 8 [April 1843]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">From 1841 to 1857, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Giles Bridle Daubeny</ref> served on a committee of the British Association for the Advancement of Science experimenting on the growth and vitality of seeds. In the committee’s report to the British Association meeting in 1842, Daubeny and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4592.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Edwin Strickland</ref> requested old seeds to be submitted for experiment (Strickland and Daubeny 1842; see also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. S. Henslow, 2 November 1840</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD refers to <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</hi>. Kemp’s original paper has not been found, but he later published a much-edited account in the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4320.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Kemp 1844</ref>). The account was drafted by CD based on Kemp’s letters (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, Appendix VI).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>