<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-58">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Coldstream<ref target="#foot.f1"/>    28 February 1829</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5095</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-58 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-58.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-58.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 33</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 33</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1007.xml">Coldstream, John</persName>
                <placeName>Leith</placeName>
                <date when="1829-02-28">28 Feb 1829</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>News of his activities in recent months, of mutual Edinburgh acquaintances, and the Plinian Society.</p>
            <p>JC has given up natural history for a time to prepare himself better for medical practice.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Edinburgh acquaintances</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I confess I was rather illpleased to receive your letter in place of yourself, as I had been looking for your arrival in Edinburgh every day for some weeks before; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barker having apprised me of your intention to visit us about Christmas. However, as you may guess, even the letter received a hearty welcome. I hope this will find you restored to health, and engaged in planning a descent upon Scotland in the summer holidays. You ask me what I have been doing since I left Paris. I remained in France till June, when I set out for Prussia with the hope of ascending the Rhine, and travelling thro‘ Switzerland &amp; the North of Italy. But I took ill in Westphalia and was obliged to hurry home thro’ Holland. I returned to Leith about the end of July, in a state of health which prevented me from deriving pleasure even from Natural History. I recovered very slowly, but now am quite well.</p>
<p>During the winter, I have been almost entirely engaged in practice, and have persevered in my abjuration of Zoology, with a few reservations in favor of walks along the Seashore &amp; occasional visits to the Black rocks.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I found these localities, abounding in so many interesting associations, and offering an ever varying succession of animals, to be more powerfully alluring even than the Jardin des Plantes. Perhaps there is no real occasion for the <hi rend="underline">greif</hi> which you express, in imagining that I have entirely forsworn Natural History: I am still ready to agree with you in the sentiment ‘that no pursuit is more becoming for a physician than Nat: Hist:’ and I feel myself as much, if not more, inclined than ever, to look into the World of Nature around me, but I feel, that as I must soon enter upon the public &amp; the responsible discharge of the duties of my profession, I owe it as a duty of the highest importance, both to others &amp; to myself, to make up as perfectly as possible, the deficiencies in <hi rend="underline">useful knowledge</hi> which, I have too good reason to fear, my devotion to science (unprofitable as it has been) has occasioned. You may depend upon this, <hi rend="underline">at least</hi>, that “the good old Cause of Zoology” is not slighted by me; and of course, still less so, the friends in whose company I formerly prosecuted it.—</p>
<p>Glasspoole<ref target="#foot.f3"/> left Paris in May with the intention of going through Switzerland &amp; Germany: I heard of his being in London in September; when I believe D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grant<ref target="#foot.f4"/> saw him: and I have since heard that he has settled in <hi rend="underline">Brighton</hi>: or, at least, that he is living there. I was happy to receive intelligence regarding M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hope: I am greatly indebted to him for a valuable collection of types of the British genera of Coleoptera, which he sent me, probably with the view of stimulating me in the study of Entomology; but I have done very little in it. I am not unmindful of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hope’s kindness, and although my long silence may appear to him a mark of ingratitude, and unpardonable carelessness, I am not without some expectation of being able at some future time to redeem my lost character in his eyes. You will probably have seen D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grant by the time you receive this. If you should be in London, be so good as present my kindest regards to him, and say, that I received his letter, and intend answering it shortly. You ask me for Edinburgh news, but truly I know of none worth giving you; excepting, indeed, that the <hi rend="underline">Plinian</hi> <ref target="#foot.f5"/> is flourishing most vigorously.— There are several very industrious young naturalists in it at present; and Brown<ref target="#foot.f6"/> continues to lend his matured experience in the presidency. David Ritchie has succeeded his father as minister of the Parish of Tarbolton in Ayr.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Your request about the Carabidae I cannot answer. The only entomological information I can give you, is, that I had an excellent opportunity in Westphalia of examining the singular habits of the Bombyx processionaria (larva) described by Reamur.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I verified most fully all his interesting description. The caterpillars were particularly abundant in the woods of Westphalia last year, and destroyed the leaves of almost all the oaks. You are, of course, aware of the publication of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fleming’s “British Animals”,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stark’s “elements of Natural History.”<ref target="#foot.f10"/> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. F’s is a very valuable work but M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stark’s, being more general and more complete, will probably enjoy the larger share of popularity. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grant is engaged in the publication of “<hi rend="underline">Outlines</hi> of Zoology &amp; Comparative Anatomy.”—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Be so good as write me again soon, and tell me something of the present state of Natural History in Cambridge. Have you had any opportunity of studying marine Zoology since you left this?—</p>
<p>With every affectionate wish I remain, | My Dear Darwin, | Yours most truly | John Coldstream</p>
<p rend="left">Leith.</p>
<p rend="left">28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Feb. 1829.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s fellow medical student and friend at the University of Edinburgh. In the <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi></ref>, p. 48, CD describes him as ‘prim, formal, highly religious and most kind-hearted: he afterwards published some good zoological articles [<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7771.xml">for Todd’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi> <hi rend="italic">of anatomy and physiology</hi></ref>].’ He proposed CD for membership of the Plinian Society (see n. 5 below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In a notebook in which CD recorded observations during the spring of 1827 there is the following entry: ‘Observed with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Coldstream at the black rocks at Leith an Asterias rubens’ (DAR 118, p. 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick Bream Glasspoole</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Edmond Grant</ref>, CD’s close associate and mentor in zoology at Edinburgh (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4198.xml">Jespersen 1948–9</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi></ref>, pp. 49, 51). In an article published in July 1827, on ‘the ova of the <hi rend="italic">Pontobdella muricata</hi>’ Grant gave CD credit for being the first to identify them: ‘The merit of having first ascertained them [the ova] to belong to that animal is due to my zealous young friend Mr <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Darwin</ref> of Shrewsbury, who kindly presented me with specimens of the ova exhibiting the animal in different stages of maturity’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Grant 1827</ref>; Darwin Library–CUL: ‘Philosophical tracts’). This was the first scientific discovery by CD to be reported in print, though CD was not the first to make it (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_233.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ashworth 1935</ref>: 105–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Plinian Natural History Society was founded in 1823 by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2536.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Jameson</ref>. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_233.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ashworth 1935</ref> has a detailed account of the Society. For mention of CD’s reports to it, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-20.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Caroline Darwin, 6 January 1826</ref>, n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_678.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Alexander Francis Browne</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In December 1826 <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4015.xml">Ritchie</ref> successfully opposed the election of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georges Cuvier</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Friedrich Blumenbach</ref> to honorary membership of the Plinian Society (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gruber and Barrett 1974</ref>, p. 39).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3900.xml">René-Antoine Ferchault de Réaumur</ref>. The <hi rend="italic">Bombyx</hi> larva is described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Réaumur 1734–42</ref>, 1: 172, pl. V.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2546.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fleming 1828</ref> (Darwin Library–CUL).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stark 1828</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">No publication with this title has been located.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>