<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-865">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. B. Carpenter   5 May 1845</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1891</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-865 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-865.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-865.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">11pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 39: 36–41</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>39: 36–41</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_839.xml">Carpenter, W. B.</persName>
                <placeName>London, St Martin’s Lane, 61</placeName>
                <date when="1845-05-05">5 May 1845</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the microscopic structure of rock samples from Chile and the Pampas. Describes organic remains found in the samples.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">rock</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Chile</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Pampas</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>61 St Martins Lane. | London—</placeName>
                    <date>May 5— 1845.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I should have written to you long since, respecting the results of my examination of the specimens you forwarded to me soon after Christmas;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> had I not been prevented by unforeseen occurrences from subjecting the sections, which were then prepared, to as close an examination as I wished to give them— This, however, I have now done; and I have also made a couple of sections of the last specimen you forwarded to me,—that of the Coquimbo deposit; and the results of this more extended investigation are sufficiently interesting, to make me think it worthwhile to go over the whole subject with you again.<anchor xml:id="ann.a2" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>You are of course aware, in the first place, that any calcareous matter, in a state of crystalline aggregation, is <hi rend="underline">transparent</hi> under the Microscope; whilst any <hi rend="underline">amorphous</hi> deposit is quite opaque, even in a <hi rend="underline">very</hi> thin layer. The two conditions are well seen in ordinary Shells of Mollusks, and in the Egg-shell. A tolerably thick section of the former is generally transparent, or at least translucent; the thinnest possible section of the latter is quite opaque. Not unfrequently there is in the Shells of certain Mollusks (e.g. the common Oyster) a layer of amorphous Carbonate of lime, which, altho’ of immeasurable thinness, renders the portion of the section, in which it presents itself, quite opaque.</p>
<p>How far it is possible for any <hi rend="underline">mechanical attrition</hi> to reduce the crystalline to the amorphous form, so completely as to change the microscopic character in the manner I have stated,—I can scarcely venture an opinion. That <hi rend="underline">Chemical precipitation</hi> will do it,—we well know; but I am inclined to believe that a sufficiently prolonged action of attrition might also effect it.</p>
<p><anchor xml:id="ann.a3" type="annotationStart"/>Now supposing a deposit to have been thus reduced to the <hi rend="underline">amorphous</hi> state, the question arises, whether, under any circumstances, it can resume, more or less a <hi rend="underline">crystalline</hi> condition. I am strongly inclined to believe that the simple percolation of water charged with a small quantity of carbonic acid (and thereby possessing a solvent power for carbonate of lime) may have this result; and that this is the history of the formation of the <hi rend="underline">Oolites</hi>, in which the condition of the calcareous matter,—both that forming the concentric deposits around the nuclei of the egg-like particles,—and that forming the cement which unites them together,—is decidedly <hi rend="underline">crystalline</hi>. In this case, the crystallization has taken place, from some unknown cause, around nuclei, which commonly consist of minute Foraminifera, more or less perfectly preserved. In other instances it may occur, <anchor xml:id="ann.a1" type="annotationStart"/>I should suppose, in irregular <hi rend="underline">patches</hi> or in more distinct <hi rend="underline">strata</hi>—</p>
<p>Now to apply these views to the case before us—<anchor xml:id="ann.a4" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>In regard to the <hi rend="underline">Chilian</hi> deposit, it is, of course sufficiently evident to the unaided eye, that a great part of it consists of comminuted fragments of Shell.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The Microscope shows, that these are mingled with still more minute particles <hi rend="underline">of the same kind</hi>; and that there is also a quantity, varying in proportion, of the amorphous substance, which I have alluded to as possibly resulting from the mechanical disintegration of the larger fragments.— I think I can also trace some <hi rend="underline">Spongioid</hi> remains in the sections I have made of the specimen you sent me,—about 12 in number.</p>
<p>In the specimen of the <hi rend="underline">Coquimbo</hi> deposit which you last sent me,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I can find <hi rend="underline">no definite appearance of organic structure</hi>; it appears to be made up of the amorphous particles of the preceding; in some parts of which a sort of stratification presents itself, some of the layers showing indications of an incipient metamorphosis into the Crystalline condition.</p>
<p>In the various sections I have made of the <hi rend="underline">Pampean</hi> deposit, amounting in all to about 25 in number, I trace a considerable variety of appearances. In a large part, I find the same appearances as in the preceding,—namely, a tolerably uniform amorphous character, with traces of incipient crystalline metamorphosis; but I also find the presence of minute rounded concretions,—resembling those of Oolites in size, but <hi rend="underline">not</hi> in the arrangement of their particles,—a very frequent character. The <hi rend="underline">substance</hi> of these concretions is still <hi rend="underline">amorphous</hi>; but that of the connecting cement is often crystalline; as if water, charged with carbonate of lime, had percolated through the deposit, <hi rend="underline">after</hi> (from whatever cause) the concretions had been formed. Of organic structures in this deposit, I find a greater variety than in either of the preceding. I have been able distinctly to recognize fragments of Shell,—though rarely. I am fully satisfied, however, that Spongioid bodies were common at the time of its formation; though their remains are by no means distinct. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bowerbank, to whom I have shown the most characteristic specimens, fully agrees with me in this. The remains of the organic fibres, of the Spicula, and I think too of the Gemmules, may be distinguished more clearly than in the <hi rend="underline">Chilian</hi> deposit. I am satisfied, also, of the existence of remains of Corals and of Polythalamia, in this deposit. But, as I said in a former communication, the great mass of it is composed of the <hi rend="underline">amorphous</hi> matter already referred to;—sometimes uniformly diffused,—sometimes in concretions.</p>
<p><anchor xml:id="ann.a5" type="annotationStart"/>This is, I think, all the light that the Microscope can throw on the history of these deposits; and if it is not entirely satisfactory, nevertheless I hope it may be regarded as a contribution of some value towards the elucidation of their relations.</p>
<p>I shall preserve the series of Sections; and shall have great pleasure in showing them to you, or to any other Geologist who may wish to examine them, at any future time. I shall be in my present domicile for about two months longer, after which I shall return to Ripley until Michaelmas; but it is probable that I shall then remove permanently to the immediate vicinity of London.</p>
<p>I hope that you will not come to Town, without giving me the pleasure of seeing you. I have now a very large collection of preparations of Shell-Structure; and am anxious to make my investigations known to Scientific Men.</p>
<p>Your specimens (which I have brought to Town) shall be forwarded to the Geological Society. I have not been able to make sections of <hi rend="underline">all</hi> of them, some being too friable.</p>
<p>Believe me to be, Dear Sir | yours very sincly | William B. Carpenter.<anchor xml:id="ann.a6" type="annotationEnd"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note target="#ann.a1" targetEnd="#ann.a2"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a3" targetEnd="#ann.a4"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 8.3 namely,] <hi rend="italic">opening quotation marks added pencil before</hi> <ref target="#foot.f4"/> </note>
                <note target="#ann.a5" targetEnd="#ann.a6"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See letters from W. B. Carpenter, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-802.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 December 1844</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-813.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">2 January [1845]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD considered it important to demonstrate that limestone formations were largely the product of disintegrated organic forms, and he quickly adopted Carpenter’s conclusion (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 77).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had asked Carpenter to compare rock specimens collected in the Pampas with those collected at Coquimbo, Chile (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 77).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD presumably marked the text in this way to indicate the beginning of the section that he subsequently paraphrased in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 77.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>