<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-360">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Caroline Darwin   [19 May – 16 June 1837]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1872</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-360 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-360.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-360.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 154: 52</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>154: 52</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 36</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1837-05-19" notAfter="1837-06-16">[19 May – 16 June 1837] </date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1208.xml">Darwin, C. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends a number of questions (to put to his father), mainly concerned with transmission of diseases, between Europeans and natives, "people packed together", etc.</p> 
<p>Is investigating how to get Government support [for <hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Europeans</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">natives</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Zoology</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1234">Darwin, R. W.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dispersion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Government</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>36. Great Marlborough St.</placeName>
                    <date>My dearest Caroline,</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>Many thanks for your letter, which you will say I am answering in a great hurry, but I want to ask my Father some questions, and a very odd string they are— But in the first place you have my direction wrong, it 36 &amp; not 46.— I had no idea that Marianne<ref target="#foot.f1"/> had the Globe, else I would never have thought of asking about it. You must send and let her know my true direction, but if it is not gone really I think, it had better not— if it is gone, I will call, at <hi rend="underline">46</hi> &amp; leave my card.— Catherine tells me to say that the Rhododendrons went by Jelby’s Van for Shrewsbury— Now for the odds &amp; ends— Will you ask my Father whether he did not say that floods of the Severn from Snow were less muddy &amp; less destructive to the soil than those from heavy rains, or was it vice versa or what was it? Is it in the Zoonomia or notes to Botanic Garden where there is a passage about acquired instincts, such as crows learning Guns are dangerous—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have been much interested at finding so many cases where ships with all their crew in good health have yet caused strange contagious disorders at Station Islands in the Pacific— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Williams, a missionary, boldly asserts that the first mingling, where both are healthy of the European race with the natives of distant climes always produces disease.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am very much inclined to suspect that there is some such mysterious law connected with the destruction of the Aborigines in both Americas—Cape of Good Hope—Australia &amp; Polynesia.— I recollect years ago my Father mentioning (from Macculloch) some little Island where the people had influenza whenever a ship arrived—&amp; such was thought to be explained by Vessels always arriving with certain wind.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Will you ask my Father what my memory is alluding to.— Again, are there not cases where people packed together have produced most deleterious contagion <hi rend="underline">without</hi> <hi rend="underline">themselves being affected.</hi>— Was not the “black Assize of Oxford” such a case?<ref target="#foot.f5"/> What year was it? Have I not heard my Father mention some other parallel instance.— Now will you be a good lady &amp; look at Ellis’ Polynesian Researches, &amp; see if he does not at Tahiti make some remarks about the belief that Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Cook’s visits produced some kinds of illness— There is some ridiculous story about humpbacks, but perhaps some truth in other cases after all.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Ellis is so well divided into Chapters, that you will easily find a probable chapter to read, if not don’t trouble yourself— Will you ask my Father whether he has ever heard of any experiment to try, as the puncture from instruments in dissecting a man is so fatal to another man whether a dead dog for instance, would so act to living dog.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Was there ever such an odd string of questions? The Governor will think I am gone mad; I cannot in letter show connection of questions—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>On Thursday I am going to spend the day at Chatham. I am going to visit D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Richardson (the Arctic man)<ref target="#foot.f9"/> he being a person of experience is going to tell me the best means of extracting funds from Government. I have got through R<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Browne’s<ref target="#foot.f10"/> assistance the Duke of S——<ref target="#foot.f11"/> signature—so all that is settled, but whether Government will help me is another question. If they do I shall thank Providence, &amp; if they don’t I shall thank Providence for having rid me of a heavy job, so I am determined to be pleased.</p>
<p>I most devoutly long to be with you, my very dear Caroline. Give my most affectionate love to my Father &amp; say I hope the questions wont plague him. Good bye. C. Darwin—</p>
<p>You, who can write, and do always write such nice letters, have no business to say Shrewsbury is dull, or any other place dull, &amp; that there is no news—</p>
<p>Miss Darwin. | Shrewsbury.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3680.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Marianne Parker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The passage is in <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 1: 158): ‘[rooks] evidently distinguish, that the danger is greater when a man is armed with a gun.’ CD had become interested in the inheritance of ‘acquired instincts’ by the tameness of the animals on the Falkland and Galápagos islands (see <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> p. 478).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8394.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Williams 1837</ref>, pp. 281–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5074.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">MacCulloch 1824</ref>, 3: 191: ‘the whole world knows, that whenever a stranger lands in St. Kilda, all the inhabitants “catch a cold” ’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In 1577 an outbreak of ‘gaol fever’ at the assizes in Oxford Castle killed 300 people (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1668.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crossley, ed. 1979</ref>, p. 296).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2327.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ellis 1829</ref>, 2: 269, refers to a ‘kind of dysentery’ that appeared after a visit of Vancouver’s ship in 1790 and ‘proved fatal to a vast portion of the population.’ The description of the spinal disease occurs on pp. 272–3. Ellis comments, ‘Some say this singular complaint was unknown to their ancestors, and has only prevailed since they have been visited by foreign shipping.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD’s <hi rend="italic">Red notebook</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5912.xml"><hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi></ref>) has a similar note (p. 178), made at about the same time (June 1837): ‘Puncture one animal with recent dead body of other, &amp; see if same effects, as with man.’ CD’s interest in this subject may have been heightened by the fact that his uncle, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1210.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Darwin</ref>, eldest son of Erasmus, died of an infection contracted while dissecting a cadaver in 1778 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 1: 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Most of the requested references are cited in chapter 21 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4249.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks</hi></ref> in the discussion of the ‘mysterious’ causes of extinction of native populations. ‘Wherever the European has trod, death seems to pursue the aboriginal.’ (p. 520).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3997.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Richardson</ref> accompanied Sir <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1742.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Franklin</ref> on his two polar expeditions and supplied appendixes on natural history and meteorology to Franklin’s <hi rend="italic">Narratives</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Franklin 1823</ref>, 1828). He also published, with government support, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6635.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richardson 1829–37</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Robert Brown.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4305.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Adolphus Seymour</ref>, 11th Duke of Somerset, President of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>, 1834–7 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>