<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13166F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   19 [May 1881]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21544</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13166F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13166F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13166F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 72</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 72</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Strasbourg</placeName>
                <date when="1881-05-19">19 [May 1881]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Is sorry to have involved himself in a priority dispute between Wortmann and Elfving. Intends to publish on circumnutation; will CD send him his notes? Apologises for taking CD’s protractor, will send it back. Has met Oscar Schmidt.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-12-11" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-22" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-30" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Strassburg (Elsass)</placeName>
                    <date>19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Many thanks for your long letter; will you please thank Bessy for her nice letters and say I will really write a decent letter next but now I want to get some axles off—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I was talking with Wortmann (the d—d circumnutator) last night about several physiolog things, and I said I had heard from Elfving that Phycomyces bends away from a damp surface   He said that he had made it out too in the winter and had his M.S ready; he hadn’t intended to publish it till the winter, but now he should do so at once so as to be before Elfving.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It is very unpleasant for me, and I have written to Elfving telling him and saying how sorry I am: I think Wortmann ought most certainly to arrange with Elfving and publish at the same time, for if it hadnt been for me Elfving would have been first   Elfving hasn’t this frightful priority mania, but everyone must like to be the first— Wortmann isn’t a bad sort fellow at all, but evidently thinks entirely of himself &amp; priority. I hope this wont prevent Elfving writing to me in the future about his work—</p>
                    <p>I expect Wortmann will publish his circumnution now too; so I think I will, or at any rate a pretty full preliminary notice; for this I should want my notes, I wonder if you could find them—do not trouble if you do not see them at once— They are all together in the cupboard on the right side of the fire; about the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> shelf from the bottom &amp; close to rt side; you will recognise them by the diagrams. There are 2 or 3 very big diagrams which need not be sent; and (if they are all together) only the diagrams marked fig 1 fig 2 &amp;c need be sent; fig 3 or 4 is marked very faintly on the rt side with blue pencil— Please do not agonise about it, as it does not matter very much   I am quite willing to let Wortmann come first but I should like to come out abt the same time<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>About your protractor, I was very sorry to find that it was packed up with my things by mistake, I will send it between 2 bits of card board, &amp; Jackson will fasten on a string &amp; lead blob.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Wortmann tried whether Phyco was sensitive to a touch &amp; says it is not; but he has found some unicellular thing which is so, which is interesting.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> He says he has talked to Sachs about the Power of Movement &amp; he approves of the circumnut<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> theory but doubts about the roots, let him doubt &amp; be d—d. Wortmann highly approves of the terms apheliotropic &amp;c &amp; things they will be generally adopted.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>De Bary took me to a meeting of the Naturforschende Gesellschaft, where Götte made a good address about sexual selection; he speaks a queer N german dialect which makes it hard to understand.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> He talked as if no one believed in sexual selection! I was introduced to Goltz who is a jolly fat old boy like a fattened &amp; elderly Moseley; he is coming to the Internat Med Congress in London in August.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I was also introduced to Oscar Schmidt who is rather common looking man, he seemed a vulgar sort of man but was very civil &amp; kindly.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>The way these people work is wonderful   Wortmann begins at 5 am &amp; goes strt on with only breaks for meals till 7; De Bary is here from <hi rend="superscript">am</hi> 9 to 7 pm, &amp; then works at home till 12; every evening from 7 to 8 he goes to “kneipe”<ref target="#foot.f11"/> i e drink beer with 2 or 3 other professors at a certain table in a certain café—</p>
<p>It was very touching about poor Dubs &amp; the ship—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Please tell him the next soldiers shall have no writing on their backs then he can cut them out<ref target="#foot.f13"/> | Yrs affec | FD</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The month and year are established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13159.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 16 and 17 May 1881</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13159.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 16 and 17 May 1881</ref>. No correspondence between Francis and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1217.xml">Elizabeth Darwin</ref> has been found. ‘Axles’: a family word for unresolved work-related issues (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12128F.xml">letter from Francis Darwin to Emma Darwin, 30 June 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9180.xml">Julius Wortmann</ref> had observed circumnutation in the mycelium of a fungus (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13155F.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 14 May 1881</ref> and n. 7). Francis had met <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1485.xml">Fredrik Elfving</ref> in Würzburg in 1879 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12067F.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 29 May 1879</ref>). Elfving was the first researcher to describe an autochemotropic (avoidance) response in the sporophore of the fungus <hi rend="italic">Phycomyces nitens</hi>. His paper ‘En obeaktad känslighet hos Phycomyces’ (An unobserved sensitivity in Phycomyces; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11407.xml">Elfving 1881</ref>) appeared in September 1881.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Wortmann’s paper, ‘Ein Beitrag zur Biologie der Mucorineen’ (A contribution on the biology of Mucorales; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11408.xml">Wortmann 1881</ref>) appeared in parts in <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung</hi>, 10 and 17 June 1881. In the first section, he described experiments with <hi rend="italic">Phycomyces nitens</hi> that demonstrated the movement of sporophores away from moisture; in the second part, he described the irregular nutation of the stolon of <hi rend="italic">Mucor stolonifer</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Rhizopus stolonifer</hi>, black bread mould). Francis’s paper, ‘Ueber Circumnutation bei einem einzelligen Organe’ (On circumnutation in a single-cell organ; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11409.xml">F. Darwin 1881b</ref>), appeared in <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung</hi>, 29 July 1881; it included three diagrams tracing the movement of a sporophore of <hi rend="italic">P. nitens</hi>. Francis described the special rotation apparatus designed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml">Horace Darwin</ref> that allowed him to observe clearly the circumnutation of the sporangium.  </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13159.xml">16 and 17 May 1881</ref>, CD had mentioned being unable to find his ‘horn semicircle for measuring angles’ (i.e. protractor). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2521.xml">William Jackson</ref> was CD’s butler.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Wortmann described the tip of the stolon of <hi rend="italic">Mucor stolonifer</hi> as sensitive to touch (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11408.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Wortmann 1881</ref>, pp. 385–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml">Julius Sachs</ref> had supervised Wortmann’s doctoral studies at Würzburg. Sachs was sceptical about CD’s conclusion in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 573, that the tip of the root was the sensitive part and directed movement in the adjoining parts. Sachs had also investigated influences on root movement (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10470.xml">Sachs 1872</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10400.xml">1873–4</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">No record of the meeting of the Naturalists’ Society that Francis attended with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref> has been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7283.xml">Alexander Goette</ref> was a professor extraordinarius of zoology at Straßburg (Strasbourg). He was born in St Petersburg, Russia, to a Baltic German family (<hi rend="italic">NDB</hi>). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8609.xml">Friedrich Leopold Goltz</ref>, a professor of physiology at Straßburg, attended the seventh International Medical Congress, held in London from 2 to 9 August 1881. Goltz’s paper ‘Discussion on the localisation of function in the cortex cerebri’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11406.xml">Goltz 1881</ref>) was published in the transactions of the congress. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3422.xml">Henry Nottidge Moseley</ref> was a professor of anatomy at Oxford (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Francis had mentioned meeting <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4223.xml">Oskar Schmidt</ref> in his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13155F.xml">14 May 1881</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Kneipe</hi>: pub, bar (German).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml">Bernard Darwin</ref> had been upset by a report of the sinking of a ship (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13159.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 16 and 17 May 1881</ref> and n. 11).</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Francis was sending paper soldiers to Bernard. Some companies produced paper soldiers with advertisements on the reverse, as a free gift with purchases (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11413.xml">Toiati 2019</ref> for more on the production of paper soldiers).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>