<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1803">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>   [before 29 December 1855]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15616</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1803 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1803.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1803.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 263</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 5: 533</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, no. 52, 29 December 1855, p. 854</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Gard. Chron. 1855: 854</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1855-12-28">[before 29 Dec 1855]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1808.xml">Gardeners’ Chronicle</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD requests accurate information on the extent to which the different varieties of fruit-trees produce seedlings like their parents. Do some varieties of pears and apples tend to produce truer offspring than other varieties?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">apples</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">fruit trees</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">pears</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
<p>As several different statements have been published on how far the different varieties of our fruit trees produce seedlings like their parents, I think very interesting information might be given by some few of your correspondents who may have carefully sown named seeds and have noted the result. Jourdan (in the “Mémoires de l’Acad. de Lyons,” vol. ii., p. 94, 114)<ref target="#foot.f1"/> states most positively that he has tried repeatedly, and that all the many seedlings which he raised from the same variety of fruit tree resembled each other in foliage and general manner of growth as perfectly as do the young plants of any wild species whatever; and therefore that they differed from the seedlings of every other variety of the same fruit tree. Hence, also, as he asserts, the seedlings of one variety can never be confounded by an experienced eye with those of another variety, being as distinct as were their parents. Moreover, he states that the fruit of seedling Pears and Apples, though differing greatly in size, succulency, and flavour from those of their parents, yet resemble them in the more important characters of form and in the nature of their seeds. On the other hand Van Mons<ref target="#foot.f2"/> asserts that he sometimes raised from the seed of one variety of Pear a quite distinct kind; but it now appears that Van Mons was careless in marking the varieties sown.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> If any one can give accurate information on this curious subject, I hope that he will be so kind as to take the trouble to do so; and will give, as far as he can, some idea what proportion of seedlings are produced which resemble their parents in foliage and general habit; for if seedlings differ from their parents only in a few rare instances, this might perhaps be attributed to an accidental cross from some neighbouring tree. Is it known whether some varieties of Pears and Apples tend to produce truer offspring than other varieties? Plums are said to come very true. Mr. Rivers,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and possibly others, could probably give very interesting details on this head. <hi rend="underline">C. Darwin.</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had read <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexis Jordan’s</ref> article on fruit-trees (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4244.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jordan 1852</ref>) in September 1855 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV, 128: 14). His copy of the volume of the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de l’Academie Royal des Sciences, Belles-Lettres, et Arts de Lyon</hi>, in which the article appeared, is in the Darwin Library–CUL. On the cover, CD wrote ‘Given me by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lindley’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5538.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mons 1835–6</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1773.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 6 November [1855]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1920.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Decaisne 1855</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1773.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 6 November [1855]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Thomas Rivers, nurseryman, specialised in fruit-trees and roses. He was a regular contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>. CD cited him frequently in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>