<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7311">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Philip Lutley Sclater   30 August [1870]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">383</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7311 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7311.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7311.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">1p</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.383)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>383</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1870-08-30">30 Aug [1870]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4251.xml">Sclater, P. L.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Encloses, for publication, note about Pampas woodpecker, opposing W. H. Hudson [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">7354</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2429">Hudson, W. H.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Pampas</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down.</hi> | Beckenham | <hi rend="print">Kent. S.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>August 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sclater,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope the Society will permit the enclosed note to be read &amp; printed, as some palliation of my remarks on the woodpecker of the plains, versus M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hudson.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Yours’ very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In the last of Mr. Hudson’s valuable articles on the Ornithology of Buenos Ayres, he remarks, with respect to my observations on the <hi rend="underline">Colaptes campestris</hi>, that it is not possible for a naturalist ‘to know much of a species from seeing perhaps one or two individuals in the course of a rapid ride across the Pampas.’<ref target="#foot.f3"/> My observations were made in Banda Oriental, on the northern bank of the Plata, where, thirty-seven years ago, this bird was common; and during my successive visits, especially near Maldonado, I repeatedly saw many specimens living on the open and undulating plains, at the distance of many miles from a tree.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I was confirmed in my belief, that these birds do not frequent trees, by the beaks of some which I shot being muddy, by their tails being but little abraded, and by their alighting on posts or branches of trees (where such grew) horizontally and crosswise, in the manner of ordinary birds, though, as I have stated, they sometimes alighted vertically. When I wrote these notes, I knew nothing of the works of Azara,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> who lived for many years in Paraguay, and is generally esteemed as an accurate observer. Now Azara calls this bird the Woodpecker of the plains, and remarks that the name is highly appropriate; for, as he asserts, it never visits woods, or climbs up trees, or searches for insects under the bark.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> He describes its manner of feeding on the open ground, and of alighting, sometimes horizontally and sometimes vertically, on trunks, rocks, &amp;c., exactly as I have done. He states that the legs are longer than those of other species of Woodpeckers. The beak, however, is not so straight and strong, nor the tail-feathers so stiff, as in the typical members of the group. Therefore this species appears to have been to a slight extent modified, in accordance with its less arboreal habits. Azara further states that it builds its nest in holes, excavated in old mud walls or in the banks of streams. I may add that the <hi rend="underline">Colaptes pitius</hi>, which in Chile represents the Pampas species, likewise frequents dry stony hills, where only a few bushes or trees grow, and may be continually seen feeding on the ground. According to Molina, this <hi rend="underline">Colaptes</hi> also builds its nest in holes in banks.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Mr. Hudson, on the other hand, states that near Buenos Ayres, where there are some woods, the <hi rend="underline">Colaptes campestris</hi> climbs trees and bores into the bark like other Woodpeckers. He says, ‘it is sometimes found several miles distant from any trees. This, however, is rare, and it is on such occasions always apparently on its way to some tree in the distance. It here builds its nest in holes in trees.’<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have not the least doubt that Mr. Hudson’s account is perfectly accurate, and that I have committed an error in stating that this species never climbs trees.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> But is it not possible that this bird may have somewhat different habits in different districts, and that I may not be quite so inaccurate as Mr. Hudson supposes? I cannot doubt, from what I saw in Banda Oriental, that this species there habitually frequents the open plains, and lives exclusively on the food thus obtained. Still less can I doubt the account given by Azara of its general habits of life, and of its manner of nidification. Finally, I trust that Mr. Hudson is mistaken when he says that any one acquainted with the habits of this bird might be induced to believe that I ‘had purposely wrested the truth in order to prove’ my theory. He exonerates me from this charge; but I should be loath to think that there are many naturalists who, without any evidence, would accuse a fellow worker of telling a deliberate falsehood to prove his theory.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 Beckenham] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘<hi rend="italic">Bromley.</hi>’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.1 as] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘in’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.2 on] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘of’ </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the date the letters referred to in the enclosure were read (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Sclater was secretary of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zoological Society of London</ref>. At the 24 February and 24 March 1870 meetings of the society, letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Hudson</ref> were read in which Hudson claimed that CD was mistaken in his description of the pampas woodpecker, <hi rend="italic">Colaptes campestris</hi> (now known as the Campo flicker), as a ‘woodpecker which never climbs a tree’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 184; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hudson 1870</ref>, p. 112, and also n. 4, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hudson 1870</ref>, p. 158.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For CD’s observations of woodpeckers in South America, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi></ref> 3: 113–14, and Keynes ed. 2000, p. 156.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Félix d’Azara.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_267.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Azara 1802–5</ref>, 2: 311–15.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Colaptes pitius</hi> is now known as the Chilean flicker. Juan Ignacio (Giovanni Ignazio) Molina described the nesting behaviour of the bird in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5532.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Molina 1788–95</ref>, 1: 262. The passage is scored in CD’s copy of the book, which is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 595).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hudson 1870</ref>, p. 159.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD added a reference to Hudson’s account in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 142.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>