<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2346G">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Skeffington Poole   [21 October 1858]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21252</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2346G by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2346G.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2346G.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Draft or contemporary copy</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Ronald Levine, Modern 1st Editions (dealer) (no date)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_236.xml">Ronald Levine</repository>
                    <collection>no date</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3820.xml">Poole, Skeffington</persName>
                <date when="1858-10-21">[21 Oct 1858]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Information about about Kattywar (Kathiawari) horses in India.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Premising the breed of horses inquired about, to be that of Kattywar.—</p>
<p>I beg to offer the following replies to the questions sent, but at the same time give them from recollection only.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>(1) “Dunn” is a colour between a brown and a black, but there are various shades of it in the Katty horse—</p>
<p>“Dunn” has nothing to do with “<hi rend="underline">Cream Colour</hi>” A “cream-coloured” horse has a <hi rend="underline">mealy mouth</hi>, and this is never seen in a “<hi rend="underline">Dun</hi>” horse— Neither Bay nor Chestnut have anything to do with “<hi rend="underline">Dun</hi>” nor is it so understood in India— “Mouse-Dun” is a colour like a mouse, only tinged with “dun”. There are also <hi rend="underline">Mouse</hi> Coloured horses that you would not apply dun to at all.</p>
<p>(2) “Tiger Marks” are stripes on the cheeks, noses withers, and fore and hind legs, many shades darker than the colour of the horses, and are called so from their resemblance to the stripes on a Tiger.</p>
<p>I have never heard these stripes called “<hi rend="underline">Zebra Marks</hi>” by the Natives nor do I suppose the people of Kattywar, where these horses are bred ever saw or heard of a Zebra, besides which, the stripes on the Katty horse are not analogous to the Zebra— Colonel Curtis<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I daresay applies both terms with the same meaning.</p>
<p>(3) There are so many shades of “Dun”, “Mouse-dun”, &amp; Mouse colour that the colt or filly varies very much in colour when first foaled, and it would be almost impossible to describe what is asked—indeed none but a most experienced hand can tell what the colour of a foal will be—</p>
<p>The stripes are more distinct on the colts being first foaled than at any other time (just the same as the wild Ass, which is found in numbers on the banks of the Runn)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> they then become less &amp; less distinct till after the first coat is shed when they come out as strong as before, and fade or grow out as the age of the horse increases, but in some horses I have known the stripes perceptible at the age of 25 years</p>
<p>(4) The “Tiger” like bars, or stripes on the legs, are common in “dun”, “Mouse-dun” and “Mouse” coloured horses, the stripes are common on both fore and hind legs, but not more so on the fore than the hind legs— These stripes are also often to be seen on the cheeks and sides of the nose, also round the eyes— If this breed of horses of the above colour had not the stripes about them they would not be of the pure Katty breed—and horses of these colours without the stripes are not considered pure—</p>
<p>There are plenty of these coloured horses in “India” but they are an inferior Animal altogether</p>
<p>In Kutch the adjoining Province these coloured horses are numerous but worth very little in comparison, the pure Katty being valued at as many thousands of rupees as the Kutch is at hundreds—</p> 
<table>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">(5)</cell>
            <cell rend="left">(1)</cell>
             <cell rend="left">The shoulder stripe like that of a domesticated ass, is general on</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left"/>
            <cell rend="left"/>
            <cell rend="left">all these pure Katty horses of the above colours—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left"/>
            <cell rend="left">(2)</cell>
            <cell rend="left">One half of the “Indian dun” horses may have a shoulder stripe, and also have the “<hi rend="underline">List</hi>”—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left"/>
            <cell rend="left">(3)</cell>
            <cell>I have often seen the shoulder stripe <hi rend="underline">double</hi> and sometimes <hi rend="doubleUnderline">treble</hi>, these are considered extra well bred.</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
 
<p>(6) I have seen both Greys &amp; Bays with these stripes when first foaled but they soon fade away. I have never known them in a chestnut. Black horses are very rare in India—</p>
<p>(7) No crossing of other colours will produce a “<hi rend="underline">dun</hi>” in my opinion, either the dam or sire must be a “<hi rend="underline">dun</hi>”—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>(8) I don’t believe that any distinct breeds of horses whether “<hi rend="underline">dun</hi>” or any other colour when crossed would produce offspring with “<hi rend="underline">List</hi>” or shoulder “stripes” or tiger like stripes on the legs unless such marks appear in one of the parents.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Skeffington Poole</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2346F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">20 October [1858]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2346H.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 October [1858]</ref> (this volume, Supplement).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Skeffington Poole, 13 October [1858]</ref> and n. 4, and this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2346F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Skeffington Poole, 20 October [1858]</ref>. CD cited information from this letter in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, pp. 164 and 166, and <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 58 and 59.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2346F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Skeffington Poole, 20 October [1858]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Runn of Kutch (or Rann of Cutch) is a salt marsh north of Kathiawar (Kattywar).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">List: a stripe of colour (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD was interested in whether the dun colour in horses could appear when neither parent was dun, as an instance of reversion to the ancestral colour; see also this volume, Supplement, letter from J. K. Ince, [1857–61?] and n. 4.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>