<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5546">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Albert Gaudry<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   22 May 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16934</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5546 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5546.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5546.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 165: 15</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>165: 15</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1829.xml">Gaudry, A. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1867-05-22">22 May 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends a notice on a reptile intermediate between true Triassic reptiles and Devonian fishes ["Sur le reptile (<hi rend="italic">Actinodon</hi>)", <hi rend="italic">C. R. Hebd. Acad. Sci.</hi> 63 (1866): 341–4].</p> 
            <p>Expresses his admiration for CD, and his growing sense that transformation of species is probable, though he does not share CD’s explanation of the cause. He avoids the question, since he lacks requisite knowledge and is convinced that there are causes of which God alone knows the secret.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fishes</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">reptiles</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Devonian</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Triassic</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">intermediate forms, gradation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00079_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00079_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
        <surface n="15:1r" xml:id="i79">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00079.jpg" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00079_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00079.dzi" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="15:1v" xml:id="i80">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00080.jpg" width="3537px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00080_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3537px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00080.dzi" width="3537px" height="6087px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="15:2r" xml:id="i81">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00081.jpg" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00081_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00081.dzi" width="3475px" height="6087px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="15:2v" xml:id="i82">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00082.jpg" width="3537px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00082_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3537px" height="6087px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00082.dzi" width="3537px" height="6087px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je vous demande la permission de vous envoyer une note sur un reptile ancien qui semble intermèdiaire entre les vrais reptiles triasiques et les poissons dévoniens.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Je saisis cette occasion pour vous remercier de la lettre que vous avez bien voulu m’envoyer, il y a quelques mois.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> J’ai été très honoré qu’un naturaliste aussi éminent que vous attache de l’intérêt à mes recherches sur les transitions des animaux fossiles. Ce n’est pas sans raison qu’on me range parmi vos admirateurs, car si je ne partage pas toutes vos vues pour l’explication des transformations des êtres, du moins ces transformations me paraissent chaque jour plus probables, et votre livre sur l’origine des espèces aura puisamment contribué à les mettre en relief.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Je ne connais pas d’étude plus belle que celle de la filiation des êtres qui se développe pendant la durée indéfinie des âges, et je m’efforcerai d’apporter des preuves de cette filiation tirées de la paléontologie. Quant aux explications des transformations, j’évite de m’en occuper, parcequ’un sujet si difficile peut être abordé seulement par un naturaliste tel que vous, ayant une expérience consommée et une science très vaste. Je vous avouerai même qu’en étudiant l’embryogénie et en voyant qu’il y a bien des causes dont Dieu seul a le secret, je pense que, dans l’évolution des espèces comme dans l’embryogénie des individus, il y a des causes que les plus beaux génies ne sauraient découvrir.</p>
<p>Votre lettre m’a trouvé au M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Léberon, près de Cucuron (Vaucluse) dans un gisement fort riche où on rencontre la même faune qu’à Pikermi. Je n’ai pas encore dégagé les ossemens que j’ai rapportés; mais ce que j’éntrevois déjà me fait penser que les animaux du M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Léberon présentent de si légères différences avec ceux de Grèce qu’il est difficile de ne pas admettre entre eux des liens d’une réelle parenté, quoiqu’il n’y ait pas identité.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je serais bien heureux, Monsieur, si votre santé et vos grands travaux vous donnaient la possibilité de venir à Paris; je vous montrerais au jardin des plantes des fossiles qui me semblent de curieux intermédiaire.</p>
<p>Je vous prie d’agréer l’expression de mes sentiments les plus respectueux. | Albert Gaudry <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">12 Rue Taranne. Paris.</p>
<p rend="left">22 Mai 1867.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="cdnotes">
            <note>I quite agree about filiation of species, in a century to come there will be splendid work— I also agree how much unknown in Embryology &amp; causes of each variation—utterly unknown [<hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi>]— | My book in French | I am aware that few follow your views &amp; Most of your leading men are bitterly opposed | <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Paris</hi>—your papers</note>
              </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <div type="cdnotes">
                <ab><ref target="#foot.f6"/></ab>
                <note>I quite agree about filiation of species, in a century to come there will be splendid work— I also agree how much unknown in Embryology &amp; causes of each variation—utterly unknown [<hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi>— | My book in French | I am aware that few follow your views &amp; Most of your leading men are bitterly opposed | <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Paris</hi>—your papers</note>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Permit me to send you a work on an ancient reptile that seems intermediate between true Triassic reptiles and Devonian fish.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I take advantage of this opportunity to thank you for the letter you were kind enough to send me a few months ago.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I was very honoured that a naturalist as eminent as you should attach any interest to my research on the transitions of fossil animals. It is not without reason that I am regarded as one of your admirers, since, although I do not share all your views on the explanation of the transformations of living things, at least these transformations seem to me every day more probable, and your book on the origin of species contributed mightily to throw light on them.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I do not know of a finer study than that of the descent of living beings that occurs during ages of indefinite extent, and I will endeavour to give evidence for this descent drawn from palaeontology. As far as explanations of the transformations are concerned, I avoid addressing them, because such a difficult subject can be approached only by a naturalist such as you, who has thorough experience and extensive knowledge. I will also admit that by studying embryogeny and by seeing that there are indeed causes of which God alone knows the secret, I think that both in the evolution of species and the embryogeny of individuals, there are facts that the greatest geniuses will not be able to discover.</p>
<p>Your letter found me on M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Léberon, near Cucuron (Vaucluse) in a very rich fossil bed in which there is found the same fauna as in Pikermi. I have not yet cleaned up the bones that I have brought back, but what I can already see makes me think that the animals of M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Léberon present such small differences from those of Greece that it is difficult not to admit some links of a real kinship, although they are not of identical parentage.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I would be really pleased, dear Sir, if your health and your great works allowed you the opportunity to visit Paris; I would show you in the Jardin des Plantes some fossils which seem to me curiously intermediate.</p>
<p>Please accept the expression of my most respectful sentiments. | Albert Gaudry <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">12 Rue Taranne. Paris.</p>
<p rend="left">22 May 1867.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. 274.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Gaudry refers to his ‘Mémoire sur le reptile (<hi rend="italic">Pleuracanthus Frossardi</hi>) découvert par M. Frossard à Muse (Saône-et-Loire)’ (Gaudry 1867a). There is an inscribed and scored offprint of this article in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Gaudry also enclosed a second paper; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5554.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Gaudry, 27 May [1867]</ref> and n. 2. The name <hi rend="italic">Pleuracanthus</hi> had already been assigned to a genus of beetles: most members of <hi rend="italic">Pleuracanthus</hi> (freshwater sharks) have been reassigned to the genus <hi rend="italic">Xenacanthus.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5213.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Gaudry, 17 September [1866]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">After excavations at Pikermi in Attica in 1855 and 1860, Gaudry had reconstructed several skeletons of new species that appeared to be intermediate between species already known. He believed that such intermediates were evidence for transmutation, but differed from CD in believing that these transmutations were the result of continuing creation by God. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2748.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gaudry 1862–7</ref>, 1: 365–70. Gaudry had sent CD an extract from this work in 1866 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5213.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Gaudry, 17 September [1866]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Gaudry published on the fossils of Mont Léberon (now Montagne de Lubéron) in the south of France in Gaudry <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1873. He made comparisons with findings at Pikermi and other sites on pp. 75–98.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD’s note is for his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5554.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Gaudry, 27 May [1867]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>