<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1237">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Syms Covington<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   30 March 1849</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5386</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1237 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1237.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1237.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Ferguson (1971): 11</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 4: 229</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Sydney Mail</hi>, 9 August 1884, p. 254</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">De Beer, Gavin 1959b: 17</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Malvern</placeName>
                <date when="1849-03-30">30 Mar 1849</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1096.xml">Covington, Syms</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on developments in recent years, his father’s death, his own poor health, publications, and work on barnacles. Asks SC to collect some specimens, if he lives near the sea.</p>
            <p>News of FitzRoy and B. J. Sulivan.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1234">Darwin, R. W.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1650">FitzRoy, Robert</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4614">Sulivan, B. J.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">news</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough, Kent, [Malvern]</placeName>
                    <date>March 30, 1849.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Covington,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>It is now some years since I have heard from you, and I hope you will take the trouble to write to me to tell me how you and your family are going on.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I should much like to hear that your worldly circumstances are in a good position, and that you are every way fortunate. I hope that your deafness has not increased.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will now tell you about myself. My poor dear father, whom you will remember at Shrewsbury, died in his 84th year on the 13th of November. My health lately has been very bad, and I thought all this winter that I should not recover. I am now not at home (though I have so dated this letter) but have come to Malvern for two months to try the cold water cure, and I have already received so much benefit that I really hope my health will be much renovated. I have finished my three geological volumes on the voyage of the old Beagle, and my journal, which you copied, has come out in a second edition, and has had a very large sale.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I am now employed on a large volume, describing the anatomy and all the species of barnacles from all over the world. I do not know whether you live near the sea, but if so I should be very glad if you would collect me any that adhere (small and large) to the coast rocks or to shells or to corals thrown up by gales, and send them to me without cleaning out the animals, and taking care of the bases. You will remember that barnacles are conical little shells, with a sort of four-valved lid on the top. There are others with long flexible footstalk, fixed to floating objects, and sometimes cast on shore. I should be very glad of any specimens, but do not give yourself much trouble about them. If you do send me any, they had better be directed to the Geological Society, Somerset House, and a letter sent to inform me of them. I shall not publish my book for 18 months more.</p>
<p>I have now six children—three boys and three girls—and all, thank God, well and strong. I have not seen any of our old officers for a long time. Captain Fitz Roy has the command of a fine steamer frigate.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Captain Sulivan has gone out to settle for a few years, and trade at the Falkland Islands, and taken his family with him.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I know nothing of the others. You will remember Evans, my father’s butler at Shrewsbury; he and his wife are both dead. I should like to hear what you think of the prospects of your country. How is Captain King?<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Should you see Mr. Philip King,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> please say that I desired to be most kindly remembered to him; I was grieved to hear some long time since that he was out of health. Has he any family? I often think how many pleasant walks I had with him. Speaking of walks, I fear my day is done, and I could never tire you again. I have not been able to walk a mile for some years, but now with the water-cure I am getting stronger again. With every hope that you are happy and prosperous, believe me, dear Covington, your sincere well-wisher, C. DARWIN.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The text of this letter and of the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1370.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Syms Covington, 23 November 1850</ref>, were published in de Beer 1959b, pp. 17–20. Gavin de Beer’s transcripts of the texts differ considerably from the versions in the <hi rend="italic">Sydney Mail</hi> but according to de Beer the <hi rend="italic">Sydney Mail</hi> was the source of his versions, a fact that is corroborated by surviving material in de Beer’s papers in the archives of University College, London. The discrepancies are, perhaps, the result of de Beer revising the transcripts in accordance with what he knew of CD’s usual writing practices.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1096.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Syms Covington</ref>, CD’s servant during the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage and in London, 1837–9, had emigrated to Australia in May 1839 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-513.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to William Sharp Macleay, 29 May 1839</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In 1843 CD had sent Covington an ear-trumpet (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-700.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Syms Covington, 7 October 1843</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">By 1 January 1848, 4100 copies had been sold (‘Journal’; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix I).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">This was the Royal Navy’s first screw-driven steamship, the 360-ton <hi rend="italic">Arrogant</hi>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> conducted the trials of the new ship (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mellersh 1968</ref>, p. 260).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1228.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Richard Owen, [24 February 1849]</ref>, n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2697.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillip Parker King</ref>, captain of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> on its first survey, had retired and settled in Australia.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2696.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Gidley King</ref>, son of P. P. King, had sailed with CD in the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> as midshipman. He left the ship at Sydney to join his father and settled in Australia.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>