<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8724">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Francis Galton   4 January [1873]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3782</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8724 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8724.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8724.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 310, DAR 221.4: 178</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 43;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pearson (1914-30) 2: 176</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">UCL Library Services, Special Collections (GALTON/1/1/9/5/7/14)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_425.xml">UC London</repository>
                    <idno>GALTON/1/1/9/5/7/14</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1873-01-04">4 Jan [1873]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1797.xml">Galton, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on FG’s article ["Hereditary improvement", <hi rend="italic">Fraser’s Mag.</hi> 87 (1873): 116–30]. Finds it "the sole feasible, yet I fear utopian, plan of procedure in improving the human race".</p> 
            <p>Thanks for rabbits for Balfour.</p> 
<p>Mentions reading W. R. Greg’s <hi rend="italic">Enigmas</hi> [<hi rend="italic">of life</hi> (1872)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Enigmas of life</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fraser’s Mag.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_258">Balfour, F. M.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Galton, Francis 1873</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Greg, W. R. 1872</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Galton</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Very many thanks for Fraser: I have been greatly interested by your article.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The idea of castes being spontaneously formed &amp; leading to intermarriage is quite new to me, &amp; I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. suppose to others.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am not, however, so hopeful as you. Your proposed Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. would have awfully laborious work, &amp; I doubt whether you could ever get efficient workers.— As it is there is much concealment of insanity &amp; wickedness in families; &amp; there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be more if there was a register.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But the greatest difficulty, I think, w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be in deciding who deserved to be on the register. How few are above mediocrity in health, strength, morals &amp; intellect; &amp; how difficult to judge on these latter heads. As far as I see within the same large superior family, only a few of the children w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. deserve to be on the register; &amp; these w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. naturally stick to their own families, so that the superior children of distinct families would have no good chance of associating much &amp; forming a caste. Though I see so much difficulty, the object seems a grand one; &amp; you have pointed out the sole feasible, yet I fear utopian, plan of procedure in improving the human race.— I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be inclined to trust more (&amp; this is part of your plan) to disseminating &amp; insisting on the importance of the all-important principle of Inheritance.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I will make one or two minor criticisms. Is it not probable that the inhabitants of malarious countries owe their degraded &amp; miserable appearance to the bad atmosphere, though this does not kill them; rather than to “economy of structure”?<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I do not see that an orthognathous face w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. cost more than a prognathous face;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> or a good morale than a bad one.— That is a fine simile (p. 419) about the chip of a statue: but surely nature does not more carefully regard races than individuals, as (I believe I have misunderstood what you mean) evidenced by the multitude of races &amp; species which have become extinct.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Would it not be truer to say that nature cares only for the superior individuals &amp; thus makes her new &amp; better races.— But we ought both to shudder in using so freely the word “nature” after what Decandolle has said.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Again let me thank you for the interest received in reading your essay.</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Ch Darwin</p>
<p>Many thanks about the Rabbits: your letter has been sent to Balfour: he is a very clever young man, &amp; I believe owes his cleverness to Salisbury blood.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>This letter will not be worth your deciphering, I have almost finished Greg’s Enigmas.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> It is grand poetry—but too utopian &amp; too full of faith for me; so that I have been rather disappointed.— What do you think about it? He must be a delightful man.—</p>
<p>I doubt whether you have made clear how the families on the Register are to be kept pure or superior, &amp; how they are to be in course of time to be still further improved.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.9 large] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.10 own] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.17 probable] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘more’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.2 chip] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.3 more] <hi rend="italic">above del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.4 (I … mean)] <hi rend="italic">written in margin; square brackets in ms</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.6 new &amp; better] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to Galton’s article ‘Hereditary improvement’, which was published in January 1873 (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Galton’s article, ‘Hereditary improvement’ (Galton 1873a), was published in <hi rend="italic">Fraser’s Magazine</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Galton hoped that instituting widespread enquiries into heredity would create a sentiment of caste among the naturally gifted, and have an influence in creating common interests and friendships among the gifted families of each class, leading often to intermarriage (Galton 1873a, pp. 123–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Galton proposed the formation of a society to ‘institute <hi rend="italic">continuous</hi> enquiries into the facts of human heredity; … be a centre of information on heredity for breeders of animals and plants; and … discuss and classify the facts that were collected’ (Galton 1873a, p. 124). A register of naturally gifted individuals would eventually be drawn up (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 126).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Galton believed that research into heredity would in itself create widespread consciousness of the importance of considering natural ability in questions of marriage and reproduction (Galton 1873a, p. 125).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In Galton 1873a, p. 118, Galton wrote that people living in malarial regions had the gift of being able to survive fever, and ‘by the law of economy of structure’, were likely to be ‘deficient in every quality less useful to the exceptional circumstances of their life’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Galton wrote that travellers to Ireland after the potato famine noted that the ‘Irish type of face’ seemed to have become more prognathous, survivors of the famine having been, according to the travellers, ‘of a low and coarse organisation’ (Galton 1873a, p. 118).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">‘The life of the individual is treated [by Nature] as of absolutely no importance, while the race is treated as everything.... It is as though individual lives were of no more consideration than are the senseless chips which fall from the chisel of the artist who is elaborating some ideal form out of a rude block’ (Galton 1873a, p. 119).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In his <hi rend="italic">Histoire des sciences</hi>, a copy of which CD had received in 1872 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8593.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alphonse de Candolle, 2 November [1872]</ref>), Candolle discussed the sense of the word ‘nature’ and its derivations, and said that he himself had renounced all uses of the word except in discussing the nature of a particular thing or the natural as opposed to the artificial (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1873</ref>, pp. 432–6). Candolle and Galton were correspondents; Galton’s <hi rend="italic">English men of science</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1874</ref>) was prompted by <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1873</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pearson 1914–30</ref>, 2: 134).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For some years Galton had been breeding from rabbits transfused with the blood of different coloured rabbits in order to test CD’s hypothesis of pangenesis (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 340–57, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1871</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 18, 19, and 20). CD had kept and bred some of the transfused rabbits at Down (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 19 and 20). Galton’s letter has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_258.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Maitland Balfour</ref> wanted to repeat Galton’s experiments, and had asked for advice on the colours of rabbit to use (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8697.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Galton, 30 December [1872]</ref>). One of Balfour’s grandfathers was James Brownlow William Gascoyne-Cecil, the second marquess of Salisbury; CD alludes to Galton’s interest in the inheritance of intelligence (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2706.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1869</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1971.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Rathbone Greg’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Enigmas of life</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Greg 1872</ref>) included a chapter titled ‘Civilisation antagonistic to the law of “natural selection” ’, which discussed Galton’s and Darwin’s concerns. Greg suggested that the destructive effects of social progress would be mitigated as the upper classes became more enlightened and more willing to reproduce rationally, and the lower became better educated and less likely to reproduce prolifically; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 124.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>