<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4069">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>   [17–24 March 1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20106</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4069 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4069.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4069.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">Draft inc</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 77</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 11: 241</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi> n.s. 4 (1863): 237<ref target="#foot.f14"/> </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">J. Hortic. n.s. 4 1863: 237</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                            <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                            <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1863-03-17" notAfter="1863-03-24">[17–24 Mar 1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2615.xml">Journal of Horticulture</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Reports the observations of Hermann Crüger and John Scott that fruit is set by orchids whose flowers never open and that pollen-tubes are emitted from pollen-masses still in their proper position. These cases convince CD that in <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> he underestimated the power of tropical orchids to produce seed without insect aid but he is not shaken in his belief that the structure of the flowers is mainly related to insect agency.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">fruit</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4503">Cruger, Hermann</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4258">Scott, John</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Down]</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Had Mr. Anderson asked me two days ago for any facts illustrative of his case of unopened flowers of Cattleya crispa and Dendrobium cretaceum producing seed-capsules, I could have given no sort of information;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> nor can I now explain the fact. By an odd coincidence, yesterday I received a very interesting letter from Dr. Hermann Cruger, the Director of the Botanic Garden at Trinidad, who informs me that certain native species, and native species alone, of Cattleya, Epidendrum, and Schomburghkia, “are hardly ever known to open their flowers, but which nearly always set fruit.”<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In answer to Dr. Cruger, I have asked him to look at the seed or send me some, and inform me whether it appears good.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Will Mr. Anderson have the kindness to send me a few seeds produced by his unopened flowers?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I further asked Dr. Cruger whether these Orchids in their native haunts <hi rend="underline">never</hi> open their flowers.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I can hardly believe that this can be the case, seeing how manifestly adapted the structure of their organs of fructification is to the action of insects. But it is known that several plants, such as Violets, Campanulas, Oxalis, &amp;c., produce two kinds of flowers: one sort adapted for self-fertilisation, and the other sort for fertilisation by insect agency or other means.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> In some cases the two kinds of flowers differ very little in structure; and it occurs to me as possible that something of this kind may occur with Orchids.</p>
<p>Dr. Cruger further informs me that with certain Orchids, as in those which do not open their flowers, the pollen-masses after a time become pulpy; and though remaining still <hi rend="underline">in situ</hi>, emit their pollen-tubes, which reach the stigma, and thus cause fertilisation.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>An excellent observer, Mr. J. Scott, of the Royal Botanic Gardens of Edinburgh, will, I am sure, permit me to state that he has been making similar observations, and has seen the pollen-tubes emitted from the pollen-masses whilst still in their proper positions.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>These facts were all unknown to me when I published my small work on the Fertilisation of Orchids; but I ought, perhaps, to have anticipated their occurrence, for I saw the pollen-tubes emitted from the pollen within the anthers in the Bird’s-nest Orchid, and likewise in <hi rend="underline">monstrous</hi> flowers of the Man Orchis.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> This latter fact seems related to Mr. Anderson’s remark, that flowers of an imperfect character, wanting a petal or sepal, had a great tendency to produce seed-capsules.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>These curious observations by Dr. Cruger, Mr.  Anderson, and Mr. Scott, convince me that I have in my work underrated the power of tropical Orchids occasionally to produce seed without the aid of insects; but I am not shaken in my belief that their structure is mainly related to insect agency.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> With most British Orchids this conclusion may be looked on as established.</p>
<p>I will only add that since the publication of my work, a number of persons have set seed-capsules with various tropical Orchids.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Charles Darwin, <hi rend="underline">Down</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Bromley</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Kent.</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date range is established by the relationship between this letter and James Anderson’s article in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, 17 March 1863, pp. 206–8 (see n. 2, below), and by CD’s reference to this letter in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter to John Scott of 24 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In an article concerning orchid breeding, published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, 17 March 1863, pp. 206–8, James Anderson, who was a gardener in Uddingston, Scotland (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1994</ref>), asked if CD could tell him why some orchids, such as <hi rend="italic">Cattleya crispa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dendrobium cretaceum</hi>, formed apparently normal seed-capsules from apparently abortive, unopening flowers. CD’s unbound annotated copy of this number of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi> is in the Darwin Library–CUL; there are also notes on the article in DAR 70: 110–11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Crüger, 23 February 1863</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The letter to Crüger has not been found; however, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Crüger, 23 April 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4071.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Anderson, 1 April 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See n. 4, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had long been interested by the occurrence in some plants of ‘imperfect’, unopening flowers in which self-pollination occurred (a phenomenon later called cleistogamy). His ‘provisional conclusion’ was that ‘the final object of the imperfect flowers is to produce seed safely, <hi rend="italic">without any crossing</hi> … the perfect flowers being adapted for getting an occasional cross’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3504.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 12 [April 1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD cited this information in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 152 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 149).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">No letter from John Scott has been found recording observations of pollen-tubes emitted from pollen masses while still <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi>; moreover, Scott denied having made such claims in his <ref target="" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to CD of [1–11] April [1863]</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref>. However, Scott had carried out, at CD’s suggestion, numerous experiments on the emission of pollen-tubes from pollen masses placed on the rostellum of orchids (see, for example, letters from John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">6 January 1863</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3921.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 January 1863</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 March [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 324 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, 17 March 1863, p. 107.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 1, CD stated that the object of the book was: <quote type="quote"> to show that the contrivances by which Orchids are fertilised, are as varied and almost as perfect as any of the most beautiful adaptations in the animal kingdom; and, secondly, to show that these contrivances have for their main object the fertilisation of each flower by the pollen of another flower. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">The only individual identified is Scott, who had succeeded in pollinating <hi rend="italic">Acropera loddigesii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gongora atropurpurea</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3800.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 11 November 1862</ref>, and this volume, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4021.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 3 March 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">There is an incomplete two-page draft of this letter at the <ref target="" resp="#mjhawkins">American Philosophical Society</ref>, Philadelphia.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>