<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6352F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Emanuel Bonavia   [before 7 September 1868]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21304</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6352F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6352F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6352F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete<ref target="#foot.f4"/></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 26 September 1868, p. 1013 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Gardeners’ Chronicle, 26 Sept 1868, p. 1013</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_520.xml">Bonavia, Emmanuel</persName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1868-09-06">[before 7 Sept 1868]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Peloric forms of flowers: <hi rend="italic">Clitoria Ternatea</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Regarding peloric forms of flowers, I have observed an instance which appears unrecorded in the Clitoria Ternatea. I send you herewith two imperfect coloured drawings, made by a native artist, to illustrate the striking difference between the irregular and peloric form.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The Clitoria Ternatea is a scandent twining plant, with solitary flowers in the axils of the leaves. As you know, the vexillum, contrary to most pea-shaped flowers, is lowermost. No. 1 shows the irregular form. It presents the following characters:—Segment of calyx corresponding to the carina longest, vexillum large, emarginate, having in its middle part a yellowish white patch, with veins pinnately disposed, its margins meet round the alæ and carina; alæ small, with recurved blue margins adhering to the carina; carina white, completely enclosed by the alæ; stamens ten, diadelphous.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In the fully developed peloric flower of the Clitoria Ternatea the alæ, carinæ, and vexillum are of equal size; they all have that middle yellowish white patch which, in the irregular form, is found only in the vexillum. Some flowers are so beautifully peloric that there is no distinguishing which petal represents the vexillum. I made a section with a knife through all the petals of one of these forms. This section shows well the twisted disposition of the petals, each of which is overlapped by the edge of the next petal. The stamens are ten, and all free and regularly disposed. This peloric form is transmitted by seed. Different forms of Clitoria graduate from the ordinary irregular shape up to the perfectly peloric flower. Different degrees of pelorism are found as a rule on different plants, but many degrees are often found on the same plant. I have observed six well marked degrees:—</p>
<p>A. Natural. Alæ small, edges recurved, and completely hiding the carina; one stamen free, nine united. This form I have always seen by itself on a plant. No peloric ones on same plant.</p>
<p>B. One of the alæ larger than the other, more expanded, allowing the carina (which is a little larger than usual) to be visible; three stamens free, seven united.</p>
<p>C. Alæ much developed, and only one of the petals of the carina largely developed; two stamens united, eight free.</p>
<p>D. Alæ almost as large as the vexillum, but still occupying the place of the alæ; petals of carina both much developed, but still somewhat enclosed by the alæ; all stamens free.</p>
<p>E. All the five petals are equal in size and similarly marked, but in æstivation the vexillum is still the outermost petal: the other four petals have a somewhat twisted disposition, totally different from that of alæ and carinæ; all stamens free. The plants which bear this form also bear some flowers, which are</p>
<p>F. Perfectly peloric, and in which (all stamens free, and regularly disposed) neither vexillum, alæ, or carinæ are distinguishable. One edge of each petal is free, while the other is overlapped by the free edge of the petal next to it.</p>
<p>I have seen several specimens with four petals only, of equal size, and with eight stamens. I have white varieties of this Clitoria, which are also peloric.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from M. T. Masters, 7 September 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Clitoria ternatea</hi>, a tropical plant in the family Leguminosae, is known as the butterfly pea, blue pea, or blue vine (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mabberley 1997</ref>). Leguminous flowers are normally bilaterally symmetrical; peloric forms are abnormal variants displaying radial symmetry. CD discussed other peloric plants, including his experiments on <hi rend="italic">Antirrhinum</hi> (the snapdragon), in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 58–60, 345–6. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 11–14. Bonavia observed <hi rend="italic">C. ternata</hi> in Lucknow, where he was the civil surgeon with the Bengal Medical Service (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oldenburg 1984</ref>, p. 97, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1782.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Darmanin 1998</ref>). The drawings have not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In leguminous flowers, the vexillum or standard is the largest, and usually the uppermost, petal, and encloses the others; the alae are the side petals; and the carina consists of the two lower and usually smallest petals (see A. Gray 1857a). The drawings were not reproduced in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, where this excerpt from Bonavia’s letter was published.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The original letter, of which this is an excerpt, has not been found; CD sent it to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3217.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maxwell Tylden Masters</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from M. T. Masters, 7 September 1868</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>