<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8718">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alois Humbert<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   [before 18] January 1873<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16268</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8718 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8718.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8718.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (French) inc †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 89: 76</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>89: 76</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2442.xml">Humbert, Alois</persName>
                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1873-01-17">[before 18] Jan 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>On a humming-bird <hi rend="italic">Sphinx</hi> moth which tried to extract nectar from flowers on wallpaper. [See <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>, 2d ed., p. 317.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">humming-bird</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">moth</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Sphinx</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nectar</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00162_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3826px" height="6537px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00162_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3826px" height="6537px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="76r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00162.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3826px" height="6537px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00162_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3826px" height="6537px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00162.dzi" width="3826px" height="6537px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="76v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00163.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3625px" height="6564px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00163_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3625px" height="6564px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00089-000-00163.dzi" width="3625px" height="6564px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai pour cabinet de travail, pendant l’été, une chambre qui est tapissée d’un papier semé de bouquets de fleurs disposés en rangées verticales. Ces bouquets sont composés de coquelicots et de bluets dont le facies est assez bien rendu, et de quelques autres fleurs reproduites avec plus de fantaisie.</p>
<p>La chambre en question étant située au premier étage &amp; dominant une terrasse bordée de massifs de fleurs, il y entre souvent des insectes ailés par la fenêtre qui est presque constamment ouverte pendant la journée; les Moro-sphinx (<hi rend="underline">Macroglossa stellatarum</hi>)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> me font en particulier de fréquentes visites. Quelquefois cet insecte ne fait qu’entrer brusquement &amp; ressortir aussitôt comme un trait. D’autres fois, lorsqu’un individu a pénétré à une certaine distance dans la chambre, les fleurs de la tapisserie attirent son attention &amp; il se précipite sur un des bouquets.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Après avoir vainement essayé de plonger sa trompe dans les différentes fleurs, il passe, par un mouvement rapide, de ce premier bouquet à celui qui est immédiatement au dessus, puis au suivant, en allant toujours d’un de ces groupes de fleurs à celui qui lui est immédiatement supérieur. Lorsqu’il a ainsi exploré tous les bouquets d’une des bandes verticales de la tapisserie, il saute brusquement à un des bouquets d’une série voisine, et recommence sa même manœuvre, c’est à dire s’arrête successivement devant chaque bouquet de la rangée, en progressant de bas en haut.</p>
<p>Suivant les cas, le Sphinx reste plus ou moins longtemps dans la chambre et s’arrête devant un plus ou moins grand nombre de bouquets, puis il repart subitement par la fenêtre. L’individu que j’ai vu persévérer avec le plus d’acharnement dans ces efforts inutiles explora successivement au moins de 25 à 30 bouquets.—</p>
<p>Aloïs Humbert <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Genève. Janvier 1873.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.7 Après … fleurs, 2.8] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘The Humming-Bird Sphinx Moth fly to flowers, on Wall-paper’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My study during the summer is a room hung with a paper strewn with bunches of flowers arranged in vertical rows. These bunches are made up of poppies and cornflowers, whose appearance is fairly well rendered, and of a few other flowers reproduced with more freedom.</p>
<p>As the room in question is situated on the first floor and overlooks a terrace edged with flower borders, winged insects often come in through the window, which is nearly always open during the day; Humming-bird sphinxes (<hi rend="underline">Macroglossa stellatarum</hi>)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> in particular pay me frequent visits. Sometimes this insect only enters abruptly &amp; leaves again like a shot. On other occasions, once an individual has penetrated a certain distance into the room, the flowers on the wallpaper attract its attention &amp; it launches itself at one of the bunches.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> After having tried in vain to plunge its proboscis into the various flowers, it goes in a swift motion from this initial bunch to the one immediately above it then to the next, going always from one of these groups of flowers to one immediately above it. When it has thus explored all the bunches in one of the vertical stripes, it skips abruptly to one of the bunches in an adjacent sequence, and begins the same manoeuvre again, that is to say it stops in front of each bunch in the row in succession, progressing from the bottom to the top.</p>
<p>Depending on the case, a Sphinx moth may remain in the room for more or less time, stopping in front of a greater or lesser number of bunches, before suddenly departing out of the window. The individual that I saw persevere most doggedly in these fruitless efforts explored at least 25 to 30 bunches in succession.—</p>
<p>Aloïs Humbert <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Geneva. January 1873.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 47–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8741.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alphonse de Candolle, 18 January [1873]</ref>. This letter may have been enclosed with the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8737.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alphonse de Candolle, 14 January 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Macroglossa stellatarum</hi> is now known as <hi rend="italic">Macroglossum stellatarum</hi> (the humming-bird hawk-moth; CD knew it as the humming-bird sphinx, see his annotation).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8672.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alphonse de Candolle, 11 December 1872</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20), CD asked Candolle about butterflies alighting on brightly coloured dresses. CD added Humbert’s testimony to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 317 (without mentioning his name); see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 400.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>