<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10425">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. C. Sorby   22 March 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10771</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10425 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10425.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10425.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 218</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 218</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4469.xml">Sorby, H. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Broomfield, Sheffield</placeName>
                <date when="1876-03-22">22 Mar 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses chemical tests for the detection of glucose and cane-sugar in solution.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cane-sugar</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Broomfield | Sheffield.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>March 22/76</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am sorry you should have felt any kind of hesitation in writing to ask my help in any of your researches since at any time I shall be only too glad to do what I can to assist in any experiments that you may think it desirable to make.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I only wish I could do more than I fear is possible in the case you name. Assuming that the sugar is glucose (i:e: grape sugar) the most delicate test I know is to take an ammoniacal solution of oxide of copper so dilute as to be only just a faint blue and to observe whether it is decolourized by boiling with the suspected substance. I really cannot say how small a quantity of glucose could be detected in this manner, but it must be a very small fraction of a grain—perhaps less than <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn> 100</mn></mfrac></math></formula>th. Perhaps other tests might be found but it would require considerable research to be sure. Even this is not a certain proof but if no decolourization occurred it would prove that <hi rend="underline">glucose</hi> is absent or in very minute quantity. I do not know any very delicate test for cane sugar.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In order to use the test one ought to have the leaves tolerably fresh and damp. If you like to send some I will try what I can do but will not promise that the results will be satisfactory.</p>
<p>All being well I must leave here for London on April 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. so you ought to send the leaves as soon as you can.</p>
<p>I inclose a ticket for my conversazione. I should be delighted to see you at it but if you could not come, perhaps one of your sons could. I have therefore filled it up merely M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Yours very truly | H. C. Sorby</p>
<p>I will send you a corrected copy of my address.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Before you publish any thing on the subject, drop me a line, so that I may let you have the most recent results.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter to Sorby has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The experiments were probably related to CD’s research on the conversion of starch to grape sugar by the digestive fluid of earthworms (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>, p. 37). Cane sugar: sucrose.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Sorby gave a conversazione to the fellows of the Microscopical Society at King’s College, London, on 21 April 1876. He exhibited a binocular spectroscope and illustrated his new method of measuring the position of bands in the spectra (<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 27 April 1876, p. 530).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Sorby had given the presidential address to the Royal Microscopical Society on 2 February 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sorby 1876</ref>; an annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL). On pp. 118–21, there was a discussion of CD’s theory of pangenesis.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>