<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9698">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   26 October 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5299</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9698 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9698.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9698.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 62</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 62</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1874-10-26">26 Oct 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>, 2d ed.</p> 
            <p>Comments on German edition of CD’s collected works.</p> 
<p>Sales of his <hi rend="italic">Anthropogenie</hi> [1874] in various countries.</p> 
            <p>Anticlericalism and progress of Darwinism in Germany.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Anthropogenie</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">anticlericalism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>26. Oct. 74.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Erst vor wenigen Tagen bin ich von einer zweimonatlichen Reise (nach Tyrol und Schweiz) hierher zurückgekehrt, und fand hier Ihren gütigen Brief vor, für welchen ich Ihnen <hi rend="underline">herzlichst</hi> danke.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Es ist mir immer die grösste Freude, wenn ich von Ihnen direct höre, und besonders, dass es <hi rend="underline">gut</hi> geht. Letzteres schliesse ich daraus, dass Sie von Ihrer Gesundheit Nichts sagen; es ist immer das Beste, wenn man davon schweigen kann. Auch las ich mit grossem Vergnügen von den höchst interessanten Versuchen über die Verdauungskraft gewisser Pflanzen!<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Welche merkwürdige Anpassung!</p>
<p>Für meine Anthropogenie erbitte ich bei Ihnen freundliche Aufnahme.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ich habe mich mit diesem Werke ununterbrochen und ausschliesslich seit meiner Rückkehr aus dem Orient (Mai 1873) beschäftigt. Es war ein hartes Stück Arbeit, zumal es <hi rend="underline">sehr schwer</hi> ist, die Ontogenie <hi rend="underline">populär</hi> darzustellen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Ich fürchte auch, dass der Versuch nur halb geglückt ist. Jedoch ist das Interesse für den Gegenstand (—Dank <hi rend="underline">Ihren</hi> bahnbrechenden Werken!—) jetzt ungemein gross, und so kommt es, dass die erste Auflage (2000)) jetzt schon verkauft ist, und dass eine zweite (<hi rend="underline">unveränderte</hi>) demnächst erscheinen wird. Leider sind die Holzschnitte nicht gut gedruckt; das würde in England viel besser sein.</p>
<p>—Nichts würde mich mehr freuen, als wenn Sie mit dem Werke zufrieden wären. Besonders würde es mich freuen, wenn die genetischen <hi rend="underline">Tabellen</hi> Ihren Beifall fänden. Die Tabellen über die <hi rend="underline">Perioden</hi> in der <hi rend="underline">Phylogenie der Organe</hi> (XXI–XXXVI) sind allerdings auch nur ein erster Versuch; allein ich glaube, dass sie sehr vervollkommnungsfähig sind, und dass sie das Verständniss der historischen Entwickelung des scheinbar teleologisch gebauten Organismus durch bloss mechanische Selection (Hereditaet und Adaptation) sehr fördern werden.</p>
<p>Besonderen Dank habe ich Ihnen noch für die freundliche Übersendung des neuen Abdrucks Ihres schönen Werkes über die Coral-Reefs zu sagen.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Mögen demselben noch viele andere folgen!</p>
<p>In Deutschland hat der Darwinismus im letzten Jahre <hi rend="underline">sehr grosse</hi> Fortschritte gemacht, besonders unter den <hi rend="underline">Philosophen</hi>. Die <hi rend="underline">principielle</hi> Bedeutung desselben, und besonders seiner Anwendung auf den Menschen, tritt immer mehr in den Vordergrund, und Sie erleben jetzt noch den grossen Triumph, durch Ihre grossartige Reform der Biologie das <hi rend="underline">ganze Getriebe</hi> der menschlichen <hi rend="underline">Wissenschaften</hi> in eine neue, höchst fruchtbare und zukunftsreiche Bahn gelenkt zu haben! Mögen Sie sich dessen noch lange erfreuen!</p>
<p>Von ganzem Herzen Ihr treu ergebener E. Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>26. Oct. 74.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Only a few days ago I arrived back here after two months of travelling (in Tyrolia and Switzerland), and found your kind letter, for which I thank you <hi rend="underline">most cordially</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It always makes me so very happy to hear from you directly, especially that you are <hi rend="underline">well</hi>. The latter I infer from your silence about your health; it’s always best if there is nothing to tell. I also read with great pleasure about the most interesting experiments regarding the digestive powers of certain plants!<ref target="#foot.f3"/> What a remarkable adaptation!</p>
<p>My Anthropogenie I beg you to receive kindly.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have been working on it without interruption and exclusively since my return from the Orient (May 1873).<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It was a demanding piece of work, particularly as it is <hi rend="underline">very difficult</hi> to give a popular account of ontogeny. I also fear that my attempt has been only half successful. But general interest in the subject is immense right now (— thanks to <hi rend="underline">your</hi> pathbreaking works!—), which is why the first edition (2000) is already sold out, and a second (<hi rend="underline">unaltered</hi>) one will appear soon. Alas, the woodcuts have not come out so well; this would be much better in England.</p>
<p>—Nothing would please me more than if you were satisfied with this work. Above all I would be glad if the genetic <hi rend="underline">tables</hi> won your approval. The tables on the <hi rend="underline">periods</hi> of the <hi rend="underline">phylogeny of organs</hi> (XXI–XXXVI) are only a first attempt, but I believe they have potential for great improvement, and that they will very much aid the understanding of historical development of seemingly teleologically constructed organisms, through simple mechanical selection (heredity and adaptation).</p>
<p>You have my special thanks for kindly sending me the new edition of your beautiful work on the coral reefs.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> May many more follow this one!</p>
<p>In Germany Darwinism has made <hi rend="underline">very great</hi> progress over the past year, especially among <hi rend="underline">philosophers</hi>. Its <hi rend="underline">fundamental</hi> significance, and especially its application to mankind, is becoming more and more apparent, and you are now experiencing the great triumph of having guided, through your splendid reform of biology, the <hi rend="underline">entire driving force</hi> of human <hi rend="underline">knowledge</hi> in a new and most fertile and promising direction! May you enjoy this for a long time yet! With all my heart, your loyally devoted E. Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9647A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 20 September 1874</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haeckel refers to CD’s work on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9647A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 20 September 1874</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel had sent CD his book <hi rend="italic">Anthropogenie, oder Entwickelungsgeschichte des Menschen</hi> (Haeckel 1874a); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9647A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 20 September 1874</ref>. CD’s copy of Haeckel 1874a is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Between March and June 1873, Haeckel had visited Egypt, Turkey, Greece, and the Sinai Peninsula to study corals (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4494.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Krauße 1987</ref>, pp. 84–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel refers to the second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>