<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-25">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. A. Darwin   [9 March 1826]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6012</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-25 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-25.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-25.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">AL</note>
            <note type="physdesc">AL 4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">Glasgow 405 9 MAR 1826</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 14</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 14</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Darwin, E. A.</persName>
                <placeName>[Glasgow]</placeName>
                <date when="1826-03-09">[9 Mar 1826]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes his trip by canal to Glasgow, and sightseeing there.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">canal</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Glasgow</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Glasgow]</placeName>
                    <salute>Dear C</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You asked me if I had time in plenty to write from Glasgow, &amp; time I have in plenty enough to write more than ever you could read. The Steam Vessel does not sail till the middle of Friday so that I have two days &amp; a half complete to spend here &amp; nothing in the world to do with myself. I shall in consequence give you a most detailed account of the journey. I got into the Tun a little before nine o’clock. There is little or nothing to be seen the whole way at least I saw nothing being confined to the cabbin from the rain which more or less was almost incessant. They have the providence to put books in the Cabin &amp; in the course of the day I read a volume of Guy Mannering of Mid Lothian,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> L’Amie Inconnue The Lounger &amp; several No’s of the Monthly Review<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; also divers Newspapers. They give a very decent breakfast &amp; at one ‘oclock I got some biscuits &amp; ’decoction of what do you call it to wit porter which served for the first boat. The canal goes thro’ a mountain by means of a tunnel 1/2 mile long &amp; which has quite a beautiful effect. It then by means of a vast number of locks goes down a Hill, but the passengers get out &amp; walk down to the second boat. I was then the only Cabin passenger, the others having dropt away one by one.</p>
<p>About four dinner. Cold veal, ham &amp; beef ham &amp; roast potatoes &amp; some most excellent bottled Ale which I recommend to your attention. Another passenger now joined us &amp; when it grew dark we played at backgammon &amp; drank some toddy till we arrived. I got a porter, took his number &amp; left him to bring my luggage up at his leisure to the Eagle, in Maxwell St. which cost 1/6. The Steam Vessel is y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Henry Bell, from Greenock. The Sovreign Steam Boat goes from the Broomielaw at Glasgow to Greenock at 12 noon. You take your passage at Laird &amp; Co 25 York St Glasgow.— This is all copied from one of the papers. Another vessel I believe sails on Tuesday but I do not know any thing about it. I found my Backgammon friend very useful as he told me all about the vessels &amp; shewed me the way to the inn.</p>
<p>I went to the college in High St which is a very handsome old building &amp; heard Thomson<ref target="#foot.f3"/> from 10 to 11. His room is not bigger than Alisons<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; has not as many pupils I think &amp; altogether a most vile turn out. He Lectures in the most singular manner about two words &amp; then a pause sitting quite quietly in his chair. Most of the students wear red gowns &amp; are a step worse than the Edinenses. I shall not try for Ure<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but the Andersonian Institution<ref target="#foot.f6"/> is in John St. I believe I saw the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> himself but am not the least sure.</p>
<p>Valeas. Read &amp; Burn.</p>
<p>I see a concert advertised here the performers Miss Paton M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thorne! Miss Noel!!— Miss Dyer came from Glasgow originally.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><hi rend="italic">Guy Mannering</hi> was published anonymously in 1815. Sir <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4262.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walter Scott’s</ref> authorship remained a closely guarded secret until 1827.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">L’amie inconnue</hi> has not been identified. <hi rend="italic">The Lounger: a periodical paper, published at Edinburgh in the years 1785 and 1786</hi> (by H. Mackenzie and others); <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Erasmus</ref> probably read one of the editions in two or three volumes that were issued in later years. <hi rend="italic">The Monthly</hi> <hi rend="italic">Review (or Literary Journal)</hi> (1749–1825); new series, London (1826–8). [Update 21 August 2009: <hi rend="italic">L’Amie Inconnue</hi> identified as <hi rend="italic">Angelina, or L’Amie Inconnue</hi> in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1452.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maria Edgeworth’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Moral Tales</hi>, first published in 1801, probably from 8th ed., 3 vols, 1821 (in 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> vol.).]</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4736.xml">Thomas Thomson</ref>, Regius Professor of Chemistry at Glasgow University.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_78.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Pulteney Alison</ref>, Professor of ‘Institutes of Medicine’ at Edinburgh University.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4846.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Ure</ref>, editor of <hi rend="italic">A dictionary of chemistry</hi>, was Professor of Chemistry at Anderson’s Institution, Glasgow.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Anderson’s Institution, founded in 1796, later affiliated with the University of Glasgow. In 1964 it was given a charter as the University of Strathclyde.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>