<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6592">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. V. Carus   2 February 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8698</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6592 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6592.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6592.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp encl 2pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 86: A45; DAR 161: 69</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 69,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>86: A45</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml">Carus, J. V.</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1869-02-02">2 Feb 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends translation of Mr Steiger’s letter responding to question CD had asked about growth of horns of merino rams.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rams, merino</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Steiger, Mr</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>39, Elsterstrasse, Leipzig</placeName>
                    <date>Febr 2 1869.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I send you hereby the translation of Mr Steiger’s answer, the latter part in a somewhat condensed form.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> You see he has had just as little opportunity of comparing different races as Mr Sison; and even his observations on the growth of the horn are just as vague as Sison’s.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> So I regret, not to be able to give you more facts to the purpose. But on the whole both concur in the fact that the horns do not appear earlier in the Merinos than in other breeds.</p>
<p>In the case you should wish for more information I am afraid I shall not be able to get it here in Saxony. I wrote to Dresden to ask our Secretary to the Government for Agriculture for directions of breeders, and I got Mr Steiger’s name.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I then applied to our Agricultural school, now in the way of being connected with the University, and I received Mr Sison’s address<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Now I confess I don’t know where to apply for more.</p>
<p>I hope you are pretty well. We all look forward for good news from you.</p>
<p>I remain | My dear Sir | Yours very sincerely | J. Victor Carus</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre">Mr.<hi rend="underline"> Steiger’s</hi> answer.</p> 
<p>On reading again Mr. Darwin’s book on the origin of species, I see that I am too little of a scientific observer for being able to enter into a thorough discussion of my views. If not in the whole extent yet on the whole I have found Darwin’s principles to be true. But that is just, what strikes me, that I don’t see, why a thing is proved by so many words, what I found true by a thirty years working in practical breeding. I think it ridiculous with Mr. Darwin to call a great many varieties “races”, which are nothing but little variations of one species and cannot yet claim that title. I lay more stress than Darwin on other causes, not only on the selection.</p>
<p>Nearly all Saxon races are Merinos, in modern times there have some English Southdowns<ref target="#foot.f5"/> come true   My observations have been made therefore only on Merinos and I am not able to compare the growth of the horns in Merinos with other breeds. Our Merino-males are all horned, a small part also of the females. They are the descendants of those Spanish Merinos which had been brought to Saxony in the last half of the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. century.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> My flock is descended, also on the part of the mother, from this <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> Spanish immigration. In the Rambouillet and Negretti breeds it was said, that in the pure breed the ewes are not horned.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> But it is proved that even in Spain the ewes bear sometimes horns. With us about 3–5 percent of the ewes are horned, while the males are all so, except some few exceptions, which occur now very seldom. These not-horned rams (the so-called Kalben-böke)<ref target="#foot.f8"/> are not liked, properly speaking without reason.</p>
<p>The horns of the Merino rams are immediately after birth mostly present as small projections on the skull; they go on growing nearly equally as the whole animal. They are fully developed when the animal has attained its full growth, in the third year of its age. In the horned ewes the horns are also visible after birth but they remain small, about the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. or 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. part of the weight of a male horn, the growth is nearly equal, in the same rate as the animal grows.</p>
<p>I tried to find if the formation of horns wants a larger amount of food; but all I found is, that the males want on the whole much more food than the ewes.</p>
<p>The castrated rams want less; but in these the horns are also often much smaller, so that I am inclined to think that the secretion or formation of the semen wants most of the food. In castrated animals all the other parts grow much quicker. Animals, on which the not-fleshy parts are covered with wool, are very difficult to breed and to keep so, and more difficult the male animals than the female and the castrated.</p>
<p>One observation is perfectly sure: that the horn of the male, as well as that of the female animal corresponds exactly to the nature of the whole animal, just as any other part. And this is the point which I should have liked to discuss with Mr Darwin.</p>
<p>While almost all breeders believe to be able to breed single parts or forms of single parts, I think the differences rest on illusion. The head of the English flesh-cattle is not absolutely smaller, but only so in relation to the greater amount of flesh on the fore part of the body, etc. etc.</p>
<p>Just the same holds good with the texture of the parts. Flesh, wool, skeleton, all that stands in close harmony.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure</hi>:</note>
                <note>2.1 On reading … reason 3.12] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.9 3–5 percent] ‘<hi rend="superscript">3–5/100</hi> Horned’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 The horns … animal. 4.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.4 In the … grows. 4.6] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 One … harmony. 9.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of enclosure:</hi> ‘All parts change in correlation.—’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi>; ‘(I think I must say that at least no great difference in development, as Horns appear so very early in Merinos.)’<ref target="#foot.f9"/> <hi rend="italic">ink; square brackets in MS</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. V. Carus, 22 January 1869</ref>. Steiger has not been further identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Carus refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6752.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Sison</ref> and the observations on merino sheep in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sison 1867</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. V. Carus, 22 January 1869</ref> and nn. 3 and 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Dresden was the capital of the Prussian province of Saxony (Sachsen). The government official has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Carus refers to the Landwirtschaftliche Institut (agricultural institute) of the University of Leipzig; the institute was founded in 1869 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4385.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kirchner 1904</ref>, p. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Southdown is a native English breed, the name of which derived from the South Down hills around Lewes in East Sussex. For more on the development of the breed, see Wood and Orel 2001, pp. 77–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. V. Carus, 22 January 1869</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The Rambouillet merino, developed from several Spanish flocks, was named after the royal experimental farm near Versailles in France (see Wood and Orel 2001, pp. 137–8). The Negretti breed was developed in Austria-Hungary from Spanish Negretti and Infantado flocks (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 179–80).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Kalben-böcke: calf-rams (German).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. V. Carus, 5 February 1869</ref> and n. 2.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>