<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5325">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. J. Sulivan   25 December 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14589</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5325 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5325.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5325.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">12pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 287</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 287</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml">Sulivan, B. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                <date when="1866-12-25">25 Dec 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the South American mission.</p>
            <p>Has been busy digging out fossil leaves from local Eocene deposits.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Eocene deposits</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, South</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Bournemouth</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">mission</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                    <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 25 | 66.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many happy returns of the season to you and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Darwin<ref target="#foot.f1"/> as well as all your party. The last account of your health was so much more cheering that I hope to hear it has continued to improve. I have had my Turkish bath at work for six weeks and I think my head gets steadily better, though slowly, and for the first time for some years I have gone so far into winter without the slightest cold or cough.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am thankful to say I can say the same of all our party so I hope Bournemouth will suit us all—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>A few days since I went to Bristol to see our Mission schooner ready for sea, and also to see the Fuegian lads before they return.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> They have been with a farmer who speaks highly of their conduct</p>
<p>I should have known Jimmy’s son from the likeness, he is said to be a very nice lad &amp; good disposition—but not so intelligent as one of them from Packsaddle Bay.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> One can hardly believe that this lad was the same race as those we saw along side in that Bay where we taught them to rub their noses and say “Old Stokes”—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> There is another lad of that party who has been at the Falkland Station,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and lately a Merchant vessel taking refuge there this lad went on board and asked the Capt to tell M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Stirling (our clergyman there), to come back to them soon<ref target="#foot.f8"/>—and he was so anxious to go away in the schooner to the Falklands that the Father insisted on his leaving her &amp; did not bring him again. This shows that some good influence is beginning to work &amp; I hope that even now a shipwrecked crew would be safe with those families.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Jimmy’s son told me several things his Father used to tell them about the Beagle and “Cappen FitzRoy”—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Stirling again gives up the Secretaryship &amp; goes out to the Fuegian work—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>We have been lately amusing ourselves with finding fossil leaves in the Eocine beds here. A gentleman came to examine them from the B. Association<ref target="#foot.f12"/>—and he asked me to look out for portions of the bed when the cliff falls. Though only found in a few places the first little fall brought down some good bits of the bed, &amp; of a second one distinct from the other; and though we destroy twenty leaves to get one we have now numerous specimens; some I hope different from any described in the 〈Ge〉ology of the Isle of Wight.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> If any of them would be of use or interest to you I should be glad to send you any after M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mitchell<ref target="#foot.f14"/>—who comes again soon—has seen them. It would amuse you to see me with a party of five or six young ladies working away till they are in a nice mess with wet clay, making the good folks of Bournemouth stare sometimes when they see us returning— Tho’, I fear the workers spoil more specimens every ten minutes than they save in a whole forenoons working. At present we are hoping for some more cliff to fall before fine days in spring come.</p>
<p>What do you think of an old <hi rend="underline">Turk</hi>, a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Packe M.P., a cousin of Hamonds’<ref target="#foot.f15"/>—refusing permission to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Michell to go up a ravine on his land where the bed was most easily accessible, though he knew M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M was employed by the B. Asso<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>.</p>
<p>When you see Hooker<ref target="#foot.f16"/> will you say to him that if he wants any specimens of these leaves I shall be glad to get all I can for him. I suppose it is more in his line than yours.</p>
<p>I see in the last Cambridge book a “Darwin” in the First Class of the first year’s men. I hope that is your second boy.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> My youngest<ref target="#foot.f18"/> has just been trying the senior Local exam<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. of Cambridge at Southampton   I hope he may do as well as he did in the junior one two years ago, as he got the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> position in Mathematical honors out of 760—candidates &amp; seven of the eight above him were a year older &amp; had gone up once before. If he does as well now I hope, when he is a year older, he may have a chance of winning a scholarship at Cambridge;<ref target="#foot.f19"/> I think of his trying at Caius or Pembroke—</p>
<p>The return of Christmass day always recalls strongly that one we passed on an Island of Chiloe, after you left our boat party,<ref target="#foot.f20"/> when after three weeks wet by night and day and that morning going without breakfast because the rain put the fire out, after the tent was blown down on us—&amp; then when Paddy S.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> &amp; I returned from egg hunting for the pudding finding the party in the Priest’s house, which a kind head Indian had opened for them, and where round a roaring fire they were drying our things and <hi rend="underline">cooking a sheep</hi>, and we had the luxury of dry clothes &amp; dry blankets for the first time for weeks—</p>
<p>You will perhaps have heard that last year a law was passed in Chile giving free toleration to all religions—<ref target="#foot.f22"/>   we have lately heard from an English gentleman who was at the time in Santiago; that our missionary clergyman at Lota, Allen Gardiner,<ref target="#foot.f23"/> was referred to by more than one speaker in the House—and the good he was doing there used as an argument for toleration. He has now made friends with the Araucanian chiefs and they are helping him to establish stations in their country.<ref target="#foot.f24"/></p>
<p>Old Harris made particular enquiries for us all (at Rio Negro)<ref target="#foot.f25"/>   He &amp; his family were very kind to Stirling and his poor wife during her illness &amp; death,<ref target="#foot.f26"/></p>
<p>&amp; now wishing you again many happy christmass &amp; new year’s days, &amp; with our kind regards to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Darwin, Believe me | yours very sincerely | B. J. Sulivan</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Sulivan may have acquired a Turkish bath after undergoing treatment in Ireland at the hydrotherapy establishment of the physician <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Barter</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5133.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 27 June 1866</ref> and nn. 4 and 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">After retiring from the Board of Trade in April 1865, Sulivan moved from London to Bournemouth (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4831.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 8 May [1865]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Patagonian Mission Society (the name was changed to South American Mission Society in 1865) owned a ship, the <hi rend="italic">Allen Gardiner</hi>, which was built in 1854 to serve as an offshore base for the society’s missionary work in the islands of Tierra del Fuego (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3464.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hazlewood 2000</ref>, pp. 161–2). In August 1865, the superintendent missionary, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Waite Hockin Stirling</ref>, had returned to England from Tierra del Fuego with four Yahgan boys, Uroopa, Mamastugadagenges, Sesoienges, and Wammestriggins, who was called Threeboys (see below, n. 5). They left for Tierra del Fuego on 8 December 1866 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 313–16). The Yahgan are one of the three indigenous peoples of Tierra del Fuego, found in the most southerly parts of the islands (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Yahgan Orundellico, known to the British as Jemmy Button, was brought to England in 1830 and returned to his native land in 1833 on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1). One of his sons, Wammestriggins, known as Threeboys, was among the Yahgan boys brought to England in 1865 (see n. 4, above). Packsaddle Bay was located off Hardy Peninsula in the south-eastern part of Tierra del Fuego (<hi rend="italic">British Admiralty chart no. 1373</hi>, 1841).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4574.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lort Stokes</ref>, who was mate and assistant surveyor on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage with CD (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1). For CD’s account of the mimicry skills of Fuegians, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, p. 229.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The Falkland missionary station was on Keppel Island (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3464.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hazlewood 2000</ref>, p. 165).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Waite Hockin Stirling</ref> (see n. 4, above).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Sulivan may be alluding to an incident that took place at Wulaia, Tierra del Fuego, in November 1859, when some Englishmen were killed by a group of Yahgans (see Hazlewood 2001, pp. 249–53).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">FitzRoy was commander of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> from 1828 to 1836; see also n. 5, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Stirling had been secretary of the Patagonian Mission Society from 1857 to 1862, when he became the society’s superintendent missionary for Tierra del Fuego (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1644.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Crockford’s clerical directory</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6351.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Stephen Mitchell</ref> had reported to the British Association for the Advancement of Science meeting in August 1866 on the fossil leaf-bed at Alum Bay, Isle of Wight (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. S. Mitchell 1866</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">The reference is to a list of Eocene plants published in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Geological Survey of Great Britain</hi> (Harpe and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6862.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Salter 1862</ref>) that included material collected at Bournemouth. Mitchell noted in his report that many new forms had been discovered since the list was published (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. S. Mitchell 1866</ref>, p. 147).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See n. 12, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Robert Nicholas Hamond had served with Sulivan and CD on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (Sulivan ed. 1896, p. 202). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6467.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles William Packe</ref>, MP for South Leicestershire, owned the Branksome Tower estate in Poole, Dorset (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7720.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Thom’s Irish almanac</hi></ref> 1866).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> achieved a first class in the ‘Junior Sophs’ examination, Michaelmas term 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cambridge University calendar</hi></ref> 1866, p. 388).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Norton Sulivan</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4831.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 8 May [1865]</ref> and nn. 20 and 21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">No record of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Norton Sulivan’s</ref> attending <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref> has been found, but Sulivan later reported that his son left Cambridge after only a few weeks owing to ill health (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-6026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 19 March 1868</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 6026).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Sulivan refers to Christmas 1834, which he spent on Chiloé Island, off the south coast of Chile (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7544.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sulivan 1896</ref>, p. 44). CD had remained on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> while Sulivan and a party of men surveyed Chiloé (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, p. 342).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4563.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter Benson Stewart</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4431.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 18 March [1864]</ref>, where ‘Paddy’ is incorrectly transcribed as ‘Padeby’). For a list of the people on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> between 1831 and 1836, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, Appendix III.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Article 5 of the Chilean constitution of 1833 prohibited the public practice of any religion other than Roman Catholicism. An amendment of 1865 made it legal to practice other religions and to establish non-Catholic schools on private property. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bizzarro 1987</ref>, s.v. Constitution.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">Lota is a coastal city in the Región del Biobío, over 200 miles south of Santiago, Chile. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5726.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Allen Weare Gardiner</ref> took up his missionary post in Chile around 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1451.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Clergy list</hi></ref> 1864, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1644.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Crockford’s clerical directory</hi></ref> 1865).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">‘Araucana’ was the name the Spanish gave to the native people (who called themselves ‘Mapuche’) occupying the area between the rivers Biobío and Toltén in southern Chile (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_700.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Blancpain 1990</ref>, p. 20). The Araucanians were not under the control of the Chilean government.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">James Harris, a trader based at Patagones (now known as Carmen de Patagones), near the mouth of the Río Negro, Patagonia, had acted as CD’s guide in Argentina (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, p. 79).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louisa Jane Stirling</ref> died in October 1864, ten weeks after her arrival at Patagones (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5078.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Macdonald 1929</ref>, p. 59).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>