<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-434">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Emma and Elizabeth Wedgwood to Catherine Darwin   [13 November 1838]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5197</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-434 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-434.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-434.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 204: 174</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 174</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Wedgwood, Emma</persName>
                <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                <date when="1838-11-13">[13 Nov 1838]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1212.xml" resp="high">Darwin, E. C.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Hopes the Darwins in Shrewsbury will help her convince CD that he must not hurry their marriage too greatly. Sarah Elizabeth Wedgwood [II] adds a postscript to the same effect.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1211">Darwins</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shrewsbury</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                    <date>Tuesday.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Catty</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Since Charles went I have been rather afraid of his being in too great a hurry so I hope you will all hold him in a little especially the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. I find Elizabeth would be very sorry if it was to happen very soon &amp; that makes me wish more that things may not go too fast.</p>
<p>She forgets herself so much that I should like her to have her wish. besides which I should wish it myself. I don’t mean to insinuate that Charles would not mind what I say but if you all thought it could happen in no time as it were it would make me appear cross &amp; disagreeable on Saturday when I mean to be particularly happy. We kept thinking of you yesterday evening &amp; hoping your arrival made a great sensation, but I shall hear all about it in a day or two I am happy to think. I had <hi rend="underline">such</hi> a charming note from Caroline yesterday &amp; Eliz. &amp; I are going to see her today which I am very impatient to do. My dear Catty I get happier &amp; happier every hour. I long to see my dear Susan. She must come over some day. Would not she come on Saturday &amp; go back with Caroline which w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be an opportunity I should be so glad if she would.</p>
<p>Goodbye my dearest. I am so glad you were hear. I had a very nice little walk to Black Brook. | Yours affectly Em W.</p>
<p>You can keep this to yourself or not as you think best</p>
<p>Tell Charles to be a good boy &amp; do his lessons &amp; take things leisurely, indeed they cant be very fast.</p>
<p>How I do wish he would, &amp; wait till Spring &amp; fine weather! F. A.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> says it is the happiest time of Emma’s life &amp; it is a thousand pities it should be a very short one— Do dear Catty clog the wheels a little</p>
<p>S E W.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Probably Frances (Fanny) Allen, aunt of Elizabeth and Emma Wedgwood.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>