<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10012">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   6 June 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5301</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10012 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10012.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10012.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 64</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 64</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1875-06-06">6 June 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on Fritz Schultze, <hi rend="italic">Kant und Darwin</hi> [1875].</p> 
            <p>Describes recent activities.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Kant und Darwin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Schultze, Fritz 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>6 Juni 1875</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Beifolgend erhalten Sie von meinem hiesigen Collegen und Freunde Fritz Schultze eine Schrift, betitelt: “<hi rend="underline">Kant und Darwin</hi>”, von der ich nicht bezweifle, dass dieselbe Sie sehr interessiren wird. Sie ersehen daraus, dass unser grösster deutscher Philosoph schon vor mehr als einem Jahrhundert Ideen vertrat, welche nicht nur als die ersten klaren Conceptionen der <hi rend="underline">Descendenz-</hi>, sondern auch Ihrer <hi rend="underline">Selections</hi>-Theorie zu betrachten sind.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich empfehle Ihnen besonders S. 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 32, 38, 46, 47, 48–50, 55–58 61 (<hi rend="underline">—1775!!</hi>), 65, 76, 84 etc.</p>
<p>Es ist ein neuer Lorber in dem Kranze <hi rend="underline">Ihres Ruhmes</hi>, in dem grössten Denker Deutschlands einen Vorgänger gehabt zu haben!— Ich hoffe, dass dadurch viele deutsche Philosophen zum “Darwinismus” bekehrt werden!—</p>
<p>Im März und April war ich in Corsica und Sardinien (besonders längere Zeit in <hi rend="underline">Ajaccio</hi>) wo ich gutes neues Material für meine <hi rend="underline">Gastraea</hi>-Theorie gesammelt habe.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Auch bin ich jetzt mit der 6. Edit. der Schöpfungsgesch. und mit der 3. der “Anthropogenie” beschäftigt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Von beiden Büchern werden Sie <hi rend="underline">englische</hi> Übersetzungen noch im Laufe dieses Sommers erhalten.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Hoffentlich geht es Ihnen gut. In bekannter Verehrung mit den herzlichsten Grüssen Ihr treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.6 25] <hi rend="italic">double underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.6 26] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.6 32] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.7 47] <hi rend="italic">double underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.7 48–50] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.7 55–58] <hi rend="italic">double underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.7 61] <hi rend="italic">double underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Hackel’ <hi rend="italic">purple crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>6 June 1875</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Accept the enclosed book, by my colleague and friend here, Fritz Schultze, entitled “<hi rend="underline">Kant und Darwin</hi>”, which I don’t doubt will interest you very much. You will see from it that over a century ago, our greatest German philosopher already advocated ideas that must be regarded not just as the first clear conception of the theory of <hi rend="underline">descent</hi>, but also of your theory of <hi rend="underline">selection</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I recommend you in particular p. 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 32, 38, 46, 47, 48–50, 55–58 61 (—<hi rend="underline">1775!!</hi>), 65, 76, 84 etc.</p>
<p>It is yet another laurel in the wreath of <hi rend="underline">your fame</hi>, to have a predecessor in the greatest thinker of Germany!— I hope that this will convert many German philosophers to “Darwinism”!—</p>
<p>In March and April I was in Corsica and Sardinia (I stayed especially long in <hi rend="underline">Ajaccio</hi>) where I collected useful new material for my <hi rend="underline">Gastraea</hi>-theory.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am now also busy with the 6th edition of Schöpfungsgesch. and with the 3rd of the “Anthropogenie”.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> You will receive <hi rend="underline">English</hi> translations of both sometime this summer.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I hope you are well. With the familiar veneration &amp; with the most cordial greetings, your loyally devoted | Ernst Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I. .</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 222–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his book on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Immanuel Kant</ref> and CD (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8741.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schultze 1875</ref>, pp. 58–79), Schultze reproduced Kant’s essay on race, ‘Von den verschiedenen Racen der Menschen’ (On the different races of man; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8697.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kant 1777</ref>). Kant had defined races as deviations within a single line of descent preserved invariably over many generations. He discussed the idea that a noble stock of human beings could be created by breeding, but noted that nature would work to hinder such a scheme (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 61). For more on Kant’s ideas about race, including a translation of his original essay on race of 1775 and the expanded version of 1777, see Mikkelsen ed. 2013.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haeckel first developed his ‘gastraea theory’ in his monograph on calcareous sponges (Haeckel 1872, 1: 344–5; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9091.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 8 October 1873</ref> and n. 7). He proposed that two primary cell types or germ layers were differentiated in the early embryonic development of all multicellular organisms and that the ancestral mode of germ-layer formation was by invagination to produce a functional gut. This stage in development was called gastrulation. He further hypothesised, drawing on his biogenetic law (ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny), that there had existed an actual ‘gastraea’, by analogy with the developmental stage. Ajaccio is on Corsica.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The sixth edition of Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Natural history of creation; Haeckel 1875a) did appear in 1875, but the third edition of <hi rend="italic">Anthropogenie oder Entwickelungsgeschichte des Menschen</hi> (Anthropogeny or the developmental history of man; Haeckel 1877) was published in 1877. CD’s copy of Haeckel 1875a has not been found; his copy of Haeckel 1877 is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">History of creation</hi> (Haeckel 1876a; translation of <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi>) was published in 1876. <hi rend="italic">Evolution of man</hi> (Haeckel 1879a; translation of <hi rend="italic">Anthropogenie</hi>) appeared in 1879.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>