<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3041">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Thomas Henry Huxley   3 January [1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3269</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3041 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3041.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3041.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp C 1p</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 215</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 177</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 1</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Imperial College of Science, Technology and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 155, 372–6)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 155</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1861-01-03">3 Jan [1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Congratulates THH on first number of <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>.</p>  
<p>THH’s article on brain ["On the zoological relations of man with the lower animals", <hi rend="italic">Nat. Hist. Rev.</hi> (1861): 67–84] completely smashes Owen.</p>  
<p>Owen’s Leeds address [<hi rend="italic">Rep. BAAS</hi> (1858): xlix–cx].</p> 
            <p>In his historical sketch of opinion on species CD has picked out some sentences [by Owen] with which he will take some revenge. CD is not bold enough to come to an open quarrel.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Nat. Hist. Rev.</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Natural History Review</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Rep. BAAS</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Leeds</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Huxley, T. H. 1861d</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Owen, Richard 1858</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific controversy, confrontation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Jan 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Huxley</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have just finished No<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> I of N. H. Review &amp; must congratulate you, as chiefly concerned, on its excellence.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The whole seems to me admirable,—so admirable that it is impossible that other numbers sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be so good, but it would be foolish to expect it. I am rather a croaker &amp; I do rather fear that the merit of the articles will be above the run of common readers &amp; subscribers.</p>
<p>I have been much interested by your Brain article.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> What a complete &amp; awful smasher (&amp; done like a “buttered angel”) it is for Owen! What a canting humbug he is to have left out that sentence in the Lecture before the orthodox Cambridge Dons.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I like Lubbock’s paper <hi rend="underline">very</hi> much: how well he writes.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> MacDonnels, of course, pleases me greatly.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> But I am very curious to know who wrote the Protozoa article:<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I shall hear, if it be not a secret, from Lubbock. It strikes me as very good, &amp; by Jove how Owen is shown up—“this great &amp; sound reasoner”.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>By the way this reminds me of a passage which I have just observed in Owen’s address at Leeds,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> which a clever Reviewer might turn into good fun. He defines (p. xc) &amp; further on amplifies his definition that Creation means “a process he knows not what”. And in previous sentence he says facts shake his confidence that the Apteryx in N. Zealand &amp; Red Grouse in England are “distinct creations”. So that he has no confidence that these birds were produced by “processes he knows not what”.— What miserable inconsistencies &amp; rubbish this truckling to opposite opinions leads the great generaliser!</p>
<p>Farewell, I heartily rejoice in the clear merit of this number.— I hope M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Huxley goes on well.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Etty keeps much the same, but has not got up to the same pitch, as when you were here.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Farewell | C. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> In my little historical sketch of opinion on Species, I have picked out the foregoing sentences and his axiom of ordained becoming &amp;c.;<ref target="#foot.f13"/> and if the reader has any acuteness, I shall thus take some revenge;<ref target="#foot.f14"/> but I shall make no comments;—I am not bold enough and do not want to come to <hi rend="underline">open</hi> quarrel. But we shall never be friends again. What an admirable résume of Botanical Papers; I suppose by Oliver.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> What labour!</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 readers &amp;] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.3 Lecture] ‘L’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘l’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.6 a] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.8 leads] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is provided by the reference to the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The first number of the new series of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review: a quarterly journal of biological science</hi>, under Huxley’s general editorship, appeared in January 1861. For CD’s doubts about whether Huxley should take on this responsibility, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2873.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 20 July [1860]</ref>. CD’s annotated copies of the journal are in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">T. H. Huxley 1861a. The article was a response to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen’s</ref> view, published in R. Owen 1857 and 1859, that the brain provided certain anatomical characters by which man could be classified in a sub-class separate from the anthropoid apes. CD had criticised Owen’s classification when it was first published in 1857 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6, letters to J. D. Dana, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2072.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">5 April [1857]</ref>, and to J. D. Hooker, 5 July [1857]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to Owen’s Rede lecture delivered at <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref> in May 1859. The lecture was the first in a new series of annual lectures to be delivered by a man of eminence in science or literature. Owen’s lecture on the classification of the Mammalia (R. Owen 1859) was but a slight modification of R. Owen 1857. In his article, Huxley cited a quotation from the earlier paper, in which Owen stated that it was difficult for an anatomist to distinguish between <hi rend="italic">Homo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pithecus</hi>; Huxley then pointed out that the statement had been omitted from R. Owen 1859 (see T. H. Huxley 1861a, p. 69).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref>, one of several co-editors of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>, contributed a paper published in the first issue on the anatomy and natural history of the entozoan <hi rend="italic">Sphaerularia bombi</hi>, a worm parasitic on humble-bees (Lubbock 1861a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Robert M’Donnell’s paper (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5081.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">M’Donnell 1861</ref>) announced his discovery of the electrical organs in skates. M’Donnell stated that he had been led to search for these organs after considering CD’s remarks in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> about the ‘unity of type resulting from community of descent’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5081.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">M’Donnell 1861</ref>, p. 58): <quote type="quote"> Considering, therefore, that on the theory of Mr. Darwin it was in the highest degree improbable that the electric organs of the Torpedo were totally absent in the Skates, I undertook a careful search, with the view of following out their homologies … I have thus been led to make out the bodies which I conceive to be the true homologues of the Torpedo’s wondrous organs </quote> CD had learned of M’Donnell’s work in advance of publication (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, letters to T. H. Huxley, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2986.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 November [1860]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2994.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 November [1860]</ref>). In his copy of this issue of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>, CD noted: ‘M’Donnell on Electric Organs— gradation, good’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD refers to an anonymous review of five recent works on various groups of Protozoa (<hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 34–43). The author may have been Huxley himself judging from the number of references to his work and the strident attack on Owen’s views.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Among the books reviewed (see n. 7, above) was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6099.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">R. Owen 1860a</ref>, in which Owen defined the fundamental attributes of the plant and animal kingdoms. On the basis of this definition, he established a third kingdom of ‘Protozoa’, which embraced all those organisms exhibiting ‘common organic characters’ that could not, using the specified criteria, be assigned to either of the other two kingdoms. The reviewer criticised Owen’s criteria for distinguishing between animal and vegetable modes of existence and suggested that there were indeed sound scientific reasons for assuming the animal nature of true Protozoa (<hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 41–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD refers to Owen’s presidential address at the 1858 meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science held in Leeds (R. Owen 1858). See nn. 13 and 14, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2478.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Anne Huxley</ref> was recovering from the birth, on 11 December 1860, of the Huxleys’ son Leonard (L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 216).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Huxley visited Down on 14 December 1860, as related in a letter of 19 December 1860 to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>: ‘I was at Down on Saturday and saw Darwin. He seems fairly well, and his daughter was up and looks better than I expected to see her.—’ (L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 223). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref> had suffered from poor health throughout 1860. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The postscript, although on a separate leaf, is clearly related to the topics discussed in the letter (see nn. 14 and 15, below). It is included among the copies of Huxley’s letters made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> in DAR 145.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD refers to Owen’s published reference to the ‘axiom of the continuous operation of the ordained becoming of living things.’ Owen first used this phrase in his presidential address to the British Association meeting at Leeds (R. Owen 1858, p. li). The phrase was also used in Owen’s unsigned review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> ([R. Owen] 1860b, p. 500).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD included a reference to passages in R. Owen 1858 (see n. 9, above) in ‘An historical sketch of the recent progress of opinion on the origin of species’, included in the third edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> published in April 1861. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed.</ref>, pp. xiii–xix. CD had been deeply distressed by Owen’s rejection of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> and by his misrepresentation of several points in his unsigned review (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref>, a botanist in the herbarium and the librarian of the Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew, was one of the botanical editors of the new series of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7880.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Turrill 1959</ref>, p. 236). Oliver contributed a bibliographic review to the first number, listing and commenting on recent publications on phanerogamic plants (<hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 85–115). The bibliography became a regular feature of the journal.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>