<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13155F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   14 May 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21542</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13155F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13155F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13155F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 70</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 70</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <date when="1881-05-14">14 May 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>News from the laboratory at Strasbourg; is working on <hi rend="italic">Equisetum</hi> roots. Wortmann has found circumnutation in the mycelium of a fast-growing fungus. Please send papers (see 13155).</p> 
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-10-02" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-17" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-29" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-25" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-25" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>May 14./81</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I got your proofs and sent off a post-card to say so. I will have a good go at them tomorrow, &amp; I have done some this morning—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I like de Bary very much &amp; I can see that he hasn’t any of the touchiness of Sachs—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have got a very nice lodging at a bootmakers looking N over a little square called the Stephan-Platz; it is close to the river and only about 4 minutes from the laboratory</p>
<p>The laboratory seems to consist of a very long room with a row of tables where people are microscoping all day; then de Bary’s room which is not large &amp; with a small table with a Hartnack<ref target="#foot.f3"/> on it &amp; an awful mess of glasses watch glasses &amp;c on it. Then comes my room and I have a separate door &amp; key of my own. D<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Bary suggested the anatomy of roots as having some connection with the root work in the Movements of P. which he called “sehr interessant”.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> So I have begun with Equisetum roots; and he snipped a lot of little roots from a great plant in the laboratory which he knocked out of its pot for the purpose— I cut longitudinal sections and saw the things in Sachs like this;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> 
    <figure rend="blockCentred width33">
        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13155F.jpg"/>
    </figure>
he said some of my prep<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi> were “ganz gut so gar”, but the shine was taken off by his saying afterwards that it was “furchtbar leicht”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Today I have been cutting transverse sections of the same roots which is much more difficult; I havn’t shown him any of the good ones yet</p>
<p>I am partly disgusted to find that de Bary’s assistant Wortmann (whom I knew at Würzburg) has found circumnutation in the mycelium of some fungus which grows an awful pace, he will show it me, &amp; then I can tell you more about it—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I will send you a few addresses, &amp; if you will send the Bramble papers off I shall be much obliged.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I forget whether I told you that Stahl is now professor at Jena, this is a horrid bore for me, as he would have been society for me;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> being in a room by myself is rather bad for getting to know the people but I dare say I shall.</p>
<p>I think I should like Dandy, he might be turned out almost at once, and if I found I didn’t ride enough to make it worth while I suppose the Leith Hill vet would find a home for him—I will write to Aunt Caroline at once.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Please thank Bessy &amp; Mother for letters<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I am very glad poor Dubs<ref target="#foot.f12"/> cheered up so soon Your affec | F. D.</p>
<p>I have met Oscar Schmidt &amp; given him herzlichen Gruss from you—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I will tell you about him</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Francis was correcting proof-sheets of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>, which was published on 10 October 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml">Freeman 1977</ref>). The postcard has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Francis was working in the laboratory of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref> in Straßburg (Strasbourg). In the summers of 1878 and 1879, Francis had worked in the laboratory of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml">Julius Sachs</ref> at the Botanical Institute in Würzburg (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vols. 26 and 27).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5854.xml">Edmund Hartnack</ref> was a German microscope maker. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Francis had assisted CD in the research for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>. One of their principal areas of research had been the study of movements in the radicle, or embryonic root. The work that De Bary found ‘sehr interessant’ (very interesting) was their study of sensitivity in the apex of the root (see <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, pp. 129–200).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Equisetum</hi> is the genus of horsetails. In Sachs’s <hi rend="italic">Text-book of botany</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6836.xml">Sachs 1875</ref>, p. 122, fig. 101) sections of the stems of two species of <hi rend="italic">Equisetum</hi> were illustrated. In <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 123, fig. 102B, a longitudinal section of a fern root was figured; Sachs noted it was representative of most cryptogams (plants that reproduce by spores). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Ganz gut so gar</hi>: really quite good; <hi rend="italic">furchtbar leicht</hi>: frightfully easy (German).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9180.xml">Julius Wortmann</ref> had completed his doctorate under Sachs in Würzburg in 1879 and was De Bary’s assistant from October 1880 to the summer of 1883 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11337.xml">Muth 1926</ref>). Mycelium is the vegetative part of a fungus, characterised by fine branching threads or hyphae. Francis had also been working on circumnutation in a fungus, and published his results in <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11409.xml">F. Darwin 1881b</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13155.xml">postcard to Francis Darwin, 12 May [1881]</ref> and n. 1; the paper was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10539.xml">F. Darwin 1880b</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4513.xml">Ernst Stahl</ref> had been Sachs’s assistant when Francis was in Würzburg in 1879; he became professor extraordinarius of botany at Straßburg (Strasbourg) in 1880. He moved to Jena as full professor of botany in 1881. (<hi rend="italic">NDB</hi>.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">A horse named Dandy is mentioned in a <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Emma Darwin to H. E. Darwin, [13 April 1868]</ref> (DAR 219.9: 51). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1208.xml">Caroline Wedgwood</ref> was CD’s sister. The veterinary surgeon has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The letters to Francis from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1217.xml">Elizabeth Darwin</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Emma Darwin</ref> have not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Dubs: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml">Bernard Darwin</ref>, Francis’s son, who had stayed behind with Emma and CD at Down House.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4223.xml">Oskar Schmidt</ref> was professor of zoology at Straßburg (Strasbourg); he had been an early supporter of Darwinism (<hi rend="italic">ADB</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Herzlichen Gruss</hi>: hearty greetings.</note>  
        </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>