<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9393">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>   6 April [1874]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15657</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9393 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9393.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9393.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 182</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 16 April 1874, p. 460 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature 9 1874: 460</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1874-04-06">6 Apr [1874]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3491.xml">Nature</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on J. T. Moggridge’s article on the fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Fumaria capreolata</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 9 (1874): 423].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fumaria capreolata</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Nature</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Moggridge, J. T. 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre">Fertilisation of the Fumariaceæ</p> 
<p>I beg permission to make a few remarks on Mr. J. Traherne Moggridge’s statement (N<hi rend="smallCaps">ature</hi>, vol. ix. p.423) that the flowers of <hi rend="underline">Fumaria capreolata</hi> are at first pale or nearly white, and only attain their brightest colouring, becoming even crimson, after the ovaries are set. He then adds:—“If the reverse had been the case there is little doubt that we should have regarded the bright colouring as specially adapted to attract insects.”<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But does Mr. Moggridge know that these flowers are visited chiefly by diurnal insects? It has often been observed that flowers which are visited by moths are commonly white or very pale; but if they are odoriferous, they may be of any tint, even very dark or green. If therefore the flowers of the above Fumaria are visited by moths, it would be an injury to the plant had the flowers been from the first of a fine crimson. I have often seen bees sucking the flowers of the fumariaceous genera, <hi rend="underline">Corydalis</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Dielytra</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Adlumia</hi>;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but many years ago I watched perseveringly the flowers of <hi rend="underline">Fumaria officinalis</hi> and <hi rend="underline">parviflora</hi>, and never saw them visited by a single insect; and I concluded from reasons which I will not here give (as I cannot find my original notes), that they were frequented during the night by small moths.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Insects are not necessary for the fertilisation of <hi rend="underline">Fumaria officinalis</hi>; for I covered up a plant, and it produced as many seeds as an uncovered one which grew near.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> On the other hand, with some species of <hi rend="underline">Corydalis</hi>, the aid of insects is indispensable. With respect to the flowers of <hi rend="underline">F. capreolata</hi> becoming brighter coloured as they grow old, we see the same thing in some hawthorns, and with the double rocket in our gardens. But is it surprising that this should sometimes occur with flowers, seeing that the leaves of a multitude of plants assume, as they become oxygenised, the most splendid tints during the autumn? <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Down, Beckenham, Kent, April 6 C<hi rend="smallCaps">harles</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">arwin</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the date of publication of this letter in <hi rend="italic">Nature.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Traherne Moggridge’s</ref> letter on the fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Fumaria capreolata</hi> appeared in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 2 April 1874, p. 423. Moggridge’s letter was communicated by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart</ref>, and contained the following remark: <quote type="quote"> side by side with the developments and modifications which are plainly beneficial to the organism … there are others, which, as far as we can see, are neither useful nor harmful to their possessor, though they may, and frequently do, supply features which especially attract our attention and admiration. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Corydalis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Adlumia</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Dielytra</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Diclytra</hi>; now <hi rend="italic">Dicentra</hi>) are now in the poppy family (Papaveraceae). On bees visiting <hi rend="italic">Corydalis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dielytra</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 59.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s observations of <hi rend="italic">Fumaria capreolata</hi> were later published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 366. After reporting that he did not see insects visiting the flowers for many days, CD wrote: ‘Nevertheless, as the nectary contains much nectar, especially in the evening, I felt convinced that they were visited, probably by moths.’ See also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 388.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 366.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>