<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7283">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Armand de Quatrefages<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   18 July 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10345</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7283 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7283.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7283.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 175: 7</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>175: 7</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3892.xml">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1870-07-18">18 July 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD lost first round of nominations at the Académie Française to Jean-Frédéric de Brandt. QdeB and Milne-Edwards continue the battle, but CD is fiercely attacked.</p>
            <p>Asks for complete citation of CD’s geological work on South America because it has to be shown he did more than collect objects.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_592">Brandt, J. F.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3335">Milne-Edwards, Henri</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_839">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, South</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Academie Francaise</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>18 Juillet 70</date>
                    <salute>Cher Monsieur et confrere</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Soyez assez bon je vous prie pour me dire si vous avez publié le volume sur la Geologie de l’Amérique du Sud qui devait faire partie de l’Expédition du Beagle.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Je l’ai vainement cherché dans notre bibliothèque du Museum; je le chercherai ailleurs. Mais dans le cas où mes investigations seraient infructueuses, il est très important que je sache s’il a paru.— On a dit à l’Académie, dans le but de nuire à votre candidature que vous n’aviez fait que recueillir des objets d’histoire naturelle et que vous aviez appelé des aides pour les décrire.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Je tiens a montrer la part que vous avez eue dans la publication.— Dites moi je vous prie quel est le format, combien il y a de pages, de cartes.—</p>
<p>Vous savez deja sans doute qu’a une premiere nomination Brandt ne l’a emporté sur vous qu’au second tour de scrutin.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Mais nous avons trois places de correspondants à donner et j’espère bien que nous réussirons Edwards et moi à convaincre l’Académie.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Deja nous avons eu deux séances de discussion. Lundi prochain nous recommencerons et ce sera à mon tour a prendre la parole. Croyez bien que je ferai mon possible pour que la bonne cause l’emporte; mais vous êtes vivement attaqué.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Hélas! s’il n’y avait encore dans le monde que les batailles de cette nature nous serions bien heureux!—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Votre bien dévoué | De Quatrefages</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>18 July 1870</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir and colleague</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Be so good, pray, as to tell me whether you have published the volume on the Geology of South America that was supposed to be part of the Expedition of the Beagle.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have looked for it in vain in our library at the Museum; I shall seek it elsewhere. But in case my investigations should prove fruitless, it is very important for me to know whether it has appeared.— It is being said at the Academy, with a view to harming your candidature, that you had done no more than collect natural history specimens and that you had called on assistants to describe them.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am bent on showing the part you had in the publication.— Tell me if you please what the format is, and how many pages and maps there are—</p>
<p>No doubt you already know that in an earlier nomination Brandt only won out over you at the second ballot.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But we have three vacancies for correspondents to award and I very much hope that we will succeed, Edwards<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and I, in convincing the Academy. We have already had two discussion sessions. Next Monday we shall start again and it will be my turn to speak. Please believe that I shall do what I can to make the good cause win; but you are being strongly attacked.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Alas! If there were nothing but battles of this sort in the world, we should be very fortunate!—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Your most devoted | De Quatrefages</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s geological observations related to the voyage of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> were published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>; all three appeared in one volume as <hi rend="italic">Geology of the ‘Beagle’.</hi> Up to this time, there had been no French translation of any part of the work.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Quatrefages refers to the Académie des Sciences. The zoological material related to the voyage of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi></ref>, was edited and overseen by CD, but individual parts were done by different authors. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2. For more on the opposition to CD’s nomination as corresponding member of the Académie, see n. 6, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_592.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Friedrich von Brandt</ref> was elected on 4 July 1870 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7267.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [6 or 7 July 1870]</ref> and n. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">According to a report in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Cours Scientifiques</hi>, 23 July 1870, p. 529, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3335.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Milne-Edwards</ref> spoke on 18 July 1870 in favour of CD’s admission.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_482.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emile Blanchard</ref> spoke for over an hour against CD’s admission. He argued that on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage, CD had merely collected and was not capable of making a scientific study of his collections; he held that CD’s theory of coral island formation was mostly derivative. He further claimed that CD’s pigeon studies demonstrated a lack of true scientific spirit, that his work on cirripedes contained hardly any new facts, and that his theory of descent was both false and unoriginal. Blanchard apparently argued against transformism with examples from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2786.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jean Baptiste de Lamarck</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Revue des Cours Scientifiques</hi>, 23 July 1870, p. 529).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Quatrefages alludes to the Franco-Prussian war; France declared war on 19 July 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wawro 2003</ref>, p. 65).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>