<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11706">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To G. D. Campbell   23 September 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13021</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11706 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11706.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11706.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description"/>
            <note type="physdesc"/>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 377;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL">
                <bibl>CUL DAR 143: 20 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 5 March 1891, p. 415</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 5 March 1891, p. 415</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-09-23">23 Sept 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_802.xml">Campbell, G. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Doubts that "the same well-characterized species should be produced in two distinct countries, or at two distinct times".</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">multiple origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="italic">Down, Beckenham,</hi></placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 23, 1878.</date>
                    <salute>D<hi rend="smallCaps">ear</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">uke of</hi> A<hi rend="smallCaps">rgyll</hi>,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The problem which you state so clearly is a very interesting one, on which I have often speculated.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> As far as I can judge, the improbability is extreme that the same <hi rend="underline">well-characterized</hi> species should be produced in two distinct countries, or at two distinct times. It is certain that the same variation may arise in two distinct places, as with albinism or with the nectarine or peach-trees.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But the evidence seems to me overwhelming that a well-marked species is the product, not of a single or of a few variations, but of a long series of modifications, each modification resulting chiefly from adaptation to infinitely complex conditions (including the inhabitants of the same country) with more or less inheritance of all the preceding modifications. Moreover, as variability depends more on the nature of the organism than on that of the environment, the variations will tend to differ at each successive stage of descent. Now it seems to me improbable in the highest degree that a species should ever have been exposed in two places to infinitely complex relations of exactly the same nature during a long series of modifications. An illustration will perhaps make what I have said clearer, though it applies only to the less important factors of inheritance and variability, and not to adaptation—viz. the improbability of two men being born in two countries identical in body and mind. If, however, it be assumed that a species at each successive stage of its modification was surrounded in two distinct countries or times by exactly the same assemblage of plants and animals, and by the same physical conditions, then I can see no theoretical difficulty to such a species giving birth to the new form in the two countries. If you will look to the sixth edition of my ‘Origin,’ at p. 100, you will find a somewhat analogous discussion perhaps more intelligible than this letter.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Yours faithfully, | C<hi rend="smallCaps">harles</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">arwin</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Campbell’s letter to CD has not been found, but when Campbell later had this letter published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, he prefaced it by saying that he had ‘put the direct question, why it was that he [CD] did assume the unity of mankind as descended from a single pair?’ (<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 5 March 1891, p. 415).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">On the repeated production of peaches from nectarines (<hi rend="italic">Prunus persica</hi>), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 1: 361–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, pp. 100–2, is a discussion of convergence of character.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>