<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6928">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   9 October 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16689</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6928 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6928.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6928.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 54</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 144</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 144</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                <date when="1869-10-09">9 Oct 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Acknowledges receipt of CD’s <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> paper [<hi rend="italic">J. Linn. Soc. Lond. (Bot.)</hi> 10 (1869): 437–54].</p> 
            <p>Nectar-sucking birds fertilise tropical flowers.</p> 
<p>Writing a "Dualistic apologia for Pangenesis" [see translation in <hi rend="italic">Sci. Opin.</hi> 2 (1869): 365–7, 391–3, 407–8].</p> 
            <p>Homology of the orchid rostellum.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">tropical flowers</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">J. Linn. Soc. Lond. (Bot.)</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Primula</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Sci. Opin.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Delpino, Federico 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">homology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nectar</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Firenze</placeName>
                    <date>addè 9. 8bre 1869</date>
                    <salute>Celeberrimo uomo!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ho ricevuto i lavori “On the specific difference between Primula veris etc,” “Offspring from the illegitimate unions of dimorphic and trimorphic plants etc.” notes on the fertilization of orchids.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Io ne rendo alla S. V. le più sentite grazie. Si sto studiando col massimo impegno, come si deve per ogni cosa che esce dalla penna e dalla mente del più grande naturalista di questo secolo.</p>
<p>Mi permetto alcune rispettose osservazioni. Una infinità di dati mi persuadono che per molti fiori tropicali (e probabilmente per molti delle Orchidee) larghissima e importante parte alla fecondazione debbono prendere gli uccelli mellisugi (Trochilus, Ornismya, Nectariania, Melitreptus e simili).<ref target="#foot.f3"/> O io verso in grave errore, o non mi so spiegare come la S. V. non abbia prego detti pronubi in Speciale considerazione.</p>
<p>Così, contemplando la struttura dei fiori di Corianthes, vedendo la enorme nettaroconea, e la enorme secrezione di liquido dolciastro, dissi tra me: questo fiore deve essere fecondato da un trochilide specialissimo. Ora mi accadde in seguito che sfogliando la opera di Gould sui trochilidi, vidi per lo appunto una tavola ove si scorge un trochilo singolare con becco curiosamente ricurvo visitare i fiori di corianthes, e sorbire il copioso liquido della nettaroconea.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> All’ incontro la spiegazione del Dott. Crüger mi sembra pochissimo fiducievole. La natura non fa glandule melliflue, nè perfettamente lavorate nettaroconche, semplicemente per inumidire le ali di una Euglossa.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Io mi rimetto ad ulteriore guidizio della S. V.</p>
<p>Mi riuscì oltremodo istruttivo lo apprendere che alcuni insetti vanno sui fiori di orchidee non già per suggere miele ma per rodere speciali escrescenze.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Questa era una idea che già da un pezzo mi girava per la mente. Piacemi che i fatti corrispondano a questa idea. Tra le orchidee nostrali senza dubbio deve succedere la stessa cosa pel genere Serapias (S. lingua, cordigera, neglecta ecc.)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Nel fondo del fiore non vi è miele; ma invece vi si trova una grossa <hi rend="underline">escrescenza tinta in purpureo</hi> che deve appunto fornir cibo ai pronubi.</p>
<p>Ho ricevuto un numero del giornale ove è comparsa una parte del mio lavoro sulla pangenesi.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> La pangenesi può essere considerata sotto due aspetti; sotto l’aspetto monistico e sotto l’aspetto dualistico.</p>
<p>Sotto l’aspetto monistico mi pare, salvo errore, che non possa concepirsi colle leggi chimiche.</p>
<p>Sotto l’aspetto dualistico, la pangenesi è una mirabile, una grande teoria, che aggruppa felicemente, a mio parere, tutti quanti i fenomeni della genesi degli organismi. Ammettendo la esistenza di gemulle di sostanza immateriale, si sfuggono le objezioni della chimica, si spiega la metagenesi, la generazione alternante, la dislocazione, la moltiplicazione, la diminuzione degli organi, i fenomeni di atavismo ecc. ecc. Io sono compreso di ammirazione per la S.V. che ha saputo formulare una così grande teoria, e sarò lieto se potrò in breve pubblicare una scrittura non indegna dell ’alto argomento, sotto il titolo —<hi rend="underline">Apologia della pangenesi sotto</hi> <hi rend="underline">il punto di vista dualistico</hi>—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Gradisca il tenuissimo dono di due miei opuscoli con cui ho cercato di utilizzare per la geografia botanica le nozioni sulla dicogamia e di estendere l’albero genealogico delle Marantaceo, nel cui stilo credo di aver ravvisato la parte omologa al rostello (!) delle orchidea.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Ho l’onore di dichiarararmi della S.V. | Ossequentissimo discepolo</p>
<p>Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName>Florence</placeName>
        <date>9. October 1869</date>
        <salute>Most illustrious man!</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>I received the works “On the specific difference between Primula veris etc,” “Offspring from the illegitimate unions of dimorphic and trimorphic plants etc.” notes on the fertilization of orchids.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I thank you wholeheartedly for them. I am studying them with the utmost care, as one must do with anything coming from the pen and the mind of the greatest naturalist of this century.</p>
        
        <p>I venture a few respectful observations. An infinite number of cases convince me that honeysucking birds (Trochilus, Ornismya, Nectariania, Melitreptus and similar),<ref target="#foot.f3"/> must take a very great and important part in the fecundation of many tropical flowers (and probably of most orchids).  Either I am gravely mistaken or I cannot understand how you did not take such pollinators into special consideration.</p>  
        
            <p>Thus, while contemplating the structure of the flowers of Corianthes and noticing the enormous nectary cups, and the enormous secretion of sweetish liquid, I said to myself: this flower must be fertilised by a very special trochilus. Now, while skimming through Gould’s work on trochilidae, I happened to see a figure showing a singular trochilus with a curiously bent beak visiting the flowers of corianthes and sucking the abundant liquid from the nectar cup.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Dr Crüger’s explanation of this seems to me hardly reliable. Nature does not produce honey glands or perfectly designed nectar cups simply to moisten the wings of an Euglossa.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I would entrust myself to your judgment on this point.</p> 
        <p>It was extremely informative for me to learn that some insects visit the flowers of orchids not so much to suck honey as to nibble some special outgrowths.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> This idea had been going around in my head for quite some time already. I was pleased that facts correspond to this idea.  No doubt the same thing must happen amongst our local orchids, in the genus Serapias (S. lingua, cordigera, neglecta etc.).<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Inside the flower, there is no honey; instead, one finds a large <hi rend="underline">purple outgrowth</hi>, the function of which is precisely to provide food for the pollinator.  </p> 
        <p>I have received an issue of the journal in which a part of my work on pangenesis has appeared.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Pangenesis can be considered from two points of view, that of monism and that of dualism.</p>  
            <p>From the monistic point of view, it seems to me that, unless I am  mistaken, pangenesis is inconceivable within the laws of chemistry.</p> 
        <p>From a dualistic point of view, pangenesis is a wonderful and great theory that groups together successfully, in my opinion, all phenomena of the genesis of organisms. By admitting the existence of gemmules of non-corporeal substance, we avoid the objections coming from chemistry, we explain metagenesis, the alternation of generations, the dislocation, multiplication, and diminution of organs, the phenomena of atavism etc. etc. I am full of admiration for you for formulating such a great theory, and I will be pleased if I can soon publish a work that is not unworthy of this eminent topic, entitled “<hi rend="underline">Apologia della pangenesi sotto il punto di vista </hi><hi rend="underline">dualistico</hi>”.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
        <p>Please accept the humble gift of two pamphlets of mine in which I endeavoured to use the notions of dichogamy for botanic geography and to extend the genealogical tree of Marantaceae whose style I recognised as homologous with the rostellum (!) of orchids.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p> 
        <p>I have the honour of declaring myself Your Honour’s | Most humble disciple | Federico Delpino</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 421–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Delpino refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Specific difference in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Illegitimate offspring of dimorphic and trimorphic plants’</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Delpino refers to the genus <hi rend="italic">Trochilus</hi> and the now invalid genus <hi rend="italic">Ornismya</hi> in the family Trochilidae (hummingbirds), the genus <hi rend="italic">Nectarinia</hi> in the family Nectariniidae (sunbirds), and the genus <hi rend="italic">Melithreptus</hi> in the family Meliphagidae (honeyeaters).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Delpino refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Gould</ref> and Gould 1861, 1: plate 3, which depicts <hi rend="italic">Eutoxeres aquila</hi> (the white-tipped sicklebill) at a flower of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes speciosa</hi>, a species of bucket orchid.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 157, CD had described <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Crüger’s</ref> observations on the visits of bees of the genus <hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes.</hi> CD wrote, ‘The fluid in the bucket formed by the basal part of the labellum is not nectar and does not attract insects, but serves, by wetting their wings, to prevent them from crawling out except through the small passages close to the anther and stigma.’ For more on pollination of orchids by <hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2144.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1968</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 157.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Serapias lingua</hi> is the tongue orchid; <hi rend="italic">S. cordigera</hi> is the heart-flowered serapias; <hi rend="italic">S. neglecta</hi> is the scarce tongue orchid. For more on pollination in this genus, see Jersáková <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2006, p. 222.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Delpino refers to the first part of the English translation of his article ‘Sulla darwiniana teoria della pangenesi’ (On the Darwinian theory of pangenesis; Delpino 1869a), published in the 29 September 1869 issue of <hi rend="italic">Scientific Opinion</hi> (Delpino 1869b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The proposed work (Defence of pangenesis from a dualistic point of view) was never published.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The articles referred to are ‘Alcuni appunti di geografia botanica a proposito delle tabelle fitografiche del Prof Hoffmann’ (Some remarks on geographical botany with reference to Prof Hoffmann’s phytographical tables; Delpino 1869c) and ‘Breve cenno sulle relazioni biologiche e genealogiche delle Marantacee’ (Brief remarks on the biology and genealogy of the Marantaceae; Delpino 1869d). CD’s annotated copies of these papers are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>