<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1102">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Bernhard Studer   4 July [1847]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13962</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1102 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1102.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1102.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Burgerbibliothek Bern, Bern, Switzerland</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_41.xml">Bern</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1847-07-04">4 July [1847]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4602.xml">Studer, Bernhard</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Glad BS intends to visit England. Fears there will be few geologists in London in August. Would be truly glad to see BS at Down, but cannot offer much geological information respecting England.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>July 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>On my return home from Oxford, I found your interesting &amp; obliging letter, which by an unfortunate mistake had not been forwarded to me at Oxford, &amp; consequently I did not make acquaintance with your friend &amp; countryman. I have, also heard that the pamphlet,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> which you have been so kind as to give me, has arrived at Park St. (my Brother’s house) &amp; I shall get it at the end of this week.— I am very glad to hear that you purpose coming to England &amp; I hope that your tour may be in every way successful. I fear that there will be few, or no geologists in London in the middle of August: M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell has gone into Scotland; Sir R. Murchison, I believe, starts soon for France, &amp; the officers of the Geological Survey will no doubt be at work.— I have some hopes M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sharpe may be then in London, &amp; he would be able to give you much information about N. Wales; &amp; I will write to him tomorrow to enquire about his plans. Prof. Sedgwick, who knows more than anyone of Wales is scarcely ever in London for more than a day or two.—</p>
<p>My house is 18 miles from London; &amp; if you can spare the time I shall be <hi rend="underline">truly glad</hi> to see you here &amp; will give you all the advice in my power. I shall be at home, I am almost sure, all August: early in September, I shall be absent though only for a short time. I am, however, sorry to say that you could not apply to a worse person for geological information respecting England than myself; shortly after my return from my long voyage, I had a tedious &amp; severe illness, &amp; I have never since recovered my strength &amp; suppose I never shall. since I have never geologised in any part of England, not even near my own house. I appear quite well, but from being a strong man, I am become incapable of any continued muscular exertion; or indeed of much exertion of mind, for even conversation, if it excites me, tires me in a very short time, so that I am compelled to live a most retired life. What little assistance I can give, I will give with the greatest pleasure, &amp; shall be able anyhow to introduce you to more useful guides. I must apologise for troubling you with so many particulars about myself, but I thought it better to forewarn you that I am incapable of being of much service.— If you will be so good as to write to me, as soon as you arrive in England, or soon before, telling me where I can address you in London, I will answer you immediately &amp; if you would like to come here at once I will direct you the best way. In the mean time I will think of people to whom to introduce you.— I may, perhaps, be able to lend you some books on English Geology, to carry with you on your tour.— I hope you are able to speak some English, for I confess with very much shame, that I cannot speak, though able to read with perfect ease, French.—</p>
<p>With every good wish, pray believe me, dear Sir, Your faithful &amp; obed sert. | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 the] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘that’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.7 since I have … house. 2.8] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Possibly <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7528.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Studer 1844</ref>. An annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>