<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1070F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To John Russell   [10 March 1847]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20963</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1070F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1070F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1070F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Memorial</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10988.xml">House of Commons Parliamentary Papers: 1847 XXXIV.253–6</ref></bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">House of Commons Parliamentary Papers: 1847 XXXIV.253–6</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1847-03-10">[10 Mar 1847]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4129.xml">Russell, John</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Memorial presented by members of the British Association for the Advancement of Science and other scientific societies, submitting that natural history is inadequately provided for by the present constitution of the Board of Trustees of the British Museum.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">British Association for the Advancement of Science</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">British Museum, board of trustees</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">scientific societies</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>To The Right Honourable Lord John Russell, M.P., First Lord of the Treasury, &amp;c. &amp;c.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>We, the undersigned,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> members of the British Society for the Advancement of Science, and of various scientific societies, respectfully submit to the consideration of your Lordship, that a strong feeling pervades the naturalists of our country, that the promotion of the science of Natural History is very inadequately provided for by the present constitution of the Board of Trustees of the British Museum.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>So long as that institution consisted only of a library, with limited collections of antiquities and natural curiosities, it was easily managed by a body consisting of public functionaries, men of rank and general attainments, and the representatives of the chief donors of the Museum.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> When, however, the establishment was so enlarged as to become a national deposit of the productions of nature, both recent and fossil, together with vast additions to the books, manuscripts, prints, statues, &amp;c., supplemental trustees were elected to aid in the direction.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> We rejoice that eminent men of letters were thus associated in the Trust;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> but even so amended, the Board, with the best intentions, we believe, has found it very difficult satisfactorily to perform the numerous and various duties devolving upon it; for although the “ex officio” Trustees, the Presidents of the Royal Society and of the College of Physicians,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> are necessarily persons of weight in science; and although we gratefully witnessed the election of the eminent astronomer, Sir John Herschel,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> we would earnestly represent to your Lordship, that the qualifications of these gifted individuals do not necessarily include an interest in, or the ability to judge of, many of those measures which may best promote Natural History; and, consequently, that there is no effective provision (in the absence of other men of science) for the proper guidance of the Natural History department, or for having at the Board, trustees who can explain to their associates the desiderata of naturalists, and estimate the value of new specimens, either offered to or purchased by the nation.</p>
<p>Fully acknowledging, that in their accomplishments and high characters the present Trustees offer the best sureties for the satisfactory execution of any duties connected with their own pursuits, we still think that, with the best disposition (and they have already done much good service) these distinguished men are unable adequately to direct the vast and rapidly increasing Natural History departments of the Museum;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> and we can even well suppose that they would themselves be happy to be relieved from the heavy responsibility which must be attached to the application of the large sum annually voted by Parliament for the support of natural science.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Now, in the event of a knowledge of Natural History being in future recognized among the grounds for election to the Trusteeship of the British Museum, we should have reason to anticipate that the sum allotted to this subject would be applied so efficiently and regularly to its extension and improvement, as would best secure the progress of science, and yield most interest and instruction to the public.</p>
<p>Deeply impressed with these sentiments, we beg to suggest, for the consideration of your Lordship, that steps should be taken to effect such an improvement in the constitution of the Trust, as shall render the management of the Natural History departments of the British Museum, as far as possible, independent of the other divisions; and on this point we would beg to refer your Lordship to the original plan of Sir Hans Sloane.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>In offering this suggestion, we do not contemplate a separation of the Natural History collections from the other departments of the British Museum, as we well know that the cultivation of natural science cannot be efficiently carried on without reference to an extensive library.</p>
<p>What we chiefly desire to see is, the formation of such a responsible system of management as may satisfy the public and ourselves, that in this great national establishment, the interests of all branches of natural science will be thoroughly protected and advanced, and that the halls devoted to it shall be so enriched with well selected and well classified objects of contemplation and comparison, as shall not merely gratify the curiosity and excite the wonder of the multitude, but shall prove of real use to the researches of the student and the man of science.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">According to a note at the head of the text, this petition was presented on 10 March 1847.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s name appears thirtieth in a list of fifty-seven signatories, in the form ‘C. Darwin, F.R.S. F.G.S. &amp;c.’ The first four signatories were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roderick Impey Murchison</ref>, president of the British Association for the Advancement of Science, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Willoughby Cole</ref>, president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Buckland</ref>, reader in geology and professor of mineralogy at the University of Oxford, and Henry Thomas de la Beche, president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>. Among the remainder were leading figures from all fields of natural history including <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Jackson Hooker</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4140.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Sabine</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_379.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Bell</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4494.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Spence</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Cardale Babington</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4939.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathaniel Wallich</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref>, Adam Sedgwick, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Giles Bridle Daubeny</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The original board of forty-one trustees of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> was composed of three principal trustees (the archbishop of Canterbury, the lord chancellor and the speaker of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7863.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">House of Commons</ref>); seventeen official trustees, drawn from major state office-holders and all appointed <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi>; six family trustees representing descendants of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4385.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hans Sloane</ref>, Robert and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Harley</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5452.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Bruce Cotton</ref>, whose collections formed the original museum holdings, and fifteen additional trustees who were elected by the twenty-six permanent members of the Board. The <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi> trustees included the presidents of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref> and the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4101.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal College of Physicians</ref> of London. By 1847 the original board had been augmented by the appointment, between 1805 and 1824, of representatives of the Towneley, Elgin, and Knight families following major donations, and by the addition of the president of the Society of Antiquaries and the president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Academy</ref> in 1824, and, from 1832, of a trustee appointed by the sovereign (<hi rend="italic">An act to enable his majesty, his heirs and successors to appoint a trustee of the British Museum</hi> [23d June 1832]). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3375.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">P. R. Harris 1998</ref>, pp. 2, 11 and n. For contemporary concern over the perceived lack of representation of men of science, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7423.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Stearn 1981</ref>, p. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For the original composition of the Board of Trustees, see n. 3 above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For details of the expansion of the museum’s collections in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3375.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">P. R. Harris 1998</ref>, pp. 29–45, 75, 134, and 144. The Royal Society’s natural history collection was transferred to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> in 1781, and the Hatchett, Mordaunt, and Cracherode collections of minerals in 1799 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7423.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Stearn 1981</ref>, p. 20). The principal acquisitions of the early nineteenth century were the King’s Library in 1823, which increased the collection of printed books by over fifty per cent, and the natural history collections of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_267.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Banks</ref> in 1827 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3375.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">P. R. Harris 1998</ref>, pp. 31–2). For changes to the composition of the Board of Trustees, see n. 3, above. Although no additional trusteeships had been created since 1832, following a <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7863.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">House of Commons</ref> Select Committee investigation in 1836, any of the fifteen elected trustees who did not attend meetings for a period of more than twelve months was expected to resign, and the committee recommended that eminent men in the sciences, literature, and art should be better represented on the board (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 11, 105–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In addition to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Frederick William Herschel</ref> (see n. 8, below), the most recently elected members of the Board of Trustees of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> were the constitutional historian <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5828.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Hallam</ref> (1837), the antiquary and diplomat <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2080.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Richard Hamilton</ref> (1838), and the diplomat <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5781.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Leveson Gower Granville</ref> (1841). Robert Peel, known for his patronage of men of science, had been a trustee since 1833. See <hi rend="italic">Statutes and rules for the British Museum</hi> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6790.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Rupke 1994</ref>, p. 53.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">For the <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi> trustees, see n. 3, above. In 1847, the president of the Royal Society was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1033.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer Joshua Alwyne Compton</ref>, and the president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4101.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal College of Physicians</ref> was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6476.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Ayrton Paris</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Herschel was elected to the Board of Trustees of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> in August 1843 (<hi rend="italic">Herschel calendar</hi>, no. 5571).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The natural history department of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> was effectively created in 1835 when the museum’s various botanical collections were brought together and placed in the care of Robert Brown. Following the recommendations of a <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7863.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">House of Commons</ref> Select Committee in 1837, the natural history department was formally split into three sections, botanical, zoological, and mineralogical and geological, each with its own keeper. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7423.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Stearn 1981</ref>, pp. 22–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For details of government expenditure on the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> in this period, see <hi rend="italic">History of the king’s works</hi> 6: 403–21.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">For Sloane’s will, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2466.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Faulkner 1829</ref>, 1: 363–73. Under its terms, Sloane left his collections for the public use and stipulated that they should remain in London, and be kept together, since they tended to ‘the manifestation of the glory of God, the confutation of atheism and its consequences, the use and improvement of physic, and other arts and sciences, and benefit of mankind’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 365). See also MacGregor ed. 1994. The head of the department of printed books, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anthony Panizzi</ref>, had been campaigning for the natural history collections to be moved to make more space available for the library (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7423.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Stearn 1981</ref>, pp. 23–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Largely as a result of this petition, a Royal Commission was appointed in June 1847 to investigate the constitution and administration of the museum; Buckland, one of the signatories to the petition (see n. 2, above) was appointed a trustee in the same year (<hi rend="italic">Statutes and rules for the British Museum</hi>). The commission reported in 1850 and recommended that the various collections should not be dispersed and that the building should be enlarged. It also recommended changes to the organisation of the natural history departments (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3375.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">P. R. Harris 1998</ref>, pp. 165–73). No serious reorganisation took place, however, until the establishment of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (Natural History) and the transfer in 1880 of the natural history collections to a separate site in Kensington (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 241–2; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6790.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Rupke 1994</ref>). For CD’s involvement with the continued campaign on behalf of the natural history collections, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 7, Appendix VI.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>