<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12375">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Antonio Mendola<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   29 December 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10106</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12375 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12375.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12375.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 150</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 150</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3293.xml">Mendola, Antonio</persName>
                <placeName>Favara</placeName>
                <date when="1879-12-29">29 Dec 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports from an Italian baron that a calf’s horn that was buried in a field set roots; mule’s hairs incubated in water come alive.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">calf</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">mule</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Italian baron</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-09" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-13" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-17" status="editorResponseCompleted">Ed response by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2018-09-21" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-09-21" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2018-11-20">Final proofreading queries checked <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00679_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00679_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="150:1r" xml:id="i679">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00679.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00679_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00679.dzi" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="150:1v" xml:id="i680">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00680.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00680_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00680.dzi" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="150:2r" xml:id="i681">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00681.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00681_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00681.dzi" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="150:2v" xml:id="i682">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00682.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00682_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00682.dzi" width="3773px" height="6291px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="150 foldout" xml:id="i683">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00683.jpg" width="6944px" height="6297px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00683_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="6944px" height="6297px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00171-000-00683.dzi" width="6944px" height="6297px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Sicilia. Provincia di Girgenti, | <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Favara</hi>.</placeName>
                    <date>29. Dic<hi rend="superscript">br</hi> 1879.</date>
                    <salute>Egregio Sig Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Credo utile alla scienza, ed a voi forse non dispiacevole, palesarvi due fatti, che mi sembrano di molto rilievo.</p>
<p>Concimai nel 1877 (Ottobre) alcune mie terre cogli avanzi del publico macello, tra i quali eranvi corni di diverse bestie. L’inverno 1878 fu piovosissimo. Un corno di giovine vitello seppellito a circa 13. centimetri di profondità, mise grosse e numerose radici della forma e grossezza dello asparagio. Nell’ultima aratura di Maggio 1878 mi accorsi dello strano fenomeno per la resistenza incontrata dall’aratro, peroché io seguivo il bifolco per diletto. Raccolsi subito il corno radicato, che conservo integro.</p> 
                    <p>Chiedo il permesso d’inviarlo a voi. Qui alcuni professori reputano sia un caso di parasitismo. Io penso che nò. Deciderete voi, se mi ordinate di spedirvelo.</p>
<p>Durante la convalescenza d’una mia lunga e penosa malattia per caduta di carrozza, per ingannare i miei forzati ozi e per mezzo d’un mio amico scopersi un altro fatto che è verissimo e che mi pare meraviglioso.</p>
<p>Alcuni peli di vario colore, strappati con tutti i rispettivi bulbi dalla coda di alcuni asini muli e cavalli, furono posti dentro un gran bicchiere d’acqua comune, che si mutava in parti quasi ogni settimana. La temperatura della stanza addetta a questo sperimento oscillava da 10 a 12. gr<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Reàmur—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Questi peli senza perdere il rispettivo colore andavano ingrossando. Dopo circa 15. giorni cominciavano a muoversi. In capo a 34 giorni divennero animali perfetti, semoventi, individuati, con muso nero.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Adesso mentre scrivo guizzano sul mio tavolo, spesso escono la testa e porzione del corpo fuor dell’acqua e aderiscono alla liscie pareti del bicchiere, o per respirare o per trastullarsi. La notte riposano e intorpidiscono a sera tardi. Trovo sporchezze ogni due o tre giorni come di limo nel fondo del vaso, forse sono dejezioni o trasudamenti. Sono questi nuovi esseri sensibili alla luce ed al calore. Accostandoli alla vivida luce d’una lampada di petrolio, o circondando il bicchiere di ca〈r〉ta nera, bucata in un punto per dove si faccia entrare un raggio di sole, corrono dalla parte opposta. Perseguitati poi col raggio di sole concentrato da una lente (luce e calorico) sfuggono celeremente a seconda la intensità della concentrazione.</p>
<p>Non chiedo il permesso di spedirvi questi animati, perché da per voi stesso potete facilmente ripetere l’esperimento studiarlo in tutte le sue fasi, e produrre animalacci meglio fatti di questi chi io possiedo.</p>
<p>Da 10. giorni ho messo nell’acqua capelli e peli di barba e di pudende, umani— Sinoggi nulla vedo di movimento. Vanno pero ingrossandosi, segnatamente quelli della barba.</p>
<p>Scrissi questi fatti al Prof. Canestrini<ref target="#foot.f4"/> in Padova per notificarveli e siccome no〈n〉 ho avuto risposta, mi sono azzardato 〈  〉o non scienziato, e che non ho l’onore di conoscervi personalmente, a volgermi direttamente a voi.</p>
<p>Scusate se scrivo italiano. La mia ignoranza dell’inglese mi ci obliga.</p>
<p>Scrissi da qualche giorno a mio figlio studente del Politecnico di Stuttgart a a scrivervi in inglese questi fatti, peroche mio figlio conosse molte lingue anche orientali. Forse ricevereto il suo scritto quasi insieme alla presente<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Perdonate alla mia arditezza.</p>
<p>Attendo vostri ordini ed il vostro preciso indirizzo per spedirvi la cassetta col corno radicato.</p>
<p>Accettate i miei ossequi e creditemi | Devotissimo | Barone Antonio Mendola</p>
<p>Il mio indirizzo in caso di risposta è il seguenti</p>
<p>Sicilia—Prov.<hi rend="superscript">ia</hi> di Girgenti | <hi rend="underline">Favara</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
    
    
    <div type="translation">
        <div type="text">
            <opener><placeName>Sicily. Province of Agrigento, | <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Favara</hi>.</placeName>
                <date>29. Dec<hi rend="superscript">ber</hi> 1879.</date>
                <salute>Dear Mr Darwin,</salute></opener>
            <div type="transcription">
                <p>I believe it useful to science, and perhaps not displeasing to you, to disclose to you two facts, which seem to me very relevant.</p>
                <p>In 1877 (October) I was fertilising some of my lands with remains of local butchers’ refuse, including horns of various animals. The winter of 1878 was very wet. A horn of a young calf buried about 13 centimetres deep had put out numerous thick roots of the shape and size of asparagus. In the last ploughing in May 1878 I was alerted to the strange phenomenon through the resistance met by the plough, because I followed the ploughman for my own pleasure. I immediately collected the horn with roots, which I am keeping intact.</p> 
                <p>I beg permission to send it to you. Some professors here consider it may be a case of parasitism. I think not. Decide for yourself, if you instruct me to dispatch it to you.</p>
                <p>During my convalescence from a long and painful illness as a result of a fall from a carriage, in order to while away my enforced idleness and by means of a friend I discovered another fact that is absolutely true and that appears marvellous to me.</p>
                <p>Some hairs of various colours, pulled out with all their respective roots from the tails of some donkeys mules and horses, were put in a big glass of ordinary water, which was changed in part nearly every week. The temperature of the room assigned to this experiment varied from 10 to 12 degrees Réaumur—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> These hairs without losing their individual colour became swollen. After about 15 days they began to move. Within 34 days they became complete creatures, self-propelled, individuated, with black snouts.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Now as I write they are darting around on my table, often they put their heads and parts of their bodies out of the water and they stick to the smooth sides of the glass, either for breathing or for amusement. At night they rest and become sluggish by late evening. Every two or three days I find a small amount of dirt like slime at the bottom of the vase, perhaps waste or droppings. These new beings are sensitive to light and to heat. Bringing them close to the bright light of a paraffin lamp, or surrounding the glass with black paper, perforated in one place where a sunbeam can come through, they rush from the side opposite. Then pursued by the sunbeam concentrated with a lens (light and heat) they quickly escape following the intensity of the concentration.</p>
                <p>I do not seek permission to dispatch these creatures to you, since it is possible for you to easily repeat the experiment again to study it in all its phases, and to produce little creatures better made than those which I possess.</p>
                <p>For 10 days I have put into water hair and beard-hair and pubic hair, human ones— Up to today I have seen no movement. But they go on getting bigger, particularly those from the beard.</p>
                <p>I have written down these facts for Prof. Canestrini<ref target="#foot.f4"/> in Padua to inform you of them and since I have not had a reply, I presume because I am not a scientist, and although I do not have the honour of knowing you personally, I am turning directly to you.</p>
                <p>Excuse me writing in Italian. My ignorance of English forces it on me.</p>
                <p>I wrote a few days ago to my son studying at the Polytechnic in Stuttgart to write these facts to you in English, since my son knows many languages including oriental ones. Perhaps you will receive his writing almost together with the enclosed<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                <p>Pardon my boldness.</p>
                <p>I await your instructions and your exact address to dispatch the package with the horn with roots to you. </p>
                <p>Accept my regards and believe me | Most devoted | Barone Antonio Mendola</p>
                <p>My address in case of reply is the following</p>
                <p>Sicily—Province of Agrigento | Favara</p>
            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 542–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">12.5 to 15°C.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For recent debates about spontaneous generation, see, for example, <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10971.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 23 May 1877</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_815.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Giovanni Canestrini</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3293.xml">Mendola</ref>’s son was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8633.xml">Giuseppe Benedetto Mendola</ref>. No other correspondence about this case has been found.</note>
            </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>