<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-82">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. D. Fox   25 [August 1830]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7031</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-82 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-82.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-82.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">Barmouth; C 27 AU 27 1830</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 166</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Christ’s College Library, Cambridge (MS 53 Fox 31)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_83.xml">CCLC</repository>
                    <collection>MS 53</collection>
                    <idno>Fox 31</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Barmouth</placeName>
                <date when="1830-08-25">25 [Aug 1830]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml">Fox, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has been in N. Wales two weeks, having gone with Hope and two Eytons. Not many good insects; disillusioned with Hope, found him egotistical and stupid.</p>
            <p>Hopes WDF will stay in Cambridge until after CD arrives.</p>
            <p>Some entomological news.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1567">Eyton, C. J.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1570">Eyton, T. C.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2372">Hope, F. W.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Cambridge</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Wales, N.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Barmouth.</placeName>
                    <date>Wednesday 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Fox</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been intending to write every hour for the last fortnight, but <hi rend="underline">really</hi> have had no time: I left Shrewsbury this day fortnight ago, &amp; have since that time been working from morning to night in catching fish or beetles. This is literally the first idle day I have had to myself: for on the rainy days I go fishing, on the good ones Entomologizing. You may recollect that for the fortnight previous to all this, you told me not to write, so that I hope I have made out some sort of defence for not having sooner answered your two long &amp; very agreeable letters: I am delighted that we agree so well about all the Wedgwoods, &amp; as you say it is so much pleasanter talking about any place or persons that both parties have seen.— I trust that Charlotte<ref target="#foot.f1"/> has driven out of the field your musical enchanter at Ashby: Cannot you imagine how very pleasant I must find Maer, not one drawback. I have not even the least dread of the <hi rend="underline">Parish</hi> a sensation, which it appears, you were not quite void of. I should enjoy most exceedingly to spend a week there with you: it is more probable now than that originally you should have been at Maer at all.—</p>
<p>I suppose you are now living in Cambridge with Prof: Henslowe. I shall enjoy hearing from you some gossip about him &amp; his wife<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; I hope you will return good for evil &amp; write soon to me.— I am afraid you must find Cambridge rather stupid. it must be such a contrast from your former life there.— of course every thing my rooms contain is most entirely at your service: you do not know how it would please me if there is any chance of your being there in the first week in October, by which time I would be up, if it were merely to eat our breakfasts together as we did in good old times.—</p>
<p>I shall be at Maer for the first week or 10 days in September, &amp; write to me there, (direction is Maer, Newcastle, <hi rend="underline">Staffordshire</hi>) &amp; tell me your plans.—</p>
<p>And now I give you some account of our Welch trip. Hope 2 Eytons (father &amp; son) &amp; myself arrived at Capel Curig on a Thursday. On Monday we went up Snowdon, &amp; were disgusted with it we took 3 Cerculis a few glabrati &amp; nothing else. Hope &amp; Eyton went off next day to Barmouth, Old E &amp; myself staid a few days longer &amp; had some pretty good trout fishing. I joined Hope &amp; young E. here on Friday, but they returned to Shrewsbury on Monday for a cricket match, &amp; here I am enjoying my solitude extremely: I am quite disgusted with Hopes egotism &amp; stupidity: how I wish you were here, the very thought of a days entomologizing with you, is quite refreshing.— Try &amp; prolong your stay in Cam. to October. I long to spend a little time with you quietly. I do not call your visit to Shrewsbury anything, there were so many people making a row &amp; confusion.— The Entomologists did not do a very great deal here, took some good Colymbetes, Cicin: hybrida, &amp; Eyton took a most beautiful Crysomela. I have taken some good Leiodes by the way ask Prof: Henslow, what is the time to get Leiodes cinnamomia. I want some very much.— You ought also to take some good water beetles this time of the year.—</p>
<p>When you write tell me what you read. Remember me most kindly to Prof: Henslowe— Excuse this patch-work letter &amp; believe me dear Fox. | Yours, sinc, | C. D.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">4.2 On] ‘O’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.2 Monday we] ‘we’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.3 we took] ‘we’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.6 ‘so that’; 1.14 ‘now’; 2.5 ‘know’; 4.6 ‘Monday’; 4.14 ‘taken some’; 5.2 ‘believe’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2810.xml">Charlotte Wedgwood</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2233.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harriet Henslow</ref>, sister of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2560.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Jenyns</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>