<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2807">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. R. Wallace   18 May 1860</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1730</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2807 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2807.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2807.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 205</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 309;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Marchant (1916) 1: 141</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 219</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Add MS 46434: 21–23v)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Add MS 46434</collection>
                    <idno>21–23v</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-05-18">18 May 1860</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Pleasure in ARW’s approbation of the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. Other supporters among scientists. ARW’s generosity.</p> 
            <p>Attacks by Owen, Sedgwick, and others.</p>
            <p>Anticipation of natural selection by Matthew in 1830.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3225">Matthew, Patrick</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>May 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1860</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wallace</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I received this morning your letter from Amboyna dated Feb. 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, containing some remarks &amp; your too high approbation of my book.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Your letter has pleased me very much, &amp; I most completely agree with you on the parts which are strongest &amp; which are weakest. The imperfection of Geolog. Record is, as you say, the weakest of all; but yet I am pleased to find that there are almost more Geological converts than of pursuers of other branches of natural science. I may mention Lyell, Ramsay, Jukes, Rogers, Keyserling, all good men &amp; true—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Pictet of Geneva is not a convert, but is evidently staggered (as I think is Bronn of Heidelberg) &amp; he has written a perfectly fair review in the Bib. Universelle of Geneva.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Old Bronn has translated my book, well-done also, into German &amp; his well-known name will give it circulation.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I think geologists are more converted than simple naturalists because more accustomed to reasoning. Before telling you about progress of opinion on subject, you must let me say how I admire the generous manner in which you speak of my Book: most persons would in your position have felt some envy or jealousy. How nobly free you seem to be of this common failing of mankind.—   But you speak far too modestly of yourself;—you would, if you had had my leisure done the work just as well, perhaps better, than I have done it.—</p>
<p>Talking of envy, you never read anything more envious &amp; spiteful (with numerous misrepresentations) than Owen is in the Edinburgh Review. I must give one instance    he throws doubts &amp; sneers at my saying that the ovigerous frena of cirripedes have been converted into Branchiæ, because I have not proved them to be Branchiæ; whereas <hi rend="underline">he himself</hi> admits, before I wrote, on cirripedes, without the least hesitation that these organs are Branchiæ.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>The attacks have been heavy &amp; incessant of late. Sedgwick &amp; Prof. Clarke attacked me savagely at Cambridge Phil. Soc. but Henslow defended me well, though not a convert.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Phillips has since attacked me in Lecture at Cambridge.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Sir W. Jardine in Eding. New Phil. Journal.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Wollaston in Annal of Nat. History.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> A. Murray before Royal Soc. of Edinburgh—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Haughton at Geolog. Soc. of Dublin—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Dawson in Canadian Nat. Magazine,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> And <hi rend="underline">many others</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> But I am got case-hardened, &amp; all these attacks will make me only more determinately fight. Agassiz sends me personal civil messages but incessantly attacks me; but Asa Gray fights like a hero in defence.—.—   Lyell keeps as firm as a tower, &amp; this autumn will publish on Geological History of Man, &amp; will there declare his conversion, which now is universally known.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I hope that you have received Hooker’s splendid Essay.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> So far is bigotry carried, that I can name 3 Botanists who will not even read Hooker’s Essay!!<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Here is a curious thing, a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pat. Matthew, a Scotchman, published in 1830 a work on Naval Timber &amp; Arboriculture, &amp; in appendix to this, he gives <hi rend="underline">most clearly</hi> but very briefly in half-dozen paragraphs our view of natural selection. It is most complete case of anticipitation. He published extracts in G. Chronicle:<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I got Book, &amp; have since published letter, acknowledging that I am fairly forestalled.—<ref target="#foot.f18"/> Yesterday I heard from Lyell that a German D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Schaffhausen has sent him a pamphet published some years ago, in which same View is nearly anticipated but I have not yet seen this pamphet.— <ref target="#foot.f19"/> My Brother, who is very sagacious man, always said you will find that some one will have been before you.—</p>
<p>I am at work at my larger work which I shall publish in separate volumes.— But from ill-health &amp; swarms of letters, I get on very very slowly.—   I hope that I shall not have wearied you with these details.—</p>
<p>With sincere thanks for your letter, &amp; with most deeply-felt wishes for your success in science &amp; in every way believe me,<ref target="#foot.f20"/> | Your sincere well-wisher | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.6 of pursuers] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘of’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.6 leisure] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘pleasure’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.1 envious &amp;] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">4.3 in Lecture] ‘in’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">5.2 this] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘do’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">5.3 but very … paragraphs] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.8 yet] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>
             
             
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Wallace’s letter has not been found. The only extant record of Wallace’s initial response to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> is given in two letters he wrote to friends at the end of 1860. In a letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Silk</ref>, dated 1 September 1860, Wallace wrote about <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8126.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1905</ref>, 1: 372): <quote type="quote"> I have read it through five or six times, each time with increasing admiration. It will live as long as the ‘Principia’ of Newton. It shows that nature is, as I before remarked to you, a study that yields to none in grandeur and immensity. The cycles of astronomy or even the periods of geology will alone enable us to appreciate the vast depths of time we have to contemplate in the endeavour to understand the slow growth of life upon the earth. The most intricate effects of the law of gravitation, the mutual disturbances of all the bodies of the solar system, are simplicity itself compared with the intricate relations and complicated struggle which have determined what forms of life shall exist and in what proportions. Mr. Darwin has given the world a <hi rend="italic">new science</hi>, and his name should, in my opinion, stand above that of every philosopher of ancient or modern times. The force of admiration can no further go!!! </quote> In a letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Walter Bates</ref>, dated 24 December 1860, Wallace again gave his reaction to the book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8126.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1905</ref>, 1: 374): <quote type="quote"> I know not how, or to whom, to express fully my admiration of Darwin’s book. To <hi rend="italic">him</hi> it would seem flattery, to others self-praise; but I do honestly believe that with however much patience I had worked and experimented on the subject, I could <hi rend="italic">never have approached</hi> the completeness of his book, its vast accumulation of evidence, its overwhelming argument, and its admirable tone and spirit. I really feel thankful that it has <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been left to me to give the theory to the world. Mr. Darwin has created a new science and a new philosophy; and I believe that never has such a complete illustration of a new branch of human knowledge been due to the labours and researches of a single man. Never have such vast masses of widely scattered and hitherto quite unconnected facts been combined into a system and brought to bear upon the establishment of such a grand and new and simple philosophy. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2620.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Beete Jukes</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Darwin Rogers</ref>, and Alexandr Andreevich Keyserling.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6299.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pictet de la Rive 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Bronn trans. 1860.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2751.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 9 April [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. S. Henslow to J. D. Hooker, 10 May 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Jardine] 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Wollaston] 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Murray 1860a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Haughton 1860a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Dawson 1860b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">For a list of reviews of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> that were published in 1859 and 1860, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.8, Appendix VII.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Lyell intended to treat the history of humankind in a new edition of his <hi rend="italic">Elements of geology</hi>, but in fact he published his work on this subject as a separate volume in 1863 (C. Lyell 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Hooker 1859.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2802.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">15 [May 1860]</ref>, and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, 18 May [1860]. The three botanists were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Harvey</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hutton Balfour</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_157.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Arnott Walker Arnott</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">For a transcription of Patrick Mathew’s letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.8, Appendix V.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">See letters to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [13 April 1860], and to J. D. Hooker, 13 [April 1860].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6917.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schaaffhausen 1853</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2806.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 18 May [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">The letter has deteriorated, and the final paragraph is now missing. The text has been taken from a transcript made by the editors at an earlier date.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>