<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11812">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. R. Greg   31 December 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">557</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11812 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11812.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11812.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.557)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>557</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-12-31">31 Dec 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1971.xml">Greg, W. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses a chapter on design, written by WRG’s son [Percy Greg, <hi rend="italic">The devil’s advocate</hi> (1878)]. Comments on the younger Greg’s criticisms of natural selection and evolution.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">The devil’s advocate</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Greg, W. R.’s son</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Greg, Percy 1878</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham</placeName>
                    <date>Dec 31, 1878</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Greg,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have read the chapter on design &amp; it seems to me very cleverly done.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> If your son has not read a book by “Physicus” just published by Trübner, I think it would be worth his reading as bearing on the argument from general laws; not that Physicus appears to me to have made out his case, tho’ the subject is beyond my tether.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> To come to my own subjects, I do not think that any of your sons objections are new, tho’ some of them are put in a new way. It would take a volume to discuss all, but I will make a few miscellaneous remarks. If your son cares to see what I think about variations having been designed, he will find this subject briefly discussed in the 3 last pages of Vol II of my ‘Variation under Domest<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>’.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Your son would hesitate in saying that no close series of forms have been found fossil if he were to read Saporta on the Tertiary plants of S. France,—Geinitz &amp; Oppell on the Jurassic ammonites—or Neumayr on the Miocene fresh water shells of East Europe.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Your son says that no links have been found between such forms as the ass &amp; zebra but he forgets that it is doubtful whether any palæontologist could distinguish their bones; &amp; bones alone afford evidence when we come to fossil mammals.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> With respect to new variations being obliterated by crossing, I have insisted on the improbability of such well marked variations as that of the Ancon sheep being preserved under nature. I cannot doubt that the process of selection under nature is the same as that called by me “unconscious selection”, when the <hi rend="underline">more or less</hi> best fitted are preserved, &amp; the <hi rend="underline">more or less</hi> ill fitted are destroyed. If your son thinks it worth while he can see what I mean by unconscious selection in Ch XX of Var<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> under Dom<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Your son does not notice the effects of separation, as on islands, in preventing crossing. By the way he says I rest exclusively on natural selection; whereas no one else as far as I know has made so many observations on the effects of use &amp; disuse. Nor do I deny the direct effect of external conditions, tho’ I probably underrated their power in the earlier editions of the Origin.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> We know far too little about the laws of inheritance to argue about them: what is certain is that some new variations are strongly inherited from the first, whilst some seem never or very rarely to be transmitted; nor until trial is made can we predict what will be the result. Your son believes that our domesticated animals were developed for man’s use;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> but let us suppose that they were all destroyed, does your son believe that man would not succeed in domesticating other quadrupeds, for instance some of the larger antilopes; &amp; in this case ought not your son to maintain that such animals had been specially designed for man. Owen goes further than your son for in referring to race horses he says that he believes the diastema or open space between their teeth to have been specially designed for the bit; &amp; as a friend of mine remarked no doubt the little jockeys were specially designed to ride them.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>Your son seems to believe that ice has been made lighter than water, as otherwise it would have sunk &amp; whole pools or seas have been frozen into a solid mass. But melted bismuth when cooling &amp; solidifying expands largely (by <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>32</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of its bulk) &amp; of course floats, is this a special adaptation?<ref target="#foot.f10"/> It is much more wonderful &amp; apparently unique case that solid bismuth if subjected to an enormous pressure becomes of <hi rend="underline">less</hi> specific gravity; if this lightness had been of any use to man, assuredly it would have been called a special adaptation.</p>
                    <p>But I shall weary you, &amp; I remain, my dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Greg | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had read the chapter ‘Design in development’ in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1970.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Percy Greg’s</ref> book, <hi rend="italic">The devil’s advocate</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">P. Greg 1878</ref>, 2: 214–55). Percy was W. R. Greg’s son.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">A candid examination of theism</hi> was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George John Romanes</ref> under the pseudonym ‘Physicus’ ([G. J. Romanes] 1878c]; the publisher was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4786.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Trübner &amp; Co.</ref> CD had made some suggestions about Romanes’s use of metaphysical terms, along with other criticisms of the book, in his letter to Romanes of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11773.xml">5 December [1878]</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 2: 426–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gaston de Saporta</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6880.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Saporta 1862–5</ref> and 1867–8; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6461.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Albert Oppel</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6000.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oppel 1856–8</ref>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3503.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Melchior Neumayr</ref> and Neumayr and Paul 1875.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">P. Greg 1878</ref>, 2: 232.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">P. Greg 1878</ref>, 2: 233–4. CD discussed ancon sheep in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 1: 104–5 and 2: 70. On unconscious selection, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 2: 195–208.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 421. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">P. Greg 1878</ref>, 2: 232–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> claimed the horse had been ‘predestined and prepared for Man’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6113.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Owen 1866–8</ref>, 3: 796; no specific reference to the diastema being specially designed has been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">P. Greg 1878</ref>, 2: 240. Bismuth is one of a handful of elements that, like water (a chemical compound), are denser in their liquid state than as solids. Specific gravity is a measure of relative density; it is the ratio of the density of a substance to the density of water. Density is the ratio of mass per unit volume.
            
            
            
            </note>
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>