<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12392F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. H. Tindal   1 January 1880</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21099</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12392F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12392F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12392F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="28">28</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 227.7: 11–13, 16, 18, 25, 128</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 11</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 12</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 13</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 16</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 18</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 25</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>227.7: 128</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_7242.xml">Tindal, C. H.</persName>
                <date when="1880-01-01">1 Jan 1880</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Encloses extracts from the correspondence of [the Ven. Robert] Clive concerning Erasmus Darwin.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-26" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2018-11-26" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-08" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2019-05-01" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name>. Corrections entered by Paul White.</change>
        <change when="2019-05-10" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name>. Corrections entered by Paul White.</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>The Manor House | Aylesbury.</placeName>
                    <date>Jan: 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1880.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have been through the whole of the Clive Correspondence &amp; have made extracts of all the allusions to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin— and I have also selected three letters in which mention is made of your father—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Pray keep the extracts if they are of any interest to you—and kindly return the three letters—</p>
                    <p>The M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gifford referred to, was the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Richard Gifford. M.A. of Balliol College Oxford. Rector of North Ockington Co: Essex &amp; Vicar of Duffield Co. Derby</p>
                    <p>He was a person of great literary attainments, &amp; a fine Hebrew &amp; Classical Scholar— The article in the gentlemans Magazine which appeared on his death will give you a fair description of him &amp; his writings generally.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I cannot say how he became acquainted with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin— The correspondence between him &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Clive began in 1760. and they were then both acquainted with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D. then.</p> 
                    <p>The M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Clive referred to is the Ven<hi rend="superscript">ble</hi>. Archdeacon Robert Clive Rector of Moreton, Prebendary of Westminster &amp; Archdeacon of Salop. He was son of the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Benjamin Clive of Duffield &amp; cousin of the celebrated L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Clive whose sister he married.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Duffield is about 5 miles from Derby. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Richard Gifford is buried there, &amp; his daughter &amp; only child Euphemia Gifford likewise— She lived to be 89 &amp; died in the year 1854.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> </p>
                    <p>It may interest you to know that I have here a picture cut out in black Paper of Archdeacon Clive, &amp; his brother George Clive a banker in London playing Chess—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The picture was cut out by Miss Wedgwood daughter of Josiah Wedgwood who married D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Robert Darwin of Shrewsbury.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> It was left together with a print of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Lord Clive to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gifford by the Archdeacon.</p>
                    <p>I have a long correspondence between M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gifford &amp; his wife,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> &amp; daughter which may throw some light on the commencement of the acquaintance with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin. I will look through this tomorrow &amp; let you know the result.</p>
<p>I must apologise for troubling you with so long a letter— containing I am afraid much that is irrelevant, &amp; subscribe myself, Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. very faithfully. | Charles H. Tindal</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="letter" n="1" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <opener>
                    <date>July 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1768</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">The Ven: R. Clive to Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> R Gifford.</seg>
                </opener><div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I thank you, for the account you sent me of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Rotton,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; was very glad to find that you were of opinion he mended very fast. I have since seen D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin, who seems to think he may get much better with care &amp; proper management, but he can by no means approve of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Bark as he apprehends his case to be dropsical. He happened to have in his pocket a little treatise which he had just written upon y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> use of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Bark, &amp; which he was going to send up to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> College of Physicians, to be printed amongst their next annual publications— he gave me y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> perusal of it, &amp; leave to transcribe a part of it, which I will send you, &amp; I dare say you will think it very judicious as I do.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> “The effect of ye Peruvian Bark &amp; other Bitters seems much to depend on their decreasing ye Irritability of the nervous system; as is evinced by their daily successful use in Fever &amp; other diseases from Irritation— And as y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> palsies &amp; dropsies described below were owing to a decrease of this Irritability, the Bark seems, whenever it was given to have produced or increased these diseases, or to have destroyed y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. patient— The words Relaxation and Braceing cannot be opposed to this idea of the effect of Bitter medicines, as they can with no propriety be ascribed to ye nervous system of animal bodies; but are mechanical terms that belong alone to dead matter, &amp; not to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> laws of life, &amp; have misled many of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> faculty to ye great detriment of their patients— One observation I shall add, which has appeared to me invariably true viz: that y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. violent coughs, &amp; y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> febrile symptoms that are attendent on obstructed Livers, after proper Evacuations by bleeding with repeated vomiting or purging, are cured with certainty by the Bark, either alone or with the addition of a slight chalybeate<ref target="#foot.f10"/> or anodyne. But I believe from the following case that, where no symptoms of Irritation are attendant on obstructed Livers, ye Bark &amp; chalybeates have induced palsies &amp; dropsies to g<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. destruction of Thousands”— Thus far y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> ingenious Doctor, whose observations stand upon facts which have happened in his own practice, &amp; which he produces in his treatise. His sentiments may be considered as a key to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. use of the Bark &amp; I am sure they will make me more cautious in recommending this medicine …… Send me word whether you will be at Moreton this day fortnight in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Evening or, coming by Lichfield, &amp; calling on D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin give me y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. meeting at D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Adams’ at Counde on Tuesday by dinner’<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="letter" n="2" xml:id="encl.2">
      
          <opener>
                    <placeName>Moreton</placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1768.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">R. Clive to R. Gifford</seg>
                </opener><div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am glad to find by your last papers to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. Doctor &amp; his letter to you, that matters are likely to be adjusted very amicably betwixt you even without the help of a moderator. I think you were a little off your guard in your definition of a Living Substance when you said you meant no more by it than ‘a substance well fitted to convey impressions to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. mind &amp; to execute her orders— <hi rend="underline">Living</hi> here signifies <hi rend="underline">apt for ‘y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. business of Life.’</hi> If this be a true definition of a <hi rend="underline">Living substance</hi> will it not follow that an axe, a saw, or an hammer, or any other material instrument that we make use of for y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. business of life is as much a <hi rend="underline">living substance</hi> fitted to convey impressions to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. mind, &amp; to execute her orders as y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. body itself is—</p>             

<p>From R. Clive to R. Gifford</p>  
<p>Moreton</p> 
                    <p>Dec: 12. 1768.</p>
             
<p>‘Dear Sir—</p>
                    <p>I am desired by Doctor Darwin to let you know, that his pig &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Whitleys<ref target="#foot.f12"/> company of comedians will be ready for our Establishment at Lichfield in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. week of January next. I propose being there on Tuesday ye 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. &amp; hope nothing will prevent you giving me y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. meeting, &amp; pray bring your strictures on Berkeleys book upon y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> material world—for y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Doctor tells me he has been writing a chapter to prove a material world, which he hopes will please you, as it plucks up the root of that kind of infidelity called scepticism.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> We must try spend two or three days with y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. Doctor, which I think we shall pass very agreeably—. Pray bring Berkeleys book with you as ye Doctor may not have it.’—</p>
<p>R. Clive to R Gifford</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="letter" n="3" xml:id="encl.3">
      
          <opener>
                    <placeName>Moreton</placeName>
                    <date>Sept: 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. (no year)</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">R. Clive to R. Gifford—</seg>
                </opener><div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I read over your remarks with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin, who took all in good part, said he was very much obliged to you &amp; would write soon— by the observations he made it appeared you had misunderstood some few passages in his book—&amp; I think he will respond to your objections very well. I mentioned to him our desire of attending him sometime when he opened an human body— to which he said that he could give us all the satisfaction we desired from an inspection of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. parts of a pig, &amp; invited us to spend two or three days with him at Xmas, when he should kill a fat pig— I propose much pleasure from this meeting &amp; hope nothing will happen to prevent it</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="letter" n="4" xml:id="encl.4">
      
          <opener>
                    <placeName>Stych.</placeName>
                    <date>Jan: 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1771.</date>
                </opener><div type="transcription">
 <p>R. Clive to R. Gifford.</p>                     
<p>I thank you for your letter &amp; your proposal to meet me at Lichfield, which perhaps I may call upon you to fulfil before it be long, as D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin has often pressed me to come and spend a week with him—&amp; two new philosophical friends who have lately settled in Lichfield, induced to it by that cheerfulness and benevolence of disposition, with which you &amp; I &amp; all who know y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. good Doctor are so much charmed.</p> 
                    
<p>R. Clive to R. Gifford</p> 
<p>Lichfield</p> 
                    <p>May 30. 1771.</p>
                    <p>I wish you could have spent tomorrow with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin &amp; his two ingenious friends Edgeworth &amp; Day<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>

<p>R. Clive to Richard Gifford</p>
<p>Moreton</p> 
                    <p>Oct: 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1772.</p>
<p>‘I have been much out of order for these last 5 days with a fever of the bilious kind—luckily D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin was in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. neighbourhood &amp; prescribed for me from my written account of myself though he had not time to see— he has lain at home but one night these five weeks so great is his fame &amp; usefulness</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="letter" n="5" xml:id="encl.5">
      
          <opener>
                    <placeName>Moreton.</placeName>
                    <date>July 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1773.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">R. Clive to R. Gifford</seg>
                </opener><div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>‘I dare say you had a very sincere pleasure in Lord Clive’s victory over his enemies in parliament which was very complete &amp; very honorable—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin wrote me a good blackguard letter on the occasion which will Entertain you better than anything else I can add to this hasty scrawl. I will therefore transcribe it “I had a great mind to have written a letter in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> newspapers on y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. following plan. To all y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. Blackguards in Great Britain— Loving friends &amp; Cousins— To it again—at him— We shall conquer this Lion at last I warrant y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. Never mind a pinch or two— Burgoyne will stave, &amp; Meredith tail—<ref target="#foot.f16"/> At him again. We’ll first demolish Clive &amp; then Chatham,<ref target="#foot.f17"/> and there shall not be a man of virtue left in the Kingdom if we can help it— Now’s the time, My loving Cousins in Parliament, proscribe &amp; confiscate all that are against the ministers at present; and when a new ministry prevails, then all the present proscribers shall be proscribed in their turn. till Temple bar is hung round with Calves heads like a Butcher’s shop— This is the true levelling principle!<ref target="#foot.f18"/> Rare times for old England! At him again, my lads next session— Never yelp &amp; howl so for one defeat— Give me another pot of porter— Oh! d— your virtue— it has saved your country”—.’</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" n="6" xml:id="encl.6">
            <opener>
                <placeName>Lichfield.</placeName>
                <date>Jan: 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. (no year).</date>
                <seg type="supplemental">R. Clive to R. Gifford.</seg>
            </opener>
          <div type="transcription">
                     
              <p>When I came here yesterday I found D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Boothby busily engaged in translating the Genera Plantarum of Linnæus into English, in which if they succeed to their Satisfaction M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Boothby is to publish it.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> It will probably be a work of time, as it will be of some nicety—in which I told them I thought you could be useful as you have y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. book. I also told them you had been trading on metaphysical ground— They both wished much to see your M.S. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. B. said he would give you his free sentiments ou bien ou mal. He is going to publish a work which Rousseau entrusted to him about 4 years ago with a request not to do it till after his death.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p> 

              <p>R. Clive to R. Gifford.</p>
            <p>Lichfield.</p>
            <p>Jan: 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. (no year).</p>
                                 
<p>I will send you some verses I found upon D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin’s table.</p>
                    <p>On the death of Brindley the great perfector of Inland Navigation.<ref target="#foot.f21"/></p>
<lg><l>Leek, Cheadle, Cheddleton, Delf, Burslem, Woor,</l>
<l>Stoke, Turnhurst, Ipstones, Draycot in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>. Moor,</l>
                    <l>All strive for Brindley’s birth, but strive in vain.<ref target="#foot.f22"/></l>
              <l>For Brindley sprung immortal from the main—</l>
                    <l>On the much lamented death of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. G–r–ck.<ref target="#foot.f23"/></l>
              <l>Ambubiarum collegia pharmacopolæ.<ref target="#foot.f24"/></l>
<l>Pimps, prompters, poets, painters, rhymers, riddlers,</l>
<l>Beaux, taylors, link boys, fruit girls, singers, fiddlers,</l>
<l>Scene shifters, tumblers, fairies, goblins, witches,</l>
<l>Backs, bullies, gamblers, demireps, &amp; bitches,</l>
<l>All mourn for Garrick dead with wild distraction</l>
              <l>A crowded playhouse was their scene of action—</l></lg> 

              <p rend="centre">R. Clive to R. Gifford</p> 
<p>Shrewsbury.</p> 
              <p>Sept 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. (no year)</p>
              <p>I received D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwins response which I think very ingenious &amp; solid. I should be glad of your sentiments as soon as you have perused it. I am now sitting in Company with the Hero of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwins book, who is in better health &amp; spirits than I ever remember him—</p> 
          </div>
            
        </div>
        

            
            
     
            
            
            
           
            
         
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="underline">Top of letter</hi>: ‘I must make note of obligation to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tindal’ <hi rend="underline">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had asked Tindal for details about <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8634.xml">Richard Gifford</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8635.xml">Robert Clive</ref> (1722/3–92), friends of his grandfather Erasmus Darwin (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12375F.xml">letter to C. H. Tindal, 29 December 1879</ref>. CD’s father was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Gifford’s obituary appeared in <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> 77 (May 1807): 477–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">‘Lord Clive’ was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_973.xml">Robert Clive</ref> (1725–74); his sister was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8818.xml">Rebecca Clive</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"> Gifford’s daughter was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9035.xml">Euphemia Gifford</ref>.</note> 
                <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9043.xml">George Clive</ref>. The plate on p. 6 shows a similar silhouette.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1241.xml">Susannah Darwin</ref> was the daughter of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5025.xml">Josiah Wedgwood I</ref>, and the wife of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin</ref>, CD’s father.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9036.xml">Elizabeth Gifford</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8819.xml">John Rotton</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">‘Peruvian bark’ from cinchona trees was a common source of quinine. Erasmus Darwin prescribed it as a stimulus for treating fevers and other conditions (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 1: 83–4, 100 and 2: <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>). Its medical properties are praised in <hi rend="italic">The botanic garden</hi>, pt 2, <hi rend="italic">The loves of plants</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10787.xml">E. Darwin 1799</ref>, pp. 103–5); however, no separate publication on Peruvian bark has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Chalybeate: water or other liquid containing iron (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 2: 175–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9045.xml">William Adams</ref> was rector of Counde, Shropshire (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9044.xml">James Whitley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6535.xml">George Berkeley</ref>’s controversial views on perception and the material world were published in <hi rend="italic">An essay towards a new theory of vision</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10545.xml">Berkeley 1709</ref>). Erasmus Darwin discussed visual perception in <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 1: 14–29).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8398.xml">Richard Lovell Edgeworth</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9038.xml">Thomas Day</ref>; both were members of the Lunar Society of Birmingham (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml">King Hele 1999</ref>, pp. 79–80).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">In 1772 and 1773, several motions were brought against <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_973.xml">Robert Clive</ref> (1725–74) in the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7863.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">House of Commons</ref>, in connection with criticism of the East India Company’s administration in Bengal. In May 1773, Clive successfully defended himself against accusations of appropriating money while serving as governor of Bengal. (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9039.xml">John Burgoyne</ref> was an army officer, MP, and outspoken critic of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8635.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Clive</ref> (1725–74) and the East India Company. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9040.xml">William Meredith</ref> served on Burgoyne’s committee to investigate the East India Company and seconded his motion to censure Clive for corruption. (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8377.xml">William Pitt</ref> (Pitt the elder), first earl of Chatham.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Temple Bar, the historic gateway to London, was used to display the severed heads of traitors until 1746. The Levellers was a name given to supporters of a democratic republic during the period of the English Civil War and Commonwealth (<hi rend="italic">EB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8459.xml">Brooke Boothby</ref>. The translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2943.xml">Carl von Linné</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Genera plantarum</hi> was credited to ‘a botanical society at Lichfield’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10547.xml">Linnaeus 1787</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml">King-Hele 1999</ref>, pp. 217–18).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><hi rend="italic">Ou bien ou mal</hi>: whether well or ill (French). Boothby edited <hi rend="italic">Rousseau juge de Jean Jacques: dialogue</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10546.xml">Rousseau 1780</ref>). On the friendship between Boothby and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6662.xml">Jean Jacques Rousseau</ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10931.xml">Zonneveld [2003]</ref>). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9041.xml">James Brindley</ref> was principal engineer on a number of canals across the Midlands; he died in 1772 (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Leek, Cheadle, Cheddleton, Delph, Burslem, Woore, Stoke-on-Trent, Ipstones, and Draycott are villages or towns in Staffordshire. Brindley was born in Wormhill, Derbyshire, and lived at Turnhurst Hall in Staffordshire after his marriage in 1765 (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">The actor <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9042.xml">David Garrick</ref> died in 1779 (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">‘Ambubiarum collegia pharmacopolae’ (correctly, ‘Ambubaiarum collegia, pharmacopolae’): ‘A band of flute girls, quack doctors …’. The source is <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2382.xml">Horace</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> 1.2.1. </note>
            
        </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>