<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3041A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. C. Watson to J. D. Hooker   4 January 1861</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20778</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3041A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3041A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3041A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Directors’ Correspondence 105: 205)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <collection>Directors’ Correspondence</collection>
                    <idno>105: 205</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4975.xml">Watson, H. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Thames Ditton</placeName>
                <date when="1861-01-04">4 Jan 1861</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on the travels of JDH.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Genera plantarum</hi> a most worthy undertaking.</p> 
            <p>Criticisms of the Darwin–Hooker understanding of HCW’s views of convergence.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Genera plantarum</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Bentham, George and Hooker, J. D. 1862–1883</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">divergence</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Thames Ditton S.W.</placeName>
                    <date>19 Jnry. 61</date>
                    <salute>My dear Hooker,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Better late than never; and where there is ample reason for lateness, there can be none for complaint. Many thanks for your letter de convergentibus &amp;c.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> How much outside the botanical circles,—or, at any rate the great circle,—not even to have heard that you had been beyond seas again!<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Was there ever a botanist who had seen so much of the earth &amp; its vestments?<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>How vastly I should have enjoyed the run over Syria with you! And yet if I had chanced to be away from England those eight weeks, inconveniences to myself &amp; others would have been so incurred, that might hardly have been removed in as many years. I seem always called on to give time &amp; thought to things no wise botanical, while wishing to give them to matters that are botanical, or connected with botany.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I can hardly conceive you &amp; Mr. Bentham employed more serviceably than on a ‘Genera Plantarum’.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> So many qualifications &amp; advantages concentrate in you two, towards such an undertaking, that the accomplishment of your task ought to date as a new formation in the series of botanical strata—&amp; doubtless will do so.— Can a <hi rend="underline">list</hi> of species under each genus be compassed, if only single names?<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>You have not yet grasped the whole idea of convergence, as I conceive of it whether rightly or erroneously.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> No wonder. If Darwin had sought to explain his notions of divergence &amp; selection in compass of a letter sheet, he might have got further or fuller than I could do with its (presumed) counterpoise, &amp; yet done it most imperfectly.</p>
<p>Darwin watches minutesimal variations; &amp; he supposes that these may &amp; do accumulate into any extent of diversity in long time.— I suspect that we should all have said, that is pure fancy or pure absurdity, if geology had not shown the fact, that enormous differences do exist between the present &amp; the past, &amp; must have come about somehow.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I watch minutesimal variations also; &amp; I suppose that these may &amp; do accumulate into any degree of similarity in long time. But, seeing that we know not the future, and cannot compare the present therewith, we lack corroboration. And we (i.e. you &amp;c.) do think convergence to such a degree mere fancy or absurdity.</p>
<p>You &amp; Darwin seem to me at present something like an Astronomer endeavouring to account for the planetary system by a centrifugal force alone, without taking into account a centripetal force, or recognising it only as occasional, anomalous, trifling.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Darwin’s idea that similitudes must be always inherited from some predecessor, common ancestor of all that so resemble, if pushed to its logical consequences, would concentrate all organic characters in the dozen (or single) original types;—and that surely is a real as well as logical absurdity?<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Observe,—every the smallest possible change in a plant, which to that extent renders it more like another plant, (whether that other plant be the nearest, or the most remote otherwise) <hi rend="underline">is</hi> a step in convergence. Advergence would perhaps be a better term. Can you point out divergences in any plants, which are certainly not advergences towards some other plants?</p>
<p>You will be ready to cry, ‘Hold enough’. And I will not inflict on you a criticism of the various ideas in your letter;—some of which indeed I quite admit the force of; though I think that the arguments against ad/convergence are not proof against reply.—</p>
<p>The Indian specimens you kindly sent some time ago are still kept apart, awaiting some other introductions into my herbarium, before trying how closely I can concur with your labels of European identity.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Unlike you, I have to go through <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the mechanical processes, such as washing over with poison, glueing to paper, &amp; so forth,—sadly time-consuming.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Writing with back to the fire, I still have to keep rubbing fingers, or the pen would fall from their cold benumbed trembling guidance—</p>
<p>Glad to have so favorable an account of your Father—<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Ever faith<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi> | Hewett C. Watson <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Dr J. D. Hooker</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter from Hooker to Watson has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Hooker had taken part in an expedition to Syria from mid-September to mid-November 1860 (L. Huxley ed. 1918, 1: 528; see also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For details of Hooker’s wide-ranging travels, see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1987.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">R. Desmond 1999</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Watson was active as a politician (<hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>). By 1861, he travelled rarely and was engaged in philanthropic activity (Frank Egerton, personal communication).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Hooker’s collaboration with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref> on <hi rend="italic">Genera plantarum</hi> is documented in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7421.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Stearn 1956</ref>, and Hooker’s work on the volume began in earnest in March 1860 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2728.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 12 March [1860]</ref> and n. 4). The aim of the work was to describe all known genera of flowering plants and gymnosperms from specimens in the herbarium at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, and to include all known synonyms. The first part of the first volume was published in 1862 (Bentham and Hooker 1862–83).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Bentham and Hooker 1862–83 did not contain lists of species. However, Hooker and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2516.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Benjamin Daydon Jackson’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Index Kewensis</hi>, financed by a bequest from CD and first published in 1893, provided such a list.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Watson’s views on ‘convergence’ were summarised in a memorandum to CD (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2636.xml" resp="#automat">letter from H. C. Watson, [3? January 1860]</ref>). Hooker wrote to CD on the subject in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3036.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of [11 May – 3 December 1860]</ref> (this volume, Supplement), and in the missing fragment of his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3000.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of [26 November – 4 December 1860]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8; see also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 4 December [1860]</ref> and n. 6). CD referred to Watson’s criticism in the revised American edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> and in the third and later editions of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed., pp. 141–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD referred to the geological record in support of his transmutation theory in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, chapters 9 and 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Hooker had previously described centripetal and centrifugal models of variation (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-947.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 1 February 1846</ref>); however, Watson and Hooker evidently understood the terms centripetal and centrifugal somewhat differently. For Watson, centripetal variation afforded a mechanism for the convergence of species (see also this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3036.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [11 May – 3 December 1860]</ref>). Hooker used centripetal variation to designate variations that were prone to revert to a parental type. CD objected to Hooker’s notion, arguing that <hi rend="italic">Gnaphalium</hi> species tended to ‘revert to more than one centre or type’ (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [16 April 1846]</ref>). Hooker used centrifugal variation to designate variation that accompanied extensive geographical distribution, as in <hi rend="italic">Senecio</hi> (Hooker 1844–7, p. 315), while Watson used it to signify the mechanism of divergence. CD disapproved of Hooker’s use of the word centrifugal (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2513.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 31 [October 1859]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The correspondence between CD and Watson on ‘convergence’ is in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8 (letters from [H. C. Watson], [3? January 1860] and 10 May 1860, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2639.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. C. Watson, [5–11 January 1860]</ref>). See also this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3036.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [11 May – 3 December 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Hooker had been on a botanical expedition to India from November 1847 to January 1851 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1987.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">R. Desmond 1999</ref>, pp. 96–177). Hooker had presumably asked for comparisons between his Indian specimens and specimens in Watson’s herbarium of British plants (<hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">These processes are stages in the preparation of herbarium specimens. For more on preparation of specimens, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5987.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Oliver 1881</ref>, pp. 269–73. Watson had private means and worked from home (<hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Watson refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Jackson Hooker</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>