<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7204">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Armand de Quatrefages   28 May [1870]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">379</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7204 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7204.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7204.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 147: 288</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 117</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.379)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>379</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1870-05-28">28 May [1870]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3892.xml">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on QdeB’s volume [<hi rend="italic">Charles Darwin et ses précurseurs Français</hi> (1870)]. Mentions error concerning his views on <hi rend="italic">Parus</hi> and nuthatch.</p>  
<p>Discusses <hi rend="italic">Canis magellanicus</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses reception of his views in France and Germany.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Canis magellanicus</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Charles Darwin et ses precurseurs Francais</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">France</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de 1870</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Beckenham | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>May 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have received and read your volume &amp; am much obliged for your present.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The whole strikes me as a wonderfully clear &amp; able discussion, &amp; I was much interested by it to the last page. It is impossible that any account of my views could be fairer, or as far as space permitted fuller, than that which you have given. The way in which you repeatedly mention my name is most gratifying to me. When I finished the second part, I thought that you had stated the case so favourably that you would make more converts on my side than on your own side. On reading the subsequent parts I had to change my sanguine view. In these latter parts many of your strictures are severe enough, but all are given with perfect courtesy &amp; fairness.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I can truly say I would rather be criticised by you in this manner than praised by many others. I agree with some of your criticisms, but differ entirely from the remainder; but I will not trouble you with any remarks. I may, however, say that you must have been deceived by the french translation as you infer that I believe that the Parus &amp; the Nuthatch (or <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Sitta</hi>) are related by direct filiation: I wished only to show by an imaginary illustration how either instincts or structure might first change.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> If you had seen <hi rend="underline">Canis magellanicus</hi> alive, you would have perceived how foxlike its appearance is, or if you had heard its voice, I think, you would never have hazarded the idea that it was a domestic dog run wild;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but this does not much concern me. It is curious how nationality influences opinion: a week hardly passes without my hearing of some naturalist in Germany who supports my views, &amp; often puts an exaggerated value on my works; whilst in France I have not heard of a single zoologist except M. Gaudry<ref target="#foot.f6"/> (and he only partially) who supports my views. But I must have a good many readers, as my books are translated, &amp; I must hope, notwithstanding your strictures, that I may influence some embryo naturalists in France.</p>
<p>You frequently speak of my good faith, &amp; no compliment <hi rend="underline">can</hi> be more <hi rend="underline">delightful</hi> to me, but I may return you the compliment with interest for every word which you write bears the stamp of your cordial love for the truth.</p>
<p>Believe me, dear Sir | with sincere respect | yours very faithfully | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. I am much obliged to you for sending me your lectures in the “Revue des Cours etc” for they have been very useful to me.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I have also to thank you for your kindness of my son George in Paris.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by CD’s reference to receiving Quatrefages’s book (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to Quatrefages’s book <hi rend="italic">Charles Darwin et ses précurseurs français</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1870</ref>). CD’s copy, with the pages uncut, is in the Darwin Library–CUL. The book was a reproduction of a collection of articles that Quatrefages had sent in 1869; CD’s annotated copy of an offprint of the articles (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1868–9</ref>) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The first part of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1870</ref> begins with an exposition of the views of some French naturalists on the transformation of species; the second chapter details CD’s theory, while the third focuses on facts that are compatible with the theory. In the second part of the book, Quatrefages presents a detailed critique of Darwinian theory.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 212, CD noted that he had seen titmice hammering yew seeds to break them ‘like a nuthatch’. On page 281, he suggested that natural selection might preserve each slight variation of the titmouse’s beak, until it had one ‘as well constructed for this purpose as that of the nuthatch’. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1868–9</ref>, p. 63, Quatrefages had questioned whether CD had demonstrated that the nuthatch was the ‘grandson’ of the titmouse. In the book version, a note was added giving a reference to the section of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> where CD had commented on the titmouse and nuthatch (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 281), but there was no mention in the note that CD had not, in fact, suggested a genealogical connection between these species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1870</ref>, p. 156).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Canis magellanicus</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Lycalopex culpaeus </hi>subsp. <hi rend="italic">culpaeus</hi>, a subspecies of the culpeo, a type of South American fox. Quatrefages had suggested that many supposedly unique species were merely dogs that had become feral and reverted to ancestral characteristics (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1870</ref>, pp. 281–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1829.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Albert Gaudry</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD refers to the published version of Quatrefages’s lectures on anthropology, which appeared in instalments in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Cours Scientifiques de la France et de l’Etranger</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6471.xml">Quatrefages 1867–9</ref>). The lectures discussed various aspects of human development; CD referred to them several times in <hi rend="italic">Descent.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> had visited Paris in March 1869 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6686.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 29 March 1869</ref> and n. 2).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>