<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-925">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Edward Hitchcock   6 November [1845]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3060</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-925 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-925.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-925.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">6 NO 6 1845</note>
    <relatedItem type="publication">
        <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 3: 216–20</bibl>
    </relatedItem>
</notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Amherst College Archives (Edward and Orra White Hitchcock papers: 2 Edward Hitchcock: Correspondence, Box 3, Folder 8)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_9.xml">Amherst</repository>
                    <collection>Edward and Orra White Hitchcock papers</collection>
                    <idno>2 Edward Hitchcock: Correspondence, Box 3, Folder 8</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1845-11-06">6 Nov [1845]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2307.xml">Hitchcock, Edward</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks EH for his <hi rend="italic">Final report on the geology of Massachusetts</hi> [1841]. Comments on EH’s discovery of fossil footprints.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Final report on the geology of Massachusetts</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Hitchcock, Edward 1841</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Absence from home has prevented me sooner acknowledging your truly generous present of the Final Report on the Geology of Massachusetts.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I assure you I feel sensibly the honour &amp; kindness you have done me. I have as yet read only a little, but I see that there will be much that will interest me greatly; I allude more especially to your detailed accounts of the alluvial deposits, ice &amp; water action, &amp;c. &amp;c. Your’s is indeed a magnificent work with its numerous &amp; striking illustrations. I am delighted to possess the excellent plates on the footsteps,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; I daresay I shall find some further information, though I have carefully read your several papers.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In my opinion these footsteps (with which subject your name is certain to go down to long future posterity) make one of the most curious discoveries of the present century &amp; highly important in its several bearings. How sincerely I wish that you may live to discover some of the bones belonging to these gigantic birds: how eminently interesting it would be know, whether their structure branches off towards the Amphibia, as I am led to imagine that you have sometimes suspected. The finding the bones of the Rhynchosaurus in the pure hard sandstone of Grindshill in Shropshire (where there are some Reptile footsteps) may give one hopes.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I am preparing a little volume on the geology of S. America, which, when published next summer, I will beg you to do me the kindness to accept; though it is a miserable acknowledgment for your grand work.</p>
<p>With my sincere thanks and much respect. Pray believe me, dear Sir | Yours faithfully &amp; obliged. C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3692.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hitchcock 1841</ref>. CD’s copy of the first edition in two volumes is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Plates 31–49 depict fossil footprints that Hitchcock thought were made by birds. They were later shown to be dinosaur tracks (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1899.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dean 1969</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Beginning in 1836, Hitchcock had published a series of papers in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> about the footprints.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> discussed the fossil bones and footprints from the sandstone of Grinshill quarry, near Shrewsbury, in R. Owen 1841, pp. 145–6.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>