<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2665">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   28 January [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3529</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2665 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2665.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2665.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 164</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 20;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 269</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 53</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (43)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>43</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-01-28">28 Jan [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>If an American edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> is considered worth while, CD would like AG’s reviews prefixed to it.</p>  
<p>Will use all his strength to produce first part of his three-volume big work [<hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My dear Gray</p>
<p>Hooker has forwarded to me your letter to him; &amp; I cannot express how deeply it has gratified me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> To receive the approval of a man, whom one has long most sincerely respected, &amp; whose judgment &amp; knowledge are universally admitted, is the highest reward an author can possibly wish for; &amp; I thank you heartily for your most kind expressions.—</p>
<p>I have been absent from home for a few days, &amp; so could not earlier answer your letter to me of the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. —<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You have been extremely kind to take so much trouble &amp; interest about the Edition. It has been a mistake of my publisher not thinking of sending over the sheets. I had entirely &amp; utterly forgotten your offer of receiving the sheets as printed off.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But I must not blame my publisher; for had I remembered your most kind offer, I feel pretty sure I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not have taken advantage of it; for I never dreamed of my Book being so successful with general readers: I believe I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have laughed at the idea of sending the sheets to America.—</p>
<p>After much consideration &amp; on the strong advice of Lyell &amp; others, I have resolved to leave the present book as it is (excepting correcting errors or here &amp; there inserting short sentence) &amp; to use all my strength <hi rend="underline">which is but little</hi> to bring out the first part (forming a separate volume with index &amp;c) of the three volumes which will make my bigger work; so that I am very unwilling to take up time in making corrections for an American Edition.— I enclose list of few corrections in the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Reprint, which you will have received by this time complete;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; I could send 4 or 5 corrections or additions of equally small importance, or rather of equal brevity.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I, also, intend to write a <hi rend="underline">short</hi> Preface with brief history of subject.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> These I will set about, as they must some day be done &amp; I will send them you in a short time,—the few corrections first, &amp; the preface afterwards, unless I hear that you have given up all idea of separate Edition. You will then be able to judge whether it is worth having new Edition with <hi rend="underline">your</hi> <hi rend="underline">Review prefixed</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Whatever be the nature of your Review, I assure you I should feel it a <hi rend="underline">great</hi> honour to have my Book thus preceded.— In business matters it is always best to speak out plainly: as I should not, as we have managed it, get anything from an American publisher, if you do print an Edition &amp; can get any profit, nothing should induce me to touch a penny of it.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> My terms with Murray are that I receive <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of Profits, &amp; he <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula>;—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> with respect to latter, I can of course say nothing.— But I expect when you come to consider the case, you will not think a new Edition worth thinking about; though an answer to Agassiz would be a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">great</hi> advantage to subject.—</p>
<p>Thank you much for telling me the magnificent compliment of Wyman &amp; for sending me extract from Agassiz.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I cannot see the force of his argument; &amp; if he wished to puff my book he could not have been more ingenious.— I am delighted to hear that H. D. Rogers, the Professor at Glasgow &amp; so excellent a geologist goes very long way with my views.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Believe me, my dear Gray I feel all your most generous sympathy &amp; assistance</p>
<p>Yours most truly | C. Darwin</p>
<p>I shall value much at any time your criticisms, either in your Review or by letter.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.5 had I] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.1 strong] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.2 (excepting] <hi rend="italic">parenthesis over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.7 received] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.9 brief] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.16 publisher,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">4.4 &amp; so excellent a geologist] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to an authorised American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2638.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray to J. D. Hooker, 5 January 1860</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2672.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [22 January 1860]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD was in London from 24 to 27 January (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 4 April [1858]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The enclosure has not been found. CD had asked his publisher to send Gray the unbound sheets of the second English edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> late in 1859 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 22 December [1859]</ref>). For some of the corrections CD made to the second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, published on 7 January 1860, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See the letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">1 February [1860]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2701.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[8 or 9 February 1860]</ref>, in which CD enclosed additional changes for the American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>. The latter changes, however, arrived too late to be incorporated into the text and were included in a ‘Supplement’ to the revised fourth printing (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> US ed.</ref>, pp. 426–32). This edition also included other previously unpublished material: a long section responding to criticisms of natural selection by naturalists such as <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4975.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hewett Cottrell Watson</ref> was added to the end of chapter four (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> US ed.</ref>, pp. 116*–21*). CD substantially reworked this discussion for the third English edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix IV.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD’s historical preface was included in the revised American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. v–xi. This issue was advertised on the title page as ‘a new edition, revised and augmented by the author’. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix IV.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Gray may have suggested this arrangement in the missing section of the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, [10 January 1860]</ref>. His review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> however, was not included in the revised and augmented American edition.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-2663.xml">Gray’s letter of 23 January [1860]</ref>, discussing details of the American negotations, did not reach CD until mid-February (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-2701.xml">see letter to Asa Gray, [8 or 9 February 1860]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For CD’s arrangement with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3464.xml">John Murray</ref> concerning the publication of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2443.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Murray, 1 April 1859</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 1 February [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jeffries Wyman</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>. The ‘extract from Agassiz’ may refer to a passage taken from a lecture delivered by Agassiz in January 1860 that was reported in a Boston newspaper. It is possible that CD sent the extract on to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, as he did other letters and material concerning <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, for in Lyell’s scientific journal for the period there is an entry headed ‘Extract from lecture by Agassiz, Boston, January 1860’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8416.xml">Wilson ed. 1970</ref>, pp. 348–9) that reads: <quote type="quote"> What has the whale in the arctic regions to do with the lion or the tiger in the tropical Indies? There is no possible connection between them; and yet they are built respectively according to one &amp; the same idea. There is behind them &amp; anterior to their existence, a thought. There is a design according to which they were built, which must have been conceived before they were called into existence; otherwise these things could not be related in this general manner. Whenever we study the general relations of animals, we study more than the affinities of beasts. We study the manner in which it has pleased the Creator to express his thoughts in living realities; and that is the value of that study for intellectual Man; for while he traced these thoughts as revealed in nature, he must be conscious that he feels, and attempts as far as it is possible for the limited mind of man to analyze the thoughts of the Creator, to approach if possible into the counsels that preceded the calling into existence of this world with its inhabitants, and there lies really the moral value of the study of nature; for it makes us acquainted with the Creator in a manner in which we cannot learn [of] Him otherwise. As the Author of Nature, we must study Him in the revelation of nature in that which is living before our eyes. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Darwin Rogers</ref>, an American-born geologist, was Regius professor of natural history at Glasgow University. On 23 December 1859, he wrote to his brother <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4061.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Barton Rogers</ref> and mentioned his opinion of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6694.xml">Rogers ed. 1896</ref>, 2: 17–18): <quote type="quote"> The only matter of any interest is the appearance of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Charles Darwin’s</ref> book “On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection.” It is a suggestive book, full of ingenious arguments in favour of the Lamarckian hypothesis … When you read it you will often say, I think, that in his geology Darwin outdoes <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell</ref> himself in ignoring paroxysmal actions. This is its chief blemish with me. </quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>