<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8667">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alexander Agassiz   9 December 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20235</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8667 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8667.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8667.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">G. R. Agassiz ed. 1913, pp. 120–1</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Agassiz, G. R. 1913: 120</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_41.xml">Agassiz, Alexander</persName>
                <placeName>Cambridge Mass.</placeName>
                <date when="1872-12-09">9 Dec 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Has lost a year’s work in the fire that has devastated Boston.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Boston</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cambridge.</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 9, 1872.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you for the trouble you have taken in sending me a copy of your “Expression of the Emotions,” which has duly come to hand.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have not had a moment to look into it, in part on account of the work of distributing some collections which have lately arrived, and in part owing to the great fire which has devastated Boston, and which has affected us all more or less seriously.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have been hit pretty hard, not in a money way, but what is worse infinitely, I have lost a year’s work by the destruction of six Plates of anatomy with the original drawings, of which I have not even a sketch. They had been sent to Boston the morning of the fire to be lettered preparatory to printing. In addition I lost all the stones of the first parts of the “Revision of the Echini;” fortunately about three fifths of the edition of the Plates had been struck off and was safely housed at the Museum. This leaves us with rather a short supply, but the remainder of the book, which I hoped to get out before spring, must be delayed a long time, as I feel neither heart nor have I the time to start fresh and do all this again just as it was completed.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have sent to the Zoölogical Society a package for you, which please claim from Mr. Sclater.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I presume it should arrive a few days after this letter. I have made pretty extensive use of the new processes of photographic printing in my book, and from what I have succeeded in obtaining trust it will hereafter be possible to supersede the old lithographic processes, which are wasteful in time and money, and not half as accurate.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Agassiz’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix V).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The fire, which blazed on 9 and 10 November 1872, had destroyed most of the business area of the city including numerous warehouses (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6870.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sammarco 1997</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Agassiz’s <hi rend="italic">Revision of the Echini</hi> was published in parts in 1872 and 1874; it included a separate atlas of plates published in 1872 and 1873. Some of the plates were lithographs, produced by drawing on stone. Agassiz also refers to the Museum of Comparative Anatony at Harvard University.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4251.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Lutley Sclater</ref> was secretary of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zoological Society of London</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">As well as lithographs and woodcuts, the atlas of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_36.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Agassiz 1872–4</ref> included plates made from photographic negatives by the Woodburytype and Albertype processes (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_36.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Agassiz 1872–4</ref>, 1: xi).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>