<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-428">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   [14] September [1838]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-428 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-428.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-428.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 140</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 295</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 104</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.11)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>11</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 36</placeName>
                <date when="1838-09-14">[14] Sept [1838]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on an article in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> [by David Brewster, 67 (1838): 271–308] on Comte’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophie positive</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses falsity of Élie de Beaumont’s views of contemporaneous parallel lines of elevation and subsidence.</p>
            <p>Owen’s views of relationship of reptiles to birds.</p> 
<p>On "question of species" CD has filled notebook after notebook with facts, "which begin to group themselves <hi rend="italic">clearly</hi> under sub-laws".</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">reptiles</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Edinburgh Review</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Philosophie positive</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Brewster, David 1838</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Comte, I. A. M. F. X. 1830–1842</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[36 Great Marlborough Street]</placeName>
                    <date>Friday night. September 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <ref target="#foot.f1"/></date>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was astonished &amp; delighted at your gloriously long letter, &amp; I am sure I am very much obliged to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Lyell for having taken the trouble to write so much.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I mean to have a good hours enjoyment &amp; scribble away to you, who have so much geological sympathy, that I do not care how egotiscally I write. But first for the main object, which makes me write at once— it is about that unfortunate letter of Governor Prescott.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I only received one letter from you at Newcastle, &amp; that came single by <hi rend="underline">the post</hi>: you had then received the communication, but do not allude to the official document, or to any frank from Lord Northhampton.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It is very provoking, for I do not know what I shall say to the Council, &amp; no one would much like accepting the offer without actually seeing the very wording of the letter.— If you have not burnt my letter which accompanied it, will you send it to me, as I will endeavour to write the letter from memory with the aid of it.— Could Lord Northhampton have kept it by mistake? If you are sure he gave you a frank for the purpose, I would write to the Secretary of Post Office &amp; find whether it is lying in the dead office from being misdirected.— Will you, also, just look over your papers, once again.— I am <hi rend="underline">very sorry</hi> to trouble you— it is hard that all this plague should have been thrown on your shoulders,—but I yet hope the letter may be recovered.</p>
<p>I have got so much to say about all sort of trifling things, that I hardly know what to begin about:—but first pray give my best thanks to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell, for his very kind invitation, which it would have been delightful to have accepted, but I am pledged to go to my Uncle’s &amp; to home for a fortnight in end of October,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; till then I must not give myself even a days holidays.— It is a very very great temptation which I must resist.— I need not say how pleased I am to hear that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell likes my Journal— to hear such tidings is a kind of resurrection, for I feel towards my first born child, as if it had long since been dead, buried &amp; forgotten,—but the past is nothing &amp; the future everything to us geologists, as you show in your capital motto to the Elements.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> By the way have you read the article in the Edinburgh Review on M. Comte Cours de la Philosophie, (or some such title)— it is capital— there are some fine sentences, about the very essence of science being prediction,—which reminded me of “its law being progress”.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I will now begin &amp; go through your letter seriatim.— I daresay your plan of putting the Elie de Beaumonts chapter separately &amp; early will be very good.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> anyhow it is showing a bold front in the first edition, which is to be translated into French.— it will be a curious point to geologists hereafter to note how long a man’s name, will support a theory, so completely exposed, as that of De Beaumonts has been by you.— You say, you “<hi rend="underline">begin to hope</hi> that the great principles there insisted on will stand the test of time”. <hi rend="underline">begin </hi> to <hi rend="underline">hope,</hi>; why the <hi rend="underline">possibility</hi> of a doubt has never crossed my mind for many a long day: this may be very unphilosophical, but my geological salvation is staked on it. After having just come back from Glen Roy, &amp; found how difficulties smooth away under your Principles, it makes me quite indignant, that you should talk of <hi rend="underline">hoping.</hi> With respect to the question how far my coral theory bears on De Beaumont’s theory,—I think it would be prudent to quote me with great caution, until my whole account is published,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> &amp; then you (&amp; others) can judge how far there is foundation for such generalization.— mind I do not doubt its truth,—but the extension of any view over such large spaces from comparatively few facts must be received with much caution.— I do not myself the least doubt that within the recent (or as you, much to my annoyment would call it, Newer Pliocene) period <hi rend="underline">tortuous</hi> bands &amp; <hi rend="underline">not</hi> all the bands parallel to each other have been elevated, &amp; corresponding ones subsided,—though within this same period, some parts probably remained for a time stationary, or even subsided.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I do not believe a more utterly false view <hi rend="doubleUnderline">could</hi> have been invented than great straight lines, being suddenly thrown up.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>When my book on Volcanos–Coral reefs will be published I hardly know,—I fear it will be at least four or five months, though much the greater part is written,—I find so much time is lost in correcting details, &amp; ascertaining their accuracy. The government Zoological work is a millstone round my neck,—&amp; the Glen Roy paper has lost me six weeks.— I will not however say lost, for supposing I can prove to others satisfaction, what I have convinced myself is the case, the inferences, I think, you will allow to be important.— I cannot doubt the molten matter beneath the earths crust possesses a high degree of fluidity, almost like the sea beneath the Polar ice.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> By the way I hope you will give me some Sweedish case to quote of shells being preserved on the surface, but not in contemporaneous beds of gravel.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I have received a most obliging letter from Sir. D. B.,<ref target="#foot.f14"/> &amp; he communicated some information so useful, that I have written to him again.—</p>
<p>The Winters <hi rend="underline">Bark</hi> <ref target="#foot.f15"/> is a tree, vegetables even in Patagonia not usually being furnished with <hi rend="underline">bark.</hi> — I cannot give you the scientific name at present, though it is a well known form.— Speaking of parrots you may say (to avoid S. lat. S. America) in Tierra del Fuego, or near Cape Horn.— In the sentence you ask me to alter, (read)—“….in Tierra del Fuego, including the wooded part immediately north of the St<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> of Mag: as well as in the Falkland Is<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. no reptile…..yet we meet with in the <hi rend="underline">former </hi> country…..the guanaco, (a kind of Llama), a deer, fox, puma <hi rend="underline">several</hi> small rodents…..&amp; in the Falkland Islands some of these animals”—<ref target="#foot.f16"/> This sentence is now correct, you must harmonize it— Port Famine is in Lat. 53<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> ’ 38’ S.—</p>
<p>I have forwarded your letter (P. paid) to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Richardson at Portsmouth.— I see you there, tell him to write to you at Kinnordy, any time before the end of <hi rend="underline">November.</hi> I hope this is a mistake, &amp; you meant to say October.— I shall be grieved if it is true; I trust you will want books, or something will bring you back before then.—<ref target="#foot.f17"/> Remember, what I have often heard you say—the country is very bad for the intellects.— the Scotch mists will put out some volcanic speculations— you see I am affecting to become very cocknefyed, &amp; to despise the poor country folk, who breath fresh air instead of smoke, &amp; see the goodly fields instead of the brick-houses in Marlborough St,—the very sight of which I confess I abhor.—</p>
<p>I am glad to hear what a favourable report you give of the British association; I am the more pleased, because I have been fighting its battle with Basil Hall, Stokes,<ref target="#foot.f18"/> &amp; several others,—having made up my mind from the report in the Athenæum, that it must have been an excellent meeting.— I have been much amused with an account I have received of the wars of Don Roderick &amp; Babbage—<ref target="#foot.f19"/> what a grievous pity it is that the latter should be so implacable, &amp; if one might so call the calculating machine, so very silly.— One regrets such a contest so much the more, from knowing the incomparable superiority, (except in finesse) of the one over the other.—</p>
<p>This is a most rigmarole letter, for after each sentence, I take breath, (&amp; you will have need of it in reading it) &amp; look to yours.— With respect to Blainvilles paper, I saw only an abstract, which would not serve your purpose to quote, so I will not make any full abstracts.— Owen must be a very much superior authority on Marsupials, (if not on every subject) than Blainville,<ref target="#foot.f20"/> whom I have heard is superficial.— I suppose Owen has pointed out to you the internal process in the Stonesfield jaws, which amongst Mammalia, is exclusively confined to the Marsupiata.— By the way Owen talks of the Ornithoryhncus<ref target="#foot.f21"/> as leading off into the reptiles, so that I should think, it was not impossible that some reptiles formerly might have approached nearer to the Mammalian type, than any existing ones now do.—</p>
<p>I suppose you have plenty of work in hand in putting the Principles to rights, after the parturition of the Elements. I see so few people, that I have not heard anything about the latter in the shape of criticism,—but judging from some very unlikely people who have bought it, I should think it must be selling well. Charlesworth, I think, is annoyed that you have not quoted him more about the embedding of of the older shells in the newer beds.—<ref target="#foot.f22"/> But poor Charlesworth is of an unhappy discontented disposition.— he is, moreover, very much to be pitied— the Zoological Soc: are going to give up the Assit. Secretary’s place, &amp; it is feared, that he has a disiase of the heart,—so that altogether he is greatly to be pitied.— My younger sister writes to me from home, that she finds the Elements requires hard reading— I am glad of this, for few are so silly as really to like a very easy book, as everyone has a sort of consciousness, that in such case the subject must be shirked. (videlicet the popularity of Herschels treatise on Nat. Phil. &amp; the still more abstruse one on astronomy).<ref target="#foot.f23"/> NB. Whilst I think of it; do not quote (if by any <hi rend="underline">chance</hi> you had so intended) Gould’s case of Water-wagtails, one species peculiar to this country &amp; one to France— the case does not hold good.—<ref target="#foot.f24"/> Will you have the kindness to write soon on the subject of the Newfoundland letter (I wish it was at the bottom of the Polar Sea) &amp; return mine, in case you can find no clue to the real one.—</p>
<p>I wish with all my heart that my Geological book was out— I have every motive to work hard, &amp; will, following your steps, work just that degree of hardness to keep well,—I should like my volume to be out before your new edition of Principles appears.— Besides the Coral theory,—the volcanic chapters, will, I think, contain some new facts.— I have lately been sadly tempted to be idle, that is as far as pure geology is concerned, by the delightful number of new views, which have been coming in, thickly &amp; steadily, on the classification &amp; affinities &amp; instincts of animals—bearing on the question of species—note book, after note book has been filled, with facts, which begin to group themselves <hi rend="underline">clearly</hi> under sub-laws.—<ref target="#foot.f25"/></p>
<p>Good night, my dear Lyell, I have filled my letter, &amp; have enjoyed my talk to you, as much as I can, without having you in propriâ personâ. Think of the bad effects of the country. so once more | good night | Ever yours | Chas. Darwin—</p>
<p>Pray again give my best thanks to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lyell.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 object] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.7 single] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.11 If] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Pray’ <hi rend="italic">and over</hi> ‘do’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.11 my] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.14 it] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘any’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.16 once again.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.4 to home] ‘to’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.11 Comte] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Le’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.11 de] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘po’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">2.13 being progress] ‘being’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">3.5 as] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">3.8 long] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘day’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">3.8 this] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">3.9 having] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘jus’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">3.10 come] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">3.12 De Beaumont’s theory] ‘theory’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘view’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">3.14 then] ‘en’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">3.18 Newer] ‘er’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">3.18 period] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘)’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">3.19 <hi rend="italic">tortuous</hi>] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘bands’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">3.19 &amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> … other] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">not</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘several’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">4.2 months] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">4.2 much] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">4.9 Sweedish] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25">5.5 )] <hi rend="italic">over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n26">5.5 including] ‘cluding’ <hi rend="italic">added to</hi> ‘in’; <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘&amp;’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n27">5.7 (a kind of Llama)] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘(an animal’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n28">5.7 a deer] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n29">5.7 fox] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n30">5.7 puma] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n31">6.2 there] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘say’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n32">6.3 I shall] ‘I’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘in’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n33">7.6 so implacable,] ‘so’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n34">7.8 superiority,] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘sp’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n35">7.9 )] <hi rend="italic">over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n36">8.4 full] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘more’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n37">8.4 authority] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘than Blainville’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n38">8.5 on every] ‘on’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n39">8.5 )] <hi rend="italic">over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n40">8.5 Blainville,] <hi rend="italic">del with deleting line cancelled</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n41">8.6 suppose] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘do’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n42">8.10 any] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘these’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n43">9.1 Principles] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Ele’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n44">9.3 very] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘pe’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n45">9.4 be] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n46">9.7 discontented] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n47">9.12 everyone] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘they all’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n48">9.12 has] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘have’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n49">9.13 the popularity of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n50">9.13 on Nat.] ‘on’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘of’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n51">9.13 the still] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n52">9.14 abstruse one] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘that’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n53">10.4 Besides] ‘B’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘b’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n54"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi> : 1.12 ‘me’; 9.7 ‘moreover’; 10.6 ‘views’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Friday was the 14th of September.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Since Lyell suffered from weak eyesight, he dictated many of his letters.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3851.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Prescott</ref>, governor of Newfoundland. The letter requested the aid of the Council of the Geological Society ‘in finding some fit person’ to make a geological survey of the colony, its legislature having granted a sum towards defraying the expenses (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>, Council Minutes, 7 November 1838, CM 1/5, p. 59).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1033.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer Joshua Alwyne Compton</ref>, 2d Marquess of Northampton had been elected a vice-president of the British Association at the Newcastle meeting.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD did not, in fact, go until 9 November; the occasion was his proposal to Emma Wedgwood (‘Journal’; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">‘It is a philosophy which never rests—its law is progress: a point which yesterday was invisible is its goal to-day, and will be its starting post to-morrow.’ The statement, quoted from the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review,</hi> appears on the title page.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_891.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Brewster] 1838</ref>. This was a review of the first two volumes of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Auguste Comte’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Cours de philosophie positive</hi> (Paris, 1830–5). For discussions of CD’s reaction to the review see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6997.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schweber 1977</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5183.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Manier 1978</ref>, pp. 40–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Refers to Lyell’s revisions for the sixth edition of <hi rend="italic">Principles</hi> (C. Lyell 1840). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 6 and 8 September 1838</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD presented a brief statement of his theory of coral reefs to the Geological Society on 31 May 1837 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 46–9) and in <hi rend="italic">Journal and</hi> <hi rend="italic">remarks,</hi> pp. 554–69. He had not yet begun to write his longer work on the subject. His ‘Journal’ entry for 5 October 1838 reads: ‘Began Coral Paper: requires much reading’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 6 and 8 September 1838</ref>, n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">This was Élie de Beaumont’s view.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">A hypothesis discussed in ‘On the connexion of certain volcanic phenomena in South America’, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 53–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD likened the evidence for subsidence and elevation in Scotland to that which Lyell had observed in Sweden; however, his theory that the roads of Glen Roy were the remains of marine beaches faced a difficulty in that no marine shells could be found on them. To overcome this problem he referred to observations by Lyell that shells were not always preserved in Swedish gravel beds where they might have been expected. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Observations on the parallel roads of Glen Roy’</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 108–14, 134.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Brewster</ref> informed CD about ‘roads’ in the valley of the Spey similar to those of Glen Roy. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 93.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">See <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> p. 342. The subject discussed in this paragraph must have been raised in the letter to Richardson, which Lyell had enclosed for CD to read and forward.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">C. Lyell 1840, 1: 241–2. CD discussed the fauna of the region in <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> pp. 300–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">The Lyells remained at Kinnordy until 14 November, when they departed for London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wilson 1972</ref>, p. 483).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Stokes</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Late in 1837, Roderick Murchison, who was General Secretary of the British Association, had offered <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Babbage</ref> the position of President for the 1839 meeting. However, when John Herschel returned to England in May 1838 after his astronomical observations at the Cape, Murchison changed his mind and offered the position to Herschel. When this double manoeuvre became known at the August meeting in Newcastle, Herschel and Babbage both refused the position, and the angry Babbage left the meeting, never to participate in the Association again. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6004.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orange 1975</ref>, p. 291.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">The question involved a fossil marsupial unearthed in the Oolitic strata at Stonesfield in Oxfordshire. Until this discovery, mammals were unknown in Secondary strata. Henri Marie Ducrotay de Blainville, who believed in a progressive sequence of fossil forms, argued that the creature was in fact a reptile (Blainville 1838a and 1838b; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_204.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Appel 1980</ref>). Lyell, who opposed the notion of progressive development, was naturally pleased with Owen’s views, which he probably heard at the Newcastle meeting (Owen 1838a; see also Owen 1841, pp. 391–4, and C. Lyell 1840, 1: 235–40).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">For CD’s description see <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> p. 526.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">In arguing against Lyell’s dating of the crag, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_890.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Charlesworth</ref> insisted that erosion of fossil-bearing strata would intermingle fossils of different periods, making it impossible to date Tertiary beds by Lyell’s method of counting the percentage of still living representatives (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1373.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charlesworth 1837</ref>). In the <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4993.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1838</ref>, pp. 300–8) Lyell accepted Charlesworth’s division of the red and coralline crag but ignored his views on dating methods.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3592.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herschel 1831</ref> and 1833. For Herschel’s influence on CD see <hi rend="italic">Autobiography,</hi> pp. 67–8, Ruse 1975b, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5183.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Manier 1978</ref>, pp. 47–51.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2949.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gould 1832–7</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">By September 1838 CD had filled the second half of the <hi rend="italic">Red notebook</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Notebooks B, C</hi>, and most of <hi rend="italic">D </hi> and <hi rend="italic">M</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5912.xml"><hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi></ref>). All these notes were made before reading Malthus’ <hi rend="italic">An essay on the principle of population</hi> during that month (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebook D</hi></ref>: 134e–5e). For an analysis of CD’s thinking and method of work on his ‘path to natural selection’ during this period, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4424.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kohn 1980</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>