<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5705">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Julius von Haast   4 December 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7262</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5705 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5705.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5705.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp, encl 5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 12; DAR 177: 243</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 12,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 243 (fragile)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2039.xml">Haast, J. F. J. von</persName>
                <placeName>Christchurch</placeName>
                <date when="1867-12-04">4 Dec 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>JvH forwards J. Stack’s replies to CD’s queries about expression [see <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>, p. 20].</p>  
<p>Sends photos of skeletons of six species of <hi rend="italic">Dinornis</hi> he is assembling for the Museum.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Dinornis</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4512">Stack, J. W.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">which! Museum</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Glückauf Christchurch</placeName>
                    <date>Decb 4. 1867</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>One of the Gentlemen to whom I submitted your Queries about expression,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> J Stack, Maori Missionary Kaipoi has sent me his answers, but they were written on such thick foolscap &amp; so wide apart, that it would have made quite a thick letter.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I therefore took the liberty to have them copied &amp; beg to enclose them, trusting that they will be of interest to you. I have no doubt that the other Gentlemen in the North Island have forwarded their answers directly to you.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I heard with great pleasure from our mutual friend D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> that you enjoy now much better health &amp; trust that this will continue, both to your comfort and in the interest of Science. Some few months ago, I had the pleasure to forward to you one of my reports on the headwaters of the Rakaia, which will make you acquainted with some of our glacier period phenomena.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have been busy lately with articulating 6 skeletons of Dinornis for our Museum &amp; they form a really curious group &amp; as I believe unique.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I enclose you a small photograph of them.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have numbered the different species for your guidance.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>No 1. Dinornis giganteus—9<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> 10<hi rend="superscript">’</hi></p>
<p>" 2 " Robustus 8<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> 5<hi rend="superscript">’</hi></p>
<p>" 3 " Elephantopus 5<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">’</hi></p>
<p>" 4 " Crassus — 4<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">’</hi></p>
<p>" 5 " casuarinus 5<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> 2<hi rend="superscript">’</hi></p>
<p>" 6 " didiformis 4<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">’</hi></p> </figure> 
<p>I have introduced the skeletons of a Kiwi (Apterix Owenii) &amp; a human figure for comparison.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Wishing you further restoration to health believe me my dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin | Yours most faithfully | Julius Haast <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Ch<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi> FRS.</p>
<p rend="left">Down, Bromley | Kent—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwins Queries about expression.</p>
<p>1. “<hi rend="underline">Is astonishment expressed by the eyes and mouth being</hi> <hi rend="underline">opened wide and by the eyebrows being raised?</hi>”</p>
<p>It is, but the action is more observable in some individuals than in others. The habitual endeavour of the maori is to conceal the workings of internal feeling and it is only when an individual is off his guard or the force of passion breaks through the habitual restraint put upon the feelings that any outward manifestations are noticeable either in the expression of the face or the attitude of the person.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>2. “<hi rend="underline">Does shame excite a blush when the color of the skin</hi> <hi rend="underline">allows it to be visible?</hi>”</p>
<p>It does. Hundreds of instances have come under my observation   An amusing one occurred only a few days ago. An old man partly tatooed and rather darker than the average of his people, let a section of land (his all) to an Englishman for a term of years for a small rental just sufficient to keep him in clothes.—For some time there has been quite a mania among the Kaiapoi maoris for the possession of gigs and dog carts, and this seized my old friend who came to me to know whether he could not draw the rent for four years in one lump sum, to enable him to buy a gig that he had set his heart upon. The idea of this poor old clumsey ragged fellow driving in his private carriage was so absurd, that I burst out laughing; the old man blushed to the roots of his hair.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>3. “<hi rend="underline">When a man is indignant or defiant, does he frown hold</hi> <hi rend="underline">his body and head erect, square his shoulders, and clench his</hi> <hi rend="underline">fists?</hi>”</p>
<p>He does. But immediately he begins to speak he loses the stiff set and tries to express his rage by the violent action of every part of his body.</p>
<p>I watched a man and woman quarrelling a few days ago and set down in my note-book the following particulars.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>—Eyes dilated.— body swayed violently backwards and forwards. Head inclined forward toward the antagonist— fists clenched, now thrown behind the body, now brought forward and directed toward eachothers faces.</p>
<p>6. “<hi rend="underline">When in good spirits do the eyes sparkle with the skin</hi> <hi rend="underline">round and under them a little wrinkled and with the mouth a</hi> <hi rend="underline">little drawn back?</hi>”</p>
<p>I took the following notes whilst watching a group of maoris who were much amused by something that was being told them.</p>
<p>—Eyes sparkling, half closed. Teeth exposed. Flesh drawn into a round lump on the cheeks.— Corners of the eyes all gathered up.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>14. “<hi rend="underline">Do children when sulky pout, or greatly protrude the</hi> <hi rend="underline">lips?</hi>”</p>
<p>Yes. I have seen them constantly do so.— Man sometimes and woman very frequently.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>I could have answered more of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin’s questions but as he so particularly requests that memory may not be trusted to in doing so, I forbear till I can do so from actual observation of persons not likely to have copied their mode of expressing their feelings from Europeans.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>signed | James Stack</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure:</hi></note>
                <note>11.1 —Eyes … up. 11.2] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon; scored pencil</hi>; ‘I ought to quote this’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of enclosure:</hi> ‘<hi rend="italic">New Zealand</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; ‘32 | N. Zealand’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD sent Haast queries about expression with his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5423.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Haast of 27 February [1867]</ref>. For the names of those who received copies of CD’s queries on expression from Haast, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5534.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Julius von Haast, 12 May – 2 June 1867</ref> and nn. 2–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haast refers to James West Stack and to Kaiapoi, near Christchurch, on South Island, New Zealand (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>). For more on Stack and his view of CD’s transmutation theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, especially pp. 514–15, and Reed ed. 1935, pp. 61–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">No replies from the other recipients have been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5534.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Julius von Haast, 12 May – 2 June 1867</ref>, n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haast refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3243.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. F. J. von Haast 1866</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5534.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Julius von Haast, 12 May – 2 June 1867</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haast refers to <hi rend="italic">Dinornis</hi>, the extinct genus of moas of New Zealand, and to the Canterbury Museum, Christchurch, New Zealand, which he founded (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, pp. 113, 123). The museum had opened to the public on 3 December 1867 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 504). Haast first described the bones in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. F. J. von Haast 1868</ref>. Haast was assisted in articulating the skeletons by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5716.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick Richardson Fuller</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, p. 482). For more on the discovery of the moa bones in December 1866, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, pp. 481–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The enclosed photograph has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL. The Canterbury Museum has two photographs of the articulated <hi rend="italic">Dinornis</hi> skeletons, taken by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6406.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Louis Mundy</ref>. One, which may be the same as that sent to CD, is reproduced facing p. 118. An engraving after one of the photographs appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Illustrated London News</hi>, 8 February 1868, p. 144; the accompanying text named the species and gave their heights in feet and inches as in this letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The male figure in the photograph reproduced facing p. 118 is probably Haast; the smallest skeleton could be that of the kiwi, <hi rend="italic">Apterix owenii</hi>, a bird related to the moas. For an overview of subsequent taxonomic changes affecting species assigned by Haast to <hi rend="italic">Dinornis</hi>, see, for example, Anderson 1989, pp. 17–38.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 279.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 317–18.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 248.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD concluded that all human races expressed good spirits similarly, referring to observations made in New Zealand, among other places, but without naming Stack (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 213).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 233.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD wrote at the end of the questionnaire, ‘Memory is so deceptive on subjects like these that I hope it may not be trusted to’ (enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5423.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Julius von Haast, 27 February [1867]</ref>). Only the five answers given here are recorded under Stack’s name in CD’s records of responses to his queries on expression (DAR 186: 1–29).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>