<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3561">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. G. Bronn<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   19 May 1862</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14090</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3561 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3561.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3561.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French) damaged †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160.3: 321</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 321</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml">Bronn, H. G.</persName>
                <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                <date when="1862-05-19">19 May 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for revisions in 2d ed. of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. Suggests correction regarding species numbers in the Tertiary.</p>  
<p>Comments on pages of <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> and problems of German translation.</p> 
            <p>Believes CD’s theory not yet proven, but that it will finally lead to truth.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Orchids</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number of species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01387_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3816px" height="6319px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01387_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3816px" height="6319px"/>
        <surface n="321:1r" xml:id="i1388">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01387.jpg" width="3816px" height="6319px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01387_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3816px" height="6319px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01387.dzi" width="3816px" height="6319px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="321:1v" xml:id="i1389">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01388.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01388_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01388.dzi" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="321:2r" xml:id="i1390">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01389.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01389_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01389.dzi" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="321:2v" xml:id="i1391">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01390.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01390_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01390.dzi" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="321:1v-2r" xml:id="i1392">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01391.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01391_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01391.dzi" width="3695px" height="6240px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                    <date>le 19 Mai 1862</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai eu l’honneur de recevoir les paquets, que Vous avez bien voulu m’addresser soit directement soit par l’intermédiaire de Mr Schweizerbart;<ref target="#foot.f2"/>—et je vous remercie sincèrement non seulement pour les additions à la dernière édition anglaise de vôtre Origin of Species, mais particulièrement encore pour la manière, dont vous m’avez su faciliter de retrouver les pages et les lignes, où un changement ou une addition doit avoir lieu dans la nouvelle édition allemande, dont l’impression va commencer dans ces jours mêmes.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Il faut cependant me permettre une observation sur un passage dans la dernière édition Anglaise, qui ne s’est pas trouvé dans la précédente.</p>
<p>Pag. 142: Geology shows us, at least within the whole imm〈ense〉 tertiary period, that the number of species of shells and probably, <hi rend="underline">of mammals</hi>, has not greatly or at all increased.</p>
<p>N’ÿ a-t-il pas là quelque faute d’impression? L〈es〉 〈    〉 n’existent au commencement de la période tertiaire 〈    〉 nombre et de peu d’ordres seulement; ils deviennent toujo〈urs〉 plus nombreux, de sorte que dans l’étage Miocène ils paraissent être même plus variés et plus abondants, qu’aujourdhui. Au moins le nombre d’espèces trouvées ensemble dans une même couche d’une même localité (à Mayance, Sansan etc)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> est quelquefois plus grand, que celui qu’on m’en trouveroit à présent dans toute l’Europe. Il n’ÿ a pas de doute, que le nombre des Mammifères, dont on ne connoît qu’une douzaine d’espèces à peu près dans les terrains pré-tertiaires, n’ait augmenté plus considérablement peutêtre que celui d’aucune autre classe justement dans la période tertiaire. Je vous prie donc, Monsieur, de bien vouloir me faire savoir comment il faut entendre ce passage?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Les feuilles de Vôtre livre sur les Orchidées m’ont fait reconnoître, qu’il sera d’une grande importance pour la science, qu’il va enrichir de nouvaux faits relativement à une famille de plantes qui sont des plus interèssantes de toutes, et dont il corrigera la théorie.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Si peût-être pas tous les lecteurs de “l’Origin” seroient assez botanistes, pour s’ÿ intéresser il ÿ aura sans doute un grand nombre de botanistes qui, ne possedent pas l’Origin, mais achèteront les Orchidées. C’est ce que j’ai écrit à Mr. Schweizerbart en lui communiquant les épreuves; cependant je l’ai prié également d’en consulter encore un botaniste même, comme p.e. Mr. <hi rend="underline">v. Mohl</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Ensuite il aura à faire son compte rélativement à ses frais; et je crois qu’il sera à même à Vous communiquer sa decision en 18–24 jours auplus!—car on vient de me prévenir qu’il est parti pour la foire de Leipsic, voÿage que‘ chaque libraire éditeur doit faire tous les ans et qui conge 2–3 semaines.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Je Vous ai dit, que je n’adhère pas à Vôtre théorie, parce-que, malgré tous les avantage qu’elle auroit pour la science, elle est encore en opposition avec des faits fondamentaux de la science (le premier developpement d’un animal sortant de matière inorganique), mais que néanmoins je suis convaincu, qu’<hi rend="underline">elle</hi> nous conduira enfin sur la route de la verité.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Peût-être, si je trouve assez de temps, j’ajouterai à la traduction quelques observations intéressantes sur la variabilité des espèces relativement à des charactères, qu’on a cru être les plus constants.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Veuillez aggréer, Monsieur, l’expression de la considération toute particulière, avec laquelle j’ai, l’honneur d’être, Monsieur | Vôtre | très devoué | H. G. Bronn</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>5.5 Peût-être, … constants. 5.7] <hi rend="italic">two crosses in margin, pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                    <date>19 May 1862</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Sir,</p>
<p>I have had the honour of receiving the packets that you were kind enough to send me either directly or through Mr Schweizerbart;<ref target="#foot.f2"/>—and I thank you sincerely not only for the additions to the latest English edition of your Origin of Species, but even more especially for the manner in which you made it easy to find the pages and the lines where a change or an addition is to be made in the new German edition, which will be going to press any day now.<ref target="#foot_trans.f3"/> I must however comment on a passage in the latest English edition that is not in the previous one.</p>
<p>Pag. 142: Geology shows us, at least within the whole imm〈ense〉 tertiary period, that the number of species of shells and probably, <hi rend="underline">of mammals</hi>, has not greatly or at all increased.</p>
<p>Is there not some printing error there? The 〈    〉 do not exist at the beginning of the tertiary period 〈    〉 number and only a few orders; they become more numerous such that in the miocene stratum they appear to be even more varied and more abundant than today. At least the number of species found together in the same bed at the same locality (at Mayance, Sansan etc)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> is sometimes greater than that to be found nowadays in the whole of Europe. There is no doubt that the number of mammals, of which only about a dozen species are known in the pre-tertiary beds, has increased considerably perhaps more than any other class precisely in the tertiary period. I beg you therefore, my dear Sir, to let me know how this passage should be understood?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>The pages of your book on the Orchids made me realize that it will be of great importance for science and that it will provide new facts relating to a family of plants of the greatest interest, the interpretation of which it will revise.<ref target="#foot_trans.f6"/> Though perhaps not all readers of the “Origin” would be sufficiently botanically minded to be interested in it, there will certainly be a great number of botanists who do not possess a copy of the Origin but who will buy the Orchids. This is what I wrote to Mr. Schweizerbart when I sent him the proofs; however I have asked him also to consult a genuine botanist, such as, for example, Mr. <hi rend="underline">v. Mohl</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Afterwards he will have to make an account of his expenses; and I think that he will himself inform you of his decision within no more than 18–24 days—since I have just been informed that he has left for the Leipzig fair, a journey that every publisher must make every year and which lasts 2 to 3 weeks.<ref target="#foot_trans.f8"/></p>
<p>I have told you that I do not support your theory because, in spite of all the advantages it would have for science, it is still in opposition to some fundamental facts of science (the first development of an animal from inorganic matter), but nevertheless I am convinced that in the long run <hi rend="underline">it</hi> will lead us on the path of truth.<ref target="#foot_trans.f9"/> It is possible that, if I have enough time, I will add to the translation some interesting observations on the variability of species with respect to some characters that are believed to be the most constant.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Please accept, Sir, the expression of my highest esteem, with which I have the honour, Sir, of being your obedient servant | H. G. Bronn</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix I. Although Bronn had previously corresponded with CD in German, he began writing in French after learning that CD found it more difficult to read German than French (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 11 March [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For the transcription of this letter in its original French and CD’s annotations, see pp. 212–14. Although Bronn had previously corresponded with CD in German, he began writing in French after learning that CD found it more difficult to read German than French (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 11 March [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 25 April [1862]</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref> was the head of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>, the publishing firm that published the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, and was preparing to publish a translation of <hi rend="italic">Orchids.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Bronn was preparing a second German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1863) from the third English edition. The manuscript alterations and corrections sent by CD with his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 25 April [1862]</ref> have not been found. However, those changes incorporated in the second German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> that do not occur in the third English edition are given in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix VIII. Bronn trans. 1863 was initially published in three parts, whose publication was announced on 6 October, 17 November, and 19 December 1862, respectively (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Börsenblatt für den Deutschen Buchhandel</hi></ref> 29 (1862): 2083, 2447, and 2735).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f3">Bronn was preparing a second German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1863) from the third English edition. The manuscript alterations and corrections sent by CD with his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 25 April [1862]</ref> have not been found. However, those changes incorporated in the second German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> that do not occur in the third English edition are given in Appendix VIII. Bronn trans. 1863 was initially published in three parts, whose publication was announced on 6 October, 17 November, and 19 December 1862, respectively (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Börsenblatt für den Deutschen Buchhandel</hi></ref> 29 (1862): 2083, 2447, and 2735).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Mayence is the French name for the German city of Mainz. Bronn refers to the rich Miocene fauna found at both Eppelsheim, a village south of Mainz, and at Sansan, a village near Auch in the south of France (see Bronn 1858, p. 473).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">No reply from CD to this query has been found, and in Bronn trans. 1863, p. 152, the sentence is translated without modification. However, Bronn added a footnote that reads: ‘Bekanntlich hat sich die Säugthier-Welt fast ganz erst im Laufe der Tertiär-Zeit entwickelt.’ [As is commonly known, mammals developed almost exclusively during the Tertiary period.] CD annotated the sentence in his copy of the third edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, and in the fourth edition published in 1866, he amended it to read: ‘But geology shows us, that from an early part of the long tertiary period the number of species of shells, and that from the middle part of this same period the number of mammals, has not greatly or at all increased’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 151). CD’s copies of his own books are in the Rare Books Room–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD sent Bronn the first half of the proof-sheets of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> at the end of April (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 25 April [1862]</ref>); Bronn’s name also appears on CD’s list of presentation copies for this work (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f6">CD sent Bronn the first half of the proof-sheets of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> at the end of April (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 25 April [1862]</ref>); Bronn’s name also appears on CD’s list of presentation copies for this work (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.10, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 25 April [1862]</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugo von Mohl</ref>, professor of botany at Tübingen, was a specialist on plant anatomy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3590.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 7 June 1862</ref>. Leipzig was a major centre for the book trade in the nineteenth century; the book fair formed part of the annual Easter fair (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Börsenblatt für den Deutschen Buchhandel</hi></ref> 29 (1862): 1172–3, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3590.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 7 June 1862</ref>. Leipzig was a major centre for the book trade in the nineteenth century; the book fair formed part of the annual Easter fair (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Börsenblatt für den Deutschen Buchhandel</hi></ref> 29 (1862): 1172–3, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3363.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. G. Bronn, [before 11 March 1862]</ref>. For a discussion of Bronn’s attitude towards CD’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Junker 1991</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f9">See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3363.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. G. Bronn, [before 11 March 1862]</ref>. For a discussion of Bronn’s attitude towards CD’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Junker 1991</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Bronn had appended a chapter commenting on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> to his translation of the first edition (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8). He added no further remarks to the second German edition, stating that, as the latest English edition (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed.</ref>) contained several responses to his original comments, he felt obliged to leave his chapter unchanged in the second German edition (Bronn trans. 1863, p. 525 n.).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>