<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9767">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   20 December 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5300</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9767 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9767.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9767.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 63</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 63</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1874-12-20">20 Dec 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses his <hi rend="italic">Anthropogenie</hi> [1874]. Remarks on the tables.</p>  
<p>Has CD received Friedrich von Hellwald’s <hi rend="italic">Culturgeschichte</hi> [1875]?</p> 
            <p>Plans research trip to the Mediterranean.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Anthropogenie</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Culturgeschichte</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Mediterranean</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1874</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Hellwald, F. A. H. von 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>20 Dec 74</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Da das Jahr 1874 seinem Ende entgegen geht, erlauben Sie mir, Ihnen zum Beginne des neuen Jahres meine herzlichsten Grüsse und Glückwünsche zu schicken. Besonders wünsche ich Ihnen dazu neue Gesundheit und Kraft, damit Sie als bahnbrechender Reformator der Wissenschaft noch lange kräftig fortwirken. Ihr leuchtendes Beispiel ist uns stetes Vorbild in jener <hi rend="underline">wissenschaftlichen</hi> Form der “struggle for life,” welche der “Kampf um die <hi rend="underline">Wahrheit</hi>” ist. Mögen Ihre <hi rend="underline">Werke</hi> uns Allen darin immer allgemeinerer Muster werden!</p>
<p>Für die freundliche Übersendung der zweiten Auflage des “Descent of man” danke ich Ihnen herzlich.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Das Werk ist jetzt in Deutschland sehr verbreitet. Dass der Verleger der deutschen Übersetzungen Ihrer Werke jetzt eine <hi rend="underline">Gesammtausgabe</hi> derselben veranstaltet, wissen Sie wohl bereits.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ich habe in der “Jenaer Literatur-Zeitung” dieselbe angezeigt, und hoffe, dass sie sehr gute Aufnahme findet.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Mir scheint, dass die <hi rend="underline">principielle</hi>, philosophische Bedeutung Ihrer Theorien und deren <hi rend="underline">Consequenzen</hi> in Deutschland viel mehr gewürdigt wird als in England.</p>
<p>Meine <hi rend="underline">Anthropogenie</hi> scheint in England <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi> viel Beifall zu finden.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Mein Verleger<ref target="#foot.f6"/> schreibt mir, dass in England noch nicht 10 Exemplare verlangt worden sind, während nach Frankreich und Russland mehrere 100 Stück abgesetzt sind. Auch lauteten die beiden englischen Besprechungen, die ich gesehen habe (—in “Saturday-Review” und “Nature”) sehr <hi rend="underline">ungünstig</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Ihre Landsleute scheinen namentlich die antiklerikale Richtung nicht zu verstehen, die bei uns in Deutschland <hi rend="underline">alle</hi> Wahrheit liebenden Gebildeten jetzt beherrscht. Mein Buch sagt darüber im Kleinen nur, was im Grossen die Politik von <hi rend="underline">Bismark</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/> ist: <hi rend="underline">Energie</hi>!</p>
<p>Hat Ihnen Friedrich v. <hi rend="underline">Hellwald</hi> sein Werk geschickt: “Culturgeschichte in ihrer natürlichen Entwickelung”? Wenn Sie es nicht haben, werde ich es Ihnen senden.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Es ist eine sehr geistreiche Anwendung des <hi rend="underline">Darwinismus</hi> auf die gesammte menschliche <hi rend="underline">Culturgeschichte</hi>.</p>
<p>—Im Februar gehe ich auf mehrere Monate an das Mittelmeer, um die Keimblätter- und Gastraea-Theorie weiter zu verfolgen.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Das Interesse für diesen Gegenstand ist jetzt in Deutschland sehr gross.</p>
<p>Mit wiederholten herzlichsten Glückwünschen und besten Grüssen Ihr treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 Da … fortwirken. 1.4] ‘Return congratulations— | Anthropogenie— I read some chapters’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>— I fear I shall never do more in world | few know German— England | Gastraea-theory— I can see importance’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of last page</hi>: ‘Huxley—Amphioxus <hi rend="italic">[</hi>will differ from you<hi rend="italic">]</hi> | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Dodel’<ref target="#foot.f11"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>20 Dec 74</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>As the year of 1874 is coming to a close, allow me to send you my most cordial greetings and my best wishes for the beginning of the new year. Above all I wish you renewed health and vigour, so you may continue in your powerful role as the trail-blazing reformer of science for a long time yet. Your shining example is ever our model in that <hi rend="underline">scientific</hi> version of the “struggle for life”, which is the “struggle for the <hi rend="underline">truth</hi>”. May your works become ever more general examples for all of us in this!</p>
<p>For kindly sending me the second edition of the “Descent of Man” I thank you cordially.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The work is now already well known in Germany. That the publisher of the German translations of your work is now producing a <hi rend="underline">complete edition</hi> of them you will know already.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I advertised it in the “Jenaer Literatur–Zeitung” and hope that it will be well received.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It seems to me that the <hi rend="underline">principal</hi> philosophical significance of your theories and their <hi rend="underline">implications</hi> were appreciated far more in Germany than in England.</p>
<p>My <hi rend="underline">Anthropogenie</hi><ref target="#foot.f5"/> does <hi rend="underline">not</hi> seem to find much acclaim in England. My publisher<ref target="#foot.f6"/> tells me that not even 10 copies have been requested in England, while in France and Russia several 100 copies were sold. Also, the two English reviews that I have seen (—in “Saturday-Review” and “Nature”) were very unfavourable.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Your countrymen specifically do not seem to understand the anti-clerical movement which now governs <hi rend="underline">all</hi> truth-loving educated persons here in Germany.</p>
<p>On this, my book only communicates on a small scale what in the greater scheme of things is the politics of <hi rend="underline">Bismark</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f8"/> <hi rend="underline">energy</hi>!</p>
<p>Has Friedrich v. <hi rend="underline">Hellwald</hi> sent you his work: “Culturgeschichte in ihrer natürlichen Entwickelung? If you have not got it, I shall send it.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> It is a most witty application of <hi rend="underline">Darwinism</hi> to the entire human <hi rend="underline">history of civilization</hi>.</p>
<p>—In February I shall visit the Mediterranean for a few months, in order to pursue further my germ layer and Gastraea theory.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Currently, there is a lot of interest in this matter in Germany.</p>
<p>Again, my most cordial wishes for your health</p>
<p>Your loyally devoted | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haeckel’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref> (see Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The German edition of CD’s complete works was translated by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Victor Carus</ref> and published by E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagshandlung, Stuttgart, from 1874 onwards.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel’s advertisement appeared in <hi rend="italic">Jenaer Literaturzeitung</hi>, 26 December 1874, pp. 820–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">There is a copy of Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Anthropogenie, oder Entwickelungsgeschichte des Menschen</hi> (Anthropogeny, or the developmental history of humans; Haeckel 1874a) in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7215.xml">Wilhelm Engelmann</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, 17 October 1874, pp. 514–15, and <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 5 November 1874, pp. 4–5, 12 November 1874, pp. 22–4. The review in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> was by the physician <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3889.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Henry Pye-Smith</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">For more on Haeckel’s changing views on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_460.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto von Bismarck</ref>, the chancellor of Germany, and his association of biological and political theories, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6619.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reynolds 2008</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">There is no known correspondence between CD and Hellwald. There is no copy of Hellwald’s <hi rend="italic">Culturgeschichte in ihrer natürlichen Entwickelung bis zur Gegenwart</hi> (Cultural history in its natural development to the present; Hellwald 1874) in CD’s libraries at CUL or Down. Haeckel did, however, send a copy; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9811.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 11 January [1875]</ref>. On Haeckel’s relationship with Hellwald, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Di Gregorio 2005</ref>, pp. 376–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In Haeckel 1872, 1: 344–5, Haeckel proposed that two primary cell types or germ layers were differentiated in the early embryonic development of all multicellular organisms and that the ancestral mode of germ-layer formation was by invagination to produce a functional gut. This stage in development was called gastrulation. He further hypothesised, drawing on his biogenetic law (ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny), that there had existed an actual ‘gastraea’, by analogy with the developmental stage. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9091.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 8 October 1873</ref> and n. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD’s annotations are notes for his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9781.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Haeckel of 26 December 1874</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>