<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5085">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 May 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10651</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5085 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5085.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5085.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German), encl ALS 3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 72</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 72</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</persName>
                <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                <date when="1866-05-10">10 May 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Encloses letter from H. B. Geinitz, who declines to handle translation of new edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. Recommends Julius Victor Carus. Also suggests Gustav von Leonhard as translator for <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p>  
<p>Discusses translation of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1838">Geinitz, H. B.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                    <date>den 10 Mai 1866.</date>
                    <salute>Verehrtester Herr</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Für Ihre gütige und baldige Antwort auf meinen Brief bin ich Ihnen recht verbunden und wollen Sie es nur nicht als Unaufmerksamkeit meiner auslegen wenn ich Ihnen so spät Nachricht darauf gebe.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Die Sache hat sich aus mehreren Ursachen verzögert. Herr Prof. Geinitz den Herr Prof Leonhard in meinem Namen befragte ob er Zeit und Lust hätte sich sowohl der Durschsicht einer neuen Auflage Ihres Werkes als auch der Uebertragung eines anderen Werkes aus Ihrer Feder zu unterziehen, gab ihm etwas spät eine ablehnende Antwort, was mich veranlasste selbst noch an ihn zu schreiben; aber ich hatte auch keinen bessern Erfolg.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Herr Geinitz schrieb mir darauf anliegenden Brief und empfahl mir nochmals Herrn Prof Carus in Leipzig.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Sie wissen aus den Tagesblättern in welch kritischen Zuständen wir in Deutschland uns dermalen befinden, wo der an Verrath am Vaterland gränzende Uebermuth eines einzigen Menschen uns in den BürgerKrieg zu treiben im Begriffe steht, in dem er gegen alles Recht und gegen den Willen der ganzen deutschen Nation seine ehrgeizigen Plane verfolgt und sich mit dem Ausland selbst verbündet!<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Dass unter solchen Umständen die Geschäfte total gelähmt werden ist unvermeidlich. Ich werde daher auch mich auf das Nöthigste beschränken, da man neue Bücher jetzt nur zwecklos aussenden würde.</p>
<p>Wie Ihnen bekannt ist, hat herr Prof. G. Leonhard schon mit Herrn Bronn das “<hi rend="underline">Jahrbuch</hi>” gemeinschaftlich redigirt und hat auch jetzt das Geschäftliche der Redaction zu besorgen.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Da nun die Uebersetzung von <hi rend="underline">Bronn</hi> ist und die Durchsicht der neuen Auflage nur mühsam ist, Herr Leonhard aber bei mir <hi rend="underline">die Geologie</hi> <hi rend="underline">von Russland</hi> Murchisons, auch die Schrift von Sedgewick &amp; Murchison: “<hi rend="underline">die palaeozoischen Gesteine</hi>” ins Deutsche übertragen hat, so dürfte er hinreichend Kenntnisse der Englischen Sprache haben um die 3<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> Aufl. nach der neuesten engl. Aufl. Ihres Origins, zu revidiren;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> ich habe ihm daher auch den Antrag gemacht, vor dem mir entfernst wohnenden H<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carus, weil ich gegen die Wittwe des Uebersetzers, <hi rend="underline">Bronn</hi>, dann wieder Verpflichtungen habe und ich der Ansicht bin dass Herr Leonhard leichter sich mit uns verständigt, da er doch der familie Bronn längst befreundet ist.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Ich möchte Sie also, verehrter Herr, ersuchen mir das betreffende Material für die 3<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. deutsche Aufl. zu senden, dann haben wir Muse es jezt mit der 2<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> deutschen Aufl. zu vergleichen und die nöthigen Abänderungen zu machen.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Was die von einigen Personen gerügten Mängel an der Arbeit des H<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bronn betrifft, so glaube ich dass wesentliche Unrichtigkeiten nicht im Texte enthalten sind; denn H<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bronn hat ausser den alten Sprachen auch die bedeutendsten neuen Sprachen inne und wenn irgend Jemand so war er ganz besonders durch seine eigenen Arbeiten zu der Uebertragung Ihres Buches geeignet, da er ein ganz eminentes Wissen besass.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>In Beziehung auf Ihr anderes Werk** das Sie so freundlich waren mir in den AushängeBogen für die Uebersetzung überlassen zu wollen, so nehme ich das Offert gerne an, aber für den Augenblick wird man damit noch zuwarten müssen, bis sich der Politische Horizont abgeklärt hat. Für dieses Werk denke ich mich dann an Herrn Carus zu wenden, möchte Sie aber bitten vorerst <hi rend="doubleUnderline">mir</hi> die davon schon gedruckten Bogen (Sheets) zu senden.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Seyen Sie überzeugt dass mir selbst sehr viel daran liegt dass die Arbeit gut ausgeführt wird, denn ich lege grossen Werth darauf, dass Sie, der so freundlich uns entgegen kam, auch ganz zufrieden gestellt werden.</p>
<p>Dass Sie sich wieder wohl befinden haben wir mit vielem Vergnügen gelesen.</p>
<p>Weiteren gütigen Nachrichten sehe ich nun entgegen und bin mit grosser Hochachtung Ihr ganz ergebenster | E. Schweizerbart<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>**Domestic animals &amp; cultivated Plants &amp;c</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Geehrtester Herr Schweizerbart!</p>
<p>So geehrt ich mich auch durch das mir von <hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi> und von Ihnen geschenkte Vertrauen bezüglich einer Revision der neuen deutschen Auflage seines berühmten Werkes und der Uebersetzung eines neuen Werkes<ref target="#foot.f13"/> von diesem ausgezeichneten Naturforscher fühle, so ist es mir dennoch nicht möglich, diese Arbeit zu übernehmen. Gerade durch mein schon im vorigen Jahre beendetes Steinkohlenbuch sind mir manche andere wissenschaftlich höchst anziehende Arbeiten länger liegen geblieben, als ich verantworten kann, und diese werden mich neben den unausgesetzten ebenfalls viel Zeit in Anspruch nehmenden Arbeiten für unser Jahrbuch, für das unter meiner Direction stehende Königliche Museum und für meine Vorlesungen an der polytechnischen Schule mehrere Jahre vollauf beschäftigen.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Wiewohl ich nicht zu den <hi rend="underline">extremen</hi> Anhängern des Darwinianismus gehöre, so verfolge ich diesen wichtigen uns durch Darwin bezeichneten Weg doch mit grossem Interesse und höre nicht auf, bei meinen specielleren Arbeiten die Thatsachen mit aller Unparteilichkeit zu prüfen.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>Ich hatte mir erlaubt, Ihre Aufmerksamkeit auf Prof. Victor Carus in Leipzig an meiner Stelle zu richten und glaube noch heute, dass er gerade die geeigneteste Persönlichkeit hierzu ist, nicht allein, weil er ein grosser Verehrer der Darwin’schen Lehre ist, sondern auch, weil er nach einem mehrjährigen Aufenthalte auf der Universität Oxford, der englischen Sprache vollkommen mächtig ist und als Professor der Physiologie namentlich auch diesen Fragen näher steht, als ich es vom geologisch–palaeontologischen Standpunkte kann.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Ich verbleibe mit grösster Hochachtung</p>
<p>Ihr ganz ergebener | H. B. Geinitz <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Dresden d. 29. Apr. 1866.</p>
<p rend="left">Herrn E. Schweizerbart in Stuttgart.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                    <date>10 May 1866</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very grateful to you for your kind and prompt reply and hope you will not interpret my late response as a sign of inattentiveness.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The delay has come about for several reasons. Prof. Geinitz was approached on my behalf by Prof. Leonhard to see whether he had the time and inclination to oversee a new edition of your work and also to translate another work from your pen. He was very late in declining, which prompted me to write to him myself, but I met with no greater success.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Herr Geinitz then sent me the enclosed letter and once again recommended Prof. Carus in Leipzig.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>You will be aware from newspapers of the critical state in which we currently find ourselves in Germany, where the presumption bordering on treason of a single individual is about to plunge us into civil war as he pursues his ambitious plans contrary to all lawfulness and against the will of the entire German nation, and even allies himself with foreign nations!<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Under such circumstances, it is inevitable that business would be totally paralysed. I will therefore also restrict myself to essentials, for at the moment it would be pointless to bring out new books.</p>
<p>As you know Prof. G. Leonhard has been co-editing the “<hi rend="underline">Jahrbuch</hi>” with Herr Bronn, and he now also has to take care of the administrative side of the editing.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Since the translation is Bronn’s and checking the new edition is just a question of effort, Herr Leonhard, who has translated into German Murchison’s <hi rend="underline">Geology of Russia</hi> and also Sedgewick and Murchison’s publication: “<hi rend="underline">paleozoic rocks</hi>”, should know the English language well enough to revise the 3rd edition of your Origin in accordance with the most recent English edition.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have, therefore, made this proposal to him rather than to Herr Carus, who lives far from here, because I also have commitments to Bronn’s widow, and I expect that Herr Leonhard is more likely to come to terms with us as he has long been a friend of the Bronn family.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>So, I would respectfully ask you to send the relevant material for the 3rd German edition. We will then have the time to compare it with the 2nd German edition and to make the necessary changes.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>With regard to the shortcomings of Herr Bronn’s work, which has been criticised by a number of people, I do not think the text contains fundamental errors, as Herr Bronn is master both of the ancient languages and of the most important modern ones. If anyone was qualified through his own work to carry out the translation of your book, then it was he, for he was eminently knowledgeable.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>With regard to your other work,** of which you were so kind to offer me page proofs for translation, I am happy to accept; but for the moment we have to wait until the political situation has cleared. For this work I am thinking of approaching Herr Carus, but I would ask you first to send me the printed proofs (sheets).<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Be assured that I take a personal interest in having the work carried out properly, as it is most important to me to completely satisfy you who approached us with such kindness.</p>
<p>We have read with much pleasure that you are well again.</p>
<p>I look forward to further kind news from you and remain with the highest esteem your most devoted | E. Schweizerbart<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>** Domestic animals &amp; cultivated Plants &amp;c</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.14, Appendix I. The letter was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, head of the Stuttgart publishing firm <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 166–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref> has not been found; however, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5038.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 23 March 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Schweizerbart refers to a third German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> and to <hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi> <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2893.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav von Leonhard</ref> was co-editor with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hans Bruno Geinitz</ref> of the <hi rend="italic">Neues Jahrbuch für Mineralogie, Geologie und Palaeontologie</hi>, published by E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Victor Carus</ref>. See enclosure.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Schweizerbart refers to the measures taken by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_460.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto von Bismarck</ref> to expand Prussian influence and territory within the German lands. Many of Bismarck’s efforts were directed against Austria, the other principal power in the German confederation of states. On 9 April 1866, Prussia had formed an alliance with Italy, effective for ninety days, that committed the two states to assist each other in the event of war with Austria. On Bismarck’s diplomacy during the years leading up to the Austro-Prussian war, and the opposition to his policies by liberal political parties and the German press, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7146.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sheehan 1989</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6265.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pflanze 1990</ref>, vol. 1, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8217.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wawro 1996</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Leonhard assumed editorial responsibilities for the <hi rend="italic">Neues Jahrbuch für Mineralogie, Geognosie, Geologie und Petrefaktenkunde</hi> in 1861. He edited the journal jointly with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn</ref> until the latter’s death in July 1862, when the name of the journal was changed to <hi rend="italic">Neues Jahrbuch für Mineralogie, Geologie und Palaeontologie.</hi> Bronn was succeeded as co-editor by Geinitz in 1863. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4260.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Jubiläums-Katalog</hi></ref>, p. xvii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The first two German editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> had been translated by Bronn (Bronn trans. 1860 and Bronn trans. 1863), who had arranged for its publication by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8). Leonhard had translated Murchison and Sedgwick 1842 and Murchison <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1845 into German; both translations were also published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref> (Leonhard trans. 1844 and 1848). In the event, the third German edition was overseen by Carus (Bronn and Carus trans. 1867). The references are to Adam Sedgwick and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roderick Impey Murchison</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Bronn’s widow has not been further identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The second German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1863) was based on the third English edition, but with additional changes (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix VIII). The third German edition was based on the fourth English edition.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For criticisms of Bronn’s translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, see the letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4611.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rudolf Suchsland</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 March 1866</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">2 April 1866</ref>; see also letter from Rufolf Oldenbourg, 28 October 1866, letters from J. V. Carus, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5269.xml" resp="#automat">7 November 1866</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5279.xml" resp="#automat">15 November 1866</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5273.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. V. Carus, 10 November 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD’s letter to Schweizerbart has not been found. The reference is to proofs of <hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi> A German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>, translated by Carus, was published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref> in 1868 (Carus trans. 1868).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5038.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 23 March 1866</ref>, n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Geinitz refers to a third German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> and to <hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Geinitz refers to H. B. Geinitz ed. 1865. He was director of the Mineralogisches Museum, and professor of geology and mineralogy at the Technische Bildungsanstalt, Dresden (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_25.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ADB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">On the reception of CD’s work in Germany, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 28 January 1866</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Carus had been conservator of the comparative anatomy collection at Oxford from 1849 to 1851; in 1853 he was appointed professor of comparative anatomy at Leipzig University (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>