<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4904">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Samuel Butler   1 October 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7482</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4904 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4904.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4904.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>H. F. Jones (1919) 1: 123–4</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 13</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 106: A1–2; Butler 1923, pp. 198–201</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>106: A1–2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Butler, Samuel (b)</persName>
                <placeName>London, Clifford’s Inn, 15</placeName>
                <date when="1865-10-01">1 Oct 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Autobiographical letter describing how, when he could not conscientiously take orders, he went to New Zealand and has now returned to England to study art.</p> 
<p>Fascinated and delighted by <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></p>  
<p>and is pleased that his pamphlet [<hi rend="italic">Evidence for the resurrection of Jesus Christ</hi>] pleases CD.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Evidence for the resurrection of Jesus Christ</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">New Zealand</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Butler, Samuel (b) 1865</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">holy orders</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00003_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00003_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
        <surface n="A:1r" xml:id="i3">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00003.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00003_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00003.dzi" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="A:1v" xml:id="i4">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00004.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00004_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00004.dzi" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="A:2r" xml:id="i5">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00005.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00005_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00005.dzi" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="A:2v" xml:id="i6">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00006.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00006_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00006.dzi" width="2982px" height="5315px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>15. Clifford’s Inn E.C</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 1. 1865.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I knew you were ill and I never meant to give you the fatigue of writing to me—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Please do not trouble yourself to do so again. As you kindly ask my plans I may say that though I very probably may return to New Zealand in three or four years I have no intention of doing so before that time.</p>
<p>My <hi rend="underline">study</hi> is art,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and any thing else I may indulge in is only by play; it may cause you some little wonder that at my age I should have started as an art student, &amp; I may perhaps be permitted to explain that this was always my wish for years, that I had begun six years ago, as soon as ever I found that I could not conscientiously take orders; my father<ref target="#foot.f3"/> so strongly disapproved of the idea that I gave it up and went out to New Zealand   staid there for five years—worked like a common Servant though on a run of my own and sold out little more than a year ago thinking that prices were going to fall—which they have since done. Being then rather at a loss what to do, and my capital being all locked up, I took the opportunity to return to my old plan and have been studying for the last 12 months unremittingly— I hope that in three or four years more I shall be able to go very well by myself, and then I may go back to N.Z or no as circumstances shall seem to render advisable.</p>
<p>I must apologise for so much detail but hardly knew how to explain myself without it.</p>
<p>I always delighted in your origin of species as soon as I saw it out in N.Z—not as knowing anything whatsoever of natural history, but it enters into so many deeply interesting questions, or rather it suggests so many that it thoroughly fascinated me. I therefore feel all the greater pleasure that my pamphlet should please you however full of errors it may be.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>The first dialogue on the origin which I wrote in the Press called forth a contemptuous rejoinder from (I believe) the Bishop of Wellington—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> (please do not mention the name, though I think that at this distance of space &amp; time I might mention it to yourself)   I answered it with the enclosed which may amuse you.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I assumed another character because my dialogue was in my hearing very severely criticised by two or three whose opinion I thought worth having, and I deferred to their judgement in my next.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I do not think I should do so now. I fear you will be shocked at an appeal to the periodicals mentioned in my letter,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> but they form a very staple article of bush diet, and we used to get a good deal of superficial knowledge out of them. I feared to go in too heavy on the side of the origin because I thought that having said my say as well as I could I had better now take a less impassioned tone: but I was really exceedingly angry.</p>
<p>Please do not trouble yourself to answer this and believe me | Your’s most sincerely | S. Butler</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>To the Editor of <hi rend="underline">The Press.</hi> Sir,</p> </figure> 
<p>In two of your numbers you have already taken notice of Darwin’s theory of the origin of species; I would venture to trespass upon your space in order to criticize briefly both your notices.</p>
<p>The first is evidently the composition of a warm adherent of the theory in question; the writer overlooks all the real difficulties in the way of accepting it, and, caught by the obvious truth of much that Darwin says, has rushed to the conclusion that all is equally true. He writes with the tone of a partisan, of one deficient in scientific caution, and from the frequent repetition of the same ideas manifest in his dialogue one would be led to suspect that he was but little versed in habits of literary composition and philosophical argument. Yet he may fairly claim the merit of having written in earnest. He has treated a serious subject seriously according to his lights; and though his lights are not brilliant ones, yet he has apparently done his best to show the theory on which he is writing in its most favourable aspect. He is rash, evidently well satisfied with himself, very possibly mistaken, and just one of those persons who (without intending it) are more apt to mislead than to lead the few people that put their trust in them. A few will always follow them, for a strong faith is always more or less impressive upon persons who are too weak to have any definite and original faith of their own. The second writer, however, assumes a very different tone. His arguments to all practical intents and purposes run as follows:</p>
<p>Old fallacies are constantly recurring. Therefore Darwin’s theory is a fallacy.</p>
<p>They come again and again, like tunes in a barrel-organ. Therefore Darwin’s theory is a fallacy.</p>
<p>Hallam made a mistake, and in his <hi rend="underline">History of the Middle Ages</hi>, p. 398, he corrects himself.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Therefore Darwin’s theory is wrong.</p>
<p>Dr. Darwin in the last century said the same thing as his son or grandson says now<ref target="#foot.f10"/>—will the writer of the article refer to anything bearing on natural selection and the struggle for existence in Dr. Darwin’s work?—and a foolish nobleman said something foolish about monkeys’ tails. Therefore Darwin’s theory is wrong.</p>
<p>Giordano Bruno was burnt in the year 1600 <hi rend="smallCaps">A.D.</hi>; he was a Pantheist; therefore Darwin’s theory is wrong.</p>
<p>And finally, as a clinching argument, in one of the neighbouring settlements there is a barrel-organ which plays its psalm tunes in the middle of its jigs and waltzes. After this all lingering doubts concerning the falsehood of Darwin’s theory must be at an end, and any person of ordinary common sense must admit that the theory of development by natural selection is unwarranted by experience and reason.</p>
<p>The articles conclude with an implied statement that Darwin supposes the Polar bear to swim about catching flies for so long a period that at last it gets the fins it wishes for.</p>
<p>Now, however sceptical I may yet feel about the truth of all Darwin’s theory, I cannot sit quietly by and see him misrepresented in such a scandalously slovenly manner. What Darwin does say is that sometimes diversified and changed habits may be observed in individuals of the same species; that is, that there are eccentric animals just as there are eccentric men. He adduces a few instances and winds up by saying that “in North America the black bear was seen by Hearne swimming for hours with widely open mouth, thus catching—almost like a whale—insects in the water.” This and nothing more. (See pp. 201 and 202.)<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Because Darwin says that a bear of rather eccentric habits happened to be seen by Hearne swimming for hours and catching insects almost like a whale, your writer (with a carelessness hardly to be reprehended in sufficiently strong terms) asserts by implication that Darwin supposes the whale to be developed from the bear by the latter having had a strong desire to possess fins. This is disgraceful.</p>
<p>I can hardly be mistaken in supposing that I have quoted the passage your writer alludes to. Should I be in error, I trust he will give the reference to the place in which Darwin is guilty of the nonsense that is fathered upon him in your article.</p>
<p>It must be remembered that there have been few great inventions in physics or discoveries in science which have not been foreshadowed to a certain extent by speculators who were indeed mistaken, but were yet more or less on the right scent. Day is heralded by dawn, Apollo by Aurora, and thus it often happens that a real discovery may wear to the careless observer much the same appearance as an exploded fallacy, whereas in fact it is widely different. As much caution is due in the rejection of a theory as in the acceptation of it. The first of your writers is too hasty in accepting, the second in refusing even a candid examination.</p>
<p>Now, when <hi rend="underline">The Saturday Review</hi>, <hi rend="underline">The Cornhill Magazine</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Once a Week</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Macmillan’s Magazine</hi>, not to mention other periodicals, have either actually and completely as in the case of the first two, provisionally as in the last mentioned, given their adherence to the theory in question,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> it may be taken for granted that the arguments in its favour are sufficiently specious to have attracted the attention and approbation of a considerable number of well-educated men in England. Three months ago the theory of development by natural selection was openly supported by Professor Huxley before the British Association at Cambridge.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I am not adducing Professor Huxley’s advocacy as a proof that Darwin is right (indeed, Owen opposed him tooth and nail),<ref target="#foot.f14"/> but as a proof that there is sufficient to be said on Darwin’s side to demand more respectful attention than your last writer has thought it worth while to give it. A theory which the British Association is discussing with great care in England is not to be set down by offhand nicknames in Canterbury.</p>
<p>To those, however, who do feel an interest in the question, I would venture to give a word or two of advice. I would strongly deprecate forming a hurried opinion for or against the theory. Naturalists in Europe are canvassing the matter with the utmost diligence, and a few years must show whether they will accept the theory or no. It is plausible; that can be decided by any one. Whether it is true or no can be decided only among naturalists themselves. We are outsiders, and most of us must be content to sit on the stairs till the great men come forth and give us the benefit of their opinion.</p>
<p>I am, Sir, | Your obedient servant, | A.M.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Samuel Butler, 30 September [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Butler studied painting at the School of Art, Bloomsbury, London. From 1867 he continued his art education at Heatherley’s School of Art, Newman Street, London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1923</ref>, p. xl).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_775.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Butler</ref>. CD had known Thomas since they were both at Shrewsbury school. Thomas shared CD’s early interest in beetles and, in the summer of 1828, they collected insects at Barmouth (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. D. Fox, [30 June 1828]</ref>, and Appendix I).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Butler refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1138.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Butler] 1865</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Samuel Butler, 30 September [1865]</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Butler refers to his anonymous article ‘Darwin on the origin of species: a dialogue’, which appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Press</hi> of Christchurch, New Zealand, on 20 December 1862. CD had been sent a copy of the article anonymously and had sent it to an unidentified periodical for possible publication (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4058.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to an editor, 24 March [1863?]</ref> and n. 3). CD’s Scrapbook of reviews contains an annotated copy of the article (DAR 226.1: 131–2). The article is reprinted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1923</ref>, pp. 188–95. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5326.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles John Abraham</ref> became the first bishop of Wellington, New Zealand, in 1858. The unsigned article, ‘Barrel-organs’, a response to Butler’s article of 20 December 1862, was printed in the <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>, 17 January 1863. It is not certain that Abraham was, in fact, the author (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1923</ref>, p. 188).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The enclosure was returned to Butler (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Samuel Butler, 6 October [1865]</ref>); the letter printed in the <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>, 21 February 1863, is reproduced here.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See enclosure. Butler, writing as ‘A.M.’, ostensibly criticises both himself as the author of the original article of 20 December 1862 and the writer of the critical response of 17 January 1863. A response to this letter, signed ‘The Savoyard’ appeared on 14 March 1863. Further letters appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Press</hi> on 18 March, 11 April, and 22 June 1863, the first and last of which were signed ‘A.M.’, while the April letter was signed ““The Savoyard,” or player on Barrel-organs” (all the letters are reprinted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1923</ref>, pp. 198–207).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See the enclosure and n. 12, below, for the names of the periodicals.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3315.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hallam 1818</ref>. In the article of 17 January 1863, the author, in fact, refers to a separately published supplement which appeared after the fourth edition of the book was published (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3316.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hallam 1848</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Erasmus Darwin, CD’s grandfather, discussed transmutation in <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">King-Hele 1999</ref>, pp. 297–301, for a synopsis of the theory).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2193.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Hearne</ref> was an explorer and Canadian administrator. The observation CD cited was recorded in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hearne 1795</ref>, p. 370. In the first edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, CD had written ‘like a whale’ but changed it to ‘almost like a whale’ in the second edition. He also deleted a qualifying sentence in which he wrote, ‘I can see no difficulty in a race of bears being rendered, by natural selection, more and more aquatic in their structure and habits.’ For more on the change to this passage, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4793.xml" resp="#automat">letter from E. P. Wright, 24 March 1865</ref>, n. 6. The passage appears on page 184 in the first two editions, but on page 202 in the third edition, which appeared in April 1861 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1977</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">For publication details of the reviews of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cornhill Magazine</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Macmillan’s Magazine</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix VII. No review has been found in <hi rend="italic">Once a Week</hi>. For more on the review in <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_621.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bevington 1941</ref>, pp. 283–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> was the president of section D, zoology and botany, at the meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science held in Cambridge from 1 to 8 October 1862. He delivered an inaugural address to the section entitled ‘On the conditions and prospects of biological science’ (<hi rend="italic">Parthenon</hi> 1 (1862): 749). <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 3 October 1862, p. 7, reported that Huxley had ‘emphatically affirmed that Mr. Darwin’s work was as perfect in its logical method as it was accurate in its scientific facts’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3755.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Huxley, 9 October 1862</ref> and n. 1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> had presented a paper at the British Association meeting, ‘On the characters of the Aye-aye, as a test of the Lamarckian and Darwinian hypothesis of the transmutation and origin of species’, in which he argued against CD’s theory (R. Owen 1862; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3755.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Huxley, 9 October 1862</ref> and n. 6).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>