<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11720">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C.-F. Reinwald<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   8 October 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10485</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11720 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11720.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11720.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 108</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 108</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3970.xml">Reinwald, C.-F.</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1878-10-08">8 Oct 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi>, translated by Édouard Heckel, is published.</p>  
<p><hi rend="italic">Cross and self-fertilisation</hi> has only sold 450–500 copies.</p>  
<p><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> sells regularly; he looks forward to a cheaper edition.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cross and self-fertilisation</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Forms of flowers</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">French</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2197">Heckel, E. M.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">15, Rue des Saints-Pères | Paris</hi> Paris.</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 8. 1878</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">A Charles Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi> | Down. Beckenham | Kent</seg>
                    <salute>Cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Depuis nos lettres du 13 Octobre et du 20 Novembre, et votre honorée réponse du 21 Novembre de l’année dernière nous avons fait traduire et imprimer votre ouvrage “On different Forms of Flowers”. Mr. le Prof. Heckel, fort de votre consentement, nous a fait abandonner nos pourparlers avec M Naudin, qui ne s’était pas décidé asez promptement pour le travail de traduction.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Quoiqu’il en soit, le livre vient d’être achevé et nous vous envoyons aujourdhui un exemplaire par la Poste, en mettant, bien entendu, d’autres exemplaires à votre disposition, si vous croyez en devoir offrir quelques uns à vos amis de France ou de l’étranger.</p>
                    <p>La préface de Mr Coutance,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> que se trouve en tête de l’ouvrage, nous a été fournie par Mr. Heckel et dans la situation, où nous nous trouvions, a du être acceptée par nous sans difficulté. Nous espérons maintenant que ce volume fera son chemin comme tout ce qui sort de votre plume. Son sujet spécial rendra pourtant la vente plus lente, que celle des autres volumes; nous espérons malgré cela pouvoir vous assurer un percentage proportionné à son prix, lorsque nous aurons réussi à en vendre 700 exemplaires, qui couriront à peu près nos frais de production.</p>
                    <p>Notre édition de la <hi rend="underline">Fertilisation</hi> croisée et directe se vend également avec lenteur, car jusqu’ici nous n’avons guère placé plus de 450 à 500 exemplaires. Nous espérons cependant qu’avec la reprise des affaires, nous serons bientot à même de vous faire le versement du percentage promis pour ce volume, ainsi que pour la seconde édition des <hi rend="underline">Emotions</hi>, publiée l’année dernière.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Notre édition de l’Origine des Especes faite avec le concours de M Edmond Barbier se vend toujours assez régulièrement. Lors d’une nouvelle édition, nous croirons devoir en faire un livre plus compacte et partout moins cher, ce qui à notre avis, devrait en accélérer la circulation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> C’est du reste une question de l’avenir.</p>
<p>Veuillez bien agréer, cher Monsieur, avec nos sincères remerciments pour la confiance, dont vous voulez bien continuer à nous honorer, l’expression de nos sentiments les plus distingués | Votre très dévoués serviteurs | C Reinwald &amp; C</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">15, Rue des Saints-Pères | Paris</hi> Paris.</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 8. 1878</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">To Charles Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi> | Down. Beckenham | Kent</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>Since our letters of 13 October and of 20 November, and your honoured reply of 21 November of last year we have had your work “On different Forms of Flowers” translated and printed. Prof. Heckel having your approval, we gave up negotiations with Mr Naudin, who did not decide promptly enough for the work of the translation.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In any case, the book has just been finished and we send you today a copy by post with the understanding that other copies are at your disposal should you feel obliged to offer some to your friends from France or abroad. </p>
                    <p>The preface of M. Coutance,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> which is found at the beginning of the work, was furnished to us by Mr. Heckel and in this situation, where we found ourselves, had to be accepted by us without difficulty. We hope now that this volume will gain ground like everything that comes from your pen. Its specialised subject will however make the sale slower than that of the other volumes; we hope in spite of that to be able to assure you a percentage of the price, when we have succeeded in selling 700 copies, which will just about cover the production cost.</p>
                    <p>Our edition of cross and self <hi rend="underline">Fertilisation</hi> is also selling slowly, for up to now we have scarcely distributed more than 450 to 500 copies. We hope however that with the resumption of business, we will soon be able to pay you directly the promised percentage for this volume, as well as for the second edition of the <hi rend="underline">Emotions</hi> published last year.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Our edition of the Origin of Species made with the aid of Mr Edmond Barbier still sells regularly enough. When there is a new edition, we believe we ought to make a book more compact and much less expensive, which in our opinion would accelerate the circulation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It is moreover a question for the future.</p>
                    <p>Please accept, dear Sir, with our sincere thanks for the trust with which you continue to honour us, the assurance of our sincere regard | Your most obliged servants | C Reinwald &amp; C
                    </p>      
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. QQQQ</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Heckel trans. 1878. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11183.xml">letter from C.-F. Reinwald, 13 October 1877</ref>; the other letters have not been found. CD had agreed to a French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref> in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11242.xml">letter to Édouard Heckel, 20 November 1877</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25). Reinwald had evidently been in negotiation with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3492.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Victor Naudin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For the preface by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8369.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Amédée Coutance</ref>, see Heckel trans. 1878, pp. ix–xxxvi.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> was published in 1877 (Heckel trans. 1877); that of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> had been published in 1874, with a second edition appearing in 1877 (Pozzi and Benoît trans. 1874 and 1877).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"> The most recent French edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> was Barbier trans. 1876. The next edition was published in 1880, and was in a slightly smaller format (Barbier trans. 1880).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>