<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3929">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Isaac Anderson-Henry   20 January [1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13394</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3929 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3929.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3929.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Balfour (1882): 286;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 297</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 11: 59</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 145: 1</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>145: 1</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1863-01-20">20 Jan [1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_115.xml">Anderson-Henry, Isaac</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses hybrid strawberry–raspberry</p> 
<p>and his research on <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Suggests breeding experiments.</p> 
<p>Doubtful about Donald Beaton’s statement about <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Mentions experiments on peloric flowers.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Linum</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">peloric flowers</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Primula</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">raspberry</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">strawberry</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Pelargonium</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_345">Beaton, Donald</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Beckenham, Kent. S.E.</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1863.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I thank you cordially for your singularly kind letter.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But your kindness leads me to overrate what I have done in Natural history.— I was much surprised at the appearance of the leaf of the hybrid strawberry;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> and was much tempted to accept your kind offer and declined only on reflection, that as my health is weak and I have many other points to attend to, I feared I should have neglected your specimen. Perhaps you will be so good as to inform me whether this hybrid produces next spring <hi rend="underline">fertile</hi> seeds. If I understand right the supposed progeny from the strawberry and raspberry have not yet fruited: but if this be really a cross you will indeed have effected a prodigy, and it will be very curious if you cross <hi rend="underline">Blackberry and Raspberry</hi>;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I shall much like to hear the result. I may mention that this past spring I tried again the crosses on <hi rend="underline">Primula</hi> with the same result rather more strongly marked; and I have gone on, now for three generations breeding them what I call homomorphically, with some curious results, which I shall publish whenever I have time.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have sent a paper on <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi> to the Linnæan Society;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> when it is published I will do myself the pleasure of <hi rend="underline">sending to you a copy</hi>; and it will I should think be in good time for your experiments.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I cannot say how glad I am that you will make some experiments on the subject.</p>
<p>It does not absolutely follow in making a cross between distinct species, that the same rules would follow in the <hi rend="underline">fertility of the pollen</hi>. I hope that you will try and mark separately (excluding insects, as you know better than I do, the necessity) the <hi rend="underline">two</hi> kinds of pollen of one species on the stigma of the other; and see in making hybrids what the difference is in fertility, and in the character of the hybrid seedlings. This would be an entirely new field for observation and discovery. You will see in my paper that some species of <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi> are <hi rend="underline">not</hi> dimorphic, and are self-fertile; and so it is in some other genera.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> You refer to <hi rend="underline">L. rubrum</hi>; I am not a Botanist and have called one of the species on which I have experimented <hi rend="underline">L. grandiflorum</hi>, which is crimson and not uncommon in flower gardens; I hope I have not made a mistake in name.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>You <hi rend="underline">most</hi> kindly permit me to mention any point on which I want information. If you are so inclined, I am curious to know from systematic experiments, whether M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D. Beaton’s statement that the pollen of two shortest anthers of scarlet <hi rend="underline">Pelargonium</hi> produce dwarf plants, in comparison with plants produced from <hi rend="underline">same</hi> mother-plants by the pollen of longer stamens from same flower.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> It would aid me much in some laborious experiments on <hi rend="underline">Melastomas</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I confess I feel a little doubtful: at least I feel pretty nearly sure that I know the meaning of short stamens in most plants. This summer (for another object) I crossed Queen of Scarlet Pelargonium with pollen of <hi rend="underline">long</hi> and <hi rend="underline">short</hi> stamens of Multiflora alba, and it so turns out that plants from <hi rend="underline">short</hi>-stamens are the tallest; but I believe this to have been mere chance.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> My few crosses in Pelargonium were made to get seed from the central <hi rend="underline">peloric</hi> or regular flower (I have got one from peloric flower by pollen of peloric); and this leads me to suggest that it would be very interesting to test fertility of <hi rend="underline">peloric</hi> flowers in three ways, own peloric <hi rend="underline">pollen on peloric stigma—common pollen on peloric stigma</hi>—peloric pollen on common stigma of same species. <hi rend="underline">My object is</hi> to discover whether with change of structure of flower there is any change in fertility of pollen or of female organs. This might, also, be tested by <hi rend="underline">trying peloric and common pollen</hi> on stigma of a distinct species, and conversely.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I believe there is a <hi rend="underline">peloric</hi> and common variety of <hi rend="underline">Tropæolum</hi>; and a <hi rend="underline">peloric</hi> or upright and common variation of some species of <hi rend="underline">Gloxinia</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> And the <hi rend="underline">medial peloric</hi> flowers of Pelargonium; and probably others unknown to me.—</p>
<p>To recur to <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi>; if you cross distinct species, it would, I think be advisable to <hi rend="underline">take</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">two</hi> <hi rend="underline">dimorphic</hi> species; and <hi rend="underline">not</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">one</hi> <hi rend="underline">dimorphic</hi> and the other self-fertile. I have reason to suspect L. trigynum is dimorphic but it has not yet flowered with me.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>Your kindness has led me to trespass at unreasonable length on your time, and, | I remain dear Sir, | yours truly obliged. | Ch. Darwin.</p>
<p>P.S. I thank you for your most kind invitation, which I fear I shall never profit by.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>P.S. Have you any <hi rend="underline">quite</hi> sterile Hybrid plant with a rather large stigma, (and of which I could procure either one or both pure parent flowers) as I very much wish to compare by dissection certain minute parts of stigma: if so, and you would have great kindness to send me by Post in a little <hi rend="underline">tin</hi> box <hi rend="underline">some flowers, it would be a very great favour</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The text of the letter is taken from a copy commissioned by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> for his editions of CD’s letters; part of the letter was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref> 2: 297–8. The copyist dated the letter 20 January 1863; however, when Francis edited the transcription he added pencil brackets to indicate that the year had been added by the copyist and was not present in the original letter. The year is confirmed by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3924.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Isaac Anderson-Henry, 17 January 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-3924.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter from Isaac Anderson-Henry, 17 January 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his letter of 17 January 1863, Anderson-Henry informed CD that he had hybridised the raspberry and strawberry, resulting in ‘one brood of plants with wiry foliage some having 4 divisions in the leaf’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his letter of 17 January 1863, Anderson-Henry informed CD that this ‘coming Season’ he planned to attempt a cross between ‘the Bramble &amp; raspberry’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD first published an account of <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> in 1862 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>). CD’s subsequent experimental results on homomorphic crosses in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> (that is, crosses between plants of the same species with the same flower forms) were discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Illegitimate offspring of dimorphic and trimorphic plants’</ref>. His notes on these experiments are preserved in DAR 108, 110, and 111. CD also suggested additional <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> experiments to John Scott, encouraging him to publish the results (see, for instance, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3844.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 3 December [1862]</ref>, and Scott 1864a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref> was read before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 5 February 1863 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3920.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Bentham, 16 January 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3924.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Isaac Anderson-Henry, 17 January 1863</ref>. Anderson-Henry’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref>, p. 82 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 104).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Linum grandiflorum</hi> is the name CD used for this plant both in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref> and in <hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_345.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Donald Beaton</ref> was a regular contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>; the reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_483.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Beaton 1861</ref>, pp. 312–13. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_482.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Beaton 1860</ref>, pp. 254–5, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, letters to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, [17 May 1861] and [before 9 July 1861], and letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3149.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">14 May [1861]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">18 [May 1861]</ref>. See Appendix V for Beaton’s responses to CD in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi> in 1863.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD continued his study of the Melastomataceae, begun in 1861, in January 1863 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3901.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Hugh Falconer, 5 [and 6] January [1863]</ref> and n. 22).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD conducted a series of crosses with different varieties of <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi> in May 1862 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3592.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 8 June [1862]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3634.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 1 July [1862]</ref>). CD’s notes on these experimental crosses are preserved in DAR 51: B4–13. See also the annotated article on pelargoniums in CD’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 15 February 1862, pp. 139–40, which is in the Cory Library, Cambridge Botanic Garden.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">These experiments on regular (peloric) flowers found on the same plant with primarily irregular flowers, were discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> under the subheading ‘Monstrosities as a cause of sterility’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 167).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD also discussed the peloric <hi rend="italic">Tropaeolum</hi> with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1123.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles William Crocker</ref>, a former gardener at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3824.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C. W. Crocker, 24 November 1862</ref> and n. 4). The <hi rend="italic">Gloxinia</hi> referred to was <hi rend="italic">G. speciosa</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 365 and 2: 167). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3868.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 19 December [1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">CD discussed the crossing of dimorphic <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi> species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 81–101. See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 100, for a discussion of <hi rend="italic">L. trigynum.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Anderson-Henry invited CD to pay him a visit if he ever came to Scotland (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3924.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Isaac Anderson-Henry, 17 January 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3934.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter to John Scott of 21 January [1863]</ref>, CD stated that he wished to observe the state of the tissues of the stigma of a sterile hybrid for comparison with ‘the same in fertile parent-species’, in order to show the ‘difference in female organs of hybrid and pure species’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>