<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7811">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Henry Reeks   8 June 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10457</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7811 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7811.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7811.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 81</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 81</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3956.xml">Reeks, Henry</persName>
                <placeName>Newbury</placeName>
                <date when="1871-06-08">8 June 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Argues that coloration of eggs is a protective adaptation.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">eggs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>North End, | East Woodhay, | Newbury.</placeName>
                    <date>June 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1871</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I felt bound to write and express my sympathy for your failing health. I am sorry to say that I had been made aware of this through your published writings, but had hoped that when you had completed the laborious undertaking of the “Descent of Man” it would have greatly improved: I very much regret to hear now that such has not been the case;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I sincerely trust, however, that you may be spared to us for many, very many years to come, and enjoy the deservedly high reputation of your works and their author—</p>
<p>At the conclusion of your note you ask me “how comes it that a Fowl has white eggs”? Now if it has been indisputably proved that the <hi rend="underline">wild stock</hi> of the domestic fowl lays white eggs and <hi rend="underline">ineffectually</hi> concealed (which I really must doubt) then, and not till then, I admit it to be one of those <hi rend="underline">very few</hi> anomalous cases which <hi rend="underline">at present</hi> cannot be accounted for on your theory. With regard to the domestic fowl I see no such difficulty, for it must be borne in mind that from having been domesticated from time immemorial, man has entirely removed the influence of selection by raising chickens from any colored eggs. We must also bear in mind that a great proportion of hens’ eggs are buff-colored; resembling the eggs of many ducks that breed in similar situations, such as Œdemia, Histrionicus, &amp;c,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and no one who has hunted for these eggs as I have done can say that they are not protectively coloured. Of course I am aware of the fact of ducks covering their eggs, but they have not time to do so when disturbed suddenly.</p>
<p>The eggs of the Columbidæ appear much exposed, but then they are pretty well removed from ground enemies, and the young, as well as the adults are protectively coloured.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> They are generally extremely abundant as species, and from being graminivorous the young would, I think, at that season, when vegetation is most luxuriant, stand a better chance than the young of insectivorous or carnivorous birds.</p>
<p>Trusting that your health may greatly improve, | Believe me, dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin | Very faithfully yours | Henry Reeks. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To | C. Darwin, Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>. M.A., F.R.S. &amp;c—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter has not been found but was evidently a reply to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Reeks, 3 June 1871</ref>. Reeks refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>. CD mentioned the delay in publication caused by his ill health in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 2 n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Oedemia</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Oidemia</hi>) was the genus of scoters, which are now in the genus <hi rend="italic">Melanitta</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Histrionicus</hi> is the genus of harlequin ducks.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Columbidae is the family of pigeons and doves.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>