<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9836">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. W. Malm   31 January 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10150</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9836 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9836.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9836.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 32</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 32</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3148.xml">Malm, A. W.</persName>
                <placeName>Göteborg</placeName>
                <date when="1875-01-31">31 Jan 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends his paper.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Goteborg</placeName>
                    <date>31 Januari 1875.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">My dear Sir</seg>
                    <salute>My eminent Charles Darwin! | England.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very much obliged for your extremely kind letter of the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1874.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I never vill forget <hi rend="underline">yours</hi> testimonium for my working in the service of the science.</p>
<p>Adressated to J. E. Gray at London send I in this days another little broschure from the meeting at Kopenhague in the Year 1873. I have therei read on several cranes of Man from that so named stone-period, who, cranes I for several years toback have found hear in Bohusländ, circa 50 Engl. miles north from Göteborg.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In these paper have I especially spoken on the by me supposed using of the stone-instruments in the named period; but I have even at the pagina 2 touched that interesting fenomen by this crane, consisting, therin that the bone-masse is so extremely developed. My declaration on this fact is shortly this, that the named developement of the animal-facultes depend of that, that the Man at that time not have had artificial instruments for finer parting of the nourishments, no knife and fork.</p>
<p>For 33 years toback I was, send by the Academy of Sciences at Stockholm, 1<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> years, winter and summer, in the northest Lappland, Enare and Utsjoki; there have I learned much, living with this relative unkultivated people; and therefore my reading on the use of the stone instruments in the earlier period of the kultur of Man.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>In the named sending will You even find a paper of my Sohn on the developement of Syngnathus, d: Siphonostoma typhle Yarr. Thise paper is his first opus, d: his dissertatio pro gradu philosophico.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He is living here at Göteborg, as lector by the Realgymnasium. He has even his eyes opened for higher vues in the continuated workings of the nature; for Darwianismus! and every wher— <hi rend="underline">who eyes hat</hi>, can not se <hi rend="underline">the world</hi> from another side;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and the chambre-philosophy in Germany will in short time only exist in the—tradition.</p>
<p>Have you read my observations (printed in the “Goteborgs Kgl. Vet. och Vitt. Samhalles Handlingar, part 8, Goteborg 1863, pag. 34) on the <hi rend="underline">Scaeva ribesii</hi> <hi rend="underline">Sc. topiaria</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Sc. vitripennis</hi>, of wich the first named and of Linnéus as <hi rend="underline">Musca ribesii</hi> is on of the most common diptera in our country.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have, by my studies on diptera and especially on <hi rend="underline">Syrphica</hi>, quickly learned that a correct determinating of named “3 species” not in many cases were to bi found. By all my researches in the nature I every with data have significated all subjects. I have at least collected and preservated a <hi rend="underline">tousand</hi> specimens of thise “3 species. At least clearned it up. <hi rend="underline">Sceva</hi> <hi rend="underline">ribesii</hi> is in our period the centrum and is the <hi rend="underline">forma æstatis</hi>. Sceva vitripennis is the <hi rend="underline">forma autumnalis</hi> and therfor lesser and not so higely colorated; Scaeva topiaria is at least the <hi rend="underline">forma veris</hi>, for <hi rend="underline">the intensity of ligth</hi> mor darkly colorated than the others and as common by diptera, ex. gr. Eristalis (spec. in <hi rend="underline">temp. vernal</hi>. vigent.) with the eyes more dense hirti. Only exeptionaly Kan man find vitripennis and topiaria in the summer season.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> These facts are by my meaning of great value. But, that is thereby a common fact, that individuals, developed in dissimilar years-times, so much are diverging, that chambre-naturalist by mean of such fenomens are creating “god species”, figthing for an “illustrated name”, but not for the veracity. J’a, illustrious Darwin, when I was power to writing the english language I have many thing to tell you. My soul is from my first days open for the nature. The nature is the best book in the world, free from errata, but in many cases dificult in deschifrating, therefor, that oft are been deluded or deceived by printed books, in many cases dictated by a tradition, unknown for the scientia vera.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | A. W. Malm.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">Photograph</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 30, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9697F.xml">letter to A. W. Malm, [25 October 1874]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Malm’s paper on findings from an ancient tomb in Sweden and the use of stone tools (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8713.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. W. Malm 1874</ref>) was read at the eleventh meeting of Scandinavian naturalists in Copenhagen in 1873. He also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Edward Gray</ref>. Cranes: i.e. crania, skulls. Bohuslän is a province in south-west Sweden.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Malm worked in Finnmark, a Norwegian province that is part of Lapland, from January 1841 until September 1842 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6915.xml"><hi rend="italic">SBL</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Malm’s son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7461.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Hugo Malm</ref>, received his PhD in 1874 with a dissertation on the broadnosed pipefish (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. H. Malm 1874</ref>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6915.xml"><hi rend="italic">SBL</hi></ref> s.v. Malm, August Wilhelm). <hi rend="italic">Syphonostoma typhle</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Syngnathus typhle.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Malm alludes to the passage in Jeremiah 5:21, ‘Hear now this, O foolish people, and without understanding; which have eyes, and see not; which have ears, and hear not.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Malm’s study of the hoverflies (Syrphidae) of Scandinavia and Finland was published in <hi rend="italic">Götheborgs Kongl. Vetenskaps och Vitterhets Samhälles Handlingar</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8711.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. W. Malm 1863</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Scaeva ribesii</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Syrphus ribesii</hi>, the common banded hoverfly; the Linnaean name, <hi rend="italic">Musca ribesii</hi>, is the original combination. <hi rend="italic">Scaeva topiaria</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. vitripennis</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Syrphus vitripennis</hi>, the glass-wing hoverfly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Malm believed that the hoverfly species mentioned were only varieties of the same species, which exhibited different seasonal forms. <hi rend="italic">Forma aestatis</hi>: summer form; <hi rend="italic">forma veris</hi>: spring form; <hi rend="italic">forma autumnalis</hi>: autumn form (Latin). Ex. gr. Eristalis (spec. in temp. vernl. vigent): for example, Eristalis (species flourish in springtime). <hi rend="italic">Eristalis</hi> is another genus of hoverfly; the spring form of some common species in this genus is often darker. Both seasonal and sexual dimorphism are characteristic in many hoverfly species.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Scientia vera</hi>: true science.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>