<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3777F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. E. Darwin   23 October [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21677</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3777F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3777F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3777F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
                <relatedItem type="publication">
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 24: 456</bibl>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Cornford Family Papers (DAR 275: 9)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                        <collection>DAR</collection>
                        <idno>275: 9</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">Darwin, W. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Southampton</placeName>
                <date when="1862-10-23">23 Oct [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends observations on Lythrum. Reports bad health of Maud Atherley.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Lythrum</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Southampton</placeName>
                    <date>Oct 23—</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am sorry to hear Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Sullivan has knocked you up,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I wonder you have heart for the Lythrum. You will have got my note saying how the first L.P. Lythrum grew. I think I said the plant grew 4 or 5 y<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi> from any other<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I am not sure that it may not have been farther; the plants along the ditch were pretty nearly all solitary plants, so that any how the first L.P. Lythrum is a solitary plant compared to the plant I have last sent you. What an odd thing it is about M.P. Lythrum the pods I sent you of M.P. are all from one plant.</p>
<p>I could easily get you some more M.P<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. on Sunday, as they are as easy to distinguish as L.P<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. and at same time I could measure, if you liked, how far the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> plant of L.P was distant from any other plants; only perhaps it will be hardly fair at this time of year, as so many plants may be broken short down.  there is one funny thing about the M.P. that I set down as rubbish at the time; that in a clumps of Lythrum, I could distinguish at a distance by the general look and colour of the <hi rend="underline">pods</hi>, the M.P.; but could not distinguish the L.P. from the S.P.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I remember this both the times I have been to get pods, but have always set it down as humbug or odd chances, and so not looked carefully.</p>
<p>Poor little Maud Atherley will not live I am afraid; yesterday she was weaker than ever, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> A. told me last night, he thought he should lose her.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have not seen him yet this morning which is a bad sign   Mrs Pratt has let her rooms at last; three set of people came for them on one day, each a better offer than the other; which is always her luck she says.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Your affect son | W. E Darwin.</p>
<p>I will send the Saturday Review tomorrow, it is not much of a review, as the reviewer does not pretend to know much about it.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I do’nt want it back</p>
<p>Mr Keele has just told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fall<ref target="#foot.f8"/> that there are very little hopes of Maud, as she is lying insensible—<hi rend="underline">3.30</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. E. Darwin, 21 October [1862]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">On 21 October 1862, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bartholomew James Sulivan</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Clements Wickham</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Mellersh</ref> visited CD at Down House and stayed overnight (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). CD’s letter to William about the visit has not been found, but CD told <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref>, ‘Two days ago three officers of the Beagle came here to dinner; I took every possible precaution, but it made me very ill with violent shaking &amp; vomiting till the early morning; &amp; Could not even wish them goodbye next morning’ (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, 23 October [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. E. Darwin, 21 October [1862]</ref>, in which he described the place in which the <hi rend="italic">Lythrum</hi> with long pistils was growing.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">William was collecting seed-pods from the three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi> (purple loosestrife), namely, those with long pistils (L.P.), medium pistils (M.P.), and short pistils (S.P.); CD published his research in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_178.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maud Elizabeth Atherley</ref>, the daughter of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Atherley</ref>, William’s banking partner, was seriously ill (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. E. Darwin, 21 October [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3850.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Pratt</ref> ran a lodging house in Southampton.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> had been reviewed in <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, 18 October 1862, p. 486.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7643.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Patton Keele</ref>. Philip Carteret Fall was a partner in the Southampton and Hampshire Bank.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>