<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-983G">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">From J. F. Stephens to Robert Peel   8 June 1846</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">22029</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-983G by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-983G.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-983G.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt> 
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Add MS 40593: 187–91 Papers of Sir Robert Peel)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                        <collection>Papers of Sir Robert Peel: Add MS 40593</collection>
                        <idno>: 187–91</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4549.xml">Stephens, J. F.</persName>
                    <placeName>Kennington</placeName>
                    <date when="1846-06-08">8 June 1846</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3730.xml">Peel, Robert</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc><abstract>
                <p>Petitions for a Civil Pension.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-10-31" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2020-02-28" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2020-03-02" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2020-05-05" status="sup-footnoted">Footnoted by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2021-08-03" status="sup-reviewed">Reviewed for vol. 30 supplement by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
            <change when="2021-11-04" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>Eltham Cottage | Foxley road | Kennington</placeName>
                        <date>8 June 46.</date>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>Emboldened by the numerous signatures of men of the highest rank and talent, in Zoological science (including D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buckland, Sir W. J. Hooker, Professors Owen, Grant, Bell &amp;c, Messrs Kirby, Brown<ref target="#foot.f1"/> and others) attached to the accompanying Memorial, I beg to forward  the same for your perusal, trusting its contents may call your serious consideration to its prayer.</p>
                        <p>I have the honour to be | Sir | Your most obedient Servant | J F Stephens.</p>
                        <p>I enclose an abstract of my scientific labours</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>To the right honourable the First Lord of the Treasury.</p>
                        <p>The Memorial of James Francis Stephens; Fellow of the Linnæan Society; Member of the Entomological Societies of London, and of Paris, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>Humbly sheweth:</p>
                        <p>That he is the author of the following scientific publications, viz<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>:</p>
                        <p>Vols</p>
                        <p>General Zoology: illustrated with 362 Plates<ref target="#foot.f2"/> 			in	12</p>
                        <p>Systematic Catalogue of British Insects<ref target="#foot.f3"/>				"	  1</p>
                        <p>Illustrations of British Entomology; embellished with 400 highly finished coloured engravings<ref target="#foot.f4"/>    "	12</p>
                        <p>Nomenclature of British Insects (2 editions)<ref target="#foot.f5"/>			"	  2</p>
                        <p>Manual of British Beetles<ref target="#foot.f6"/>						"	  1</p>
                        <p>Total	<hi rend="doubleUnderline">28</hi>;</p>
                        <p>of several hundred Articles in the Encyclopædia Metropolitana,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and of a few detailed papers in sundry periodical works, and Transactions of Learned Societies.</p>
                        <p>That the work first mentioned was commenced, at an early age (19), at the instigation of the late Dr Leach<ref target="#foot.f8"/> of the British Museum, and published under the auspices of the leading Booksellers;—and that the others were undertaken upon your Memorialist’s own responsibility:—the entire costs exceeding £20,000.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="underline">That your Memorialist,</hi> not being blinded by the splendour attached to the name of the great Linnæus,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> presumed at the onset of his career to depart from the system promulgated by him; and, in the course of the 12 volumes on Ornithology, <hi rend="underline">ventured to carry out the modern</hi> continental <hi rend="underline">views, on</hi> that science, throughout <hi rend="underline">the entire Class of Birds, for the first time in Britain,</hi> and thus opened the way for their present universal adoption.</p>
                        <p>That the same feelings guided him in the production of his Catalogue of British Insects,—in which are not only recorded 10,012 species, with above 50,000 references to about 700 volumes,—but it forms an index to all previous English writers on the subject—in whose works only 3673 species are mentioned, and in the arrangement therein adopted (as more fully developed in his Illustrations, containing above 8000 descriptions) he was so eminently successful in the opinion of competent judges, as to have formed by its publication an epoch in the science of Entomology, and thus to have produced a favourable impression abroad in regard to the labours of British Naturalists in opposition to the obloquy previously cast upon them, as servile adherents of Linné; and, moreover, from the stimulus thus created, an infinity of work on Entomology, based upon the same views, has been published in this country, within these few years, and slowly his exertions have conduced materially to the national glory and benefit.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                        <p>That the celebrity of his labour, induced Professor Rennie, late of King’s College, to pirate one division thereof, and your Memorialist was compelled to resort to the Court of Chancery for protection, whereby he incurred enormous charges for Law costs, which with their concomitant losses during a period of severe domestic illness and intense disquietude, exceeded £1500, to the serious injury of your memorialist, and obliging him for several years to relinquish housekeeping.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                        <p><hi rend="underline">That your memorialist was for upwards of 38 years a Clerk in the Admiralty Office, whence he has recently been superannuated,</hi> in a reorganization thereof, <hi rend="underline">on the small pension of £225</hi> per annum:—<hi rend="underline">the proportion for 35 years</hi> only, <hi rend="doubleUnderline">thus losing 3 years</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Finally, that your Memorialist upon learning that the Trustees of the British Museum, intended to form a collection of Native Animals in the year 1816, presented to that Establishment—from his own collection—then forming with great exertions, and with unwearied assiduity and enthusiasm,—for the purpose of corroborating his views—many hundreds of specimens of British Birds, Insects and Shells,—several of which are the only examples now extant;—that he lent his gratuitous assistance for some months (with the sanction of the Admiralty Board) at the above period, towards the first arrangement thereof; has subsequently given his aid thereto; and at the present moment he fortunately possesses the means of enabling the said Trustees to publish more perfectly, a portion of the contents of this Museum by the use of some, otherwise unobtainable, works in his Library, which latter, as also his collection;—both unrivalled in extent on the subject,—the Library from the munificent present of numerous individuals—has been gratuitously thrown open for these last 25 years, during which period many thousands of students have availed themselves thereof.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="underline">Your Memorialist therefore under these circumstances, and the advantage that has accrued to his country from his scientific exertions, </hi><hi rend="doubleUnderline">as testified by the eminent men,</hi><hi rend="underline"> whose names are hereunto appended</hi>, humbly prays that your Lordship would take his case into your serious consideration, and <hi rend="doubleUnderline">obtain for him a small grant</hi><hi rend="underline"> from the Civil List</hi>, in order that he may maintain his station in society, and be enabled to carry forward his scientific pursuits, with greater benefit to his country.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                        <p>And your Memorialist, as in duty bound, will ever pray, &amp;c | J F Stephens. | Eltham Cottage, Foxley road | Kennington <lb/> <lb/></p>
                        <p rend="left">March 1846.</p>
                        <p>W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Jackson Hooker | F.RS.</p>
                        <p>W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Kirby, F.R.S</p>
                        <p>W. Spence. F.R.S.</p>
                        <p>Will<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Buckland. F.R.S.</p>
                        <p>Robert E. Grant. MD.</p>
                        <p>Charles R. Darwin. F.R.S.</p>
                        <p>Thomas Bell F.R.S. F.L.S. &amp;c | Prof<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Zool<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> King’s Coll.</p>
                        <p>Richard Owen Hunterian Professor, R<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> College of Surgeons.</p>
                        <p>Rob<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Brown V.P.L.S.—</p>
                        <p>[And 45 others]
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                
                     
                
                
                
                
                </div>
            
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_707.xml">William Buckland</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2367.xml">William Jackson Hooker</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml">Richard Owen</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1951.xml">Robert Edmond Grant</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_379.xml">Thomas Bell</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2708.xml">William Kirby</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_671.xml">Robert Brown</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">Vols. 9 to 14 (ornithology) of <hi rend="italic">General zoology</hi>, which had been started by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4319.xml">George Shaw</ref>, were by Stephens (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7140.xml">Shaw 1800–26</ref>).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7458.xml">J. F. Stephens 1829a</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7457.xml">J. F. Stephens 1828–46</ref>. CD had sent Stephens specimens and was delighted to have been cited in Stephens’s <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of British entomology</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6562.xml">‘Recollections’</ref>, p. 342).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9854.xml">J. F. Stephens 1829b</ref>; a second edition was published in 1833.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9855.xml">J. F. Stephens 1839</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9856.xml"><hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia metropolitana</hi></ref> was issued in parts between 1817 and 1845.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2850.xml">William Elford Leach</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2943.xml">Carl von Linné</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f10">Stephens commented on his efforts to update the Linnean system in the introduction to his <hi rend="italic">Systematic catalogue of British insects</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7458.xml">J. F. Stephens 1829a</ref>)</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f11">Stephens accused <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3979.xml">James Rennie</ref> of pirating his work in Rennie’s <hi rend="italic">Conspectus of the butterflies and moths found in Britain</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9857.xml">Rennie 1832</ref>). For more on the dispute between Stephens and Rennie, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref> s.v.  Stephens, James Francis.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f12">Stephens’s application for a Civil List pension was unsuccessful (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            </div>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>