<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1759">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To T. H. Huxley   3 [September 1855]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3209</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1759 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1759.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1759.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 160</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 18)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 18</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1855-09-03">3 [Sept 1855]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Approves drawing. No one who cannot draw should attempt to be a naturalist. Suggests corrections to [<hi rend="italic">Lepas</hi>?] drawing. Comments on position of ganglia, cement glands, and stomach.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Huxley</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I think your Diagrams will do very well.— What an advantage to be able to sketch easily! no one has a right to attempt to be a naturalist who cannot.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have made a few pencil marks— The chief correction is the position of the great ganglion, which ought to be more to left-hand.— I never c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. see cement-gland in Lepas, though I traced cement-duct some way up peduncle; but from the analogy of 4 other genera its most probable position is where I have put cross.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I think the stomach ought to be larger, though of course there is some variability in its size according to its contents &amp;c. in same species.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | C. Darwin  [DIAGRAM HERE] The <hi rend="underline">lower</hi> end of œsophagus rather more bell-shaped; more medial; whole upper end of stomach broader, as I have put it: cæca arise where bell-end of oesophagus joins the stomach— Put the Cement gland (see my Pl. IX fig 3) <hi rend="underline">here</hi>: &amp; let the ovarian tubes &amp; cæca branch out &amp; fill the whole peduncle.— In Peduncle there ought to be transverse &amp; oblique muscles It w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be more strictly correct, but really does not signify on this scale, if the antennæ were put a little more to left. ie not quite medial, or not at basal point of peduncle. [DIAGRAM HERE] The main sub-œsophageal ganglion ought to be more to left, where I have put pencil cross— The whole stomach ought to be larger &amp; I think this w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> also make your drawing plainer: you had better not have put in cæca, as their presence is evidently of very little importance. The arborescent testes ought to extend posteriorly over whole stomach, but perhaps you purposely leave them out to prevent confusion.— You had better draw two thin reddish-brown lines from the ovaria to within the Antennæ.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 gland] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘du’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.3 whole] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">7.3 not at] ‘not’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">7.3 basal point] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘apex’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">9.1 &amp; I … plainer 9.2] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is based on annotations on related drawings among the Huxley papers indicating that Huxley collected specimens and prepared drawings of marine invertebrates, probably for use in his natural history lectures at the Government School of Mines, during his stay in Tenby in August and September 1855. Huxley had given his first series of twenty-four lectures commencing in November 1854. The 1855–6 series was extended to fifty lectures and, according to an announcement in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 16 February 1856, commenced on 20 February 1856. Some of the diagrams prepared at Tenby in 1855 appeared in the published versions of these lectures (printed in the <hi rend="italic">Medical Times and Gazette</hi> during 1856 and 1857), and the cirripede drawings accompanying this letter were used in the published lecture on the Cirripedia (see n. 4, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Julian Huxley wrote of his grandfather: ‘Huxley was a great scientist and a great man of letters; if he had had time and opportunity he would have been a great artist as well.’ (J. S. Huxley ed. 1935, p. 5). On Huxley’s skill as an illustrator, see Newth and Turlington 1956.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 29 [September 1855]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The published versions of the <hi rend="italic">Lepas</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi> drawings (T. H. Huxley 1857) show that Huxley made the revisions suggested by CD.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>