<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11054">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   14 July 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10710</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11054 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11054.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11054.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 107</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 107</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1877-07-14">14 July 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for permission to print ["Sketch of an infant"] in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses children’s ability to distinguish colours.</p>
            <p>Describes disagreements among German supporters of CD. Discusses reaction of German protestants to Darwinism.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Kosmos</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">German protestants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin | Friedenstrasse 10. I.</placeName>
                    <date>den 14. 7. 77.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ihr gütiges Schreiben vom 30 Juni ist sehr verspaetet in meinen Besitz gelangt, weil es die Verlags-Buchhandlung nicht sofort expedirt hatte. Ich danke Ihnen tausendmal für Ihre freundliche Mittheilung hinsichtlich der Farbentheorie, sowie für die Erlaubniss die “biographische Skizze” im Kosmos abdrucken zu duerfen. Ich werde mir erlauben, Ihre hoechst merkwürdige Beobachtung ueber die Schwierigkeit der Farben unterscheidung fuer Kinder am Schlusse hinzuzufügen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Diese Thatsachen sprechen allerdings fast zu Gunsten der Geiger–Gladstone’schen Auffassung.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Dennoch kann ich mich nicht entschliessen derselben beizustimmen. Auch Herr Professor Jaeger<ref target="#foot.f4"/> schreibt mir, dass er den Geiger’schen Aufstellungen kein Gewicht beimessen könne, und der berühmte Aegyptologe Professor Duemichen<ref target="#foot.f5"/> in Strassburg, den ich um sein Urtheil bat, ob in den <hi rend="underline">allerältesten</hi> aegyptischen Gemälden die Farben der Natur, wie wir sie heute sehen, entsprechend angewendet worden seien, antwortete mir: sie seien es. Gleichwohl muss ich gestehen dass ein definitives Urtheil in dieser Frage recht schwierig ist, wenn ich auch zunächst entschieden auf meinem Standpunkte beharre.</p>
<p>Was die Artikel des Kosmos betrifft, so hoffe ich dass wir allmälig von der blossen unfruchtbaren Speculation zu mehr praktischen unmittelbareren Diskussionen gelangen werden, und mein ganzes Bestreben ist dahin gerichtet, diese rein philosophischen Discussionen auf ein geringeres Maass zu beschraenken, und dagegen die Beobachtungs-Resultate zu begünstigen. Leider ist die Spaltung der Unterparteien sehr gross. Herr Prof. Wagner will nichts anderes als die Migrations-Theorie gelten lassen; Herr Pr. Carl Vogt findet nichts anderes studirenswerth als die Microcephalen, Prof. Semper schwärmt für die Anneliden-Verwandschaft der Wirbelthiere, und Alle befehden sich gegenseitig statt einander in die Hände zu arbeiten.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Sehr merklich mindert sich dagegen bei uns die Opposition der Geistlichkeit gegen die neue Weltanschauung; die Anhänger des sogenannten Protestanten-Vereins haben bereits wiederholt auf ihren Versammlungen sich mit dem Darwinismus beschaeftigt, und gefunden, dass er gar nicht so unvereinbar mit Religion und Sitte sei, als man geglaubt hatte.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Langsam aber unwiderstehlich vollzieht sich die Revolution der Geister.</p>
<p>Ich bitte Sie, nicht ungehalten zu sein dass ich Sie mit so allgemeinen Bemerkungen aufhalte und zeichne</p>
<p>Mit herzlicher Verehrung | Ihr | treulich ergebener | Ernst Krause.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin | Friedenstrasse 10. I.</placeName>
                    <date>14. 7. 77.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>Your kind reply of 30 June has come into my possession after a great delay, for the publisher did not send it on straight away. I thank you a thousand times for your kind communication regarding the theory of colour, as well as for permission to print the “biographische Skizze” in Kosmos. I will take the liberty of adding at the end your most remarkable observation on the difficulty in colour differentiation for children.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>These facts certainly support the Geiger–Gladstonean proposition.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Nonetheless I cannot make up my mind to agree with the latter. Professor Jaeger<ref target="#foot.f4"/> also writes me that he cannot attach any weight to the Geiger proposition, and the famous Egyptologist Professor Duemichen<ref target="#foot.f5"/> in Strasburg, whom I asked for his opinion whether in the <hi rend="underline">most ancient</hi> Egyptian paintings colours were used as we see them today, replied that indeed they were. Nevertheless I must confess that it is rather difficult to settle this problem, even if for the time being I decidedly insist on my point of view.</p>
<p>Regarding the articles in Kosmos, I hope that we will gradually progress from fruitless speculation to more practical concrete discussions, and my whole aim is directed at confining these purely philosophical discussions to a minimum, and furthering, on the other hand, observational results. Sadly the division among the parties is very great. Prof. Wagner will not consider anything other than the theory of migration; Pr. Carl Vogt deems nothing worthy of study but microcephaly, Prof. Semper enthuses about the annelid affinity to vertebrates, and all of them are feuding with one another instead of working hand in hand.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>On the other hand, the opposition of the clergy over here to the new world-view is dwindling noticeably; the followers of the so-called Protestanten-Verein have already debated Darwinism at their meetings several times, and they found it not at all as irreconcilable with religion and morals as had been believed.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Slowly but irresistibly a revolution of minds is taking place.</p>
<p>I ask you not to be displeased with me for detaining you with such general remarks and remain With cordial respect | Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Krause.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Krause</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11023.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">30 June 1877</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">11 July [1877]</ref>. A German translation of CD’s <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Biographical sketch of an infant’</ref>, with the additional note from the letter of 30 June on colour perception, appeared in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> 1 (1877): 367–76.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1883.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Ewart Gladstone</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1835.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lazarus Geiger</ref> both claimed that speakers of ancient languages did not name colours as precisely and consistently as speakers of modern European languages, and hypothesised that there was a universal evolutionary sequence in which colour vocabulary evolved in tandem with the senses (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9544.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gladstone 1858</ref>, 3: 457–96, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9545.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geiger 1871</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Jäger</ref> published an article on colour perception, ‘Einiges über Farben und Farbensinn’, in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> 1 (1877): 486–95.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johannes Dümichen</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moritz Wagner</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Vogt</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4291.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Gottfried Semper</ref> were German Darwinists (see Wagner 1868, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vogt 1867</ref>, and Semper 1874.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The Protestantenverein was a German liberal religious organisation founded in 1863 with the aim of unifying the German Protestant churches and promoting change in harmony with secular culture and on the basis of Christianity (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>). For a discussion of Darwinism in the <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch des Deutschen Protestanten-Vereins</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9546.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zittel 1871</ref>. For more on the reception of Darwinism in Germany, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5550.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. M. Montgomery 1988</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>