<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3258">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. C. Watson   20 September 1861</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6178A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3258 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3258.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3258.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 39</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 39</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4975.xml">Watson, H. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Thames Ditton</placeName>
                <date when="1861-09-20">20 Sept 1861</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> experiments of J. Sidebotham; HCW’s distrust of the results [see J. Sidebotham, "Specific identity of the cowslip and the primrose", <hi rend="italic">Phytologist</hi> 3 (1849): 703–5].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cowslip</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Primula</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Phytologist</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Sidebotham, Joseph 1849</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Thames Ditton S.W.</placeName>
                    <date>Sept 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 61</date>
                    <salute>Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have some recollection of intimating a distrust of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Sidebotham’s recorded experiments on Primroses, &amp;c. though I cannot now hit upon the intimation.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> However, I find his two papers in Phytol<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.   The first (Vol. 2, p. 887)<ref target="#foot.f2"/> is of no moment, except as calling forth a P.S. mem. by Newman or Luxford, to the effect that the Primula Jacquinii—(Bardfield oxlip) comes true from seed in second &amp; third generations.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have again looked over his second paper, &amp; am still unwilling to rely on his accuracy;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; likely enough the objections which I should now make to the record, are such as were made before, &amp; fell under your notice.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">First</hi>, I do not believe that he had botanical skill or experience adequate to name his var<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. &amp; species correctly; especially, as to distinguishing P. Jacquinii from Cowslip &amp; umbellate Primrose.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Second</hi>— He states a result which no one else has hitherto shown; namely, that P. Jacquinii produced Primroses, &amp; a Cowslip produced P. Jacquinii. That these (unusual, at least) results should <hi rend="underline">both</hi> have come out at <hi rend="underline">same time</hi> from <hi rend="underline">single</hi> experiments, seems in the highest degree unlikely. I have tried P. Jacquinii for (I think) 16 descents and never got a primrose from it; nor has <hi rend="underline">it</hi> ever sprung from seed of Cowslip or Primrose during 20 years of observation &amp; experiment. I prefer to think either that he misnamed the plants, or mingled seed by some chance.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Third</hi>— He writes that in order “to prevent all errors as much as possible, I collected the seed myself, and again sowed it on beds, where no Primulæ had been previously grown”. He does not tell us whether these beds were near or wide apart, so that dew-worms &amp;c. could not carry a seed from one to another. Nor does he show that any precaution was taken to prevent the seeds of Oxlips, primroses, cowslips (already in the garden) from being chance-mingled in the soil of those beds. The experimenter who thinks that “all errors as much as possible” are guarded against by the course he describes, must have very imperfect notion of the precautions which <hi rend="underline">are</hi> necessary in such experiments. Had he been operating with exotic plants, never before grown in the garden, he might have assumed absence of seeds other than those purposely sown on his “beds”.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Fourthly</hi>— There are other instances, which show that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. S. is unreliable in his botanical statements; i.e. he hazards statements in print, which are not true; although I think from carelessness &amp; imperfect knowledge, rather than mala fides (Phytol. III, p. 144— Cybele Brit. II p. 168.)<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>It is for yourself to decide how far I am warranted in distrust on such grounds.</p>
<p>In the paper to which you refer,—Phytol. III, p. 703–5,—M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sidebotham says nothing about “artificial fertilization”. He simply writes, “to prevent any hybridization from the visits of insects, I protected them” (the oxlips, cowslips, primroses) “with glass during the early part of their flowering” (p. 704).</p>
<p>Cowslips, primroses, &amp; polyanthuses are so usually grown, &amp; have been so long grown in gardens, that we should never feel sure of their seeds not being in the ground, unless under some special cir˜ces. My own course has been, for particular experiments, to sow the seeds in flower pots, filled with mould from asparagus beds, or peat-earth dug where no Primula can be found. I dare not trust to the ordinary earth of the garden; for I see Primulæ spring up among potatoes, &amp; other unlikely crops.</p>
<p>The asparagus beds, here very carefully kept weeded, &amp; invariably forked over in spring, are extremely unlikely to have Primula seeds in them. Still, a chance seed <hi rend="underline">might</hi> be brought to them on a tool, blown thither by wind, perhaps even come in the old horse-litter used as a manure dressing. Thus if I sowed primrose-seed in a flower-pot filled from an asparagus bed, &amp; got 49 primroses &amp; one cowslip, I should distrust my own experiment. But when I sow the seeds of an intermediate form in such soil, &amp; find <hi rend="underline">several</hi> primroses, <hi rend="underline">several</hi> cowslips, &amp; <hi rend="underline">several</hi> intermediates, &amp; look in vain for a primula on the Asparagus bed,—then I rely on the results. This result, I believe, is the only one that we can yet rely upon; namely, that an intermediate form can produce cowslips, primroses, &amp; intermediates; vice versa cowslips &amp; primroses can each produce the intermediates. As yet, distrust all else.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I hope that some benefit was found from your stay at Torquay. I have just returned from a few weeks of indolence in the Isle of Wight, &amp; the better for it.—</p>
<p>Believe me, always very truly | Hewett C. Watson <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">C. Darwin | Esqre</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had apparently written to Watson inquiring about the reliability of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Sidebotham’s</ref> experiments on <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>. Watson’s ‘intimation’ has not been traced, although he had criticised Sidebotham on a different topic, accusing him of making ‘mis-statements’ that he said were attributable to an ‘intellectual rather than moral deficiency’ (see <hi rend="italic">Phytologist</hi> 3 (1848): 145).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Sidebotham 1847.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The editorial comment reads: ‘We have lately had an opportunity of observing seedlings produced in the second and third generation from Primula Jacquinii (<hi rend="italic">Newm.</hi>) or Jacquin’s Primula, and find that they are in all respects identical with the parent plant. We again express a hope that the names of <hi rend="italic">elatior</hi> and <hi rend="italic">oxlip</hi> will not be applied to this species.’ <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3513.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Newman</ref> was the general editor of the <hi rend="italic">Phytologist</hi>, while <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3049.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Luxford</ref> was the managing editor and a frequent contributor of articles (see <hi rend="italic">Phytologist</hi> 1 (1844): v–vi).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7178.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sidebotham 1849</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See n. 4, above, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Watson 1847–59</ref>, 2: 168.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD referred to Sidebotham’s work in the notes to his paper ‘On the two forms, or dimorphic condition, in the species of <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>, and on their remarkable sexual relations’, read before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> of London on 21 November 1861 (<hi rend="italic">Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society (Botany)</hi> 6 (1862): 77–96; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 45–63). Discussing the question whether the primrose (<hi rend="italic">Primula vulgaris</hi>), the cowslip (<hi rend="italic">P. veris</hi>), and the oxlip (<hi rend="italic">P. elatior</hi>) were distinct species or only varieties of one species, CD stated his belief that oxlips were produced by cross-fertilisation between primroses and cowslips. In a note, he made reference to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7178.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sidebotham 1849</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 63 n. 6): <quote type="quote"> Mr. Sidebotham (Phytologist, vol. iii. pp. 703–5) states that he protected his plants from crossing; but as he gives in detail all the precautions which he took, and says nothing about artificial fertilization, we may conclude that he did not fertilize his plants. As he raised very numerous seedlings, he would have had to fertilize many flowers, if they had been really well guarded against the visits of insects. Hence I conclude that his results are not worthy of trust. </quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>