<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7030">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   21 December 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14801</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7030 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7030.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7030.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 85: A106–6a</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>85: A106–6a</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>R. Bot. Gard., Calcutta</placeName>
                <date when="1869-12-21">21 Dec 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Observations on expression and variation in Asian peoples: when colour of beard and hair differ, beard is always lighter. Differences in swimming strokes. Polydactylism.</p> 
<p>Has just sent Hooker a paper on Sikkim tree-ferns [<hi rend="italic">Trans. Linn. Soc. Lond.</hi> 30 (1875): 1–44, read 1870].</p> 
            <p>Has had fever since the end of the rains.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">tree-ferns</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Asian peoples</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Trans. Linn. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2357">Hooker, J. D.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Sikkim</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Scott, John 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00216_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5392px" height="7759px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00216_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5392px" height="7759px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="A106r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00216.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5392px" height="7759px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00216_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5392px" height="7759px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00216.dzi" width="5392px" height="7759px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="A106v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00217.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5278px" height="7651px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00217_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5278px" height="7651px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00217.dzi" width="5278px" height="7651px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="A106ar">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00218.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5294px" height="7759px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00218_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5294px" height="7759px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00218.dzi" width="5294px" height="7759px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="A106av">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00219.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5240px" height="7749px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00219_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5240px" height="7749px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00219.dzi" width="5240px" height="7749px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Royal Botanic Gardens | Calcutta</placeName>
                    <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> /69</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I often think on subjects, material I may have collected information likely to interest you, but I get together even in India so slowly little scraps that I am long in getting sufficient to fill a sheet or so. I was indeed very much pleased to find that my observations on expressions were valued of you.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I do not think I have anything noteworthy to add to them … I have particularly observed, since I heard from you, the colour of hair and beard, and invariably seen that when they do differ the former is of the darker shade.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> (<hi rend="underline">beard always lighter coloured</hi> <hi rend="underline">than the hair</hi>) I have indeed seen it somewhat marked in the thinly bearded Lepchas and Mechis of Sikkim: the <hi rend="underline">Bhotea</hi> also show it as do many Burmese and Chinamen—all of which have very little hair in general on the face.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I have frequently thought—though you are in all probability already familiar—that the native mode of swimming might interest you: the action is so known, by that of the lower animals. It is different of course with some of the sea-faring races as the Burmese and Malays who have been much in contact with Europeans. I refer only to those races who have come little in contact with Europeans. The Santhals, or Dhangars of Nagpore illustrate it well,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> as do also the generality of the country nurtured Bengalee and various other Indian races. These in the act of swimming pose the body at a high angle (<hi rend="underline">nearly</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">45<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> </hi>) in the water, throw the head slightly backward so that the water level is in a line with the middle of the chin base of the ears and nape of neck; thus strikingly different from the Europeans. Again the progressive action is simply “pawing”, the manner of short, quick, alternate, almost vertical strokes, with slightly bent or curved hands, the motion of feet spurring, the right limb being drawn forward and struck out again with the stroke of the left hand and so on alternately in a <hi rend="underline">somewhat</hi> <hi rend="underline">devious</hi> <hi rend="underline">course</hi> with opposing limbs and arms. I was oft struck with their truly animal like mode of progression and frequently thought of mentioning it to you. Lately however, I had the opporunity of seeing one of our big Hanuman monkeys<ref target="#foot.f5"/> fall accidentally from a tree into one of our garden tanks in making a long spring. After composing himself somewhat his movements resembled very strikingly indeed those which I have above described: this has induced me to bring it to your notice.</p>
<p>I have often thought also of monkey like mode natives here generally adopt in carrying their children. It is striking to see the youngest infants tied astride the mothers hip with its slender arms athwart her body. Truly they need to have but a slight elongation of the latter so that they might clasp the body to complete the comparison.</p>
<p>I shall now add a few notes on a different subject which I have thought might interest you. <hi rend="underline">Polydactylism</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/>   This occurs in several native families, from whom I have had the following <hi rend="italic">[</hi>records<hi rend="italic">]</hi>. In the first case is a family of two sons and a daughter, of whom the latter and one of the former had six digits; the supernumerary being a finger attached to the metacarpal bone on the outer margin of the hand. The feet had the ordinary number of digits in the feet. In this case the grandfathers brother had six digits on one hand. Both brothers and sister were married but none of their children have inherited this peculiarity.</p>
<p>Another case is of a man with six digits on one foot (supernumerary on outer margin) the left, while this man’s <hi rend="underline">grandfather</hi> had a sixth on the right foot. It has appeared in none of the other members of their families. A third had six fingers (very perfectly developed) on both hands, as had also a brother and uncle—but none of their descendants, which are as yet however confined to a single generation. A fourth family had a supernumary thumb (perfectly developed) supported on the metacarpal bone, and this <hi rend="underline">man’s</hi> <hi rend="underline">grandson</hi> (an infant of 10 months) has also six digits but in this case a finger on the outer margin of the left hand.— I have also to note a Bengale〈e〉 family which for three generations have had all its members strongly prognathic. The present family consists of three male and two female children all of whom present the peculiarity and which has been inherited from the father and grandfather. I have seen all the present male members of the family and found in each with the upper maxillary bone projecting considerably more than lower with exceedingly large though equably developed teeth: the canine are same plane and not longer than the others; <hi rend="underline">previously</hi> to <hi rend="underline">seeing</hi> the <hi rend="underline">family</hi> <hi rend="underline">I had been told that they</hi> <hi rend="underline">projected</hi> and <hi rend="underline">were much longer</hi>.</p>
<p>I do not think that I have anything further worth communicating (if indeed what I have already written is) I have been much bothered with fever and ague since the close of the rains and have really been little able for work of any sort. I am now however I think fairly clear of them—I have just sent to Dr. Hooker a paper on the tree-ferns of Sikkim in which I treat of their distribution, economic uses, structures of caudex, and relations with the higher plants and a few other peculiarities with descriptions and figures of the species—also a number of plates illustrations of their structure. Dr. Hooker promises to look it over for me and if it proves worthy he will communicate it to the Linnean.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I am just commencing a book on Indian Horticulture, in which I devote a chapter to acclimatization.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I am Dear Sir | Yours respectfully | John Scott.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I often … them … 1.5] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.5 I have] <hi rend="italic">opening square bracket added, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.7 (<hi rend="italic">beard</hi> … <hi rend="italic">hair</hi>) 1.7] <hi rend="italic">two crosses in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>1.7 (<hi rend="italic">beard</hi> … face. 1.10] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.1 I … comparison. 3.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 I shall … peculiarity. 4.8] ‘Supernumerary Digit’ <hi rend="italic">margin, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.8 I have … acclimatization 6.10] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘J. Scott’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For previous communication between Scott and CD on human expression, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 4 May 1868</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6226F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 3 June 1868</ref>. Scott sent further observations in his letter of 2 July 1869.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6815.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 2 July 1869</ref> and n. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD included Scott’s information on the beard and hair colour of ‘two races in Sikhim, the Bhoteas, Hindoos, Burmese, and Chinese’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 319. On the Mechi, or Mech, and Lepcha people, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6815.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 2 July 1869</ref> and nn. 4 and 6. The Bhutia are a Himalayan people who migrated southward from Tibet, settling in Bhutan and India, particularly in Sikkim (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Santals, or Santhals, were a large group of people in eastern India; they now constitute one of the largest tribal communities in the country. The Dhangar people are based in Maharashtra state, which now includes the city of Nagpur in central India; in 1861 the Nagpur province of British India was merged into the Central Provinces. (<hi rend="italic">EB.</hi>)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Scott refers to the Hanuman langur (<hi rend="italic">Semnopithecus entellus</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD discussed polydactylism in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 12–17.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>. ‘Notes on the tree ferns of British Sikkim, with descriptions of three new species, and a few supplemental remarks on their relations to palms and cycads’ (Scott 1870) was read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> of London on 17 February 1870 by John Anderson.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD and Scott previously corresponded on the acclimatisation of plants; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 15 and 16, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Scott 1868</ref>. Scott never completed the book.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>