<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. A. Darwin   14 November 1822</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6002</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">Cambridge 52</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 3</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 3</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Darwin, E. A.</persName>
                <placeName>[Cambridge]</placeName>
                <date when="1822-11-14">14 Nov 1822</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>EAD wants changes made and shelves built to improve the laboratory at the Mount [Darwin residence]; sends drawings and will bring chemical instruments, a book, and his record of experiments done in his chemistry course.</p>
            <p>He has now been matriculated.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Darwin residence</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">laboratory</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Mount</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">names and references (used here only of references)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">matriculation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Cambridge]</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1822.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Bobby.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am going to honour you again by writing, &amp; first of all, I think it would be an improvement in the Lab:<ref target="#foot.f1"/> to have some more shelves fixed up. The places I have thought of are, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. a shelf to go over the window</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAGRAM HERE] I have drawn a picture of what I mean, &amp; have put some bottles on the shelf to ornament it.</p> </figure> 
<p>It is to extend from wall to wall, so that the shelf of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> lamp &amp; also of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> cork bottles must come down NB. the little shelf for y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> test glasses may stay up, &amp; if it is possible, let there be one over the door, so as to be a continuation of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> one over the fire place, &amp; if that takes place, the little shelf on which the pounded marble &amp;c is, must also come down, but the little ones above may stay up. Perhaps the shelf over the window had better not be more than a foot wide, otherwise I shall be knocking my head against it.— Get it done as soon as you conveniently can, &amp; pay for it, &amp; I will then have the remainder of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> cow<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAGRAM HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>sent up to me, &amp; I will spend it in chemical instruments.— I have ordered a small goniometer (an instrument to measure angles) so that we shall be able to seperate the different crystalls in your cab: I have not yet procured any of the minerals you mentioned. Hensleigh has promised me a bit of asphaltum which he obtained at Teignmouth. I dont think you have any, it is a kind of bitumen very light, will burn, &amp; is of a snuff colour.—</p>
<p>I have bought a book which will be very useful. there are directions for finding out the names of minerals &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp; the rules are not very difficult.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I dare say I shall be able obtain some specimens of rocks for you, for Professor Sedgwick<ref target="#foot.f4"/> said that at the Gog Magog hills (about 4 miles distant) there were a vast number of specimens, which I shall certainly some day go &amp; explore.— I am attending Professor Cumming’s<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Lectures on Chemistry which are very entertaining. I have written all his experiments down as far as we have proceded, which we shall be able to try over again This is y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> shape of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Lecture Room</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAGRAM HERE] aa the seats c.c. 2 large tables b. y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Lecturer dddd, a long place like a blacksmith chimney, under wh: are furnaces &amp;c G. a private room.—</p> </figure> 
<p>He has 3 men to assist him so that we get over a good deal of ground in an hour. he lectures every day, all this term. I think my <hi rend="underline">vacation</hi> &amp; your <hi rend="underline">holidays</hi> will about fit, as my term divided, a few days ago i.e. half the term is over.—</p>
<p>I have just been to chapel, in wh: respect we are better off than you, as we are only obliged to attend 7 times a week. Some evenings preceding St<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> days we go to Chapel in surplices, wh: look for all the world like sheets, &amp; indeed one man of St Johns went, for a wager, into chapel dressed in a sheet, &amp; sat before the master without being discovered. I was yesterday matriculated, in wh: you swear that you will not do this &amp; that, wh: one does every day, you swear you wont wear a hat, wont ride, wont play at cricket &amp;c before 12 o clock &amp; half a hundred other things.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> They have affixed a notice, that if you submit yourself humbly after any offence they wont consider you guilty of perjury. I suppose you have heard of black Frank Lightons<ref target="#foot.f7"/> being rusticated. When he came up his Tutor asked him, why he had not read the things he was desired; he answered “why to be frank with you, one gentleman should be frank to another, in the first part of the vacation I was at some very pleasant places and it was impossible quite impossible, you know to read; &amp; in the last, what with shooting &amp; hunting it was impossible”— “Then perhaps M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Leighton it wont be impossible for you to go down to the country” replied the Tutor, &amp; so down he went.</p>
<p>Give my love to Massie, Pearson, J Lawson,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; all others. I remain your affectionate brother | E. Darwin. *S 2</p>
<p rend="left">Thursday. 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In the <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi></ref>, pp. 45–6, CD wrote: ‘Towards the close of my school life, my brother worked hard at chemistry and made a fair laboratory with proper apparatus in the tool-house in the garden, and I was allowed to aid him as a servant in most of his experiments. He made all the gases and many compounds, and I read with care several books on chemistry, such as Henry [<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3527.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry 1810</ref>] and Parkes’s <hi rend="italic">Chemical Catechism</hi> [<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Parkes 1806</ref>]. The subject interested me greatly, and we often used to go on working till rather late at night. This was the best part of my education at school’. CD’s tutelage in chemistry lasted from 1822 to October 1825, when the brothers entered Edinburgh University.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Apparently a reference to a fund set aside for laboratory expenses. On the cover of the letter, perhaps in CD’s hand, is written: 
<figure type="inlinediagram"> 
<p>5. 2. 6 44. 17. 6 2 6.</p> </figure></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Possibly <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1816</ref>. The <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6284.xml">third edition (1823)</ref> is preserved in CD’s library at Down House.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4276.xml">Adam Sedgwick</ref>, Woodwardian Professor of Geology.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1151.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Cumming</ref>, Professor of Chemistry.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">By signing the matriculation book undergraduates swore to observe the laws, statutes, and privileges of the University. It is the statutes, many of which were obsolete, to which Erasmus refers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2879.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Leighton</ref> of Shrewsbury, admitted pensioner at Trinity College, Cambridge in 1821 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_144.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Alum. Cantab.</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Massie</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3722.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Pearson</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lawson</ref> were schoolfellows of Erasmus and CD at Shrewsbury School (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7166.xml"><hi rend="italic">Shrewsbury School Register</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>