<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8246">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Gaston de Saporta<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   18 March 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10622</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8246 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8246.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8246.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 32</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 32</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4181.xml">Saporta, L. C. J. G. de</persName>
                <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                <date when="1872-03-18">18 Mar 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD insists too strongly, in <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>, on man’s origin from a simian ancestor, rather than some other primate.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">primate</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">simian ancestor</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-01-14" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-01-14" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-01-14" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00125_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00125_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="32:1r" xml:id="i125">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00125.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00125_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00125.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:1v" xml:id="i126">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00126.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00126_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00126.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:2r" xml:id="i127">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00127.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00127_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00127.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:2v" xml:id="i128">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00128.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00128_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00128.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:3r" xml:id="i129">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00129.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00129_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00129.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:3v" xml:id="i130">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00130.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00130_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00130.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:4r" xml:id="i131">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00131.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00131_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00131.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="32:4v" xml:id="i132">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00132.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00132_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00132.dzi" width="5832px" height="7746px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                    <date>le 18 mars 1872</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai attendu pour venir vous remercier de l’obligeant envoi de votre livre <hi rend="underline">sur la descendance de l’homme</hi> d’avoir achevé de le lire une première fois, sans à y revenir un peu plus tard, car vos ouvrages demandent d’être relus, si l’on veut bien saisir l’enchaînement de vos idées.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Il y a cette fois des parties, dans votre travail, qui m’ont frappé particulièrement, tout ce qui est philosophique, surtout l’exposition des phénomènes moraux et intellectuels chez l’homme et chez les animaux, les relations et les passages de la pensée à l’instinct, la génération de la conscience etc.— Vous avez déployé dans l’examen de ces questions difficiles et des plus complexes une puissance d’analyse des plus rares, et j’ai pu souvent, en faisant des retours sur moi-même me convaincre de la vérité de vos déductions. Je suis entièrement de votre avis lorsque vous insistez sur la place incontestable de l’homme comme faisant partie intégrante des mammifères. Les liens intimes qui rattachent l’homme à cette classe sont tellement peu susceptibles d’être méconnus que la démonstration même en paraît singulière, et que l’on conçoit à peine que l’on soit dans le cas de le démontrer à des naturalistes, en accumulant preuves sur preuves en faveur d’une vérité de ce genre. Que l’homme soit un animal par son corps, tous les philosophes et les religions même n’ont cessé d’en faire l’aveu; qu’il se soit élevé au dessus des autres animaux par un développement prodigieux, mais très-inégalement départi, de ses facultés mentales, basées pourtant sur le même fond commun, c’est encore une réalité dont vous rapportez des preuves surabondantes avec votre force, votre abondance et votre logique ordinaires. Mais vous insistez trop, et c’est sur ce point que je veux vous faire part de mes objections, vous insistez trop à mon sens, et inutilement, si ce n’est pas démontrable <hi rend="underline">hic et nunc</hi>, sur la descendance de l’homme d’un prototype <hi rend="underline">Simien</hi> et <hi rend="underline">grimpeur</hi> soit anthropomorphe soit provenant de quelque autre rameau détaché de la même famille.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Je trouve que votre doctrine n’implique nullement, à mes yeux, ce résultat, mais qu’elle entraîne seulement la descendance d’un prototype plus voisin de l’animalité proprement dite que le type humain actuel et dépourvu par conséquent d’une partie au moins des facultés mentales et de l’organisation physique qui sont l’apanage des races humaines les plus inférieures. Je ne remarque parmi les indices sérieux d’une descendance directe Simienne que les suivants dont la portée est loin, il est vrai, d’être méprisable: Le caractère tiré de la dentition qui doit être placé en première ligne; puisqu’il semble dénoter une liaison exclusive avec les Singes de l’ancien continent, ensuite les règles des femelles et subsidiairement l’odeur qui rend les femmes attrayantes à beaucoup de singes.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ce sont là des présomptions graves qui s’expliquent cependant par l’hypothèse de la descendance d’une prototype, souche commune des deux groupes, avec divergence mutuelle et progressive. Il existe chez tous les singes une adaptation évidente à l’état de grimpeur. Chez les Anthromorphes eux-même cette adaptation demeure visible bien qu’elle tende à se modifier quelque peu de manière à produire une marche incomplète et en tout cas différente par son mécanisme de celle qui est propre à l’homme. Il n’y a chez l’homme inférieur aucune tendance de retour, aucune transition vers la vie de grimpeur, et vous ne pouvez citer à ce point de vue, dont l’importance ne saurait vous échapper que le penchant qui porte les enfants à grimper sur les arbres.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> L’homme aussi bien qu’on le suive vers son berceau primitif se montre <hi rend="underline">troglodyte</hi>, c’est à dire marcheur, s’aidant des pieds et des mains pour gravir et s’élever et se servant sans doute de cette faculté, si rare chez les animaux de grande taille pour se procurer un genre de vie spécial. Je suis parfaitement et entièrement de votre avis, lorsque vous supposez que l’homme avait acquis un commencement d’intelligence et de langage articulé et inventé probablement le feu avant sa dispersion qui l’amena à multiplier ses peuplades et à les répandre jusqu’aux extrémités des grands continents, dès une époque probablement fort reculée. Physiquement l’homme était alors à peu près ce qu’il est, et il l’avait été antérieurement depuis un temps déjà long; car une loi invariable et universelle en paléontologie veut que les groupes se soient comporté jadis à travers le temps, <hi rend="underline">comme ils se comportent actuellement lorsqu’on les considère dans l’espace</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Cette faculté particulière à l’homme de ne donner lieu qu’à des races, de varier beaucoup et aisément, mais dans des limites restreints, de façon à ne jamais diverger audelà d’un certain terme, en gardant la fécondité mutuelle des races entr’elles, cette faculté a du distinguer l’espèce humaine depuis très-longtemps, probablement à partir de l’époque même où elle se detacha de la souche prototypique pour revêtir les caractères du groupe qu’elle représente, de même que les Simiens se détachaient de leur côté de la même souche pour accentuer de plus en plus l’organisation propre à leur groupe et manifester sous bien des points de vue des caractères qui sont l’opposé de ceux du groupe humain.</p>
<p>En effet, La multiplicité des tribus et des genres, la pluralité des espèces, et l’impossibilité physique des rapports sexuels entre les formes les plus élevées, comme on le voit pour les Anthropomorphes, constituent des caractères propres aux Simiens et il en existe encore d’autres. Mais je voudrais aborder la question à un autre point de vue.— J’ai toujours pensé que les questions d’origine, beaucoup moins insolubles qu’on est porté à le supposer, ne se résoudraient pourtant qu’a l’aide de <hi rend="underline">l’accord des faits actuels</hi> et <hi rend="underline">des faits anciens</hi> et par l’étude comparative de ces deux ordres de phénomènes. Je le crois encore et j’admets également que dans cet ordre d’idées les mêmes lois et les mêmes indices ou aperçus se trouvent plus ou moins applicables à tous les êtres organisés, sans en excepter l’homme. Je me suis donc appliqué à découvrir les lois ou commencement de lois ou encore les règles qui résultent de l’examen des genres fossiles et en particulier de ceux, comme c’est le cas pour les plantes, qui, attachés au sol et naturellement immuables, doivent fournir plus de lumières sur la marche suivie autrefois par les êtres, dans leur mode de distribution et de développement. C’est ainsi que je suis arrivé à un certain nombre de notions générales qui me paraissent applicables à l’origine même de l’homme.</p>
<p>Les types génériques, vous le savez, sont parfois étonnamment fixes; ceux même qui sont le résultat d’une longue série de modifications successives se montrent tels que nous les voyons jusque dans un temps fort éloigné. C’était l’opinion de M. Lartet pour le Renne, le cerf et le Cheval, qu’il fallait remonter jusque dans le Miocène pour apercevoir dans ces types, même en les considérant sous leur forme actuelle, les changements susceptibles d’être traduits par la charpente osseuse.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Et cependant, il s’agit là de types qui ont du subir <hi rend="underline">physiquement</hi> une élaboration des plus complexes, puis qu’ils n’ont revêtu leurs caractères définitifs, qu’a force de s’éloigner de prototypes construits tout autrement qu’ils ne le sont et par suite d’une adaptation des plus rigoureuses. Chez l’homme, cette adaptation est loin d’avoir exigé <hi rend="underline">au physique</hi>, le même travail organique de soudure et d’avortement des parties dures, et la tendance à la marche bipède a pu exister chez le prototype humain, comme elle se montre chez quelques rongeurs. L’adaptation simienne aux fonctions d’animal grimpeur est au moins aussi exclusive que celle de l’homme pour la marche, et rien ne peut dire si l’un de ces états a précédé l’autre, en ce qui concerne le prototype des deux groupes, ou si ce prototype, ainsi qu’il a du arriver le plus souvent, n’a pas été une sorte de terme vague, susceptible de donner également passage vers ces deux états. Je suis donc porté à croire que l’homme est fort ancien sous sa forme physique actuelle et qu’on le retrouverait avec peu de changement, en remontant très-loin, sauf pourtant le développement du cerveau qui a du accompagner celui des facultés mentales. J’ai été frappé de la probabilité de ce fait en voyant les restes humains trouvés à <hi rend="underline">la Denyse</hi> près du Puy en Velay, que je considère comme les plus anciens connus jusqu’ ici, bien qu’il ait été fait peu de bruit autour de la découverte; le propriétaire de ces restes, homme <hi rend="underline">peu sensé</hi>, s’attachant, par bizarrerie d’esprit, à suspecter leur authenticité, pourtant <hi rend="underline">irrécusable</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> On reconnait sur une des têtes, dont la calotte cranienne est dégagée de la gangue, une énorme dépression des parties du front qui correspondent à l’intelligence pure, mais peu de crétes osseuses et rien qui rappelle autre chose que l’homme actuel avec une <hi rend="underline">tournure idiote</hi>. L’ homme primitif, mais non encore pourtant prototypique, il est vrai, devait ressembler plus ou moins au crétin; c’est la je crois le veritable retour à un état antérieur, sans les ressources de l’instinct qui se sont sans doute de plus en plus oblitérées.</p>
<p>Mais je continue et je trouve ceci.— En prenant pour point de départ les végétaux fossiles, je déduis de leur observation deux lois ou indices de lois.— La première c’est que beaucoup de genres observés dans la végétation tertiaire ancienne se trouvent encore <hi rend="underline">actuellement</hi> disposés suivant un mode de distribution en rapport avec la configuration des terres et des mers particuliers à la période à laquelle ils appartiennent. Ainsi les genres caractéristiques de la Flore des Gypses d’Aix (Eocène supérieur) habitent de nos jours des régions qui étaient <hi rend="underline">terre ferme</hi> au temps de la mer nummulitique, ce qui fait voir que leur distribution moderne est en relation avec leur aire d’extension primitive et que ces genres parconséquent ne sont que des prolongements d’un ordre antérieur. Il ne s’agit pas évidemment ici de ces genres qui étant purement cosmopolites ne sauraient donner lieu à aucun indication véritable, mais de genres soit amoindrés soit ayant persisté dans les pays chaud seulement: ou sur certains points extraeuropéens.</p>
<p>Le second principe constaté par moi est le suivant: il existe un parallélisme et un balancement d’un hémisphère à l’autre, d’un continent à l’autre, et même de genre à genre et d’espèce à espèce d’une région à l’autre, ensorte que les groupes qui se sont développés largement sur une partie du globe peuvent être restés faibles ou rudimentaire sur le point opposé ou n’ avoir donné lieu qu’ à un développement des plus inégaux. De cette façon, les deux groupes rivaux correspondants peuvent chacun regner dans un des hémisphères et posséder pourtant des répresentants isolés et peu caractérisés dans l’autre. Il en est ainsi des Protéacées qui paraissent avoir été remplacées dans l’Europe tertiaire par des Myricées, tandis qu’à côté même de ces nombreuses Myricées, il a du exister un petit groupe de Protéacées tertiaires européennes sans importance, de même qu’en Australie et au Cap à côté de la foule des Protéacées prédominantes quelques rares Myricées se montrent également.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Les Fagus antarctiques comparées aux aux riche Quercinées de l’hémisphère boréal font voir les effets de la même inégalité de parallélisme et on pourrait multiplier les exemples de cette loi dont les Marsupiaux d’Australie persistant vis à vis de ceux de l’Europe, si promptement éliminés offrent une autre application.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Je crois les deux lois que je viens de déterminer parfaitement susceptibles d’application relativement à l’homme et à ses origines et toutes deux tendent, si elles lui sont appliquées, à démontrer l’ancienneté de son type physique.</p>
<p>J’ai souvent été frappé de ceci que les principales races humaines se trouvaient distribuées à la surface de l’ancien continent d’une manière conforme a l’ancienne répartition des terres et des mers tertiaires. Pour vérifier ce fait, il faut faire abstraction des changements et mélanges que les traditions historiques permettent de saisir. Dans ces conditions, si l’on remet en place cette grande mer interieure, partageant tout l’ancien continent, dont la méditeranée n’est qu’un reste, et qui a persisté en variant fort peu dans ces limites principales jusqu’à la fin du Miocène, si on la fait de nouveau s’étendre d’une part vers l’Océan indien, de l’autre au centre de l’Asie et jusqu’en Chine, on reconnait aisément combien les principales races humaines sont groupées naturellement le long des rivages de cette mer. C’est ainsi que les Malais des îles de l’Afrique à l’Asie méridionale se rattachent à des terres jadis continues, depuis en partie submergées. Les Nègres ne dépassent pas au nord la limite du Sahara et ont pour région mère le sol primitif de l’ Afrique centrale, ancien littoral de la mer Saharienne. Les Canaries dont le rôle a été si grand autrefois, possédait les Guanches.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> La race Jaune a été parqué au Nord est de la grande mer intérieure asiatique. Au nord, en Europe, comme en Sibérie cette mer a eu les Ouraliens, Touraniens,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Finnois Lapons, les races troglodites de l’âge de pierre— Sur le rivage opposé, dans la haute Asie, se trouve le berceau des Aryas et des Sémites, qui n’ont du commencer à se disperser et à s’étendre dans plusieurs directions divergentes qu’après le retrait de la grande Méditerranée centro-asiatique. Il n’est pas jusqu’aux Eskimaux dont l’existence ne soit en rapport avec ce que la paléontologie végétale nous apprend sur le passé des contrées qu’ils habitent. Ces peuples se sentent eux-même décheoir. Ils n’ont certainement pas pénétré dans les pays arctiques sous l’empire des conditions actuelles; mais nous savons qu’il y avait là, dans l’âge miocène, un grand continent continu avec l’ancien et le nouveau continent, richement peuplé en plantes et en animaux. L’homme s’y est répandu sans doute dans un temps où le climat y conservait encore quelque chose de sa primitive douceur. Depuis, il y est resté forcément luttant contre des changements défavorables et s’y adaptant peu à peu. Les Esquimaux sont à mon sens un exemple excellent et le premier de tous de qu’a du être l’homme, immédiatement après que ses facultés lui eurent permis de se répandre sur toutes les grandes terres. L’Esquimaux est encore ce qu’il a été originairement et une fois stationnaires les races ne changent jamais plus. Comme le Sequoia de Californie, l’Esquimaux est un type devenu permanent à partir d’une certaine époque et qui peut disparaître, mais ne se modifiera jamais plus.</p>
<p>Cette distribution de l’homme, conforme à celle des genres de plantes que l’on observe à l’état fossile et en rélation avec la configuration ancienne des terres et des mers, est évidemment favorable à la croyance qu’il remonte, entant qu’homme physique, à une antiquité fort-réculée et que ses caractères matériels n’ont pas varié depuis longtemps, circonstance qui explique du reste à merveille la fécondité mutuelle de ses races.</p>
<p>La seconde loi n’est pas moins applicable à l’homme, et loin que je voie en lui une déviation latérale du type simien, je reconnais chez lui les caractères d’un <hi rend="underline">ordre longtemps parallèle</hi>, devenu enfin supérieur, dont le développement est très-loin d’avoir suivi la même marche, et cette sorte d’antagonisme entre les deux groupes me fait parfaitement comprendre la voie divergente suivie par chacun d’eux. Je vois chez l’homme les caractères d’une adaptation tout à fait opposée à celle des singes. Le type <hi rend="underline">simien</hi>, grimpeur, arboricole, fécond en <hi rend="underline">diversités</hi> de tribus, de genres et d’espèces, divergeant rapidement et multipliant les types secondaires de manière à donner lieu a une ramification complexe et à aboutir à un certain nombre de chefs de série sans rapports directs entr’eux, se développe <hi rend="underline">exclusivement</hi> dans la zone tropicale; il exige impérieusement la chaleur et se trouve promptement éliminé dès ce que cet élément fait défaut; chez lui, le plus souvent il existe un arrêt brusque de l’intelligence vers l’âge adulte, des cris et rien qui ressemble à l’articulation des mots ni à une voix; puis si l’on s’attache à ce qui est secondaire: abondance de poils rudes, peu de différences entre le poil des membres et celui de la tête— Les tendances de l’homme sont opposées: marcheur, troglodyte, il ne donne lieu, même en pénétrant partout qu’à des diversités superficielles qui n’altèrent jamais assez les convenances physiques pour rendre stériles les unions réciproques. Il a donc du diverger lentement et s’éloigner peu, sauf par le développement intellectuel du prototype d’où il est derivé. L’ homme, <hi rend="underline">contrairement à ce qui existe pour les Singes</hi>, est <hi rend="underline">cosmopolite</hi> de plus, il ne s’est pleinement développé que sous l’influence d’un climat froid ou tempéré et à l’époque où cette sorte de climat a prévalu. Ce qui a éliminé le type simien de l’hémisphère boréal a évidemment favorisé l’homme. Son expansion date justement du temps ou la température s’est graduellement abaissée. Chez lui, peu de force musculaire, mais une tendance au développement des facultés de l’intelligence— Les Sauvages, il faut le remarquer, ne sont pas musculairement plus forts que nous, et de plus, ils sont généalement <hi rend="underline">glabres</hi> quoique nus. Là encore la divergence est très-marquée.</p>
<p>Il semble donc que l’homme ait eté originairement un type propre à l’hémisphère boréal, de même que le type simien est un produit équatorial et torride qui s’avançait jusque dans nos latitudes, tant que notre zone a été chaude et qui s’en est retiré dès qu’elle s’est refroidie. L’homme, tout l’annonce et c’est même ce qui explique cette invention première de feu, a du se constituer vers le nord, et plus tard il aura envoyé des peuplades dans les autres directions et jusque dans le Sud, de même que les Simiens en ont eu Jadis dans le nord. Mais je crois que ces événements, c’est à dire le détachement progressive de l’homme de son prototype, quel qu’il soit, et l’affinité probable de ce dernier avec une souche encore plus primitive reporte l’homme immensément loin dans le passé. L’homme avant sa diffusion a du vivre à l’écart, au fond des bois, à portée des cavernes où grâce à son mode de progression il a du se retirer et amasser des provisions— Il a du être timide, défiant, vivant par couples ou familles isolées, et la nécéssité où il a été, de se procurer des armes le prouve— Avant de posséder le feu, l’homme devait éprouver bien des difficultés pour se nourrir; il vivait sans doute exclusivement de certains fruits et peutêtre de racines et d’oeufs. Ce que vous dites de la séparation antérieure probable du type simien d’Amérique de celui de l’ancien continent a pour soi les apparences et la probabilité;<ref target="#foot.f13"/> comment le savoir pourtant? L’homme tend effectivement à perdre les dents de sagesse;<ref target="#foot.f14"/> il a pu antérieurement en perdre d’autres encore. La formule dentaire a pu varier plus ou moins chez le prototype et se fixer définitivement, alorsque les trois types avaient déjà divergé.... Comment? il est impossible de le savoir et vous le dites vous- même; mais plus je reflêchis, plus je suis porté à admettre que la divergence à partir d’une souche prototypique ne peut être que très-éloignée. Et lorsque l’on voit dès l’<hi rend="underline">éocène</hi> le type <hi rend="underline">Vespertilio</hi><ref target="#foot.f15"/> déjà tout constitué et n’ayant dès lors plus varié, on est bien forcé d’avouer qu’au point de vue physique, et tout l’effort d’adaptation ayant porté du côté purement intellectuel, l’homme a bien pu être à peu près ce qu’il est encore, <hi rend="underline">matériellement</hi>, à partir d’un âge excessivement lointain peutêtre dès l’éocène. Je vous livre, Monsieur, ces réflexions jetées au hazard de la plume et qui partent du reste d’un transformiste des plus convaincus et d’un admirateur sincère de vos travaux— J’avais offert à la <hi rend="underline">Revue des deux mondes</hi> de rendre compte de votre dernier ouvrage, mais je n’ai pas encore su ce que souhaite à cet égard la rédaction.— Je suis du reste tellement absorbé en ce moment par mes travaux et sur la flore Jurassique et sur celle de l’Eocène des Gypses d’Aix que je n’insiste pas, me réservant pour les mois d’été où je dispose de plus de temps.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Je vous prie d’excuser une aussi longue lettre et d’agréer l’expression de mes sentiments les plus devoué | C<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> G. de Saporta</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                    <date>18 March 1872</date>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have put off thanking you for so kindly sending your book on the descent of man until I had finished reading it through once, but before returning to it in a little while, because your works demand to be re-read if one really wants to grasp the sequence of your ideas.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This time there are parts of your work that have particularly struck me, everything that is philosophical, especially the exposition of moral and intellectual phenomena in man and the animals, the relations and passages from thought to instinct, the generation of conscience etc.— You have deployed, in examining these difficult and most complex questions, a power of analysis of the rarest kind, and I was often able, by reflecting on my own conduct, to convince myself of the truth of your deductions. I am wholly of your opinion when you insist on the indisputable place of man as an integral part of the mammals. The close links that tie man to that class are so little susceptible of being misunderstood, that even to prove that tie seems singular in itself, and one can hardly conceive that one would be in a position to demonstrate it to naturalists by accumulating proof after proof in support of a truth of that kind. That man is an animal in body is constantly avowed by all philosophers and even all religions; that he has risen above the other animals through a development of his mental faculties that is prodigious, yet very unevenly distributed, even though those faculties are founded on the same common basis: this is a reality for which you report superabundant proof with your ordinary power, abundance and logic. But you insist too much, and it is on this point that I want to share my objections with you, you insist too much to my mind, and uselessly so, since it is not demonstrable <hi rend="underline">hic et nunc</hi>, on the descent of man from a <hi rend="underline">Simian</hi> and <hi rend="underline">climbing</hi> prototype, whether anthropomorphic or deriving from some other detached branch of the same family.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In my view, your doctrine does not imply this outcome, merely descent from a prototype closer to animality, properly understood, than the current human type, and therefore deprived of part at least of the mental faculties and physical organisation that are the lot of the most inferior human races. Among the serious signs of direct Simian descent, I observe only the following, whose significance is indeed far from contemptible: The character drawn from dentition, which must be accorded primary importance, since it seems to denote an exclusive link with the Monkeys of the old continent; next, female menstruation and, as a corollary, the odour that makes women attractive to many monkeys.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> These are weighty presumptions, which can nonetheless be explained by the hypothesis of descent from a prototype that is the common stock of both groups, with mutual and progressive divergence. In all monkeys, there is evident adaptation to the climbing state. Even in the Anthropomorphs, this adaptation remains visible, although it tends to be modified somewhat so as to produce incomplete walking, at any rate differing in its mechanism from the walking proper to man. In lower man, there is no tendency to revert, no transition to the climbing lifestyle, and you are only able to quote in that regard, the importance of which cannot escape you, the inclination which leads children to climb trees.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Indeed, as one follows man back to his primeval cradle, he shows himself to be a <hi rend="underline">troglodyte</hi>, or in other words a walker, using his feet and hands to help himself climb and stand up, and doubtless making use of this faculty, which is so rare among the larger animals, in order to procure a special lifestyle for himself. I completely and wholly share your view that man had acquired the beginnings of intelligence and articulate language, and had probably invented fire, before the dispersal that led him to multiply his tribes and spread them to the limits of the large continents, in an epoch that is probably very remote. Physically, man was then about what he is now, and already had been for a long time; for an invariable and universal law in palaeontology holds that groups in the past behaved over time, <hi rend="underline">as they now behave when considered over distance</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>That faculty particular to man of only producing races, of varying widely and easily, but within narrow limits, so as never to diverge beyond a certain point, while preserving the mutual fecundity of the races between themselves, must have characterised the human species for a very long time, probably from the very epoch in which it detached itself from the prototypical stock and took on the characters of the group it represents, just as the Simians on their side detached themselves from the same stock and increasingly accentuated the organisation proper to their group, in many regards manifesting characters that are the opposite of those of the human group.</p>
<p>Indeed, a multiplicity of tribes and genera, a plurality of species, and a physical impossibility of sexual relations between the highest forms, as one sees in the case of the Anthropomorphs, constitute characters proper to the Simians, and there are other such characters too. But I wanted to address the question from a different perspective.— I have always thought that the question of origins, far less insoluble than one is led to believe, would nonetheless only be resolved with the aid of <hi rend="underline">the agreement of current facts</hi> with <hi rend="underline">ancient facts</hi> and by a comparative study of these two orders of phenomena. I still believe this and I also allow that in this order of ideas, the same laws and signs or perceptions are more or less applicable to all organised beings, man not excepted. So I have applied myself to discovering the laws or beginnings of laws, or yet the rules, that result from the examination of fossil genera, and in particular of those, such as the plants, which, as they are fixed to the soil and naturally immobile, must provide the most illumination about the course that beings have followed in the past, in their modes of distribution and development. In this way I have arrived at a certain number of general notions which seem to me applicable to the very origin of man himself.</p>
<p>The generic types, as you know, are sometimes astonishingly stable; even those that are the result of a long series of successive modifications appear as we see them today, into the very distant past. It was Mr. Lartet’s opinion regarding the Reindeer, the red deer and the Horse, that for these types, even in their current form, one had to go back to the Miocene before observing changes capable of being manifested in the skeleton.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> And yet in such cases the types must have undergone a most complex elaboration in <hi rend="underline">physical terms</hi>, since they only took on their definitive characters by dint of distancing themselves from prototypes constructed quite differently from themselves, and in consequence of a very rigorous adaptation. In man, that adaptation was far from having required <hi rend="underline">in his physique</hi> the same organic work of union or imperfect development in the bony parts, and the tendency towards bipedal walking may have existed in the human prototype, as it is exhibited by some rodents. The simian adaptation to the functions of a climbing animal is at least as exclusive as that of man to walking, and there is no way of saying whether one of these states preceded the other, as far as the prototype of the two groups is concerned; or whether this prototype, as must most often have occurred, was not some sort of vague term that was equally capable of producing either of the two states. So I am led to believe that the current physical form of man is very ancient, and that it could be found far back in time with little alteration, except perhaps for the brain development that must have accompanied the development in mental faculties. I was struck by the likelihood of this fact on seeing the human remains found at <hi rend="underline">Denyse</hi>, near Puy-en-Velay, which I consider to be the oldest known to date, even though very little noise has been made about the discovery; the owner of these remains, a man of <hi rend="underline">little sense</hi>, clinging out of whimsical-mindedness to a suspicion of their authenticity, which is nevertheless <hi rend="underline">unimpeachable</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> On one of the heads, where the crown of the cranium is detached from the matrix, one can see an enormous depression of the parts of the forehead that correspond to pure intelligence, but few bony crests and nothing that recalls anything other than contemporary man with an <hi rend="underline">imbecile cast</hi>. Primitive man, though not yet, it is true, entirely prototypical, ought to resemble the cretin more or less; this is, I believe, a genuine reversion to an earlier state, without the resources of instinct, which have doubtless been increasingly obliterated.</p>
<p>To go on, however, I find the following.— Taking fossil plants as a point of departure, I deduce two laws or signs of laws from my observation of them.— The first is that many genera observed in ancient Tertiary vegetation are still <hi rend="underline">today</hi> found arranged in accordance with a mode of distribution related to the lie of individual land masses and seas in the period to which they belong. Thus, the characteristic genera of the Flora of the Aix Gypsum (Upper Eocene) today inhabit regions that were <hi rend="underline">dry land</hi> at the time of the nummulitic sea, which shows that their modern distribution is related to their primitive area of spread, and that these genera, in consequence, are nothing more than the continuation of an earlier order. Clearly those genera which, being purely cosmopolitan, could not give rise to any genuine indication, are not at issue here, but rather genera which have either diminished or persisted only in warm countries: or in some extra-European spots.</p>
<p>The second principle I have confirmed is as follows: there is a parallelism and a balancing between one hemisphere and another, between one continent and another, and even from genus to genus and species to species between one region and another, such that the groups that have developed widely in one part of the globe may have remained weak or rudimentary in the opposite spot or have only produced a very unequal development. In this way, the corresponding two rival groups may each reign in one of the hemispheres and yet possess isolated and poorly characterised representatives in the other. It is so in the Proteaceae, which seem to have been replaced in Tertiary Europe by the Myricaceae, even while a small group of insignificant European Tertiary Proteaceae must have existed alongside these numerous Myricaceae, just as in Australia and at the Cape a few rare Myricaceae appear alongside the host of predominant Proteaceae.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> The Antarctic Fagus compared to the rich Quercinaceae of the boreal hemisphere make visible the effects of the same inequality of parallelism, and one could multiply examples of this law, another case of which is the Australian Marsupials persisting, as against those of Europe which were so promptly eliminated.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I have often been struck by the fact that the principal human races were distributed across the surface of the ancient continent in a manner in keeping with the ancient division of Tertiary land masses and seas. To verify that fact, one needs to make an abstraction of the changes and mixtures that historical traditions permit one to grasp. Under such conditions, if one restores the great interior sea, of which the Mediterranean is no more than a residue, and which persisted by varying very little within these principal limits up to the end of the Miocene, to its situation, dividing the whole of the ancient continent; if one causes that sea to extend once more up to the Indian Ocean on one side and as far as the centre of Asia, even to China, on the other, one can easily recognise the extent to which the principal human races are grouped naturally along its shores. In this way the Malays from the islands of Africa to South Asia are associated with lands which were once continuous and are now partly submerged. The Negroes do not exceed the limits of the Sahara to the north and have as their natal region the primitive soil of Central Africa, the ancient coastline of the Saharan sea. The Canaries, whose role was once so great, had the Guanches.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The Yellow race was penned to the North-east of the great interior Asiatic sea. To the north, in Europe as in Siberia, this sea had the Uralians, Turanians,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Finns, Lapps, the troglodyte races of the Stone Age— On the opposite shore, in Upper Asia, is the birthplace of the Aryans and Semites, who must only have begun to disperse and spread in several different directions after the retreat of the great Centro-Asiatic Mediterranean. Not even the existence of the Eskimos is unrelated to what plant palaeontology teaches us of the past of the countries they inhabit. These peoples feel themselves to be in decline. They certainly have not penetrated the arctic countries under the sway of current conditions; but we know that there was a great continent there during the Miocene Age, continuous with the old and the new continents, and richly populated with plants and animals. Man doubtless spread there at a time when the climate still retained something of its primitive gentleness. Since that time, he has remained there, perforce struggling against the unfavourable changes and adapting to them little by little. The Eskimos are in my opinion an excellent example, and the foremost among all, of what man must have been immediately after his faculties permitted him to spread through all the large land areas. The Eskimo is still what he originally was, and once they are stationary, races never change again. Like the Sequoia of California, the Eskimo is a type which became permanent after a certain epoch, and which might vanish, but will never again be modified.</p>
<p>This distribution of humans, conforming to that of the plant genera observed in the fossil state and relative to the ancient configuration of land and sea, evidently supports the belief that man, <hi rend="underline">qua</hi> physical man, dates back to a very remote antiquity and that his material characters have not varied for a long time, a circumstance that also wonderfully explains the mutual fecundity of the races.</p>
<p>The second law is no less applicable to man, and far from seeing in him a lateral deviation from the simian type, I recognise in him characters of an <hi rend="underline">order that has long been its parallel</hi>, and finally become its superior, whose development is very far from having followed the same course, and this sort of antagonism between the two groups makes me understand perfectly the divergent route each of them has followed. In man I see the characters of an adaptation wholly opposed to that of the monkeys. The <hi rend="underline">simian</hi> type, climbing, tree-dwelling, fecund in <hi rend="underline">varied</hi> tribes, genera and species, rapidly diverging and multiplying secondary types in such a way as to give rise to a complex ramification, and to result in a certain number of heads of series without direct interrelations, develops <hi rend="underline">exclusively</hi> in the tropical zone; it necessarily requires heat and is promptly eliminated if that element is lacking; most commonly it displays an abrupt halt to intelligence around adulthood, cries and nothing which resembles the articulation of words or a voice; then if one dwells on what is secondary: an abundance of coarse hair, few distinctions between the hair on the limbs and that on the head— Man’s tendencies are the opposite: a walker and troglodyte, he only produces superficial diversity, even when he has penetrated everywhere, which never alters physical fitness enough to render reciprocal unions sterile. Thus he must have diverged slowly and have distanced himself but little, except in intellectual development, from the prototype from which he derives. <hi rend="underline">Contrary to what is the case for Monkeys</hi>, man is also <hi rend="underline">cosmopolitan</hi>; he has only developed fully under the influence of cold or temperate climates and in the epoch when that sort of climate prevailed. That which eliminated the simian type from the boreal hemisphere, evidently favoured man. His expansion dates precisely from the time when the temperature gradually declined. He has little muscular force, but tends rather to the development of the faculties of intelligence— Savages, it should be noted, have no greater muscular development than ourselves, and in addition they are generally <hi rend="underline">glabrous</hi> although naked. There too, divergence is very marked.</p>
<p>So it seems that man was originally a type proper to the boreal hemisphere, just as the simian type is an equatorial and torrid product that advanced into our latitudes while our zone was hot, and withdrew from it once it cooled. Everything proclaims that man must have been constituted towards the north; this even explains that first invention of fire. He would later have sent tribes in other directions, even into the South, just as the Simians once had them in the north. But I believe that these events, that is to say the progressive detachment of man from his prototype, whatever it may be, and the probable affinity of the latter with a still more primitive stock, take man back immensely far into the past. Before his diffusion, man must have lived hidden away, in the depths of the woods, within reach of caves, where thanks to his mode of progression he must have withdrawn and amassed provisions— He must have been timid, fearful, living in couples or isolated families, and the necessity he was in of procuring weapons proves this— Before possessing fire, man would have experienced many problems in feeding himself; he doubtless lived exclusively on certain fruits, perhaps roots and eggs. What you say of the probable prior separation of the simian type of America from that of the old continent has appearances and probability on its side;<ref target="#foot.f13"/> yet how can one know? Man tends to lose his wisdom teeth, it’s true;<ref target="#foot.f14"/> he may formerly have lost others. The dental formula may have varied more or less in the prototype and have fixed itself definitively once the three types had already diverged.... What? It’s impossible to know that and you say so yourself; but the more I reflect, the more I am led to allow that divergence from a prototypical stock can only be very remote. And when we see the type <hi rend="underline">Vespertilio</hi><ref target="#foot.f15"/> already completely constituted since the <hi rend="underline">Eocene</hi> and not having varied since, we are quite forced to avow that from the physical point of view, with all the effort of adaptation having borne on the purely intellectual side, man may perhaps well have been approximately what he still is <hi rend="underline">materially</hi> from an age excessively remote from the Eocene. I offer you these reflections thrown haphazardly from my pen, dear Sir, which come besides from one of the most convinced transformists, a sincere admirer of your work— I had offered to review your latest work for the <hi rend="underline">Revue des deux mondes</hi>, but I have not yet learnt the editors’ wishes in that regard.— Besides, I am so absorbed in my work on the Jurassic and Eocene flora of the Aix Gypsums at the moment that I shan’t press the matter, but shall save myself for the summer months when I have more free time.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Please excuse such a long letter and believe me yours obediently | C<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> G. de Saporta</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 111–17.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Saporta had evidently received a copy of the first volume of the French edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> (Moulinié trans. 1872). The second volume was not published until November 1872 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8643.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C.-F. Reinwald, 23 November 1872</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Hic et nunc</hi>: here and now (Latin). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 185–213, CD discussed evidence for a simian ancestor of humans. He wrote: ‘There can consequently hardly be a doubt that man is an offshoot from the Old World Simian stem; and that under a genealogical point of view, he must be classed with the Catarhine division’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 196).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had pointed out the similarity in human and Old World monkey dentition in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 196. CD did not discuss menstruation in humans and Old World apes and monkeys in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>. For more on the attractiveness of human females to apes, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6665.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ritvo 1990</ref>, p. 33, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6919.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schaik 2004</ref>, pp. 88–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD discussed tree-climbing in children in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 122, and bipedalism in humans in <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 141–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 390, CD concluded that the development of human intellect including language and tool use occurred in the remote past.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2819.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Lartet</ref> had described Miocene fossils at Sansan, including those of extinct deer (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lartet 1851</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The remains found at Denise formed part of the collection of M. Pichot-Dumazel, who has not been further identified, but who was described by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> as ‘an advocate of Le Puy’ (C. Lyell 1863, p. 196). The authenticity of the remains was discussed at the twenty-second scientific congress of France in 1855 (see <hi rend="italic">Congrès scientifique de France. Vingt-deuxième session, tenue au Puy, en Septembre 1855</hi>, pp. 299–303, and C. Lyell 1863, pp. 194–200).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Myricaceae (sweet gale) is a family in the subclass Hamamelidae; Proteaceae (proteas) is a family in the subclass Rosidae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Antarctic or southern beeches are now in the genus <hi rend="italic">Nothofagus</hi> in the family Nothofagaceae; the former family Quercinaceae is now subsumed within the family Fagaceae (beeches, chestnuts, and oaks).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The Guanches were the original inhabitants of the Canary Islands. Although their origins were not known for certain, from remnants of their language they were believed to be related to the Berbers of northern Africa (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1814–29</ref>, 1: 279–82).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">‘Turanian’ was broadly used to refer to languages of Asiatic origin, except the Aryan and Semitic, and similarly applied to the speakers of these languages (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 198–202.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><hi rend="italic">Vespertilio</hi> is a genus of bats.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Saporta refers to his work on the classification of plant fossils found in gypsum beds of Aix. His ‘Révision de la flore des gypses d’Aix’ was published in parts between 1872 and 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6891.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Saporta 1872–4</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>