<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-665">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. D. Fox   [25 March 1843]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7066</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-665 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-665.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-665.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 202</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 321</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 352</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Christ’s College Library, Cambridge (MS 53 Fox 66)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_83.xml">CCLC</repository>
                    <collection>MS 53</collection>
                    <idno>Fox 66</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1843-03-25">[25 Mar 1843]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml">Fox, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sympathises with WDF’s persisting grief.</p> 
<p>Describes Down House and additions being built, which interfere with <hi rend="italic">Geology</hi> [<hi rend="italic">of "Beagle"</hi>].</p> 
            <p>Bodily health is improved, but cannot stand mental excitement.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, good or improving</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Down House</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down. Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Saturday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Fox</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I was very glad to get your letter some six weeks since, but grieved to the heart at its contents. Your’s does indeed seem at present a hopeless case— I should have thought that time <hi rend="underline">inevitably </hi> would have done you more good, than it seems to have done— I had hoped (for experience I have none) that the mind w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have refused to dwell so long &amp; so intently on any object, although the most cherished one— Strong affections, have always appeared to me, the most noble part of a man’s character &amp; the absence of them an irreparable failure; you ought to console yourself with thinking that your grief is the necessary price for having been born with (for I am convinced they are not to be acquired) such feelings— But I am writing away without really being able to put myself in your position—you have my sincerest sympathy &amp; respect in your sorrow—I can only hope that the intensity of your grief may shorten (however little you may think it possible) their duration.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I will tell you all the trifling particulars about myself, that I can think of.— we are now exceedingly busy, with the first brick laid down yesterday to an addition to our house; with this, with almost making a new kitchen garden &amp; sundry other projected schemes, my days are very full. I find all this very bad for geology—but I am very slowly progressing with a vol: or rather pamphlet on the Volcanic islands, wh we visited; I manage only a couple of hours per day, &amp; that not very regularly.— It is up-hill work, writing books, which cost money in publishing &amp; which are not read even by geologists.— I forget whether I ever described this place: it is a good, very ugly house with 18 acres; situated on a chalk-flat, 560 ft above sea— There are peeps of far-distant country &amp; the scenery is moderately pretty; its chief merit is its extreme rurality; I think I was never in a more perfectly quiet country: Three miles South of us the great chalk escarpment quite cuts us off from the low country of Kent, &amp; between us &amp; the escarpment, there is not a village or gent<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>: house, but only great woods &amp; arable fields (the latter in sadly preponderant numbers), so that we are absolutely at extreme verge of world.— The whole country is intersected by foot-paths; but the surface over the chalk is clayey &amp; sticky, which is worst feature in our purchase.— The dingles &amp; banks often remind me of Cambridgeshire &amp; walking with you to Cherry Hinton, &amp; other places, though the general aspect of the country is very different. I was looking over my arranged cabinet (the only remnant, I have preserved of all my English insects) &amp; was admiring Panagæus crux major: it is curious the vivid manner in which this insect always calls up my mind, your appearance, with little Fan trotting after, when I was first introduced to you— Those entomological days were very pleasant ones—</p>
<p>I occasionally hear from Henslow: he is absorbed at present with making the Suffolk farmers experimenters in agricultural chemistry, &amp; has commenced by doing wonders in exciting their zealous cooperation. He seems very busy with parish concerns—</p>
<p>We are all well here—that is essentially so for Emma is as bad as she usually is in her present state.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am <hi rend="underline">very</hi> much stronger corporeally, but am b〈ut〉 little better in being able to stand mental fatigue or rather excitement, so that I cannot dine out or receive visitors, except relations with whom I can pass some time after dinner in silence.</p>
<p>Farewell my dear Fox with my best wishes.— Ever yours | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 intently] ‘n’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.6 islands] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.6 I] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘—-’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.8 I ever] ‘I’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.9 on a] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.12 South] ‘outh’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">4.4 some] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi> : 2.13 ‘not’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Fox’s wife Harriet had died on 19 March 1842.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref> was born 25 September 1843.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>