<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7720">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>   [before 27 April 1871]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15651</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7720 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7720.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7720.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 165</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 27 April 1871, pp. 502–3 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature 3 1871: 502</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1871-04-26">[before 27 Apr 1871]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3491.xml">Nature</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Replies to Francis Galton’s paper on tranfusing blood between rabbits to test Pangenesis [<hi rend="italic">Proc. R. Soc. Lond.</hi> 19 (1871): 393–40]. FG’s conclusion that his experiments prove Pangenesis to be false is "a little hasty", since CD had never maintained that gemmules in the blood formed any part of his hypothesis.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Proc. R. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Galton, Francis 1871</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In a paper, read March 30, 1871, before the Royal Society, and just published in the Proceedings, Mr. Galton gives the results of his interesting experiments on the inter-transfusion of the blood of distinct varieties of rabbits.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> These experiments were undertaken to test whether there was any truth in my provisional hypothesis of Pangenesis. Mr. Galton, in recapitulating “the cardinal points,” says that the gemmules are supposed “to swarm in the blood.” He enlarges on this head, and remarks, “Under Mr. Darwin’s theory, the gemmules in each individual must, therefore, be looked upon as entozoa of his blood,” &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Now, in the chapter on Pangenesis in my “Variation of Animals and Plants under Domestication,” I have not said one word about the blood, or about any fluid proper to any circulating system.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It is, indeed, obvious that the presence of gemmules in the blood can form no necessary part of my hypothesis; for I refer in illustration of it to the lowest animals, such as the Protozoa, which do not possess blood or any vessels; and I refer to plants in which the fluid, when present in the vessels, cannot be considered as true blood.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The fundamental laws of growth, reproduction, inheritance, &amp;c., are so closely similar throughout the whole organic kingdom, that the means by which the gemmules (assuming for the moment their existence) are diffused through the body, would probably be the same in all beings; therefore the means can hardly be diffusion through the blood. Nevertheless, when I first heard of Mr. Galton’s experiments, I did not sufficiently reflect on the subject, and saw not the difficulty of believing in the presence of gemmules in the blood.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have said (Variation, &amp;c., vol. ii., p. 379) that “the gemmules in each organism must be thoroughly diffused; nor does this seem improbable, considering their minuteness, and the steady circulation of fluids throughout the body.”<ref target="#foot.f7"/> But when I used these latter words and other similar ones, I presume that I was thinking of the diffusion of the gemmules through the tissues, or from cell to cell, independently of the presence of the vessels,—as in the remarkable experiments by Dr. Bence Jones, in which chemical elements absorbed by the stomach were detected in the course of some minutes in the crystalline lens of the eye;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> or again as in the repeated loss of colour and its recovery after a few days by the hair, in the singular case of a neuralgic lady recorded by Mr. Paget.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Nor can it be objected that the gemmules could not pass through tissues or cell-walls, for the contents of each pollen-grain have to pass through the coats, both of the pollen-tube and embryonic sack. I may add, with respect to the passage of fluids through membrane, that they pass from cell to cell in the absorbing hairs of the roots of living plants at a rate, as I have myself observed under the microscope, which is truly surprising.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>When, therefore, Mr. Galton concludes from the fact that rabbits of one variety, with a large proportion of the blood of another variety in their veins, do not produce mongrelised offspring, that the hypothesis of Pangenesis is false, it seems to me that his conclusion is a little hasty. His words are, “I have now made experiments of transfusion and cross circulation on a large scale in rabbits, and have arrived at definite results, negativing, in my opinion, beyond all doubt the truth of the doctrine of Pangenesis.”<ref target="#foot.f11"/> If Mr. Galton could have proved that the reproductive elements were contained in the blood of the higher animals, and were merely separated or collected by the reproductive glands, he would have made a most important physiological discovery. As it is, I think every one will admit that his experiments are extremely curious, and that he deserves the highest credit for his ingenuity and perseverance. But it does not appear to me that Pangenesis has, as yet, received its death blow; though, from presenting so many vulnerable points, its life is always in jeopardy; and this is my excuse for having said a few words in its defence.</p>
<p>Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the publication of this letter in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> on 27 April 1871.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Galton</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1871</ref>. For more on Galton’s experiments to test CD’s hypothesis of pangenesis, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7432.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Galton, 9 January 1871</ref> and n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD quotes <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1871</ref>, p. 394.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD discusses pangenesis in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 372–404.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 376, 379–80.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Galton had been consulting CD about his experiments on pangenesis since 1869 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Galton, 11 December 1869</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7717.xml">letter of 25 April 1871</ref>, Galton had cited this passage as one source of confusion.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Bence Jones</ref> discussed these experiments in Jones 1865a and 1865b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3643.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Paget</ref> gave this case in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6139.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paget 1853</ref>, 1: 46; CD cited it in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, 2: 374.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD refers to his work on <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 17 October [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1871</ref>, p. 395.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>