<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11334">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. E. Hart   27 January 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17563</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11334 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11334.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11334.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 109</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 109</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2146.xml">Hart, W. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Kilderry, Donegal</placeName>
                <date when="1878-01-27">27 Jan 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Offers observations on pollination.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Kilderry | (Near Londonderry) | C<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Donegal</placeName>
                    <date>January 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1878</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Since you have done me the honor of referring in your latest work, “On the Different Forms of Flowers”, p. 301, to certain observations of mine on the irregularity of the distribution of the two forms of Nepeta glechoma, will you kindly allow me to call your attention to an error in your citation? “<hi rend="underline">Kilderry</hi>”, not <hi rend="underline">Kilkenny</hi>, is merely the name of my father’s residence. The nearest town is Derry. Since the date of my communication to “Nature” I have only been able to find within several miles a solitary hermaphrodite plant of the ground-ivy.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It would seem therefore that the female form, which is not at all rare (and its prevalence cannot be due here to any lack of moisture!), must for a very long time have propagated itself solely by root.</p>
<p>Something parallel is presented by Carduus arvensis,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and teaches the danger of overvaluing the efficacy of insects in crossing the flowers of plants growing at not very great distances apart. There are near this two large patches of this thistle, male and female, separated by a distance of much less than a mile, which throughout the summer form a centre of attraction for hosts of insects of many different kinds; yet I have never been able to discover the production of a single seed— If agriculture permitted it, these two patches would probably spread until they meet each other, and their guests would then become useful to the flowers; but at present, while they are so bountifully supplied by the flowers of one patch, they have little temptation to leave it in search of any others— Under the name of “Cirsium arvense, L.” D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. H. Müller has described (“Befruchtung der Blumen”, p. 387)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> an hermaphrodite species, capable of self fertilisation in the absence of insects. Is there here some confusion of synonymy, or a difference of habit in the same species in the two countries?</p>
<p>Axell again (“Fanerogama Växternas Befruktning”, p. 41, 106) compares the structure of the flowers of Viola palustris to that of V. tricolor. V. palustris of British authors has flowers of the type of V. odorata or canina.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Müller (“Befruchtung”, p. 399) has remarked that Senecio vulgaris<ref target="#foot.f5"/> is scarcely ever visited by insects, but is almost wholly dependent on its self fertility for the production of seed. Once only during bright sunshine I have had the satisfaction of seeing a rank patch of groundsel with its flowers crowded by many species of Diptera and one or two of Hemiptera. Is not this plant also capable of being crossed by other agencies, for instance by the wind striking the flower-heads together, or by animals rubbing against them in passing?</p>
<p>Another example of the need for long continued observation at all hours before pronouncing a flower wholly unattractive to insects is afforded by Oxalis acetosella.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> As far as I have yet been able to see, the only regular visitor of this species is a small leaf-cutting bee, which is busy for hardly more than an hour at mid-day: at all other times the flowers seem to be quite neglected.</p>
<p>Hoping you will pardon the liberty I have taken in thus venturing to address you, | I beg leave to subscribe myself | Your most sincere admirer and unworthy disciple | W. E. Hart <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        <div type="annotations">
            <note>1.1 Since … Derry. 1.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
            <note>2.4 separated … mile,] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi>; <hi rend="italic">cross in margin pencil</hi></note>
            <note>4.3 satisfaction … Diptera 4.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
            <note>5.1 Another … hours] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
        </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 301, CD referred to Hart’s comments on <hi rend="italic">Nepeta glechoma</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Glechoma hederacea</hi>, ground ivy) published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 26 June 1873, p. 162. Hart had said that all the plants that he examined at Kilderry were female, while all those he examined at Bath, in Somerset, were hermaphrodites, and at Hertford he found both forms, but mostly hermaphrodites. Hart’s father was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8269.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Vaughan Hart</ref>. CD had written Kilkenny rather than Kilderry; the mistake was not corrected in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9500.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi> 2d ed.</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Carduus arvensis</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Cirsium arvense</hi> (creeping thistle).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johan Severin Axell</ref>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_262.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Axell 1869</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Viola palustris</hi> is the marsh violet; <hi rend="italic">V. tricolor</hi> is heart’s-ease; <hi rend="italic">V. odorata</hi> is the sweet violet; <hi rend="italic">V. canina</hi> is the dog violet.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Common groundsel.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Wood sorrel.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>