<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-170">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Susan Darwin   12 May [– 2 June] 1832</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5016</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-170 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-170.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-170.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">JU 2 1832</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 96</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 96</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1239.xml">Darwin, S. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Maer and Shrewsbury</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1832-05-12" notAfter="1832-06-02">12 May [– 2 June] 1832 </date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>News from Maer and Shrewsbury of family, friends, and reports of reactions to CD’s first letters.</p>
            <p>Sedgwick suggests he look for fossils in gravel banks of rivers.</p>
            <p>Fanny Owen is married to R. M. Biddulph. Reform Bill prospects.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">gravel banks</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_440">Biddulph, R. M. (b)</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3619">Owen, F. M. (a)</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4276">Sedgwick, Adam</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Maer</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">rivers</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shrewsbury</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">marriage</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">news</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00421_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00421_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="96:1r" xml:id="i421">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00421.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00421_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00421.dzi" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="96:1v" xml:id="i422">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00422.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00422_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00422.dzi" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="96:2r" xml:id="i423">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00423.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00423_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00423.dzi" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="96:2v" xml:id="i424">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00424.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00424_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00204-000-00424.dzi" width="5192px" height="8482px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maer.</placeName>
                    <date>May 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1832.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles.—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. of May we received your <hi rend="underline">last</hi> written letter from S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Salvador, which all the house rejoiced over most heartily: the happy account you give of yourself and all your enjoyments in the tropical world far exceeded what we most hoped for you.— Your letter has been read very often over to Papa (like M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Bates)<ref target="#foot.f1"/> and I think he never can again for shame make his old speech of <hi rend="underline">the gaol</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">the ship</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> now he has heard what a comfortable home you find it.— Nancy &amp; Edward were as much pleased as any of us to have tidings of you: Erasmus had been making some very bruttal jokes to the former a week before: “how that you were lost &amp; we kept it from her” so the poor old soul very nearly cried when she heard you were really alive &amp; well.— Papa was much interested by your miserable account of the sea sickness you had endured, &amp; not a little proud of his prescription of the Raisins answering so well. I think he should publish such a discovery for the benefit of all such sufferers.—</p>
<p>The Letter you wrote by the Lyra came to us the day after we had your other letter which was very odd as the dates were so different but I suppose the Winds had kept all the Ships out together. We have sent your letters to Erasmus who is to shew them to Charlotte <hi rend="underline">Langton</hi> &amp; then the family here must see it for many enquiries they are making about you &amp; many kind messages they desire me to send you.— The day after yr news came I had to write several despatches, first to Eyton copying out all your messages which I hope may have the desired effect of instantly starting him accross the Atlantic, which I fully expect he will do some time he talks so much about it: &amp; whenever I have an opportunity I shall certainly urge him on.— Major Bayley &amp; Woodhouse too I had to send the joyful intelligence, as they all begged to hear the first news of you, so I can promise you my dear Charley you are not att all forgotten amongst any of us, &amp; I am very glad to hear the warm climate agrees so well with all your affectionate feelings.— We were very sorry for yr disappointment at the Canaries but I hope Cape Verd Islands comforted you: Master Parky went through the whole of yr voyage as a Geographical lesson: so Marianne made profit as well as pleasure fr your letter.—</p>
<p>Catherine wrote last month to Monte Video, where Caroline sent her March letter also.— I am in hopes we shall before very long hear from you again in answer to the letters you will find at Rio, &amp; I hope then you will give us some more directions for our future letters as I think it is doubtful whether this ever reaches you.— I cannot help thinking how lucky it was you took that Tour with Professor Sedgwick as Geology seems to be so great a pleasure now.— Poor Arthur Owen sails this week I believe to Madras, he wrote me a little note f<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. London where he had been seeing his Ship very often It is the Abberton: there are only 2 young Ladies amongst the Passengers which I think he regrets as a very short allowance amongst all the <hi rend="underline">Writers</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f3"/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Owen is with him in London now preparing his Outfit: &amp; Arthur expected he would be in such a bustle that by some mistake he would go in his place to India.— Francis wanted very much to go out with Arthur &amp; I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. think it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be by far the best scheme if they can get any situation for such a pickle as he is.— Caroline Owen is staying in town with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Williams: so poor Fanny who has very much lost her former <hi rend="underline">housemaid</hi> spirits is left all alone with the M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. in the Forest.— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Biddulph has at last settled to have an Entail which has caused all this delay, &amp; the marriage will take place as soon as M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Owen returns.— I am now spending a fortnight at Maer which I find sadly changed: Charlotte’s loss is quite irreparable! &amp; Frank being gone too, makes the party appear much smaller.— Uncle Jos talks much of poverty his Children having taken off so much money with their Marriages:— Fanny Wedgwood has a flirtation in han〈d〉 with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Paget Moseley (brother to Franks wife) but as I hear he is a very dull man, I have no f〈ear〉 of Fanny accepting him.— Politics are much t〈alked〉 of here, as the Ministers are gone out, not being able to get the King to make Peers to carry the Reform, &amp; of course that interests this public spirited family very deeply.— The week before I left home M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Edward Holland on their bridal Tour came &amp; spent 3 days with us.— It was rather strange their liking to come so directly after their marriage, particularly as little M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. H. is very shy.— however Papa joked away with them famously &amp; made them very merry &amp; easy.— We heard such dismal accounts of the Bride from Erasmus who is a most fastidious mortal: that we were very agreeably surprised to find her rather pretty &amp; a nice little creature all together &amp; particularly well suited to Edward who seemed very proud of her.—</p>
<p>I am come home from Maer, &amp; I find Eyton has been calling in consequence of our hearing from you: but he is going immediately into Germany for the next 3 months with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. F Hope on a Beetle expedition.— Professor Sedgwick dropped in here last week on his way into Wales: he talked much about you &amp; sent his kind regards, &amp; begged you might be told to examine the gravel banks of small rivers for animal remains.— We have seen to day in the papers a sad piece of news: that Sir James Mackintosh is dead: he had been ill about a week, &amp; died the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of May:— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Hensleigh Wedgwood will be obliged to retrench very much after losing £1200 a year.— Lord Grey is come into Office again so the Reform Bill will certainly pass triumphantly. It is a great pity poor Sir James has died before he has finished his History of England.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Papa desires I will give you his most affectionate love &amp; many thanks for your very nice letter which has given him a great deal of pleasure.— When I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Owen how happy you were tears came into his eyes with pleasure I am sure he considers you one of his own children.— Fanny was married on the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. of May to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Biddulph. I have not room here for any particulars, but Caroline will fill her next letter with them.</p>
<p>God bless you my very dear Charley. All our Loves &amp; I am | Ever yr affecti | Susan E Darwin</p>
<p>We have written once every Month since you left us. All directed to Rio Janeiro, till 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. of April, &amp; then M Video M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Owen has also written to Rio Janeiro.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Widow of the Vicar of Highbury, in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jane Austen’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> (1816).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The italicised phrase echoes an aphorism of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2589.xml">Samuel Johnson</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_808.xml">Boswell 1791</ref>, 2: 21): ‘A ship is worse than a gaol. There is, in a gaol, better air, better company, better conveniency of every kind; and a ship has the additional disadvantage of being in danger.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Writer: ‘A clerk in the service of the former East India Company’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5113.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mackintosh 1830–2</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>