<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8303F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. W. Bennett   [before 16 November 1871]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21593</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8303F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8303F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8303F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>) 13 (1873): 152 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Journal of the Linnean Society (Botany) 13 (1873): 152</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <date notBefore="1871-11-01" notAfter="1871-11-14">[before 16 Nov 1871]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_389.xml">Bennett, A. W.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discussed observations made in 1863 of <hi rend="italic">Impatiens</hi> pollen and humble-bees.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Impatiens</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1957">Gray, Asa</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am glad you have drawn attention to the difference in the bud-state of the perfect and imperfect flowers; for I remember, many years ago, objecting to Asa Gray that he considered the imperfect flowers (not, I think, in the case of <hi rend="underline">Impatiens</hi>) arrested buds, and I maintained that their structure had been specially modified for their functions.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> From observations by myself in 1863, I find I was struck with the small size of the anthers, and the very small quantity of pollen. The grains are of the same diameter as in the perfect flowers, but they appeared to be more unequal in size. I distinctly saw pollen-grains protruding from the grains <hi rend="underline">whilst within the anthers</hi>, and penetrating the stigma. I cannot believe that I could have overlooked the facts of the anthers not dehiscing. I do not mention in my notes that the pollen-grains are tied together by threads, as I do in the case of the pollen of the perfect flowers. I speak of the nectary in the cleistogenous flowers as a mere rudiment.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> From the fact of the nectary in the perfect flowers containing nectar, and from the pollen-grains being tied together by threads, I cannot doubt that they are crossed by insects, and I am almost certain that they are frequently visited by humble-bees. The structure of the flowers seems to me so well adapted for crossing, that I expected that the perfect flowers would be sterile without the aid of insects. In this I was quite wrong, as the perfect flowers, when protected, produced pods.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Eleven such pods from perfect flowers, <hi rend="underline">spontaneously</hi> self-fertilized, yielded on an average 3.45 seeds. I carefully brushed away the pollen from some of the perfect flowers, and fertilized them with pollen from a <hi rend="underline">distinct</hi> plant, but got only three pods, containing, to my surprise, only 2, 2, and 1 seed. I attributed this poverty at the time to this plant probably requiring repeated doses of pollen, as is certainly sometimes the case.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the date that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_389.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred William Bennett’s</ref> paper ‘On the floral structure of <hi rend="italic">Impatiens fulva</hi>’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_549.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bennett 1871</ref>) was read. CD’s comments, probably based on a manuscript version of the paper, were included in the published version.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> described small, unopened, ‘imperfect’ flowers in ‘Dimorphism in the genitalia of flowers’ (A. Gray 1862d, p. 419); the condition later became known as cleistogamy and plants bearing such flowers were called cleistogenous. In a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3830.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Gray of 26[–7] November [1862]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10), CD had argued, ‘the state of corolla, of stigma &amp; pollen-grains [in cleistogamic flowers] is different from state of parts in bud; that they are in a condition of special modification’. Gray had replied, ‘In Violets &amp; Impatiens, Lespedeza, &amp;c &amp;c—I believe that the condition is not so much “special modification” as it is <hi rend="italic">arrest of development</hi>’ (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3882.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 29 December 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s observations on the anthers and pollen of both perfect (CD uses ‘perfect’ to describe open or chasmogamic flowers) and imperfect (cleistogamic) flowers of <hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-me-tangere</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>), made on 22 June 1863, are in DAR 111: A41.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Notes made by CD in July 1864 on the production of seed by protected and unprotected flowers of <hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-me-tangere</hi> are in DAR 49: 105.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>