<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6483">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Fritz Müller   28 November 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1690</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6483 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6483.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6483.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 453</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 353</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Loan MS 10 no 26)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Loan MS 10</collection>
                    <idno>26</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1868-11-28">28 Nov 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Delay in translating <hi rend="italic">Für Darwin</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Comments on plan to repeat CD’s experiments on illegitimate offspring.</p>
            <p>FM’s observations on stridulation.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fur Darwin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Müller, J. F. T. 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Nov 28 | 1868</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You end y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> letter of Sep. 9 by saying that it is a very dull one; indeed you make a very great mistake, for it abounds with interesting facts &amp; thoughts.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Your account of the tameness of the birds which apparently have wandered from the interior, is very curious.</p>
<p>But I must begin on another subject: there has been a great &amp; very vexatious, but unavoidable delay in the publication of your book. Prof. Huxley agrees with me that Mr Dallas is by far the best translator, but he is much overworked &amp; had not quite finished the translation about a fortnight ago.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> He has charge of the Museum at York &amp; is now trying to get the situation of Assistant Sec. at the Geolog. Soc; &amp; all the canvassing &amp;c, &amp; his removal, if he gets the place, will I fear cause more than a month’s delay in the completion of the translation; &amp; this I very much regret.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I am particularly glad to hear that you intend to repeat my experiments on illegitimate offspring, for no one’s observations can be trusted until repeated.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> You will find the work very troublesome, owing to the death of plants &amp; accidents of all kinds. Some dimorphic plants will probably prove too sterile for you to raise offspring; &amp; others too fertile for much sterility to be expected in their offspring. Primula is bad on account of the difficulty of deciding which seeds may be considered as good. I have earnestly wished that some one would repeat these experiments, but I feared that years w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> elapse before any one w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> take the trouble. I received y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> paper on Bignonia in Bot. Zeit. &amp; it interested me much.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am convinced that if you can prove that a plant growing in a distant place under different conditions is more effective in fertilization than one growing close by, you will make a great step in the essence of sexual reproduction.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Prof. Asa Gray &amp; D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker have been staying here &amp; oddly enough, they knew nothing of y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> paper on Martha; tho’ the former was aware of the curious movements of the stamens, but so little understood the structure of the plant that he thought it was probably a dimorphic species. Accordingly I shewed them your drawings &amp; gave them a little lecture &amp; they were perfectly charmed with your account.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Hildebrand has repeated his exp. on potatoes &amp; so have I, but this summer with no result.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I am particularly obliged to you for y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> observations on the stridulation of the 2 sexes of Lamellicorns: I begin to fear that I am completely in error, owing to that common cause viz mistaking at first individual variability for sexual difference.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I go on working at sexual selection, &amp; tho’ never idle I am able to do so little work each day that I make very slow progress.</p>
<p>I will sow the seed of the Chinese Cabbage &amp; look out for the very curious montrosity.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I knew from Azara about the young of the tapir being striped, &amp; about young deer being spotted; I have often reflected on this subject, &amp; know not what to conclude about the loss of the stripes &amp; spots.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>From the Geograph. Distribution of the striped &amp; unstriped species of Equus there seems to be something very mysterious about the loss of stripes; &amp; I cannot persuade myself that the common ass has lost its stripes owing to being rendered more conspicuous from having stripes &amp; thus exposed to danger.</p>
<p>Believe me my dear Sir | yours very sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The final portion of Müller’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 9 September 1868</ref> has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Sweetland Dallas</ref>, and Dallas’s translation of Müller’s book <hi rend="italic">Für Darwin</hi> (F. Müller 1864; W. S. Dallas trans. 1869). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6481.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. S. Dallas, 27 November 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his letter of 27 November 1868, Dallas informed CD he had been elected to the post of assistant secretary of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>. Dallas had been curator of the museum of the Yorkshire Philosophical Society.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 9 September 1868</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD refers to F. Müller 1868b, which appeared in the 25 September 1868 issue of <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Müller reported that he was surprised at the lessened fertility when he pollinated plants using pollen from other plants growing close by. He speculated that these plants might have grown from seeds of the same ‘mother plant’ and that this close relationship had lessened the fertility of the offspring (F. Müller 1868b, p. 629). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 306, CD cited Müller’s results and agreed with his conclusions about the lessened fertility of closely related plants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Gray and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> visited CD between 24 and 30 October 1868 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). CD refers to F. Müller 1866, where Müller described the mechanism by which <hi rend="italic">Martha fragrans</hi> prevented self-pollination. The paper included diagrams of the flowers and the ‘catapult mechanism’ of the stamens (F. Müller 1866, facing p. 129). CD discussed the plant in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 5, refering to it as <hi rend="italic">Posoqueria fragrans.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Martha fragrans</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Posoqueria fragrans</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Posoqueria latifolia</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">latifolia</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Friedrich Hildebrand, 18 May 1868</ref> and n. 1, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6444.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from M. T. Masters, 2 November 1868</ref>, n. 1. For CD’s own experiments with potatoes, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6459F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Friedrich Hildebrand, 14 November [1868]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 9 September 1868</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Müller had evidently sent CD some seeds of a <hi rend="italic">Brassica</hi>, but not all of his discussion of the plant has been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 9 September 1868</ref> and n. 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD refers to Félix Azara and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Azara 1809</ref>, 1: 247. CD scored the relevant passage in his copy, which is now in the Darwin Library–CUL, and noted on a separate sheet pasted into the back ‘young Tapirs striped’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 26–8). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 9 September 1868</ref> and n. 15.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>