<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13245">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>   13 July [1881]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15672</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13245 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13245.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13245.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 230</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 21 July 1881, p. 257 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature, 21 July 1881, p. 257</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1881-07-13">13 July [1881]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3491.xml">Nature</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Communicates two cases of inheritance reported by J. P. Bishop [in <hi rend="doubleUnderline">13137</hi>]. The work of E. Brown-Séquard has demonstrated that effects of injuries can be inherited ["Hereditary transmission of an epileptiform affection accidentally produced", <hi rend="italic">Proc. R. Soc. Lond.</hi> 10 (1860): 297–8]. E. Dupuy has sent CD a still more remarkable case.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">13137</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmission, ‘taking after’</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">use and disuse, acquired characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-10" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-09" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-23" status="editorResponseCompleted">Responded <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Down.]</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">Inheritance</hi></p> 
<p><hi rend="smallCaps">The</hi> tendency in any new character or modification to reappear in the offspring at the same age at which it first appeared in the parents or in one of the parents, is of so much importance in reference to the diversified characters proper to the larvæ of many animals at successive ages, that almost any fresh instance is worth putting on record. I have given many such instances under the term of “inheritance at corresponding ages.”<ref target="#foot.f2"/> No doubt the fact of variations being sometimes inherited at an earlier age than that at which they first appeared—a form of inheritance which has been called by some naturalists “accelerated inheritance”—is almost equally important, for, as was shown in the first edition of the “Origin of Species”, all the leading facts of embryology can be explained by these two forms of inheritance, combined with the fact of many variations arising at a somewhat late stage of life.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> A good instance of inheritance at a corresponding age has lately been communicated to me by Mr. J. P. Bishop of Perry, Wyoming, N.Y., United States:—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The hair of a gentleman of American birth (whose name I suppress) began to turn grey when he was twenty years old, and in the course of four or five years became perfectly white. He is now seventy-five years old, and retains plenty of hair on his head. His wife had dark hair, which, at the age of seventy, was only sprinkled with grey. They had four children, all daughters, now grown to womanhood.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The eldest daughter began to turn grey at about twenty, and her hair at thirty was perfectly white. A second daughter began to be grey at the same age, and her hair is now almost white. The two remaining daughters have not inherited the peculiarity. Two of the maternal aunts of the father of these children “began to turn grey at an early age, so that by middle life their hair was white.” Hence the gentleman in question spoke of the change of colour of his own hair as “a family peculiarity.”</p>
<p>Mr. Bishop has also given me a case of inheritance of another kind, namely, of a peculiarity which arose, as it appears, from an injury, accompanied by a diseased state of the part. This latter fact seems to be an important element in all such cases, as I have elsewhere endeavoured to show. A gentleman,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> when a boy, had the skin of both thumbs badly cracked from exposure to cold, combined with some skin disease. His thumbs swelled greatly, and remained in this state for a long time. When they healed they were misshapen, and the nails ever afterwards were singularly narrow, short, and thick. This gentleman had four children, of whom the eldest, Sarah, had both her thumbs and nails like her father’s; the third child, also a daughter, had one thumb similarly deformed. The two other children, a boy and girl, were normal.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The daughter, Sarah, had four children, of whom the eldest and the third, both daughters, had their two thumbs deformed; the other two children, a boy and girl, were normal. The great-grandchildren of this gentleman were all normal. Mr. Bishop believes that the old gentleman was correct in attributing the state of his thumbs to cold aided by skin disease, as he positively asserted that his thumbs were not originally misshapen, and there was no record of any previous inherited tendency of the kind in his family. He had six brothers and sisters, who lived to have families, some of them very large families, and in none was there any trace of deformity in their thumbs.</p>
<p>Several more or less closely analogous cases have been recorded; but until within a recent period every one naturally felt much doubt whether the effects of a mutilation or injury were ever really inherited, as accidental coincidences would almost certainly occasionally occur. The subject, however, now wears a totally different aspect, since Dr. Brown-Séquard’s famous experiments proving that guinea-pigs of the next generation were affected by operations on certain nerves.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Mr. Eugène Dupuy of San Francisco, California, has likewise found, as he informs me, that with these animals “lesions of nerve-trunks are almost invariably transmitted.” For instance, “the effects of sections of the cervical sympathetic on the eyes are reproduced in the young, also epilepsy (as described by my eminent friend and master, Dr. Brown-Séquard) when induced by lesions of the sciatic nerve.” Mr. Dupuy has communicated to me a still more remarkable case of the transmitted effects on the brain from an injury to a nerve; but I do not feel at liberty to give this case, as Mr. Dupuy intends to pursue his researches, and will, as I hope, publish the results.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p><hi rend="smallCaps">Charles Darwin</hi> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">July 13</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the date of publication of this letter in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 448, 455, 480; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 12, 2: 397, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 184, 211, 212, 222, 236–7, 304.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, pp. 447–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_458.xml">Irving Prescott Bishop</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13137.xml">letter from I. P. Bishop, 24 April 1881</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The gentleman was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9221.xml">Ebenezer Backus Jones</ref>; his wife was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9222.xml">Lucy Ann</ref> and his daughters were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9224.xml">Julia Backus Beach</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9225.xml">Isabella Beman</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9226.xml">Helen Louise Knickerbacker</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9223.xml">Katharine Judd Platt</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The gentleman was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9227.xml">Abraham Marcy</ref>, Bishop’s grandfather.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9230.xml">Sarah Anne Thomas</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9229.xml">Maria M. Johnson</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9231.xml">Esther Mary Bishop</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9228.xml">Newton A. Marcy</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_674.xml">Charles Édouard Brown-Séquard</ref> had induced epileptic convulsions in guinea pigs by means of surgical operations; he claimed that the epileptic tendency was transmitted to offspring (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1000.xml">Brown-Séquard 1860</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8250.xml">Dupuy</ref>’s letters to CD have not been found, but see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 26, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11622.xml">letter to Eugène Dupuy, 21 July 1878</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10432.xml">Dupuy 1877</ref>. Dupuy summarised his researches in this area in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9830.xml">Dupuy 1890</ref>.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>