<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3984">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From S. P. Woodward   14 February 1863</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11126</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3984 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3984.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3984.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp inc †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 154</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 154</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5239.xml">Woodward, S. P.</persName>
                <placeName>British Museum</placeName>
                <date when="1863-02-14">14 Feb 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Points out some errata in the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses the factors producing the shape of the cells of the honeycomb.</p>
            <p>Reports case of two varieties of musk-rat that behave very differently but are, according to Waterhouse, the same.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bee</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">musk-rat</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4972">Waterhouse, G. R.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nesting and other home-making or web-making behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>British Museum.</placeName>
                    <date>Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 14/63</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been unable to find the Review of your ‘Orchids’ which I promised to send—or at least the <hi rend="underline">copy of it</hi> just then given me by one of my colleagues— But if you will not mind the trouble of returning it I will send a rough proof—&amp; also (by way of complement) another article <hi rend="underline">contra Scottos</hi>—which it is to be hoped they enjoyed, altho’ not nearly equal to their deserts.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>When I first read the ‘Origin’ I made a list of errata &amp; <hi rend="underline">objections</hi>—but found them not worth sending.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have only seen the <hi rend="underline">first ed</hi>. &amp; you must have long since corrected such errata as p. 49 <hi rend="underline">Primula acuulis</hi> or p. 29 where “Herefords” were spoken of as if they were “Short-horns”—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Did you notice when you came to see the Assyrian relics, the little bas-relief of the Tibetan mastiff?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Its character is well represented—in contrast with 〈the〉 Syrian hunting dogs—</p>
<p>There was an obscure expression at p. 429 where you speak of no “single insect of a new order being found in Australia”— If any new order (i.e unknown elsewhere) should be f〈ound〉 there, it would surely be represented by <hi rend="underline">many specie</hi>〈<hi rend="underline">s</hi>.〉 The phrase appears to require inversion—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Respecting that endless problem—the honeycomb! Mr Walter Mitchell objects that if the form of the cell results only from the necessity of the case (as I hold) then the chances are a million to one against the result we get—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The cell of the humble bee is elliptical—&amp; the chances are that the bottom of the honey bees’ cell will be elliptical—or more or less obtuse than it is now. But I cannot see the force of this objection as the chances are the same <hi rend="underline">against</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">any</hi> form you may please to imagine—&amp; not more against the true sphere than the spheroid— The shape &amp; proportions of the honey bee being what they are it must strike a circle—or excavate a segment of a sphere— If it were more acute or more obtuse it would make something different—but I can’t see any reason why it shouldn’t just as soon happen to be— what it is—</p>
<p>Mr Mitchell could understand the form of the bees’ cell <hi rend="underline">if</hi> wax had a <hi rend="underline">hexagonal</hi> cleavage like <hi rend="underline">graphite</hi> (which is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">C</hi>’.) But according to the accepted doctrine it <hi rend="underline">must</hi> have a cleavage (whether apparent to us or not) at right angles to the incidence of pressure—&amp; that (according to my notion) will be such as to give hexagonal cleavage—</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">six lines excised</hi>〉</p>
<p>If you come to a — edn. I hope you will erase all mention of Buckman’s exp<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi>. at Cirencester—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> it will be better not to mention his name than give it with the admission made in ed. 1. I went to see <hi rend="underline">my old</hi> “B.G.” at Cisseter under Buckman’s managem<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, &amp; took care to examine <hi rend="underline">it alone</hi>—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> “What I saw there I will not declare”—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> But it will be sufficient to say that one of the students (who owed the Prof. a grudge) confessed to R. Tomes (<hi rend="underline">vespertilio</hi>)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> that <hi rend="doubleUnderline">he</hi> himself had mixed the seeds intended for experiment in the Botanic Garden—</p>
<p>Have you met Mr Lord? the traveller in Oregon—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> He brought up the other day, (just before you came) two varieties of Musk rat— One builds houses out in the water, like the Beaver— the other burrows in the bank &amp; only makes sub-aqueous <hi rend="underline">runs</hi>— Yet Waterhouse would not admit any difference in the animals!<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">six lines excised</hi>〉 roots chiefly, are not nearly so formidable as described— Whereas the same species on the East flank of the Rocky mtns feeding on Bisons (left by the Indian Hunters) become large &amp; heavy &amp; very savage.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Yours sincerely | S. P. Woodward <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Cha<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I have … p. 49 2.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>2.3 p. 29 … “Short-horns”— 2.4] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 There was … <hi rend="italic">specie</hi>〈<hi rend="italic">s</hi>.〉 3.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 If you … animals! 7.4] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 roots … savage. 8.3] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘Musk Rat | <hi rend="italic">2 vars in Habits</hi> | <hi rend="italic">Bees   different Habits</hi> | Buffaloes | W. of Rocky Mountains’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The review and article to which Woodward refers have not been identified. While he was in London between 4 and 14 February 1863, CD visited the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (see n. 4, below), where Woodward worked as an assistant in the department of geology and mineralogy (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD sent Woodward a presentation copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the first edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (1859), CD referred in error to the primrose and cowslip, respectively, as ‘Primula veris and elatior’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 49). This should have read ‘Primula vulgaris and veris’. <hi rend="italic">P. acaulis</hi> (‘acuulis’ is a misspelling) is English primrose. CD corrected his mistake in the second edition (1860). Concerning the Hereford breed of cattle, CD had written: ‘Ask, as I have asked, a celebrated raiser of Hereford cattle, whether his cattle might not have descended from long-horns, and he will laugh you to scorn’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 29). The sentence remained unaltered in subsequent editions.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD visited the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> while he was staying in London between 4 and 14 February (see ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, Appendix II), and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3978.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Frederick Smith, 11 February 1863</ref>). The reference is to an Assyrian bas-relief, dated <hi rend="italic">circa</hi> 640 <hi rend="smallCaps">B.C.</hi>, taken from the tomb of the son of Esar-haddon, king of Assyria. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>, CD stated that he had seen drawings and clay models of the antiquity in the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref>, adding that there was some doubt as to whether the dog depicted was a ‘Thibetan mastiff’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 17, n. 4). An illustration of the bas-relief is given in Nott and Gliddon 1854, p. 392, an annotated copy of which is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 603–6). CD used the evidence of the representation of dogs in antiquities to argue that the different breeds existing in modern times were of extreme antiquity and multiple origin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 33).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The phrase referred to occurs in the following sentence (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 429): <quote type="quote"> As showing how few the higher groups are in number, and how widely spread they are throughout the world, the fact is striking, that the discovery of Australia has not added a single insect belonging to a new order; and that in the vegetable kingdom … it has added only two or three orders of small size. </quote> This sentence was modified in subsequent editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, but not in the form suggested by Woodward. CD changed ‘order’ to ‘class’ in the second edition, and in the third edition, ‘only two or three orders’ is replaced by ‘only two or three families’. There were further slight changes to the sentence in the fourth, fifth, and sixth editions (see Peckham ed. 1959, p. 670).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3346.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walter Mitchell</ref> was a clergyman and natural philosopher with a special interest in crystallography (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_144.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Alum. Cantab.</hi></ref>). CD discussed bee-cell construction in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 224–35. In his discussion, CD sought to demonstrate that the hexagonal geometry of the honeycomb constructed by hive-bees could be explained by reference to simple instincts and natural selection. CD made several minor changes to the text in subsequent editions, but did not discuss the point raised by Mitchell (see Peckham ed. 1959, pp. 402–12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Buckman</ref> was professor of geology and botany at the Royal Agricultural College, Cirencester (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 10, discussing the effect of external conditions as a cause of variation, CD described ‘extremely valuable’ research by Buckman that appeared to show that species of the same genus, differing widely in appearance in their natural habitat, became indistinguishable from one another when grown under the same conditions in experimental plots (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1046.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Buckman 1857</ref>). CD had held the ‘deepest &amp; most lively interest’ in these experiments (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2151.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to James Buckman, 4 October [1857]</ref>). There is an annotated copy of Buckman’s paper in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. The reference to Buckman’s work was removed from the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Peckham ed. 1959, p. 82).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Between 1845 and 1848, Woodward occupied the chair of geology and natural history at the newly established Royal Agricultural College, Cirencester (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8482.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Woodward 1881</ref>, pp. 286–90). ‘B.G.’ is an abbreviation for botanic garden.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The source of the quotation has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Fisher Tomes</ref> had published many papers on the Vespertilionidae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Royal Society catalogue of scientific papers</hi></ref>); <hi rend="italic">Vespertilio</hi> is a genus of bats.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">In 1858, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2993.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Keast Lord</ref> was appointed naturalist to the British North American boundary commission sent to British Columbia and Washington Territory (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). Lord travelled through Oregon in May 1860 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4866.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lord 1866</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Lord displayed two specimens of muskrat at a meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zoological Society of London</ref> on 24 March 1863, claiming that although the structural differences were trivial, his new species <hi rend="italic">Fiber osoyooensis</hi> differed from the well-known <hi rend="italic">F. zibethecus</hi> in habit, size, colour, and distribution, and therefore was a separate species, not a well-marked variety of the same species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4865.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lord 1863</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4972.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Robert Waterhouse</ref> was keeper of geology in the department of natural history at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> and a vice-president of the Zoological Society (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1863, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">British imperial calendar</hi></ref> 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">This may be a reference to the prairie wolf; in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 22, CD states: <quote type="quote"> North America is inhabited by a second kind of wolf, the prairie-wolf (<hi rend="italic">Canis latrans</hi>), which is now looked at by all naturalists as specifically distinct from the common wolf; and is, according to Mr. J. K. Lord, in some respects intermediate in habits between a wolf and a fox. </quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>