<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9299A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To G. E. Shuttleworth   17 February [1874]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20560</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9299A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9299A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9299A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Wellcome Collection (MS.5134)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_437.xml">Wellcome</repository>
                    <idno>MS.5134</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1874-02-17">17 Feb [1874]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_7353.xml">Shuttleworth, G. E.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>At the suggestion of Crichton-Browne CD writes on behalf of his son George, who is making a study of marriages between first cousins and of their offspring to determine the proportion of the latter who may be among the insane, deaf and dumb, idiotic, blind etc. Is GES willing to ask his patients [at the Royal Albert Asylum] for the information relevant to this study?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">blind</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">deaf and dumb</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">idiotic</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">insane</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">patients</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_677">Crichton-Browne, James</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1224">Darwin, G. H.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4338">Shuttleworth, G. E.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Royal Albert Asylum</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">consanguineous marriages</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham | Kent.</placeName>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My son George Darwin (who is a good mathematician, having been 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. wrangler at Cambridge) has been at work for nearly a year in trying to discover, by several independent statistical methods, what proportion of all marriages are between first cousins; and he now feels pretty confident that his results will not be subject to an error of so much as one per cent.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> He is being greatly aided in this part of his enquiry by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Farre, the Registrar General.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> He now wishes to utilize these results by the disovery of what the proportion of the offspring of first cousin marriages may be amongst the insane, deaf and dumb, idiotic, blind &amp;c. I have for 30 years considered an answer to this enquiry of importance. We have here, I think, the rare case of an enquiry, the answer to which will be of value, whatever it may be; for we shall either find that such marriages are injurious, or that they may be persevered in with impunity.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Crichton Brown, who has been at great pains to help my son, has been kind enough to permit me to use his name in introducing myself to you; and he appears to think it very likely that you will consider this enquiry of sufficient importance to be willing to aid my son by asking the patients in the asylum in which you are in attendance, either by means of assistants or personally, whether or not they are the offspring of first cousin marriages, and recording the answers.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The question which my son proposes to ask is, <quote type="quote"> Were your parents first cousins or not? The questioner will doubtless be the best judge of the most prudent way of approaching the subject, and of explaining the question in each individual case, and would be to a great extent able to judge of the trustworthiness of the answer from the known character of the patient. </quote></p>
<p>If you should be willing to undertake this laborious task you would be conferring a very great favour both on my son and on myself; and I would beg you to send the results to him at Trinity College, Cambridge, where he is a resident fellow.</p>
<p>Would you have the kindness to add a general description of the rank of life from which the majority of your patients are drawn,— e.g. labourers and artizans,— shop-keeper and commercial,—upper ranks.</p>
<p>With apologies for my intrusion on you, | Believe me | Dear Sir | Yours faithfully, | Ch. Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Feb. 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">5.2 Ch.… 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 6.1] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. H. Darwin, 6 February 1874</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. H. Darwin, 6 February 1874</ref>. This is one of the letters George wrote for CD to send to people suggested by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_677.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Crichton-Browne</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Farr</ref>, who had a senior position in the General Register Office; however, the registrar-general was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Graham</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Crichton-Browne’s letters to CD on this subject have not been found, but for CD’s request for his help, see the letter to James Crichton-Brown, 5 January 1874. Shuttleworth was superintendent of the Royal Albert Asylum in Lancaster (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5344.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Medical directory</hi></ref>); his reply has not been found, but <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> cited him for the information that five per cent of his patients were the offspring of cousin marriages in G. H. Darwin 1875a.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>