<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10524">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. J. Romanes   1 June 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15508</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10524 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10524.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10524.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">E. D. Romanes 1896, pp. 52–4</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Romanes, E. D. 1896: 50</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Dunskaith</placeName>
                <date when="1876-06-01">1 June 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Anticipates reading Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Perigenesis der Plastidule</hi> [1876].</p> 
            <p>Physiologists will think vivisection bill stringent.</p>
            <p>Honorary memberships of Physiological Society created expressly to honour CD.</p>
            <p>Working hard at jellyfish just now. Needs snake poison.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">jellyfish</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">snake</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Perigenesis der Plastidule</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4653">physiologists</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">honorary membership</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Physiological Society</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">vivisection bill</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Dunskaith, Nigg, Ross-shire, N.B.:</placeName>
                    <date>June 1, 1876.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many thanks for your long and kind letter. Also for the accompanying essay.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It seems to me, from your epitome of the latter, that if Pangenesis is ‘airy,’ Perigenesis must be almost vacuous. However, I anticipate much pleasure in reading the work, for anything by Häckel on such a subject cannot fail to be interesting.</p>
<p>I am sorry to hear that you ‘much needed rest,’ and also about Frank.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I had hoped, too, that you would have mentioned Mrs. Litchfield.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Having been away from London for several weeks, I cannot say anything about the feeling with regard to the Bill.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Sanderson and Foster<ref target="#foot.f5"/> think it ‘stringent,’ and so I suppose will all the Physiologists. The former wants me to write articles in the ‘Fortnightly,’ ‘to make people take more sensible views on vivisection:’ but I cannot see that it would be of any use.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The heat of battle is not the time for us to expect fanatics to listen to ‘sense.’ Do you not think so?</p>
<p>I am sure the Physiological Society will be very pleased that you like being an hon. member, for it was on your account that honorary membership was instituted.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> At the committee meeting which was called to frame the constitution of the Society, the chairman (Dr. Foster) ejaculated with reference to you—‘Let us pile on him all the honour we possibly can,’ a sentiment which was heartily enough responded to by all present; but when it came to considering what form the expression of it was to take, it was found that a nascent society could do nothing further than make honorary members. Accordingly you were made an hon. member all by yourself; but later on it was thought, on the one hand, that you might feel lonely, and on the other that in a Physiological Society the most suitable companion for you was Dr. Sharpey.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Perhaps a ‘secretary’ ought not to be giving all the details about committee meetings, but if not, I know you will take it in confidence. It seems to me that you never fully realise the height of your pedestal, so that I am glad of any little opportunity of this kind to show you the angle at which the upturned faces are inclined. I am glad, too, to see from the inscription in Häckel’s essay, that he is still doing his best to show that in Germany this angle is fast being lost in horizontality.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>As this spring was so backward, the plants at Kew were too small to graft before I had to leave for the Medusæ. But this does not much matter, as I had a lot of vegetables planted down here also, which are doing well. Pangenesis I always expected would require a good deal of patience, and one year’s work on such a subject only counts for apprenticeship.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> If, by the time I am a skilled workman, I am not able to send anything to the international exhibitions, I shall not envy any one else who may resolve to enter the same trade.</p>
<p>I am working hard at the jelly-fish just now, and have succeeded in extracting several new confessions. The nerve-plexus theory, in particular, is coming out with greater clearness. The new poisons, too, are giving very interesting results.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I suppose you do not happen to know where I could get any snake poison. The ‘Phil. Trans.’ seem very long in coming out. I have not yet got the proofs of my paper.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10516.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. J. Romanes, 29 May [1876]</ref>. CD sent a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Die Perigenesis der Plastidule</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3283.xml">Haeckel 1876a</ref>). There is an annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3283.xml">Haeckel 1876a</ref> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10516.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 29 May [1876]</ref>, CD had written that he had gone to Hopedene in Surrey for some rest, and also that his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> had a feverish cold.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Litchfield</ref>, CD’s eldest daughter, had been ill (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-10461.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to C. S. Wedgwood, 20 April 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">A bill to regulate vivisection was introduced into the House of Lords on 15 May 1876 (<hi rend="italic">Hansard Parliamentary Debates</hi> 3d ser. vol. 229 col. 665). CD and Romanes had drafted a vivisection bill in 1875, but it had not become law (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Scott Burdon Sanderson</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1699.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Michael Foster</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Romanes did not write on vivisection for the <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly Review</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The Physiological Society was founded in response to the anti-vivisection movement; its inaugural dinner took place on 26 May 1876 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sharpey-Schafer 1927</ref>, p. 15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4314.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Sharpey</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Inside the front cover of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3283.xml">Haeckel 1876a</ref>, Haeckel wrote, ‘Seinem hochverehrten Freunde und Meister <hi rend="italic">Charles Darwin</hi> in unveränderlichen Treue und bewundernden Verehrung’ (To his revered friend and master <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Darwin</ref> in unchanging faithfulness and admiring respect).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Romanes was testing CD’s hypothesis of pangenesis in a series of plant-grafting experiments; CD had asked <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> to give Romanes research facilities at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. J. Romanes, 14 January 1875</ref> and nn. 2 and 4). Romanes had also worked on medusae (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8730.xml">G. J. Romanes 1875</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8729.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. J. Romanes 1876</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8919.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. J. Romanes 1876–7</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8729.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. J. Romanes 1876</ref>, p. 171. Romanes was investigating whether the nerve tissue of medusae responded to poisons in the same way as that of more complex animals. His experiments led him to infer the existence of a fine plexus of nerve fibres, in which the constituent threads crossed and recrossed one another without coalescing (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8728.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. D. Romanes 1896</ref>, p. 18).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Romanes’s paper ‘Preliminary observations on the locomotor system of medusae’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8730.xml">G. J. Romanes 1875</ref>) was published in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</hi>. It was read on 16 December 1875, and published in 1877.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>