<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-840">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To William Parsons, earl of Rosse, Chairman of the Committee of Papers, Royal Society   16 March [1852]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1250</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-840 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-840.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-840.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The Royal Society (RR2: 226)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_364.xml">Royal Society</repository>
                    <idno>RR2: 226</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1852-03-16">16 Mar [1852]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3702.xml">Parsons, William</persName>
                <orgName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml">Royal Society of London</orgName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Referee’s report on paper by Daniel Sharpe ["On foliation and cleavage", <hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond.</hi> 142 (1852): 445–62].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">foliation</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Sharpe, Daniel 1852</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Kent</placeName>
                    <date>March. 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>In my opinion M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sharpe’s paper is eligible for publication in the Philosophical Transactions.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Its object is to show that the laminæ in the metamorphic schists follow the same laws with the cleavage planes in clay-slates. The subject has been little attended to; &amp; I do not believe that it has hitherto been attempted to show on a map the range, as well as dip, of the foliation (whatever its theoretical origin may have been) over an extensive district.— I am on the other hand bound to state that owing to the obscurity of the structure in many parts, and to the presence (as admitted by the author) of many minor curvatures, I think further evidence is necessary, before the existence of the several great arches extending across Scotland can be accepted as at all certain. I should have hesitated in advising the publication of this paper, had not the places, in which a vertical &amp; fan-like arrangement of the folia occur, been separately marked on the map; for such facts seem liable to little error:— Moreover, statements by Macculloch<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; other Scotch authors are used by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Sharpe, &amp; these support his general inferences. If we consider in the author’s sections, simply the fan-like layers, &amp; neglect as doubtful, the broad intermediate districts with convoluted &amp; less steeply inclined layers, we may, I think, see evidence of arrangement, distinct from ordinary stratification. I may here just allude to the observations by Humboldt &amp; others,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> showing the uniformity of strike in the metamorphic schists in one given direction over surprisingly large regions in other parts of the world,—as for instance in New S. Wales, where the strike serves as a compass to people travelling through the woods,— I allude to this, as offering some proof that the subject is not of limited interest.—</p>
<p>With regard to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Sharpe’s map, I must express a strong opinion (though fully admitting that the author in most cases is the best judge) that it would have been very much better, if not a single line had been inserted without some distinct authority: on account of the rather small scale, it might perhaps have been necessary to have extended the lines a little beyond the points observed, but some definite limit ought, in my opinion, to have been fixed on &amp; stated. As the map now stands, it tells at once the authors views, but it is not possible to discover which lines, &amp; how far along each line, are the result of actual observation, &amp; how much has been conjecturally added.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The author’s attention might be called to one other point,—namely to his use of the term “arches or lines of elevation”, as applied to his arches of foliation; considering that the very object of the memoir is to show that the folia are not merely upturned layers of deposition in a metamorphosed condition, it appears unfortunate that this term, which at once calls before the mind beds folded by ordinary mechanical forces, should have been adopted, when axes of foliation or some other term might have easily been found, which would not have been confounded with ordinary lines of elevation, &amp; yet would not have precluded the idea of the foliation having resulted indirectly from mechanical action,—as seems to be the Author’s view.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Notwithstanding the foregoing objections, from the novelty &amp;, as it appears to me, importance of the subject, I am of decided opinion that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sharpe’s memoir ought to be published in the Transactions.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Apologising for the length of this Report | I remain, Sir, Your obedient servant | Charles Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> To the Chairman of | the Committee of Papers.</p>
<p>P.S. | The author ought to state whether his bearings have been corrected for variation; &amp; a scale of colours should appear on the map, together with an explanation of the several lines used.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.13 Macculloch] ‘h’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘k’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.19 the metamorphic schists in 1.20] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.11 of foliation] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.1 the foregoing] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘these’; ‘foregoing’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7133.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sharpe 1852</ref>, which <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4311.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Sharpe</ref> had told CD he was writing for the Royal Society (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-1458.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Sharpe, 16 October [1851]</ref>). The paper had been read at meetings of the Royal Society on 12 and 19 February 1852 (<hi rend="italic">Abstracts of the papers</hi> <hi rend="italic">communicated to the Royal Society of London</hi> 6 (1850–4): 152).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John MacCulloch</ref>, physician and geologist, had been commissioned in 1826 to prepare a geological map of Scotland.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD cited <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2718.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gardner 1840</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6969.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schomburgk 1842</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1814–29</ref> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 141. No location is given for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2443.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander von Humboldt’s</ref> observation, but see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1814–29</ref>, 4: 384–5, and 5: 394–8. CD’s copy of this work is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his explanation of the map (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7133.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sharpe 1852</ref>, pp. 460–1), Sharpe stated that: ‘The <hi rend="italic">strike</hi> or direction of the foliation and cleavage across the surface is indicated by black lines … The dotted lines show the direction supposed to be followed, in unexamined districts, by the lines just explained. All the lines are laid down on the Map with more continuity and regularity than really exist; this error can only be fully corrected by a minute examination of the whole country.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The term ‘arches’ appears in the published version, but ‘lines of elevation’ has been omitted. Theoretical reconstructions are illustrated on Plate XXIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Another report recommending that Sharpe’s paper be published, dated 4 March 1852, was written by Adam Sedgwick. Sedgwick observed: ‘If the cleavage planes of the unequivocably stratified slates be parallel to the foliations of the crystalline slates, it seems to follow, of absolute necessity, that the <hi rend="italic">foliations</hi> must themselves be due, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to planes of original &amp; mechanical <hi rend="italic">deposition</hi>, but to a subsequent crystalline action. This is the fundamental point of the paper; &amp; the conclusion agrees with the views published by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin’ (Royal Society (RR2: 224)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his explanation of the map, Sharpe included a note detailing how the variation in the measurements of strike was corrected. He also explained the various lines used on the map. The map itself bears a key relating colour to rock type and this is also spelled out in the explanatory text (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7133.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sharpe 1852</ref>, pp. 460–1).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>