<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7381">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From V. O. Kovalevsky   22 November 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17784</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7381 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7381.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7381.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 85</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 85</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2751.xml">Kovalevsky, V. O.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1870-11-22">22 Nov 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sofya Kovalevsky not admitted to University in Berlin.</p> 
<p>Translating the four sheets CD sent. When will book [<hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>] be printed?</p> 
            <p>Alexander [Kovalevsky] has gone to the Red Sea to study corals.</p> 
<p>Will work on live <hi rend="italic">Scalpellum</hi> at Naples in spring.</p> 
            <p>Bemoans England’s Prussian sympathies. Paris will fall without bombardment.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">corals</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Scalpellum</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2749">Kovalevsky, A. O.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2750">Kovalevsky, Sophie</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Naples</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Paris</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Prussia</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Red Sea</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">University of Berlin</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin 7. Georgienstrasse.</placeName>
                    <date>22 Nov. 1870.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I did not write You such a long Time not beeing quite sure shall I remain at Berlin or go to Leipsic, and although my wife was not admitted to the University here we resolved to remain at Berlin there beeing here so many means of pursuing studies privately.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I hope Your intended visit did You good and delayed a little the printing of Your book what I most fervently wish as I am a little backward with the translation; still, the four sheets You kindly sent me are soon finished and I pray You dear Sir to send me some more if there is any printed.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Could You not inform me when do You hope that both volumes will appear in England.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>From my brother I had news before yesterday, he could not procure himself live Scalpellum’s and hopes to get them in the spring, when as the pescatori assured him they are much more abundant.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He received an offer from the Kiev University to send him for 5 months to the Red Sea and started the 8 Nov. from Naples, I have letters from Alexandria, where he arrived safe the 11 of November and got the same day to Suez; I expect he will remain the whole time at Tor (Tûr) on the west side of the Sinai peninsula and work there on the coral reefs.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>It seems dear Sir that we are going to have a fight with You, that comes all from Your Prussian sympaties; now You allowed Your best and truest ally to be murdered, who shall prevent Russia &amp; Prussia to divide Austria and trottle the Sick man.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> We are very anxious about the state of Paris, as my sister in Law is shut up there; the siege is drawing to the close as the provisions become scanty, so Paris will surrender without bombardement, one is happy even at this.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> My wife send You her compliments and prays to remember her to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Darwin and the ladies</p>
<p>Yours | Very truly | W. Kowalevsky.—</p>
<p>P.S. The proof sheets can be sent under cover by post, it is generally a safer way.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Kovalevsky’s last letter to CD is dated 11 October [1870]. Sofia Vasilyevna Kovalevskaya was studying privately in Berlin with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6988.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Theodor Wilhelm Weierstrass</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7647.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tee 1976–7</ref>, pp. 122–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had been at Leith Hill Place, the home of his brother-in-law <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Josiah Wedgwood III</ref>, and Ightam Mote, from 13 to 20 October 1870 (see ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)). Kovalevsky was translating <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> from the corrected proof-sheets.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> was published on 24 February 1871 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. B. Freeman 1977</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Kovalevsky refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Onufrievich Kovalevsky</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7320.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 15 September 1870</ref> and n. 2. <hi rend="italic">Pescatori</hi>: fishermen (Italian). <hi rend="italic">Scalpellum</hi> is a barnacle genus.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For more on A. O. Kovalevsky’s plans for work in Egypt, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7121.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 28 February [1870]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The French government declared war on Prussia in July 1870. French hopes that other German states would seize the opportunity to turn on Prussia proved unfounded, and most supported the Prussians; Austria seemed divided in its hostility to both parties and maintained neutrality. The Russian government maintained friendly relations with Prussia, and, in September, announced that it repudiated an article in the Paris Treaty of 1856 referring to the neutrality of the Black Sea. This deeply alarmed the Turkish government, who recognised it as a prelude to the establishment of a Russian fleet in the Black Sea. The Ottoman (Turkish) empire was at the time sometimes referred to as the ‘sick man of Europe’. Collusion between the Russians and the Prussians at a time of French weakness was suspected, and the British Government rejected any adjustment of the terms of the treaty. (<hi rend="italic">Annual Register</hi> (1870): 109 (United Kingdom); 154–221 (France); 233 (Germany); 251 (Austria); 284–5 (Russia); 288 (Turkey).)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Paris came under siege by the Prussians in September 1870. In October, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_460.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto von Bismarck</ref> had announced his intention of reducing the city by famine rather than bombardment (<hi rend="italic">Annual Register</hi> (1870): 187). Sofia’s sister was Anna Korvin-Krukovskaya.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>