<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6965">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   1 November 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16691</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6965 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6965.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6965.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian) †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 60</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 145</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 145</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                <date when="1869-11-01">1 Nov 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on Hermann Crüger’s paper, sent by CD, on fertilisation of orchids [<hi rend="italic">J. Linn. Soc. Lond. (Bot.)</hi> 8 (1865): 127–35].</p> 
            <p>Observations on dichogamy in grasses (wheat, rye, barley).</p> 
<p>Has not yet read CD’s reply to his article on Pangenesis [<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 158–60].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">barley</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">grasses</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">rye</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">wheat</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Collected papers</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">J. Linn. Soc. Lond. (Bot.)</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Cruger, Hermann 1865</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dichogamy, sexual dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Firenze</placeName>
                    <date>1. 9bre 1869</date>
                    <salute>Celeberrimo uomo!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Rendo grazie alla S.V. pella indulgente e cortese lettera ultimamente speditami, nonchè pel grazioso dono dell’interessante memoria del Dott. Crüger. La quale è scritta con tanta chiarezza e tanto discernimento, che ha scosso non poco i miei dubbii intorno alla realtà della fecondazione dei <hi rend="underline">Coryanthes</hi> per intervento dell’ <hi rend="underline">Euglossae</hi>, e collo stranissimo processo <hi rend="underline">a bagno freddo</hi> ivi descritto.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Non ostante mi resta ad approfondire maggiormente la razionalità delle forme florali dei <hi rend="underline">Coryanthes</hi> e <hi rend="underline">Gongora</hi>. Non dissimulo però fin d’ora che mi dà a pensare la circostanza che il liquido, il quale si raccoglie per stillicidio nel labello, <hi rend="underline">è segregato da due cospicue glandole nettarifere</hi>. La natura è molto economa, e non mi contenta che un liquido, il quale avesse semplicemente la funzione indicata dal D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Crüger, debba venir segregato da un apparato secretorio e glandoloso.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Mi è giunto singolarmente gradito il cenno datomi che la <hi rend="underline">Strelitzia</hi>, giusta le ricerche della S.V., venga al Capo di Buona speranza fecondata da nettarinie.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ciò viene a conferma delle mie congetture. Il Prof. Hildebrand suppose che la fecondazione di questa pianta venga effetuata dagli insetti: ma ciò a me parce meno verisimile, perocchè gl’insetti, anche di grossa taglia, non avrebbero la forza sufficiente per far divaricare i lobi della scatola che racchiude le antere.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Farò tesoro di questo suo cenno, e, se la S.V. non dissente, me ne prevarrò ad opportuna occasione.</p>
<p>Il suggerimento, che la S.V. mi diede, di studiare la fecondazione nel grano,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> mi giunse tanto più gradito, in quanto che nella state passata ho fatto appunto alcuni studi in proposito. Mi pare di aver messo fuori dubbio, 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> che ogni flosculo del grano sta aperto per circa un quarto d’ora, in tempo che la fecondazione stimmatica non è ancora avvenuta; 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. che in consequenza la dicogamia è possibilissima nel grano; 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. che per altro ogni fiore del grano è suscettibile di essere fecondato col proprio polline. Presso la segala ho trovato che la fecondazione dicogamica è di gran lunga la più facile. Presso <hi rend="underline">l’Hordeum vulgare</hi> ho trovato che un terzo dei fiori non si aprono menomamente (e quindi non possono essere fecondati dicogamicamente) mentre gli altri due terzi si aprono e possono essere fecondati dicogamicamente.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Presso l’<hi rend="underline">Hordeum diytichum</hi> <ref target="#foot.f8"/> (con strana eccezione) la fecondazione omogamica (e non dicogamica) è veramente necessaria, perocchè succede quando ancora le spighe non uscirono fuori dalla guaina fogliare. Ma ecco che, con mirabile alternativa, questa specie d’orzo possiede due specie di fiori: gli uni (pochissimi) che si aprono e sono predestinati per la dicogamia; gli altri (moltissimi) che non si aprono, e sono predestinati per la omogamia. Cosicchè presso questa pianta si ripeta il bene conosciuto fenomeno dei fiori di <hi rend="underline">Viola</hi>, di <hi rend="underline">Vicia amphicarpa</hi> ecc. ecc.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Così, anche presso <hi rend="underline">l’Hordeum distichum</hi> rimane intatta la gran legge “no hermaphrodite fertilises itself for a perpetuity of generations.”<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Ora sto scrivendo una piccola memoria in proposito, e appena sarà stampata, mi farò un dovere di rassegnarla alla S.V.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Della “Scientific opinion” non mi è pervenuto che il primo fascicolo, cioè il N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 48. Ho venuto a sapere per caso che nel N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 51 la S.V. deve avere inserito una risposta al mio scritto.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Io la prego con sommissione a volermene favorire un esemplare: e, se Ella permette, io farò <hi rend="underline">per deferenza</hi> la traduzione della sua risposta, e la farò inserire sulla <hi rend="underline">Revista Contemporanea</hi>, che oggi muta nome in <hi rend="underline">Revista Europea</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Ho avuto pure il libro svedese di <hi rend="underline">Axell</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> È un opera che mi pare di molto merito e scritta con rara coscienza. Godo assai che Axell faccia un altissima stima degli scritti del più grande naturalista del secolo, di cui ho l’onore di riconfermarmi</p>
<p>Ossequentissimo discepolo | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName>Florence</placeName>
        <date>1. November 1869</date>
        <salute>Most famous man!</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>I thank you both for your tolerant and gracious letter recently sent to me and for the kind present of Dr Crüger's interesting memoir, which is written with such clarity and acuity that it greatly undermined my doubt about the reality of the fertilisation of <hi rend="underline">Coryanthes</hi> through the mediation of <hi rend="underline">Euglossae</hi> and the very strange process of <hi rend="underline">cold bath</hi> there described.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This notwithstanding, I still have to deepen my understanding of the rationality of the floral forms of <hi rend="underline">Coryanthes</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Gongora</hi>.  I would admit straightaway that it puzzles me that the liquid collected in the labellum by distillation, <hi rend="underline">is produced by two peculiar nectar-producing glands.</hi>  Nature is very economical, and I am not happy that a liquid having simply the function indicated by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Crüger, should be produced by a secretory and glandular apparatus.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
        <p>I am especially pleased that you mentioned that, according to your discoveries at the Cape of Good Hope, <hi rend="underline">Strelitzia</hi> is fertilised by nectarinae.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> This confirms my views.  Prof. Hildebrand thought that the fertilisation of this flower was effected by insects; but that did not seem very likely to me, for insects, even of large size, would not have sufficient strength to open wide the lobes of the box containing the anthers.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I set great store by this point of yours, and, if you agree, I will use it on a suitable occasion.  </p> 
        <p>I am especially pleased with your suggestion that I should study the fertilisation of wheat,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> especially considering that I worked on that last Summer.  I think I dispelled any doubt, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> that every floret of wheat stays open for about a quarter of an hour, a period of time in which stigmatic fecundation has not yet taken place; 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> that consequently dichogamy in wheat is very possible; 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> that, however, the flower of wheat can be fertilised by its own pollen.  I found that in rye dichogamic fertilisation is by far the easiest.  I found out that in <hi rend="underline">Hordeum</hi> <hi rend="underline">vulgare</hi> one third of the flowers do not open at all (and therefore they cannot be fertilised dichogamically), whereas two thirds of them open and can be fertilised dichogamically.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> In <hi rend="underline">Hordeum</hi> <hi rend="underline">distichum</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/> (a strange exception) homogamic (and not dichogamic) fertilisation is really necessary, for it takes place when the ears are not yet out of their foliaceous sheaths. But then, as a wonderful alternative, this species of barley has two kinds of flowers: some (very few) that open and are predestined to dichogamy; and others (very many) that do not open, and are predestined to homogamy.  So that in this plant we see the repetition of the well known phenomenon that takes place in the flowers of <hi rend="underline">Viola</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Vicia</hi> <hi rend="underline">amphicarpa</hi> etc. etc.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Thus, even in <hi rend="underline">Hordeum</hi> <hi rend="underline">distichum</hi> the great law remains intact “no hermaphrodite fertilises itself for a perpetuity of generations.”<ref target="#foot.f10"/> At present I am writing a short paper about this, and I will send it to you as soon as it is printed.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p> 
        <p>I received only the first issue of “Scientific Opinion”, that is N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 48.  I came to know by chance that you inserted a reply to my work in N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 51.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I humbly beg you to be kind enough to send me a copy, and if I have your permission, I will translate <hi rend="underline">in deference to you</hi> your reply to appear in the <hi rend="underline">Revista</hi> <hi rend="underline">contemporanea</hi>, which today changes its name to <hi rend="underline">Revista</hi> <hi rend="underline">Europea</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p> 
        <p>I received <hi rend="underline">Axell</hi>’s Swedish book.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> It seems to me very good and written with unusual care.  I am really pleased that Axell praises very greatly indeed the works of the greatest naturalist of our century, of whom I have the honour of confirming myself</p> 
        <p>a very respectful disciple | Federico Delpino</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 458–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Federico Delpino, 14 October 1869</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Crüger’s</ref> paper described how the pollen-mass of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> was secured onto the back of the bee (<hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi>) as it tried to force its way out through a passage after falling into a ‘bucket’ of nectar; when the bee next fell into the bucket of the same or another flower, the pollen was deposited on the stigma as it tried to leave (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 130). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 229–30, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 157 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 153–4), <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 173–6, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See also the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Federico Delpino, 9 October 1869</ref>. Visits of bees to flowers of the orchid genus <hi rend="italic">Gongora</hi> were also described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For CD’s remark on the Nectarinae (now the family Nectariniidae, sunbirds) fertilising <hi rend="italic">Strelitzia</hi>, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Federico Delpino, 14 October 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Hildebrand</ref> recorded his opinion on <hi rend="italic">Strelitzia</hi> pollination in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hildebrand 1869</ref>, pp. 508–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had suggested that Delpino study the fertilisation of ‘Gramineæ’, the grass family; see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Federico Delpino, 14 October 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">On dichogamy, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6833.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. C. Tait, 17 July [1869]</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Hordeum vulgare</hi> is common barley.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Hordeum distichum</hi> is an alternative spelling of <hi rend="italic">H. distichon</hi>, now considered to be a variety of <hi rend="italic">H. vulgare vulgare.</hi> It was known as two-rowed barley.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Delpino refers to violets and to the vetch <hi rend="italic">Vicia amphicarpa</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Vicia sativa amphicarpa</hi>); see also letters from T. H. Farrer, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6857.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">8 August 1869</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6861.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">12 August 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Delpino refers to CD’s conclusion in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 359: ‘Nature thus tells us, in the most emphatic manner, that she abhors perpetual self-fertilisation.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Delpino probably refers to his paper on dichogamy in cereals (Delpino 1871); an inscribed copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Issue 48 (29 September 1869) of <hi rend="italic">Scientific Opinion</hi> included the first part of Delpino 1869, the translation of Delpino’s review of pangenesis. In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6938.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Delpino of 14 October 1869</ref>, CD had offered to send the remaining parts. CD replied to Delpino’s criticism in the letter to <hi rend="italic">Scientific Opinion</hi>, [before 20 October 1869]; this was published in issue 51 (20 October 1869).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Delpino’s translation of CD’s letter to <hi rend="italic">Scientific Opinion</hi>, [before 20 October 1869], appeared in the first volume of <hi rend="italic">Rivista Europea</hi> (1869): 118–24.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The references are to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johan Severin Axell</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_262.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Axell 1869</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>