<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4847">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From George Maw   1 June 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10041</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4847 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4847.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4847.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 100</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 100</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3232.xml">Maw, George</persName>
                <placeName>Benthall Hall</placeName>
                <date when="1865-06-01">1 June 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports a monstrous pig that looks like an elephant. It was born of a pregnant sow which had been frightened by a circus elephant. He offers the monster, which died at birth, to any London museum.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">elephant</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pig</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">London</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">circus</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">museum</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Benthall Hall. | n<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Broseley.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>June 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1865</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to day come across a very remarkable case of animal monstrosity with the particulars of which you will I think be interested</p>
<p>On the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. or 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of May 1863 a sow belonging to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wood of the Star Hotel Shiffnal<ref target="#foot.f1"/> brought forth a litter of eleven pigs all of which were well formed excepting the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. born which is formed in several points like an Elephant. It has a distinct proboscis depending from the nose. Ears &amp; mouth shaped exactly like an elephants &amp; in one or two other respects deviating from the usual formation of a young pig. it is supposed to have been brought forth alive tho’ never seen alive as the mother overlaid it— There was an interval of two or three hours between its birth &amp; the birth of the succeeding nine healthy pigs all of which were delivered in the usual rapid succession.</p>
<p>The Mother has had previous &amp; subsequent litters all of which have been healthy &amp; well formed.</p>
<p>The history of the gestation of the litter to which this pig belonged is very remarkable &amp; I have been very careful in sifting &amp; ascertaining the probable correctness of the following facts.</p>
<p>In July 1863, the Sow was put to the Boar &amp; one or two days afterwards (I cannot clearly ascertain the exact interval) Some Elephants belonging to Edmund’s menagerie<ref target="#foot.f2"/> were quartered at the Star Hotel   one of these had a peculiar antipathy to pigs &amp; on going up the hotel yard endeavoured to reach the sow with its trunk. The ostler tells me the pig appeared quite terror striken &amp; to this is attributed the singular malformations in its young—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The young pig has been preserved in spirits &amp; is now in possession of a chemist in the town— I believe it has not yet been seen by any one who would be likely to appreciate its scientific importance. The present owner wants £2 for it &amp; if you think it is of sufficient importance to place in one of the London museums I shall be very happy to purchase it for this purpose &amp; present it to the museum of the R C of Surgeons<ref target="#foot.f4"/> or wherever you think it will be better located. It seems a pity it should be left in the obscurity of a small country town. I am not acquainted with Professor Owen<ref target="#foot.f5"/> or would have written to him on the subject of placing the pig in the museum of the College of Surgeons</p>
<p>One point I am quite certain of; that it is not a made up specimen nor do I see any reason to doubt the fact of the Elephants visit soon after the sow received the boar, however we may view its possible connection with the monstrosity—</p>
<p>I have recently been investigating some deposits in N Wales which underlie the Boulder clay drift that I fully expect will prove to be of Tertiary age.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> They consist of white black or variegated sands alternating with Curious white clay &amp; various colored Pipe clays &amp; Earthy lignite— The general series is very much like many of the tertiary beds of Dorsetshire</p>
<p>The little remnants are preserved in pockets in the mountain limestone of Flintshire &amp; Carnarvonshire &amp; belong to a formation that must once have had a wide distribution in N Wales. I have observed it over a distance of 30 miles from East to West— I hope next week to make a careful examination of the district &amp; shall try &amp; find some organic remains.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>If you think the monstrous pig will be acceptable at one of the London museums will you kindly favor me with a line by an early post that I may secure it.</p>
<p>I am D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sir | very truly your’s | Geo Maw <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">C Darwin Esq.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">John Wood was the proprietor of the Star Hotel, Market Place, Shiffnal, near Shrewsbury in Shropshire (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6368.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office directory of Gloucestershire, with Bath, Bristol, Herefordshire, and Shropshire</hi></ref> 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">James ‘Barney’ Edmonds, who married a niece of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7037.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Wombwell</ref>, took over the running of Wombwell’s Windsor Castle Menagerie, one of three Wombwell menageries; the name was changed to Edmonds’ Menagerie in the 1860s after the death of Wombwell’s widow (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7868.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Turner 1995</ref>, pp. 42, 136–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The ancient belief in the effect of maternal imagination on the development of the foetus was well established by the early eighteenth century, when it was used to account for a wide variety of malformations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7770.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Todd 1995</ref>, pp. 47–52). In the nineteenth century, the work of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1840.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire</ref> began a new era in the study of monstrous development, bringing it more in line with the general study of embryogenesis (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8411.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. Wilson 1993</ref>, p. 173). For more on popular belief in the effect of maternal imagination, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Huet 1993</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8411.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. Wilson 1993</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7770.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Todd 1995</ref>; for the scientific debate on the significance of monsters in an evolutionary context, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6627.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Richards 1994</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Maw refers to the Hunterian Museum of the Royal College of Surgeons.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> was the curator of the Hunterian Museum from 1836 to 1856. Although Owen no longer held the post, he would still have been a useful person to consult on the subject of specimens in his capacity as superintendent of the natural history collections at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6790.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rupke 1994</ref>, pp. 30–1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The results of Maw’s investigation were published in Maw 1865a. He concluded that, in the absence of fossil evidence, the deposits underlying the boulder-clay drift of North Wales were probably restricted to the Cretaceous or Tertiary periods (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 202). He encouraged other investigators to examine the deposits in order to find organic remains that would clarify their true geological age (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 204). Prior to 1863 the correspondence between CD and Maw mostly concerned botanical and zoological subjects (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 9 and 10). In 1863, Maw wrote to CD about his interest in the drift deposits of the Severn Gorge near his home (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4128.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Maw, 25 April 1863</ref>). He was elected a member of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>, with CD as one of the nominating members, in February 1864 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, letter to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 28 December 1863] and n. 1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In a brief report summarising Maw 1865a given at the British Association for the Advancement of Science meeting in September 1865, Maw referred to these deposits as a ‘widely distributed series of unfossiliferous deposits’ and stated that they closely resembled ‘some of the Tertiary deposits in the south of England’ (Maw 1865b, p. 68).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>