<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11944">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Ernst Krause   19 March 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8103</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11944 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11944.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11944.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The Huntington Library (HM 36177)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_187.xml">Huntington</repository>
                    <idno>HM 36177</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1879-03-19">19 Mar 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends copy of a lecture [by John Dowson, see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">11949</hi>] published in 1861.</p> 
            <p>Has not yet found a copy of Anna Seward’s biography for EK. It is a wretched, inaccurate book. To contradict Anna Seward’s version, CD intends to write a short preface to the translation of EK’s essay. Doubts that it will be worth translating into German.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1377">Dowson, John</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4303">Seward, Anna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-06" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-19" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-19" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-07-19" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi> | (<hi rend="print">Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi>)</placeName>
                    <date>Mar 19. 79</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I send by this post a duplicate copy of a lecture published in 1861, which I remembered after writing to you. I have not yet succeeded in getting a copy of Miss Seward for you.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have now reread it, &amp; it is a wretched production. I have also read the correspondence which passed between my father, other members of the family &amp; Miss Seward, they are unanimous that it is full of inaccuracies even to his age when he died. Unfortunately they do not give particulars with the exception about one malignant account of my grandfather’s behaviour on hearing of his son’s death; &amp; this they prove by witnesses to be absolutely false.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Miss Seward published a retractation, but this seems to have been universally forgotten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In order to have an opportunity of contradicting Miss Seward, I intend to publish a short preface to the translation of your essay; &amp; in this I will give a few particulars about the family, together with a few remarks by my father with respect to Eras Darwin, &amp; possibly two or three letters.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I do not think you could work up these scanty materials in your account, because I must give them on my own authority. I doubt whether my preface will be worth translating into german, but when written I would of course send it to you, if you so wish, either to read or to have translated.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have written to two gentlemen for the chance of getting more materials, and intend to consult one or two likely books.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> For these reasons &amp; from being very busy at present, I have thought of not writing the preface until I leave home towards the end of april.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> My son is going to take steps as soon as he can about the photograph of the picture<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Dear Sir | Yours faithfully | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                    <p>P.S | There is one little error in your essay. My grandfather’s house was <hi rend="underline">within</hi> Lichfield &amp; it was a sort of villa &amp; botanic garden which were at the distance of about one or two miles out of the town.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>The above was written before your kind letter of 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> arrived. The story about the drunkenness is quite incorrect.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>The Botanic Garden was written in due order, but he thought that the second part would be more popular than the first, &amp; therefore published the second first.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                    <p>I will look to M.S of translation before it goes to press; &amp; I am glad that you are not in a hurry.</p>
                    <p>From what you say I have thought that you would allow me to strike out the note about Miss Seward.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> You are the best &amp; sole judge, but I should think that if you discuss the writings of all the predecessors of Lamarck, the Essay would cease to be a life of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
                    <p>Would it not be better to reserve this discussion for a separate essay? Small books for some reason never sell well in England, but should your Biography pay more than the expences of publication, which is very unlikely, the balance will of course be handed over to you.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
                    <p>I must apologise for the unreasonable length of this letter, but I must trouble you on one other point, for I do not quite understand whether the sheets with the footnotes received yesterday are in their final state &amp; ready for the translator.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Will you kindly inform me on this head, &amp; then I hope to cause you no more trouble.</p>
                    <p>My dear Sir | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>               
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
           <note>4.2 a sort of] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘his’ <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi></note> 
                <note>4.3 one or two] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi></note>  
                <note>4.3 miles] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘mile’ <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi></note>  
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD sent <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8551.xml">John Dowson</ref>’s lecture to the Literary and Philosophical Society of Whitby <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin: philosopher, poet, and physician</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2132.xml">Dowson 1861</ref>); no copy has been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL. CD was trying to find a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref>’s biography of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>) for Krause (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 14 March 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 14 March 1879</ref> and n. 4. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Seward’s retraction appeared in a footnote to the essay review of her book in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10825.xml">[T. Thomson] 1804</ref>, pp. 236–7 n.).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his introductory sketch of the life of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>, CD quoted from Seward’s account of his grandfather’s behaviour and from that by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8388.xml">Emma Georgiana Elizabeth Darwin</ref>, who was with Erasmus when he heard the news of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8435.xml">his son</ref>’s death (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 70–4). CD’s published introduction ran to 127 pages, while Krause’s expanded essay on the scientific works of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> was 87 pages long.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">A German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> appeared in 1880, titled <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin und seine Stellung in der Geschichte der Descendenz-Theorie von Ernst Krause. Mit seinem Lebens- und Charakterbilde von Charles Darwin</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>). Krause expanded his part of the work, adding a section on precursors to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 78–124).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See letter to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11934.xml">B. W. Richardson, 14 March 1879</ref>, and letter to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11947.xml">Francis Galton, 22 March 1879</ref>. No published references other than <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2132.xml">Dowson 1861</ref> are mentioned in the preface to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In the event, CD was away from home from 6 to 26 May 1879 visiting friends and family (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 14 March 1879</ref> and n. 6. The son was probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml">Leonard Darwin</ref>; the picture was a portrait of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5257.xml">Joseph Wright</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD evidently refers to a now missing revision of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref> (see n. 15, below); in the published version, Krause had only noted that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> settled in Lichfield (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 398). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11942.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 17 March 1879</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11942.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 17 March 1879</ref> and n. 6; the reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Krause had added a footnote to his revised version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref> discrediting <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11942.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 17 March 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Krause suggested adding an account of the views of several predecessors of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2786.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jean Baptiste de Lamarck</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11942.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 17 March 1879</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Krause added a section on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> precursors to the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>; see n. 5, above). CD’s prediction about sales was accurate; in his <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6562.xml">‘Recollections’</ref>, p. 419, he stated that by 1881 only 800 or 900 copies of the book had been sold. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Krause had evidently sent a revised version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>; CD had asked for sheets to be sent as they became available (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 14 March 1879</ref>).</note>
        </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>