<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-310">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Robert FitzRoy   6 October [1836]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1837</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-310 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-310.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-310.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">3pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 269</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 506</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 144: 114</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 114</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Shrewsbury</placeName>
                <date when="1836-10-06">6 Oct [1836]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml">FitzRoy, Robert</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD describes his happy home-coming. Finds his family and Shrewsbury unchanged.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1202">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shrewsbury</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Thursday morning. Oct 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></placeName>
                    <salute>My dear FitzRoy,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I arrived here yesterday morning at Breakfast time, &amp; thank God, found all my dear good sisters &amp; father quite well— My father appears more cheerful and very little older than when I left    My sisters assure me I do not look the least different, &amp; I am able to return the compliment— Indeed all England appears changed, excepting the good old Town of Shrewsbury &amp; its inhabitants— which for all I can see to the contrary may go on as they now are to Doomsday— I wish with all my heart, I was writing to you, amongst your friends instead of at that horrid Plymouth. But the day will soon come and you will be as happy as I now am— I do assure you I am a very great man at home— the five years voyage has certainly raised me a hundred per cent. I fear such greatness must experience a fall—</p>
<p>I am thoroughly ashamed of myself, in what a dead and half alive state, I spent the few last days on board, my only excuse is, that certainly I was not quite well.— The first day in the mail tired me but as I drew nearer to Shrewsbury everything looked more beautiful &amp; cheerful— In passing Gloucestershire &amp; Worcestershire I wished much for you to admire the fields woods &amp; orchards.— The stupid people on the coach did not seem to think the fields one bit greener than usual but I am sure, we should have thoroughly agreed, that the wide world does not contain so happy a prospect as the rich cultivated land of England—</p>
<p>I hope you will not forget to send me a note telling me how you go on.— I do indeed hope all your vexations and trouble with respect to our voyage which we now <hi rend="underline">know</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">has</hi> an end, have come to a close.— If you do not receive much satisfaction for all the mental and bodily energy, you have expended in His Majesty’s Service, you will be most hardly treated— I put my radical sisters into an uproar at some of the <hi rend="underline">prudent</hi> (if they were not <hi rend="underline">honest</hi> whigs, I <hi rend="underline">would</hi> say shabby), proceedings of our Government. By the way I must tell you for the honor &amp; glory of the family, that my father has a large engraving of King George the IV. put up in his sitting Room. But I am no renegade, and by the time we meet, my politics will be as firmly fixed and as wisely founded as ever they were—</p>
<p>I thought when I began this letter I would convince you what a steady &amp; sober frame of mind I was in. But I find I am writing most precious nonsense. Two or three of our labourers yesterday immediately set to work, and got most excessively drunk in honour of the arrival of Master Charles.— Who then shall gainsay if Master Charles himself chooses to make himself a fool.</p>
<p>Good bye— God bless you— I hope you are as happy, but much wiser than your most sincere but unworthy Philos. | Chas. Darwin. *S 2</p>
<p rend="left">Shrewsbury.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>