<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10402">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   18 February 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6721</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10402 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10402.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10402.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">4pp (PS by Francis Darwin)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Thiselton-Dyer, W.T., Letters from Charles Darwin 1873–81: 39–40)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Thiselton-Dyer, W. T. letters: 39–40</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent" subtype="personGrp">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1876-02-18">18 Feb 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for plants supplied from Kew.</p>
            <p>On structure and function of leaf glands of certain plants.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Kew</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Feb 18. 76</date>
                    <salute>My dear Dyer</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many thanks about Cinerarea: I had no idea it was a Senecio: whenever you see M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Moore pray thank him for me.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I will return the Pleroma in a few days by rail, and let you know by <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula><hi rend="superscript">d</hi> card when it is dispatched.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> We have cut off the branches which straggled up to the roof, leaving some of the lower ones. By the way I have made out that pollen from the shorter stamens fertilises much fewer seeds than that from the longer stamens. Cecropia &amp; the Acacia have arrived in good state but I am frightened at having the unique specimen of the latter.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> They are both in fine condition for Frank to investigate; and Cecropia abounds with the little eggs or pats of butter whichever they may be called.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>With respect to the glands on the leaves of the common laurel, the stipules of Vicia, the phyllodium of some acacias &amp;c I believe they are simple excretory organs; and this seems to me probable considering that some leaves under certain climatic influences secrete a sweet juice without possessing any glands.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Delpino argues that the glands serve in every case to attract ants as a protection; but I do not believe this &amp; with our common laurel hive bees suck the secretion much oftener than ants.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> A German whose name I can’t recollect (Reinke) maintains that the points of all crenated leaves are furnished in the very early bud condition with glands which excrete.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>With very many thanks for all your kind assistance | Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>PS I | I understood from Murie that he had nothing to do with the Edinburgh Courant, but he hinted about some botanist who thought himself very unfairly treated by not going on the Arctic exped<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> | CD</p>
<p>PS II | Many thanks for the beautifully clear labels, &amp; for the Stipa information<ref target="#foot.f9"/> | FD</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 14 February [1876]</ref> and n. 2. Thiselton-Dyer sent CD a letter he received from Thomas Moore discussing the botanical name of florist’s cineraria (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-10394.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Thomas Moore to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 15 February 1876</ref>). At this time, the plant was placed in the genus <hi rend="italic">Senecio</hi> (ragworts and groundsels), although it had formerly been classified as <hi rend="italic">Cineraria</hi> (a related genus that is now mostly restricted to South African species).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 14 February [1876]</ref> and n. 3. <hi rend="italic">Pleroma</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Tibouchina</hi>) is a neotropical plant genus of the family Melastomataceae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 14 February [1876]</ref> and n. 5. <hi rend="italic">Acacia cornigera</hi> (bull-horn acacia) and <hi rend="italic">Cecropia peltata</hi> (the embauba or trumpet-tree) were the species sent.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> wanted to analyse the nutrient composition of the food bodies produced by <hi rend="italic">Cecropia peltata</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Acacia cornigera</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 14 February [1876]</ref> and n. 4). The ‘little eggs or pats of butter’ are now called Müllerian bodies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The common laurel is <hi rend="italic">Prunus laurocerasus</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vicia</hi> is the genus of vetch. The phyllodium (now more commonly referred to as the phyllode) is an expanded, usually flattened petiole resembling and functioning as a leaf-blade, the true leaf-blade being absent or much reduced in size (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref> had argued in ‘Rapporti tra insetti i tra nettarii estranuziali in alcune piante’ (Relations between insects and extranuptual nectaries in some plants; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8918.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1875</ref>, pp. 76–7) that extrafloral (or extanuptual) nectaries were only associated with ants or wasps.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7538.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johannes Reinke</ref> had made the observation in ‘Ueber die Function der Blattzähne und die morphologische Werthigkeit einiger Laubblatt-Nectarien’ (On the function of leaf teeth and the morphological significance of foliage leaf nectaries; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reinke 1873</ref>, pp. 824–5). CD added a reference to Reinke’s observation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 403 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Murie</ref> had visited CD in December 1875, and may have commented on an article in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi>, but it has not been identified (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10308.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, [19 December 1875]</ref>). The Arctic expedition of 1875–6 was led by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3481.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Strong Nares</ref>; two naturalists were employed, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Wemyss Feilden</ref>, an army officer and naturalist who served on HMS <hi rend="italic">Alert</hi>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7440.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Chichester Hart</ref>, a botanist who served on HMS <hi rend="italic">Discovery</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8722.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nares 1878</ref>, 1: ix–x). The botanist mentioned has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles and Francis Darwin to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 14 February [1876]</ref> and n. 9.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>