<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6615">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Jean Jacques Moulinié   15 February 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10184</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6615 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6615.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6615.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp, encl 6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 272; DAR 193: 59–62</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 272,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>193: 59–62</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3428.xml">Moulinié, J. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                <date when="1869-02-15">15 Feb 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends abstract of an article by Carrière [<hi rend="italic">J. Agric. Pratique</hi> 1 (1869): 159–67] on the improvement of wild radish by selection.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">radish</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">J. Agric. Pratique</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Carriere, E. A. 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                    <date>15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1869</date>
                    <salute>Dear sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In perusing a french periodical intitled Journal d’Agriculture pratique, published weekly in Paris, I fall on an article published by a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Carrière,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> concerning a very curious case of variation observed on the wild radish (<hi rend="underline">Raphanus raphanistru〈m</hi>)〉; and describing the remarkable results obtained in a very short time, by selection and a rational cultivation of that wild plant. Thinking that the case, owing to the paper in which it is published, and which is perhaps not much known in England, might not come to your knowledge,—and may be of some interest for you,—I inclose hereby,—with a rough outline of the woodcuts accompanying the notice, and showing the wonderful differences obtained after four generations only, between the wild radish roots and those of the derived varieties improved by selection,—an abstract of the author’s paper, describing the experiment, its results, and the very simple process followed by him.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Hoping that my little abstract, from your being still unacquainted with its object, may have some interest for you, and still more that this letter may find you in good health, pray, dear Sir, present my respectful compliments to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Darwin, remember me kindly to all the members of your amiable and hospitable family,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> and believe me | your’s ever and truly devoted | J. J. Moulinié</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="left">Journal d’Agriculture pratique. T. I, N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 5, 1869. 33<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Année; p. 159. Paris.— Rédacteur en chef, E. Lecouteux.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">The wild radish improved, an insight on the origin of cultivated plants, in reference to <hi rend="underline">Raphanus raphanistrum.</hi> | by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. A. Carrière. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>The <hi rend="underline">Raphanus raphanistrum</hi> is a wild plant well known by agricultors as a very inconvenient weed, for its tendancy to invade with much tenacity cultivated fields. It belongs to the Cruciferae, and has some likeness with the <hi rend="underline">Sinapis arvense</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> with which it is often mistaken. Its flowers are sometimes of a pale yellow, sometimes white or streaked with lilac. Having remarked some analogy between the fruit of the garden radish and that of the wild <hi rend="underline">R. raphanistrum</hi>, the author gathered some of this last’s seed, sowed it in good soil, during five years, each time selecting with care the seeds borne by the plants modified in the most advantageous manner. The experiment was pursued in two different conditions; in Paris, in the dry and light soil of the Museum’s nursery gardens; and in the country, in a heavier, calcareous and clayish ground. The results of the two trials were similar but not identical. In Paris the elongated napiform shape was predominant in the roots; in the country it was the reverse. In Paris the roots were all white or pink, while in those raised in the country, besides those two colours, a great many were very dark lilac or brown, some nearly black, and others of all shapes and colours representing all the various known forms of radishes &amp; turnips, and much alike them, though not identical. One particular root (fig. 3) quite similar to the large China-radish, had a particular savour, between that of radish and turnip. Another (fig. 5) had a fine lilac skin, with flesh of the same colour and was consequently amongst vegetables, analogous to the red fleshed beetroot, the lilac potato; and certain flesh-coloured peeches &amp; pears amongst fruit.</p> 
<p/>

    <table>
        <row>
            <cell rend="centre" cols="2">Table of characters of <hi rend="underline">R. raphanistrum</hi> wild, and of its cultivated varieties, compared.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width45"><hi rend="underline">R. raphanistrum.</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="left width45">Varieties <hi rend="underline">derived.</hi></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Flowers</hi>, pale yellow or white,</cell>
            <cell rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Flowers</hi>, white, yellow or lilac-pink,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">sometimes slightly streaked with lilac.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">sometimes of one colour, oftener</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">streaked.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Pods</hi>, small, inclined, hard.</cell>
            <cell rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Pods</hi>, variable in size and shape,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">inclined, sometimes erect, sometimes</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">as large and long as the pods of</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">Madagascar radish, and then fleshy</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">and good for eating.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Roots</hi> filiform, dry, fibrous, uniform,</cell>
            <cell rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Roots</hi> large, sometimes enormous,</cell>
        </row> 
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">always white, hard, subligneous,</cell>
            <cell rend="left">fleshy, varying considerably in</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">uneatable.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">shape and colour; flesh, white,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">sometimes pinkish or yellowish,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">sometimes lilac, juicy, soft, and</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">eatable.</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
 

    <table>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width20">Figure 1,</cell>
            <cell rend="left">represents half-size, the roots of the wild plant at
                full</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">growth, weighing 22 grammes, white, hard,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">and quite uneatable.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 2.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">root white, top lilac; total length 0.45 centimeter;—largest</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">diameter 0.06 cent.:— weight 345 grammes.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 3.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Colour fine dark reddish pink, with top nearly lilac,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">hardly to be distinguished from the China-radish.— Total</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">length, 0.40 cent.— diameter, 0.09 ct.— weight, 445 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 4.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">White, with a lilac hue at the summit.— Length 0.25 ct.—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">diameter, 0.07 ct.— weight 201 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 5.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Dark black-lilac, veined; flesh lilac, with darker shades</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">and streaks to a depth of 0.01 ct.;—the rest of the pulp</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">being of a purplish white.— Length 22 ct. —diameter</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">0.07 ct.—weight 145 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 6</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Dark black chesnut skin; flesh milky white, very soft.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">Length, 27 ct.,— diameter, 0.06ct.;— weight 87 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 7</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Skin delicate and thin, of a fine pink colour; flesh of a very</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">juicy and melting quality. This root spreads near the surface</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">like certain breeds of turnips, and owing to its wide</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">and flattened shape, much ressembles the fine radishes</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">that gardeners select for seed. Length 0.12 ct.—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">Diameter, 0.06 ct.— Weight, 68 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 8</cell>
            <cell rend="left">This root has a pinkish brick colour: skin wrinkled, as</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">embroidered; flesh pink, with red streaks or veins to</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">0.01 centimeter’s depth, the rest being of a light flesh-</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">coloured white. Length, 0.26 ct;— diameter 0.13 ct:—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">weight 625 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 9.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">White, smooth and glossy skin; ressembling much a good</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">kind of turnip. Length, 0.32 ct.; diameter, 0.10 ct.—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">weight 651 gr.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 10</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Fruit branch of the wild radish, <hi rend="underline">R. raphanistrum</hi>,</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">—natural size.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Fig. 11.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Pod of the same, improved by cultivation. Natural size.</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
 
<p>All these roots though so different in shape and colour, were juicy, with a plain and marked flavour of radish, in some much like that of black radish. Tasted with care, a certain sweet flavour can be detected in several, reminding somewhat that of turnips, very slight in the raw state, but strong when cooked, the astringency of the radish disappearing completely. In the roots exposed to the air, and undergoing decomposition, the same smell of turnips was sensible. Their flesh was not quite similar to the radish, but more consistent, hardly sweet, and somewhat flowery, consequently more nutritious.</p>
<p>Here is a plant that can be ranked neither amongst radishes nor turnips, but partakes of the two, of radish when raw, of turnips when cooked, though generally the radish flavour is preponderant. This vegetable has been found excellent by all who have tasted it; the roots of all size are never hollow, and can be kept with all their qualities, for months in the cellar, and be used during the whole winter.</p>
<p>After some remarks on the effects of exterior conditions, and particularly the influence of the soil in modifying plants, shown by the different results obtained in the country soil, where the short roots were preponderant; while in the light and deep soil of Paris, they were exclusively long, white or slightly purplish (fig. 2), though all were derived from the same seed, the author concludes his paper in giving the best process to be used, and how selection must be practised in order to obtain in the quickest manner the desired modifications.</p>
<p>The object being the greatest growth of the underground part of the plant, he starts from seeds taken on the wild individuals which present already the largest roots, and continues in the same way with the offspring. The period of sowing the seed is not indifferent and must vary according to the part of the plant that is to be improved, so that it may come to its full growth.</p>
<p>To get large pods or improve any other aerial part, the seed must be sown in April or May, in a rich soil, in the best conditions of growth possible, and the best seed of the best plants selected for the next generations till the desired end be obtained.</p>
<p>To improve and increase the size of the roots, the seed must be sown in the beginning of September, so that the plants should not grow to seed the same year. When the cold season approaches, they are to be pulled out; and kept during the winter, sheltered from the frost, in a cool place, all their leaves, excepting those of the central part of the collar, being taken away. Next spring as soon as frost will be over, the finest of these wintered plants will be replanted in the best conditions, and their mature seed sown the same year, and the same process will have to be continued till the breed be fixed. Four generations and five years have been sufficient to give the results figured 2–9.</p>
<p>To improve rapidly and transform the <hi rend="underline">R. raphanistrum</hi>, gather seed on the wild plant, sow it the next spring in a good soil, in favouring its growth by all possible manner. On the most vigourous plants choose again the finest seed, to be sown the same autumn, and continue in the same manner till the desired results be obtained.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAGRAM HERE]</p> </figure> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAGRAM HERE]</p> </figure> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of enclosure</hi>: ‘Effects of conditions &amp; Selection’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_843.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Elie Abel Carrière</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD later received a copy of a revised version of the article, <hi rend="italic">Origine des plantes domestiques démontrée par la culture du radis sauvage</hi> (Origin of domestic plants shown by the cultivation of wild radish; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carrière 1869</ref>) from the author; this copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. CD cited Carrière’s paper and gave information on the radish in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, 1: 345.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Moulinié had visited CD on 31 August 1868 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6355.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. J. Moulinié, 7 September 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6137.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Lecouteux</ref> (editor-in-chief).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Moulinié refers to <hi rend="italic">Sinapis arvensis</hi> (wild mustard).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>