<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-498">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Andrew Smith<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   16 March 1839</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5193</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-498 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-498.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-498.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 204: 172</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 172</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4396.xml">Smith, Andrew</persName>
                <placeName>Fort Pitt, Chatham</placeName>
                <date when="1839-03-16">16 Mar 1839</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends his congratulations and best wishes on CD’s marriage.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">marriage</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Fort Pitt Chatham</placeName>
                    <date>16 March 1839</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I have been making inquiries of late regarding you and have at last discovered you were again in Town and with more cares upon your shoulders than you had when last I had the pleasure of seeing you. I am quite uncertain whether or not I ever answered your last letter wherein you mentioned to me your intentions, if I did not you must not be angry with me for not evincing my sense of your friendship and confidence the omission you must ascribe entirely to the condition of my health—nothing short of such would have prevented me immediately replying to the letter and congratulating you on the judicious decision to which it appeared you had arrived. I am well satisfied that the position in which you have placed yourself is by far the most comfortable one and it is only a misfortune that more of mankind cannot seek it without so interfering with their occupations that it might actually be productive of a certain quantum of misery. Having said this much you will of course expect my congratulations and those you have with all sincerity. I hope you will live long to enjoy your new position and that all the good things of this world may be showered in profusion upon yourself and your better half</p>
<p>I wish I were able to place myself in a situation where I could make the above declaration in person but at present that is impossible, my health is still bad and though I find I am improving yet I fear it will be some time before I can visit London—perhaps, the return of warm weather may prove advantageous to me—if it does not I shall despair. I would ask you to run down here were it not too early to venture upon inducing you to seperate from rib I can only say a glimpse of your good natured face would do me a world of good. When does the Journal appear? I am glad to hear from M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>Fitz Roy that the Captain has nearly finished his labours. As regards my proceedings I have not been able to do any thing during the last six months you are walking away in style from me now—but I must be satisfied with being able to keep in your rear. Should you be able to find a little leisure time I should be delighted to hear from you I send this letter to Stewart<ref target="#foot.f2"/> as I do not know your address</p>
<p>I am | My Dear Darwin | Yours most sincerely | And<hi rend="superscript">w </hi>Smith</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="annotations">
    <note><hi rend="italic">On cover</hi>: ‘Physiology of Blushing’<ref target="#foot.f3"/></note>
</div>
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-304.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. S. Henslow, 9 July 1836</ref>, and <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> pp. 99–101. Smith had returned from South Africa and Natal in 1837; at this period he was writing his <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the zoology of South Africa</hi> (A. Smith 1838–49).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Possibly with the firm of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4560.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stewart and Murray</ref>, Old Bailey, London, the printers of both Smith’s work and the <hi rend="italic">Zoology.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5907.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebook C</hi></ref>: 265, an entry reads ‘March 20<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> h. 1839. Philosophy of Blushing lately advertised. /6s’ Burgess’s <hi rend="italic">Physiology or mechanism of blushing</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1090.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burgess 1839</ref>) is listed in the <hi rend="italic">The Publishers’ Circular</hi> of 15 March 1839, p. 120. CD cites it frequently in chapter 13 of <hi rend="italic">Expression.</hi> See also CD’s entries in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebook N</hi></ref>: 15, 51–5 for his early interest in blushing. A copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1090.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burgess 1839</ref> is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>