<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2869A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Giles Bridle Daubeny   16 July [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20868</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2869A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2869A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2869A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Magdalen College, Oxford (MC:F26/C1/118)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_253.xml">Magdalen College, Oxford</repository>
                    <idno>MC:F26/C1/118</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Hartfield</placeName>
                <date when="1860-07-16">16 July [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1248.xml">Daubeny, C. G. B.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Confirms CGBD’s impression given in a letter to J. S. Henslow that CD in the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> did not touch directly upon the final causes of sexuality, which CD considers one of the "profoundest mysteries in nature". CD is inclined to stress sexuality as the means of keeping forms constant and checking variation although he grants its role in the origination of varieties. [See <hi rend="doubleUnderline">2869</hi>.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2235">Henslow, J. S.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Hartfield | Tonbridge Wells<ref target="#foot.f2"/></placeName>
                    <date>16 July</date>
                    <salute>My dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Daubeny</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Henslow has sent me part of a note of yours &amp; his answer.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You are quite right that there is nothing direct in my Book on the final cause or manner of origination of the sexes.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It seems to me one of the profoundest mysteries in nature. Especially since the facts of parthenogenesis have been clearly made out.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have heard Huxley remark that the old saying was “it was a wise child who knew who his Father was”, but now the saying might be, “it was a wise child who knew whether he had a Father.”—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I have often speculated on your view,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> &amp; I have somewhere got a case of a trifling variation being propagated by gemmation with anim〈als〉 (in a coral) just as we see almost every shade of difference propagated by grafts &amp; buds with plants.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I daresay that you are quite right that one of the final causes of sexuality is the origination of varieties;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> but the number of cases which can be collected of “sporting” plants ie plants which have varied by gemmation has made me rather doubtful on this head.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I am inclined to lay <hi rend="doubleUnderline">more</hi> stress on sexuality (p. 103 Origin of Species 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> edit) being the means of keeping forms constant ie of checking variation. This is a subject on which I have worked much; but have said hardly anything in the Origin.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The whole subject of sexuality seems to me profoundly interesting &amp; mysterious; &amp; the more it is stirred up the better.</p>
<p>Pray believe me | My dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Daubeny | Yours very sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">3.8 mysterious;] ‘;’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘—-’</note>
                </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the date on which Daubeny read his paper in Oxford (see n. 3, below) and from CD’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2869.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. S. Henslow, 16 July [1860]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8), which refers to CD’s sending the present letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">From 10 July to 2 August, CD joined Emma and Henrietta Darwin at The Ridge, Hartfield, East Sussex, the home of Emma’s sister, Sarah Elizabeth Wedgwood (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, including Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Daubeny’s note and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Stevens Henslow’s</ref> answer have not been found; however, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2869.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. S. Henslow, 16 July [1860]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8). The correspondence between Daubeny and Henslow was evidently prompted by a paper read by Daubeny at the meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science in Oxford, in a session chaired by Henslow on 28 June 1860 (see <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 7 July 1860, p. 25). CD did not attend the meeting (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2846.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 26 [June 1860]</ref>). In writing the present letter to Daubeny, CD probably relied on information from Henslow on the content of Daubeny’s paper, as he did not receive the published text (Daubeny 1860a) until later (see this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2887A.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Charles Daubeny, 1 August [1860]</ref> and n. 2). CD may also have read a report of Daubeny’s paper in the press (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 7 July 1860, pp. 25–6, reproduced in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, Appendix VI).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">According to the report of his paper in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> (see n. 3, above), Daubeny questioned the final cause of sexes in plants in view of the allegedly identical results of sexual and asexual reproduction. Daubeny cited various possible uses of sexual reproduction in plants, such as the provision of fruit for food, the gratification of the human senses, and the spatial dissemination of species, but contended that CD’s theory of natural selection, subject to its acceptance, offered a more plausible and universal final cause than these. CD’s own earlier interest in the final cause of sexual difference is reflected in his <hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi>: ‘My theory gives great final cause … of <hi rend="italic">sexes</hi> …: for otherwise, there would be as many species, as individuals.... [I]f my theory be true then the formation of sexes rigidly necessary’ (Notebook E, 48–9; see also <hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi>, Notebook C, 236, Notebook D, 167). In <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, however, CD confined himself to more general observations on the origin of sexual reproduction, such as, for example, ‘that it is a general law of nature … that no organic being self-fertilises itself for an eternity of generations’ (<hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, p. 97). In his ‘Provisional hypothesis of pangenesis’, CD again considered the final cause of sexual reproduction (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2: 362). For recent discussions of the teleology implied in the nineteenth-century use of the term ‘final cause’, and of the teleology implied in CD’s writings in particular, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2358.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">England 2001</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7227.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Sloan 2001</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">During the previous decade, several publications on parthenogenesis had appeared, for example R. Owen 1849 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7183.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Siebold 1857</ref>, annotated copies of which are in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi> 1: 656–7, 756–7). These were followed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley’s</ref> paper on parthenogenesis in aphids, which challenged <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen’s</ref> explanation of the phenomenon (T. H. Huxley 1858; see also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, [before 12 November 1857]</ref>). In the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> there is no reference to parthenogenesis, but CD added a single reference in the second edition, published on 7 January 1860, in the phrase ‘with the exception of the curious and not well-understood cases of parthenogenesis’ (<hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 2d ed., p. 96).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">This quotation has not been found in Huxley’s writings. It appears to derive from ‘It is a wise father that knows his own child’, Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Merchant of Venice</hi>, 2.2.72–3 (S. Wells and Taylor eds. 1988). Huxley’s work on parthenogenesis in aphids prompted him to question the necessity of the male in reproduction (T. H. Huxley 1858, p. 220).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Daubeny held that sexual reproduction in plants provided a mechanism for variation, whereas asexual reproduction produced ‘a mere counterpart’ of the parental stock (see <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 7 July 1860, pp. 25–6; see also Daubeny 1860a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Gemmation in this sense means ‘the formation of a new individual by the protrusion and complete or partial separation of a part of the parent’ (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>). CD’s ‘case of a trifling variation’ propagated by the vegetative reproduction of an animal in coral has not been identified. For CD’s later discussion of asexual reproduction and variation, see <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 374 and 2: 358–9, 371–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See n. 7, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD’s point about variation in plants raised by gemmation was cited by Daubeny in a footnote, with a reference to this letter (Daubeny 1860a, p. 23 n.). ‘Sports’ are new varieties that arise from mutations, chiefly in buds, and are then propagated by vegetative reproduction. CD gave numerous examples of sports in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 373–411. As examples of variation independent of sexual reproduction, sports were a challenge to Daubeny’s view; see also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2869.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. S. Henslow, 16 July [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD alludes to the sentence ‘Intercrossing plays a very important part in nature in keeping the individuals of the same species, or of the same variety, true and uniform in character’ in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, p. 103. CD maintained this view in all editions of <hi rend="italic">Origin.</hi> There are further details of his work on the role of crossing in the origination of species in <hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi>, p. 271, where he states: ‘Intercrossing will prevent or retard the process of natural selection; but here we are involved in much doubt.’</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>