<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-693">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> <ref target="#foot.f1"/>   [late August 1843]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15601</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-693 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-693.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-693.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 175</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 383</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, no. 36, 9 September 1843, p. 628</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Gard. Chron. 1843: 628</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1843-08-01" notAfter="1843-08-31">[late Aug 1843]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1808.xml">Gardeners’ Chronicle</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends some examples of <hi rend="italic">Gentiana</hi> that he thinks may shed light on the origin of double flowers. Since specimens grew in sterile soil their double flowering cannot be attributed to excess food. CD advances the hypothesis that some change in natural conditions causes sterility, which then causes compensatory development of petals, the organs closest in morphology to those whose functions have been checked.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Gentiana</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">double flowers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
<p>The inclosed specimens appear to me curious, as in some degree connected with the origin of double flowers. They consist of plants of the Gentiana amarella, found in a wild state, covered with abortive buds, or rather minute double flowers. Each head consists of innumerable small petal-like purplish scales, having in their centre a tuft of still smaller green scales. A plant covered with these little heads not infrequently bears, especially near the top of the stem, one or two more perfect flowers. By examining these, a series can be shown, by which the stamens are seen to become deformed, and gradually to pass into small petals and scales. The pistil also can be traced, becoming more and more foliaceous. The change in the pistil has been effected in several flowers, whilst the stamens have remained nearly perfect. In the same manner I have observed in double Violets and some other garden flowers, that the pistil, contrary to the general rule, is metamorphosed before the stamens. In other semi-perfect flowers of the Gentiana, the divisions of the corolla and the number of the stamens, with their filaments flattened, are increased; in others, besides the five ordinary stamens, in an imperfect state, the divisions of the corolla are partially converted into stamen-like bodies: if this conversion had been effected, the flower would have become apetalous. In a Bladder-nut (Staphylea) growing in a shady wood, I last summer noticed a similar fact, namely, that the petals showed a tendency to form additional stamens. The plants of the Gentiana bearing the little tufts are generally, but not always, dwarfer than the perfect plants; their leaves are less pointed, and the entire plant is much less symmetrical. The much greater number of the imperfect flowers on one plant than are ever produced of the perfect, shows, I presume, that the metamorphic change must be determined early in the plant’s life. Except in their small size, less beauty, and in the occasional presence on the same stem of flowers in different stages of monstrosity; these purple tufts seem to be essentially similar in their nature to the double flowers of Horticulturists.</p>
<p>The plants of the Gentiana in both states grow mingled together on a very hard, dry, bare chalk bank; but those with the abortive flowers grow on rather the barest spots, where it was surprising that anything could grow. You state in your “Theory of Horticulture,”<ref target="#foot.f2"/> that the origin of double flowers is not well understood. Some have attributed it to excess of food; but the dry chalk bank surely was not too rich a soil; and I may mention that late last autumn, I found on an adjoining field of wretchedly sterile clay, great numbers of the Ranunculus repens, producing semi-double flowers, some having three, some additional rows of petals. The partial or entire sterility of double flowers is generally attributed to their doubleness; but is not this putting the effect before the cause? It is well known that plants (and indeed animals, as I could show by a series of facts) when placed out of their natural conditions, become, often from apparently slight and unintelligible causes, sterile. How many American plants fail in producing pollen in this country! the anthers of the Persian and Chinese Lilacs, as I observed this summer, are as destitute of good pollen as if they had been hybrids. Other plants produce good pollen, but are defective, as it appears, in their ovules, as their germen never swells. Linnæus has remarked that most Alpine plants, when cultivated in the lowlands, are rendered quite sterile. In most of these cases, we see that sterility is compatible with long life and health. Is it, then, too bold a theory to suppose that all double flowers are first rendered by some change in their natural condition, to a certain degree, sterile; and that their vessels being charged with organizable matter in excess, (which would be greatly formed by high cultivation,) it is converted into petals—the organs which are nearest in their morphological nature and position to those whose functions are checked? Is there any shadow of truth in this theory, or is it an abortive one, as are the buds of the Gentiana?— <hi rend="underline">C. Darwin.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>P.S.— I also send a curious Cabbage-leaf, grown into the form of a perfect funnel, like the fold of paper into which grocers put sugar. It was borne on a long footstalk from the centre of an old stalk, from which a Cabbage had been cut this summer. I remember that De Candolle describes pitchers at the end of the leaves of some Cabbages, which he compares to those of the Nepenthes.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Is this leaf something of the same kind?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter was printed in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle </hi> under the heading ‘Double flowers—their origin’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 175–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4766.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lindley 1840</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">At this point the editor (Lindley) interpolated the following: ‘We can only say that this is at least as reasonable an hypothesis as any that we have seen; but the greater frequency of double flowers in gardens where soil is rich, than in fields where it is poor, offers some difficulty in the way of Mr. Darwin’s speculation.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1839–40</ref>, 1: 272.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">At this point an editorial insertion reads ‘Yes’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>