<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7274">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Bernhard Tegetmeier   14 July 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">2616</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7274 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7274.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7274.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 82, DAR 193: 43</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 82</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4682.xml">Tegetmeier, W. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Finchley</placeName>
                <date when="1870-07-14">14 July 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends a letter by Mr Teebay on variation in wild ducks.</p>
            <p>Offers to lend Dr Cooper’s book on game fowls.</p> 
<p>Is preparing a new edition [1873] of his <hi rend="italic">Poultry book</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ducks</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fowls, game</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Poultry book</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Cooper, Dr</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4681">Tebay, Septimus</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Tegetmeier, W. B. 1873</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Finchley | N</placeName>
                    <date>July 14/70</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I enclose you a proof of a very interesting letter on Variation in Wild Ducks by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Teebay on whose accuracy of observation I can fully rely.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I do not know whether you are working at varieties now. If you are would you like to look at D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cooper’s octavo volume on Game fowls.— It is an American Treatise on Fighting Cocks.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> with a vast amount of valuable information in an American form.— — If you would like to see it I can lend you my own copy or I could get you one at the publishing price 5 dollars. but mine is very much at your service for as long as you like</p>
<p>I am at work on a new edition of my own large poultry book and will, with your permission, avail myself of your store of information in your work on ‘<hi rend="underline">Variation</hi>’.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I have lately been making some observations respecting your theory of analogous variation,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; I have thought of collecting the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">prototypes</hi>? of our varieties of pigeons. and comparing with the varieties.. and having drawings made of each, the analogy is closer than I could have imagined. After all the breeds of the fancier are but imitations of the colorations, etc. of wild species of the same group</p>
<p>The cases would form a good subject for a paper—</p>
<p>I am breeding from the Crested Turkey but the young are not yet old enough for me to say whether any have crests. but you shall know—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I have not been able to work much lately at subjects of purely scientific interest   Fortune holds to many hostages and constrains me to work for her but as my work is congenial I am thankful.</p>
<p>Trusting your health is good | Believe me truly yours | W B Tegetmeier</p>
<p>I forget whether or no I ever sent you a drawing of the crested turkey so forward one<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">White Wild Ducks</hi></p> 
<p><hi rend="underline">I have a pure-bred wild duck and drake that last year had two nests of young ones. In the first hatch were ten of the true wild duck colour, and one (which turned out a duck) with pure white plumage. In the second nest there was<ref target="#foot.f7"/> again ten of the true wild colour and one pure white drake, and a duck all white, except a black spot on the top of the head and black tail coverts—this duck is now pure white in plumage. The beaks of the two that were pure white are bright orange; the beak of the other ducks is bright orange, with the saddle on the upper beak much speckled with rich black. The legs of all three are orange, the webs of the feet of a more dusky colour. All three are remarkably slender in form, and have the long graceful shape of the pure wild duck.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">This year the same pair of old birds have eleven youngs ones of the true wild duck colour, and one, pure white. Both the old birds were from eggs taken from separate wild duck nests, are both pinioned, and the duck has had no access to any other drake.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Early this year the white drake was paired with the white duck. She has eight young ones nearly full grown, five of which are pure white in plumage, the other three white with the small black spot on the top of the head and black in the coverts. The black on these three is much less than it was when they were in their first feathers, and will very likely be replaced with white when they make up their plumage.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">The other duck that had the black spot on the head and the black tail coverts was paired with a wild drake of the true colour. Her nests having been twice destroyed, she has only four young ones, which are not yet feathered, but from appearance three will be pure white, and one with the spot on the head and some black above the tail.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">The white drake and two ducks have not been pinioned, and during last autumn and beginning of winter had full liberty of flying miles round, but never, that I know of, alighting anywhere except at their own ponds. When taking a long flight they would go an immense height, and to my mind there are few more beautiful sights than to watch their manœvres in the air on a windy day, especially when coming down.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">I am totally at a loss to account for these white birds, as the remainder of the old duck’s young are as near like one another and like their parents as possible, and it is more strange that the nearly white duck put to the grey drake should produce white young ones. It is again singular the the coloured feathers should be all black, not one having had a grey feather. Beautiful as these white birds are, if they would retain the black spot on the top of the head, and the black tail coverts some of them have in their earlier feathers, they would be still more beautiful.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Richard Teebay.</hi></p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 I am … ‘<hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>’. 3.2] <hi rend="italic">scored ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure</hi>:</note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Right margin</hi>: ‘The Field | July 1870’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; ‘7’ <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘6’</note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Tegetmeier enclosed an article, ‘White wild ducks’, by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6846.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Teebay</ref>, that appeared in the 18 July 1870 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Field</hi> (the annotated cutting is in DAR 193: 43). Teebay described the offspring of a pair of pinioned wild ducks, among which were three white individuals. He also described the progeny of the white individuals. Tegetmeier was pigeon and poultry editor of the <hi rend="italic">Field</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Tegetmeier refers to John W. Cooper and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1559.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cooper [1869]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Tegetmeier refers to <hi rend="italic">The poultry book</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tegetmeier 1867</ref>) and to <hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi> The new edition of <hi rend="italic">The poultry book</hi> (Tegetmeier 1873) appeared in monthly parts between March 1872 and May 1873. Tegetmeier mentioned CD’s work in the preface to the new edition, and quoted a long passage from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> on the peafowl (Tegetmeier 1873, pp. 331–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 348, CD had discussed analogous variation, or the appearance of similar characteristics in several varieties or races descended from the same, or even distinct, species.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Tegetmeier had sent CD an engraving of the crested turkey and enclosed specimens of the crest feathers in his letter of 20 July 1869 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See n. 5, above. The only extant image of the crested turkey in the Darwin Archive–CUL is the one Tegetmeier had already sent. It is in DAR 193: 39.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The word ‘was’ has been crossed through with pen and ‘were’ added in the margin.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>