<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1116">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   8 [September 1847]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1912</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1116 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1116.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1116.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp &amp; CC 6pp &amp; C</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 167</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 181</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 4: 65</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 50: C3–C6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>50: C3–C6</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <idno>68</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1847-09-08">8 [Sept 1847]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses David Milne’s Glen Roy paper ["On the parallel roads of Lochaber", <hi rend="italic">Trans. R. Soc. Edinburgh</hi> 16 (1849): 395–418]. Rejects Milne’s theory that outlet of Glen Roy is blocked by detritus. Impressed by Milne’s discovery of an outlet at the level of the second shelf. Believes this strengthens theory that lakes were formed by glacier blocking Glen Roy. Offers arguments against glacier theory.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">parallel roads</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Trans. R. Soc. Edinburgh</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Glen Roy</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Milne-Home, David 1849</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Wednesday 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Many thanks for the Paper.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I do admire your zeal on a subject on which you are not immediately at work. I will give my opinion as briefly as I can &amp; I have endeavoured my best to be honest. Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Lyell will have, I foresee, a long letter to read aloud, but I will try to write better than usual.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Imprimis, it is provoking that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne has read my paper with little attention, for he makes me say several things, which I do not believe,—as that the water sunk suddenly p. 10!! that valley of Glen p. 13. &amp; Spean<ref target="#foot.f4"/> was filled with detritus up to level of the lower shelf, against which I conceive there is good evidence &amp;c,—but I suppose it is the consequence of my paper being most tediously written. He gives me a just snub for talking of demonstration;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; he fights me in a very pleasant manner.</p>
<p>Now for business,—I utterly disbelieve in the <hi rend="underline">barriers</hi> for his lakes &amp; think he has left that point exactly where it was in the time of Macculloch &amp; Dick.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Indeed in showing that there is a passage at Glen Glaster at the level of the intermediate shelf he makes the difficulty to my mind greater. When I think of the gradual manner in which the 2 upper terraces die out at Glen Collarig, &amp; at mouth of Glen Roy—the smooth rounded form of the hills there,—the lower shelf retaining its usual width where the immense barrier stood;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I can deliberately repeat “that more convincing proofs of the non existence of the imaginary Loch Roy could scarcely have been invented with full play given to the imagination.” &amp;c<ref target="#foot.f8"/> But I do not adhere to this remark with such strength, when applied to the Glacier lake theory:<ref target="#foot.f9"/> oddly I never was at all staggered by this theory, until now having read M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne’s arguments against it; I now can hardly doubt that a great glacier did emerge from L. Treig, &amp; this by the ice itself (not moraine) might have blocked up the 3 outlets from Glen Roy. I do not, however, yet believe in the glacier theory, for reasons which I will presently give.—</p>
<p>There are three chiefly hostile considerations in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne’s paper.— First the Glen luy shelf not coinciding in height with the upper one: four observations giving 12<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>, 15<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>, 29<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>, 23<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>;<ref target="#foot.f10"/> if the latter are correct, this terrace must be quite independent &amp; the case is hostile,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> but M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne shows that there is one in Glen Roy 14 ft below the upper one, &amp; a second one again (which I observed) beneath this, &amp; then we come to the proper second shelf. Hence there is no great improbability in an independent shelf having been formed in Glen Gluy.</p>
<p>This leads me to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Milnes second class of facts, (obvious to everyone) namely the non-extension of the three shelves beyond Glen Roy; but I abide by what I have written on that point,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> &amp; repeat, that if in Glen Roy,, where circumstances have been so favourable for the preservation or formation of the terraces, a terrace could be formed quite plain for <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of a mile with hardly a trace elsewhere, we cannot argue from the non-existence of shelves, that water did not stand at these same levels in other valleys. Feeling absolutely convinced that there was no barrier of detritus at the mouth of Glen Roy, &amp; pretty well convinced there was none of ice, the manner in which the terraces die out when entering Glen Spean, which must have been a tide way, shows on what small circumstances the formation of these shelves depended. With respect to the non-existence of shelves in other parts of Scotland, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne shows that many others do exist, &amp; their heights above the sea have not yet been carefully measured, nor have even those of Glen Roy, which I suspect are all 100 ft too high.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Moreover according to Bravais,<ref target="#foot.f14"/> we must not feel sure that either the absolute heights, or the intermediate heights between the terraces, would be at all the same at distant points. In levelling the terraces in Lochaber, all I believe have been taken in Glen Roy neary N. &amp; S; there sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be levels taken at right angles to this line, &amp; to the Great Glen of Scotland, or chief line of elevation.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Thirdly</hi>: the nature of the outlets from the supposed lakes: this appears to me the best &amp; newest part of the paper. If Sir James Clark<ref target="#foot.f15"/> would like to attend to any particular points, direct his attention to this; especially to follow Glen Glastig from Glen Roy to L. Laggan. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne describes this as an old &amp; great river course with a fall of 212 ft. He states that the rocks are smooth on upper face &amp; rough on lower, but he does not mention whether this character prevails throughout the whole 212 vertical feet,—a most important consideration. Nor does he state whether these rocks are polished or scratched, as might have happened even to a considerable depth beneath the water (Mem. great icebergs in <hi rend="underline">narrow</hi> fiords of T. del Fuego)<ref target="#foot.f16"/> by the action of icebergs, for that icebergs transported boulders on to the terraces, I have no doubt. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne’s description of the outlets of his lakes, sound to me more like tidal channels nor does he give any arguments how such are to be distinguished from old river courses. I cannot believe in the body of fresh water, which must on the lake theory have flowed out of them. At the pass of Muckul, he states that the outlet is 70 feet wide &amp; the rocky bottom 21 feet below the level of the shelf, &amp; that the gorge expands to the eastwards, “<hi rend="underline">into a broad channel of several hundred yards in width, divided in</hi> <hi rend="underline">the middle by what has formerly been a rocky islet, against which</hi> <hi rend="underline">the waters of this large river had chafed in issuing from the</hi> <hi rend="underline">pass</hi>.”<ref target="#foot.f17"/> We know the size of the river at the present day which would flow out through this pass, &amp; it seems to me (&amp; in the other given cases) to be as inadequate: the whole seems to me far easier explained by a tideway, than by a formerly more humid climate.</p>
<p>With respect to the very remarkable coincidence between the shelves &amp; the outlets (rendered more remarkable by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne’s discovery of the outlet to the intermediate shelf at Glen Glastig),<ref target="#foot.f18"/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne gives only half of my explanation; he alludes to (&amp; disputes) the smoothing &amp; silting up action, which I still believe in. I state “If we consider what must take place during the gradual rise of a group of islands, we shall have the currents endeavouring to cut down &amp; deepen some shallow parts in the channels, as they are successively brought <hi rend="underline">near the surface</hi>, but tending from the opposition of tides to choke up others with littoral deposits. During a long interval of rest, from the length of time allowed to the above processes, the tendency would often prove effective, both in forming, by accumulation of matter, isthmuses, &amp; in keeping open channels. Hence such isthmuses &amp; <hi rend="doubleUnderline">channels just kept open</hi>, would oftener be formed at the level, which the waters held at the interval of rest, than at any one other p. 65”<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>I look at the pass of Muckul (21 ft deep, Milne) as a channel just kept open, &amp; the head of Glen Roy (where there is a great Bay silted up) &amp; of Kilfinnin,<ref target="#foot.f20"/> (at both which places, there are level-topped mounds of detritus <hi rend="underline">above</hi> the level of the terraces) as instances of channels filled up at the stationary levels. I have long thought it a probable conjecture, that when a rising surface becomes stationary, it becomes so not at once, but by the movements first becoming very slow: this would greatly favour the cutting down many gaps in the mountains to the level of the stationary periods.—</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Glacial Theory</hi>.— If a glacialist admitted that the Sea before the formation of the terraces covered the country (which would account for “<hi rend="underline">land-straits</hi>” above level of terraces) &amp; that the land <hi rend="underline">gradually</hi> emerged; &amp; if he supposed his lakes were banked by ice alone, he would make out, in my opinion, the best case against the marine origin of the terraces. From the <hi rend="underline">scattered</hi> boulders &amp; till, you &amp; I must look at it as certain that the sea did cover the whole country; &amp; I abide quite by my arguments from the buttresses &amp;c &amp;c<ref target="#foot.f21"/> that water of some kind receded slowly from the valleys of Lochaber (I presume M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne admits this). Now I do not believe in the ice-lake theory, from the following weak, but accumulated reasons because 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> the receding water must have been that of a lake in Glen Spean &amp; of the sea in the other valleys of Scotland, where I saw similar buttresses at many levels. 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. because the outlets of the supposed lakes, as already stated, seem from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milnes statements too much worn &amp; too large. 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. When the lake stood at the <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of mile shelf, the water from it must have flowed over ice itself <hi rend="underline">for a very long time</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">kept at the</hi> <hi rend="underline">same</hi> <hi rend="underline">exact level</hi>: certainly this shelf required a long time for its formation 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I cannot believe a glacier c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have blocked up the short, very wide, valley of Kilfinnin, the Great Glen of Scotland, also, being very low there. 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> The country at some places, where M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne has described terraces, is not mountainous, &amp; the number of ice-lakes appears to me very improbable. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I do not believe any lake could scoop the rocks<ref target="#foot.f22"/> so much as they are at the entrance of Loch Treig, or cut them off at the head of upper Glen Roy 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. the very gradual dying away of the terraces at the mouth of Glen Roy, does not look like a barrier of any kind.— 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have expected great terminal moraines across the mouth of Glen Roy, Glen Collarig &amp; Glastig, at least at the bottoms of the valleys; such I feel pretty sure do not exist.<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p>
<p>I fear I must have wearied you with the length of this letter, which I have not had time to arrange properly.— I could argue at great length against M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milnes theory of barriers of detritus,<ref target="#foot.f24"/> though I could help him in one way, viz by the soundings which occur at the entrances of the deepest fiords in T. del Fuego.<ref target="#foot.f25"/> I do not think he gives the smallest satisfaction with respect to the successive &amp; comparatively sudden breakage of his many lakes.</p>
<p>Well, I enjoyed my trip to Glen Roy very much, but it was time thrown away: I heartily wish you would go there: it should be some one who knows glacier &amp; iceberg action &amp; sea-action well: I wish the Queen would command you.— I had intended being in London tomorrow, but one of my painful plagues will, I believe, stop me; if I do I will assuredly call on you. I have not yet read M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Milne on Elevation, so will keep his paper for a day or two.<ref target="#foot.f26"/></p>
<p>Farewell, my dear Lyell, ever most truly yours C. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. As you cannot want this letter, I wish you would return it me, as it will serve as a memorandum for me—possibly I shall write to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Chambers,<ref target="#foot.f27"/> though I do not know whether he will care what I think on the subject. This letter is too long &amp; ill-written for Sir J. Clark</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.2 Wednesday 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘Thursday’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.4 aloud,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.3 p. 10] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.3 p. 13.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.3 &amp; Spean] <hi rend="italic">interl after del</hi> ‘Roy’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.6 just] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘proper’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.1 the <hi rend="italic">barriers</hi>] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.5 2 upper] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.5 &amp; at mouth of Glen Roy— 3.6] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.12 can] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘cannot’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">3.12 hardly] <hi rend="italic">after omitted point</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">3.13 this] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">3.14 the glacier] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">4.5 a second] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘another’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">4.6 this,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">4.7 Gluy.] <hi rend="italic">followed by closing and opening square brackets in MS to indicate the end and beginning of paragraphs</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">5.3 that if] ‘that’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘if’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">5.4 or formation] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">5.7 levels] <hi rend="italic">caret over full stop</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">5.7 in other valleys.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">5.12 many] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">5.13 even] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">5.15 either] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">6.6 throughout the] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25">6.9 beneath the water] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n26">6.10 by the action of icebergs, for that] <hi rend="italic">interl after del</hi> ‘&amp; that’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n27">6.10 on to] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘to’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n28">6.11 terraces] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘shores of’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n29">6.12 such] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘these’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n30">6.13 from old river courses.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n31">6.14 the] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n32">6.14 have] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n33">6.15 Muckul] ‘M’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘m’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n34">6.16 &amp; that] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n35">6.16 the gorge] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘where’; <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘pass’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n36">6.20 to me] <hi rend="italic">before del interl</hi> ‘&amp; is admitted’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n37">6.20 to be] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘&amp; is admitted’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n38">6.21 a tideway] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n39">6.21 a formerly] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n40">7.4 smoothing &amp;] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n41">7.4 still] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n42">7.8 littoral] ‘i’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘o’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n43">8.1 (21 ft deep, Milne)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n44">8.2 (where] ‘w’ <hi rend="italic">over ‘&amp;’</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n45">8.3 level-topped] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n46">8.4 terraces)] ‘)’ <hi rend="italic">over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n47">8.4 filled] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘silted’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n48">8.4 levels] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘level’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n49">8.6 movements] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘anterior’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n50">8.6 first becoming] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘being’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n51">8.7 to the] ‘to’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n52">8.8 stationary] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘fir’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n53">9.2 (which would … terraces) 9.3] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n54">9.3 that] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘gradually receded’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n55">9.3 the land] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘it’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n56">9.3 emerged;] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘rose’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n57">9.5 <hi rend="italic">scattered</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n58">9.7 from the buttresses &amp;c &amp;c] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n59">9.9 from the following … reasons] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n60">9.13 lake] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘water’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n61">9.14 the water] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n62">9.15 <hi rend="italic">same</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n63">9.15 required] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘for’; ‘r’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n64">9.17 Great] ‘G’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘g’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n65">9.17 , also,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n66">9.19 improbable.] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. The nature of the rounded Boulders on the terraces w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> throw much light on this point, viz whether icebergs from the glaciers of Ben Nevis could have brought such rocks..’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n67">9.20 the entrance] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n68">9.22 the mouth] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n69">9.23 have] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n70">9.23 terminal] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n71">10.4 deepest] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n72">10.6 breakage] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘fallings’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n73">11.2 &amp; iceberg 11.3] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n74">13.2 M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is based on the assumption that the paper CD refers to in the letter is Milne 1847b. CD received a copy of Milne 1847b in September. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1115.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Robert Chambers to David Milne, 7 September 1847</ref>, in which CD is referred to as being anxious to obtain a copy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Milne 1847b. The page references in the letter correspond to those of the privately printed memoir on the parallel roads of Lochaber. An annotated copy is in DAR 139: 5. References in the notes below are to Milne 1849, the version published in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Because of Lyell’s poor eyesight, his wife Mary Elizabeth frequently read to him. This letter was apparently returned to CD, as requested in the postscript, but a copy of it was also made by an unknown amanuensis, presumably for Lyell to retain. The copy is preserved among the letters to Lyell at the <ref target="" resp="#mjhawkins">American Philosophical Society</ref> (APS 68).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In the original letter CD wrote ‘Glen Roy’, with ‘p. 13.’ interlined after ‘Glen’ and ‘&amp; Spean’ interlined after ‘Roy’. This text is followed in the copy. Later, apparently, CD deleted ‘Roy’ and the ampersand, so that the text then read ‘Glen p. 13. Spean’. However, Milne referred only to Glen Roy on page thirteen, so it appears that CD deleted ‘Roy’ and the ampersand by mistake. The deletion is ignored in the copy. In his discussion of Milne’s paper CD followed a list of rough notes and comments he had made as he read it. These notes, together with a large number of others, some of which are labelled ‘Glen Roy scraps’, are preserved in DAR 50 (ser. 3): 7–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Observations on the parallel roads of Glen Roy’</ref> CD stated that the marine theory of the origin of the roads ‘appears to me demonstrated’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 118). Milne, in his paper, regretted that CD ‘should have expressed himself in these very decided and confident terms, especially as his survey was incomplete’ (Milne 1849, p. 400).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5072.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">MacCulloch 1817</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2000.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dick 1823</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD alludes to the lack of any remnants of earthen barriers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 98.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Buckland</ref>, the parallel roads were formed as a result of a glacier damming up the valley and forming a glacial lake, of which the roads were former beaches. See Agassiz 1840b, 1840c, and 1842b, pp. 237–40. CD rejected this theory mainly because of the absence of a known outlet for the lake, except over the glacier itself. CD could not accept the possibility that a glacier could have existed at a particular level long enough to create a ‘road’ without having been worn down by the waterflow over it. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, [9 March 1841]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The four figures were obtained by four different observers in Glen Gluoy and Glen Roy (see Milne 1849, p. 397). CD wrote ‘Glen luy’, but Milne’s text makes clear that ‘Gluoy’ was intended.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">On the assumption that the roads were of marine origin, the height should have been the same. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 116 and Milne 1849, p. 401.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 111–14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See Milne 1849, pp. 402, 414–17, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 111–13.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_867.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bravais 1845</ref>, in which <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_596.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Auguste Bravais</ref> stated the need for accurately measured levels of ancient coast lines, and described a method of measuring them based on present mean sea-levels, in turn determined by the upper range of littoral algae. He discussed the problems of measurement at Glen Roy (pp. 542–4). See also Milne 1849, p. 396, which refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_867.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bravais 1845</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_940.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Clark</ref>, physician to Queen Victoria and friend of Lyell, was probably accompanying the Royal family on their visit to a Highland lodge located on the shores of Loch Laggan, in the vicinity of Glen Roy and Glen Spean. The visit took place from 11 August to 17 September, see <hi rend="italic">Annual Register</hi> 1847, Chronicle pp. 116–18.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">CD argued that icebergs floating in a narrow strait were capable of scraping and polishing the sea bottom. See <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> <hi rend="italic">of researches</hi>, pp. 617–25.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Milne 1849, p. 399; for his discussion of the river courses, see pp. 398–400. The Pass of Mukkull is at the eastern end of Glen Spean.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Milne had discovered a col in adjacent Glen Glaster (not ‘Glastig’, as CD has it) at the level of Glen Roy’s middle shelf. Earlier supporters of the lake hypothesis, as well as CD, had overlooked it. This discovery of a likely drainage point removed a powerful objection to the lake theory (see Milne 1849, p. 398).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 115. CD’s argument, which he hoped would render any coincidences of height between ‘roads’ and cols irrelevant, was that the cols were ‘land straits’, which emerged between branches of the sea as the land rose and which were maintained just at the level of the water through choking by littoral deposits.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">CD described Kilfinnin in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 92, 132 n. 10. See also CD’s map of the Glen Roy area, p. 87.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">CD observed that these ‘buttresses’ had been formed at various levels on the sides of the valley. Some of them were associated with, and formed extensions to, the shelves, while others were smaller and unconnected with any shelf. The buttresses were found along the courses of streamlets descending the valley, which led CD to conclude that they had been formed by the deposition of detritus when the descending stream met the edge of the lake filling the valley. If the water-level in the valley had stayed constant for a long period, both shelves and buttresses would have been formed; if it had remained at the same level for a shorter period then buttresses alone would have been formed. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 102–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">At this point (presumably after the letter was returned, see n. 3, above) CD added in pencil, ‘Have Lakes much more power with ice’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> reported many evidences of glaciers at Glen Roy and neighbouring valleys, including polished rocks and moraine deposits (Agassiz 1842b, pp. 222, 236–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">Milne 1849, pp. 404–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 24 n. CD described these ‘fiords’ as much shallower at their mouths than further inland. He attributed this to the accumulation of sediment formed by the wearing of the rocks exposed to the open sea. Such ‘sea channels’ resemble CD’s conception of Glen Roy’s ancient waterways, and this resemblance allowed CD to attribute any accumulation of detrital matter, such as those described by Milne (1849, p. 405), to the action of the sea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">The last section of Milne 1847b is devoted to showing that Scotland ‘to the depth of at least 1200 feet, has been recently immersed in the ocean, and for a very long period’ (p. 25). Milne concluded, however, that if a survey revealed that raised beaches along the coasts of Scotland, Ireland, England, and France were continuous and horizontal, the cause of these and of the parallel roads would be changing levels of the ocean rather than of the land (p. 54).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-1119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to Robert Chambers, 11 September 1847</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>