<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12143">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 July 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5460</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12143 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12143.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12143.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B31–2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B31–B32</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-07-10">10 July 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has received printed sheets from CD. Hopes CD does not intend to delete anything. EK comments on value of his own sketch for <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>.</p>  
<p>Hopes CD can excuse article he wrote in response to a review of Grant Allen’s book [<hi rend="italic">The colour-sense</hi> (1879)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Colour sense</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Allen, C. G. B. 1879</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-02-20" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-22" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-25" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-23" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-08-23" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00180_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00180_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <surface n="B:31r" xml:id="i180">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00180.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00180_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00180.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:31v" xml:id="i181">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00181.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00181_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00181.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:32r" xml:id="i182">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00182.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00182_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00182.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:32v" xml:id="i183">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00183.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00183_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00183.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 10.7.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Ihr gütiges Schreiben vom 7<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. und die Druckbogen empfing ich gestern und danke Ihnen für Beides auf das Herzlichste.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich habe Ihre Darstellung in einen Zuge durchgelesen und einen grossen Genuss davon gehabt. Wenn man sich eine Zeit hindurch mit den Lebensumständen einer, wenn auch sonst fernstehenden Person beschäftigt hat, so gewinnt man eine ähnliche Zuneigung und Sympathie für dieselbe, wie sie sonst aus persönlichem Umgange entsteht, und es macht uns eine rein menschliche Freude, immer mehr Einzelnheiten über dieselbe zu erfahren. Da ich annehme, dass es dem weniger interessirten Leser doch, wenn auch im minderen Grade, ähnlich gehen muss, so wäre ich sehr froh, wenn Sie Ihr Vorhaben einiges zu streichen, <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi> ausführen wollten. Zwar weiss ich nicht, welche Stellen Sie mit den “trifling passages” meinen, allein ich kann Ihnen versichern, nichts gefunden zu haben, was man nicht in Deutschland mit Behagen lesen würde. Vor Allem wünschte ich, dass Sie dabei nicht an den Brief an Miss Mary Howard gedacht haben möchten; derselbe erscheint mir im höchsten Grade reizend.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Zu meiner grossen Freude ist es nicht viel, was in den beiden Characterbildern doppelt vorkömmt, und ich glaube jetzt, wenn Sie aus meiner Schilderung alles dasjenige herausstreichen wollten, was Sie in der Einleitung bereits berührt haben, so könnten—durch die besondern Umstände ihrer Entstehung entschuldigt,—recht wohl die beiden biographischen Skizzen in demselben Bande nebeneinander gegeben werden. Die meinige giebt eine kurze Zusammenstellung des Hauptsächlichsten, was bereits veröffentlicht war, die Ihrige Zusätze aus noch nicht benutzten Quellen. Für das Ausland, Frankreich, Amerika, Deutschland würde meine zusammenfassende Lebenskizze kaum entbehrlich sein, und auch für England hätte sie vielleicht eine gewisse Berechtigung, sofern sie ein Zurückgehen auf das Buch von Miss Seward für den gewöhnlichen Leser entbehrlich macht, und so gewissermassen die älteren Biographieen ersetzt, indem sie deren Inhalt resumirt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Manche Wendung, wird dem englischen Leser allerdings sonderbar vorkommen, z.B. wenn ich andeute, wer Boulton, Edgeworth u.s.w. waren, allein man wird solcher Wendungen dem Ausländer verzeihen, denn für seine Landsleute und wahrscheinlich auch für Franzosen und Amerikaner dürften sie unerlässlich sein.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Auch meine Polemik gegen Miss Seward scheint mir durch Ihre höchst nothwendigen Winke über dieselbe, nicht überflüssig gemacht worden zu sein.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Denn soweit Sie Miss Seward discreditiren, könnte man entgegnen, es geschähe aus Pietät gegen den Grossvater, aber indem ich Walter Scott und andre unbetheiligte Personen in demselben Sinne urtheilend anführe, gewinnt dieses Urtheil eine grössere Objectivität. Sogar der dritte Abschnitt, über die humanitären Bestrebungen Erasmus Darwin’s scheint mir, wenn auch mit einigen Kürzungen nothwendig, falls Sie nicht vorziehen, ihn in die Präliminar-Notiz aufzunehmen, denn dem Ausländer dürfte es unentbehrlich sein z.B. zu erfahren, wie die Satire The loves of the triangles entstanden ist, und ebenso will mir die kleine Wasserfahrts-Anecdote, wegen der prächtigen Rede an die Arbeiter sehr mittheilenswerth erscheinen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Ich weiss, hochverehrter Herr, dass Sie mir es gewiss nicht übeldeuten, wenn ich Ihnen meine Auffassung der Sache ganz offen darlege, zumal ich Ihnen ja wiederholt versichert habe, dass ich mit jeder Anordnung, die Sie treffen, vollkommen einverstanden sein werde. Aber ich finde, dass Ihre Präliminar-Notiz gradezu einige weitere Nachrichten voraussetzt. So z.B. sagen Sie über Mrs. Pole gar nichts, und spielen z.B. auf die Wasserfahrt-Geschichte an, ohne Sie zu erzählen.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Für England wäre das gerechtfertigt, für das Ausland nicht.</p>
                    <p>Ausserdem hätte ich einen ganz äusserlichen, so zusagen aesthetischen Grund, zu wünschen, dass mein Theil an dem Buche nicht gar zu klein, ich meine zu bogenarm, ausfalle. Es würde nicht gut aussehen, fürchte ich, wenn Ihre Einleitung von 150 Seiten, vor einem Buche von kaum 100 Seiten stünde. Aus diesem Grunde erscheint mir jede räumliche Vermehrung meines Antheils, die sich nicht als blosse Wiederholung darstellt, wünschenswerth. Die wirklichen Wiederholungen werden bereits in der jetztigen Gestalt, kaum mehr als 5–6 Druckseiten betragen, und liessen sich noch erheblich vermindern. Es ist auch nicht dieser Umstand, der besonders ins Gewicht fällt, sondern vielmehr der, dass die Lebensbeschreibung überhaupt zweimal <hi rend="underline">anfängt</hi>. Allein, wenn Sie die Bemerkung im Eingange, über die gegenseitige Unbekanntschaft der Verfasser mit der Skizze des Andern stehen liessen, so würde diese Anomatie, glaube ich, von jedem Leser gebilligt und entschuldigt werden.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>Noch möchte ich mir die Frage erlauben, ob ich die corrigirten Druckbogen behalten darf, um sie der Uebersetzung zu Grunde zu legen, oder ob Sie dieselben noch gebrauchen? Im ersteren Falle würde ich Sie bitten, mir die Zusätze über den Ursprung Ihrer Familie gütigst in Abschrift senden zu wollen, im zweiten könnte ich vielleicht die Drucklegung abwarten, und würde dann Mr. Murraÿ bitten, mir jeden Bogen, so wie er fertig wird, zu senden.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>Ich muss noch einige Worte hinzusetzen über einen Artikel, den ich im letzten Hefte des Kosmos veröffentlicht habe, und der Ihnen vielleicht keinen guten Eindruck machen wird. Er betrifft das Buch des Mr. Grant Allen über den Farbensinn.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Der Verfasser erklärt darin, meine Artikel im Kosmos über die Gladstone-Geiger-Magnus’sche Theorie gelesen zu haben, erwähnt aber mit keiner Sÿlbe, dass ich seine gesammte Auffassung der Sache, schon ein paar Jahre früher dargelegt habe, ja im Gegentheil, er sucht den Schein zu erwecken, als ob diese Theorie in Deutschland fast angenommen wäre.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Dieses Verfahren empörte mich so sehr, dass ich gleich in der ersten Hitze jenen etwas heftigen Artikel schrieb, und sogleich drucken liess, obwohl ich jetzt Manches anders gesagt zu haben wünschte. Die Sache ist vielleicht des Lärmens nicht werth, aber ich hoffe, <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi> sowohl als andre Leser, werden den von mir angeschlagenen Ton entschuldbar finden, wenn Sie erwägen, dass die gesammten Umrisse des Allen’schen Buches in jenen von ihm gekannten Artikeln gegeben waren, deren Inhalt er mit völligem Stillschweigen übergeht. Er hat sich dadurch einem Verdachte ausgesetzt, der niemals hätte ausgesprochen werden können, wenn er nur mit zwei Worten angedeutet hätte, dass in meinen Artikeln dieselben Ansichten dargelegt worden seien, wie in seinem Buche.</p>
                    <p>In der Hoffnung und mit dem herzlichen Wunsche, dass Sie sich trotz dieses abscheulichen Wetters wohl befinden mögen,<ref target="#foot.f13"/> zeichne ich hochverehrter Herr | Ihr | treulich ergebener | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>10.7.79.</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Yesterday, I received your kind letter of the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and the printed sheets and I thank you most cordially for both.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I read your account in one go and derived great pleasure from it. When one has looked into someone’s circumstances for a time, even an otherwise unconnected person, one develops a fondness and liking for this person, similar to that which otherwise develops from personal acquaintance, and it becomes a purely human pleasure to learn even more details about them. Since I assume that the less interested reader, even if to a lesser degree, must still feel similarly, I would be very glad if you would <hi rend="underline">not</hi> carry out your plan to delete some things. To be sure I have no idea which passages you mean by “trifling passages”, but I can assure you that I have found nothing that would not be read with pleasure in Germany. Above all I hope you were not thinking of the letter to Miss Mary Howard; in my view it was charming in the highest degree.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>To my great delight the two character sketches do not duplicate one another much and I now believe that, if you were to strike out from my account everything you have already covered in the introduction, both biographical sketches could very well appear side by side in one volume—excused by the special circumstances of their origin. Mine provides a brief outline of the main material that has been published already, yours additions from sources as yet unused. For foreign countries, France, America, Germany my summarising sketch would hardly be expendable, and even for England it is to some degree justified, insofar as it makes it superfluous for the common reader to consult Miss Seward’s book and thus to a certain extent replaces the older biographies by summarising their content.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Some phrases will strike the English reader as peculiar, e.g. when I point out who Boulton, Edgeworth etc. were, but a foreigner will be forgiven such phrases, since for his compatriots and very likely also for the French and the Americans they would be obligatory.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>It also does not seem to me as though my polemic against Miss Seward has been rendered superfluous by your most important hints about her.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> For insofar as you discredit Miss Seward it could be replied that this happened out of piety towards your grandfather, but since I quote Walter Scott and other neutral persons who pass identical judgments on her, your assessment acquires greater objectivity. Even the third section, on the humanitarian endeavours of Erasmus Darwin seems to me indispensable, even though it needs cutting, unless you prefer to include it in the preliminary notice, because it will be essential for the foreigner, e.g., in learning how the satire The loves of the triangles came into being, and likewise the little anecdote about a trip on the water seems to me well worth imparting because of the splendid speech to the workers.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>I know, highly respected Sir, that you certainly will not mind if I tell you quite frankly my views on this matter, since I have assured you repeatedly that I will be wholly in agreement with any decision of yours. However, I feel that your preliminary notice presupposes even further information. Thus, e.g., you say nothing at all about Mrs Pole, and you allude <hi rend="underline">to</hi> the incident of the trip on the water without narrating it.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> For an English audience this would be justified, but for a foreign one not.</p>
                    <p>Besides, I have a wholly extraneous, so to speak aesthetic reason for wishing that my portion of the book should not be too small, meaning, too wanting in the number of pages. I fear it would not look well if your introduction of 150 pages were to preface a book of barely 100 pages. For this reason any increase in the length of my portion that is not a mere repetition strikes me as desirable. The actual repetitions in the current form would amount to barely more than 5–6 printed pages and could still be reduced considerably; nor is it this circumstance that is of specific importance, but rather the fact that the biographical account as such <hi rend="underline">starts</hi> twice over. However, if you leave in the remark at the beginning, that the authors were not acquainted with each other’s sketches, this anomaly will, I believe, be condoned and excused by every reader.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>I would also like to take the liberty to ask whether I may keep the corrected sheets to use as a basis for the translation, or whether you still need them? If the former were the case I would ask you to kindly send me a copy of the additional remarks on the origins of your family, in the latter case I could perhaps wait for the book to go to press and then ask Mr Murray to send me every sheet as soon as it comes off the press.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>I must also add a few words about the article that I published in the latest issue of Kosmos, and that will perhaps not impress you favourably. It concerns the book by Mr Grant Allen on the sense of colour.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> In it the author announces that he has read my article in Kosmos on the Gladstone-Geiger-Magnus theory, but does not breathe a word about the fact that I had already a number of years ago expounded his entire position on the matter; on the contrary, he tries to create the impression that this theory is almost accepted in Germany.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> This action outraged me so much that in the heat of the moment I at once wrote the somewhat vehement article in question, and let it go to press at once, while now I wish I had stated some things differently. Perhaps this matter is not worth fussing over, but I hope <hi rend="underline">you</hi> and other readers will find the tone I struck excusable, when you consider that the entire outline of Allen’s book was provided in the article in question, of which he knew, yet whose content he passed over in complete silence. Thus he has laid himself open to a suspicion that would never have been raised had he indicated with just a couple of words that in my article the same views had been presented as in his book.</p>
                    <p>In the hope and with the cordial wish that you may be well despite this horrid weather<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I remain highly esteemed Sir | Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
                       
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12136.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 7 July 1879</ref>. CD had sent proof-sheets of his introductory essay for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD included the complete text of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>’s letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8390.xml">Mary Howard</ref> shortly before their wedding in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 21–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref>’s biography of Erasmus Darwin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>) had been strongly criticised by Darwin family members for its inaccuracies (see letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Krause</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">14 March 1879</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11944.xml">19 March 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the published version of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8434.xml">Matthew Boulton</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8398.xml">Richard Lovell Edgeworth</ref> were not mentioned in Krause’s section of the book.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Krause’s polemic against Seward does not appear in the published version of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD mentioned <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4262.xml">Scott</ref> only once in <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 91; he quoted from a letter written to Scott by Edgeworth. Krause added a long footnote to the German version, expanding on Scott’s evaluation of Seward (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 195–6). The poem ‘The loves of the triangles’ was a parody of <hi rend="italic">The loves of the plants</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>, pt 2; see <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, pp. 95–6). The anecdote about the trip down the Trent river and the extemporaneous speech is mentioned in <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 58–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Erasmus Darwin’s second wife, the former Mrs <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1216.xml">Elizabeth Pole</ref>, is mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In the published version of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, CD’s introductory essay (‘preliminary notice’) was 127 pages long while Krause’s section, revised and retitled ‘The scientific works of Erasmus Darwin’, was 85 pages.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">John Murray (1808–92)</ref> was CD’s publisher. Krause was planning to make a German translation of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11961.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 30 March 1879</ref>). In the event, Krause reinstated parts of his text not included in the English edition as well as adding over one hundred pages of notes (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 75–124, 180–286).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD had received a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_81.xml">Allen</ref>’s book <hi rend="italic">The colour-sense: its origin and development: an essay in comparative psychology</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10344.xml">G. Allen 1879a</ref>) from the author (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11891.xml">letter to Grant Allen, [before 21 February 1879]</ref>). Allen’s book was favourably reviewed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Hermann Müller</ref> in the July 1879 issue of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10842.xml">H. Müller 1879b</ref>); the review was followed by an article by Krause, ‘Nachschrift über Ideen-Adoptiv-Väter’ (Postscript on adoptive fathers of ideas; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10841.xml">Krause 1879b</ref>), in which Krause claimed priority for many of the views expressed in Allen’s book.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See G. Allen 1879a, pp. 81–2; for the reference to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10017.xml">Krause 1877a</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10301.xml">Krause 1877b</ref>, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 82 n. 5. The linguist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1835.xml">Lazarus Geiger</ref> had suggested that the development of colour-related words was connected to physiological development, and proposed that there were two types of colour words, which he called ‘natural’ and ‘artificial’; artificial words were more recent and were derived from objects, while natural words had developed from extremes (light and dark; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10843.xml">Geiger 1867</ref>). The ophthalmologist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3127.xml">Hugo Magnus</ref>’s work <hi rend="italic">Die geschichtliche Entwickelung des Farbensinnes</hi> (The historical development of the colour-sense; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9543.xml">Magnus 1877</ref>) further developed Geiger’s thesis; Magnus was supported by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1883.xml">William Ewart Gladstone</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10014.xml">Gladstone 1877</ref>). Krause, Allen, and others argued that while languages developed more terms for colours over time, human ability to distinguish colours had not altered.  For more on this debate among naturalists, ethnologists, physicists, physicians, and philologists from the late 1870s to early 1880s see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10844.xml">Saunders ed. 2007</ref>, pp. 7–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">The year 1879 saw the wettest summer in Europe, particularly in England, since records began in 1750 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10845.xml">Briffa <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2009</ref>, p. 1897).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>