<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2658">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>   [14–19 January 1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15624</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2658 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2658.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2658.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 31</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 32</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 21 January 1860, p. 49 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Gard. Chron. 1860: 49</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1860-01-14" notAfter="1860-01-19">[14–19 Jan 1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1808.xml">Gardeners’ Chronicle</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Hopes readers will send information on the permanence of cross-bred plants and animals. No one doubts that cross-bred productions tend to revert in various degrees to either parent for many generations. But are there not cases of crossed breeds of sheep and pigs that breed true? CD believes occasional cross-breeding of varieties is advantageous in nature as well as under domestication. [See reply to this letter by J. O. Westwood, <hi rend="italic">Gard. Chron.</hi> (1860): 122.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pigs</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sheep</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">generations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reversion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>–</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope that some of your readers will respond to Mr. Westwood’s wish, and give any information which they may possess on the permanence of cross-bred plants and animals.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Will Mr. Westwood be so good as to give a reference to any account of the variability of the Swedish Turnip?<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I did not even know that it was reputed to be a cross-bred production. I am aware that this is supposed to be the case with some Turnips; but I have searched in vain for any authentic history of their origin. No one, I believe, doubts that cross-bred productions tend to revert in various degrees to either parent for many generations; some say for a dozen, others for a score or even more generations. But cannot breeders adduce some cases of crossed breeds of sheep and pigs (such as the Shropshire or Oxford sheep, or Lord Harborough’s pigs) which are now true?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> With respect to the Cottagers’ Kale, I was so much surprised at the accounts of its trueness that I procured seed from the raisers; but in my soil the plants were far from presenting a uniform appearance.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In addition to the tendency to reversion to either parent form, it is almost universally asserted that cross-bred productions are highly variable, and often display characters not observed in either parent. I do not wish to dispute this common belief, but I suspect it would puzzle any one to adduce satisfactory cases; and certainly Gärtner has advanced a mass of evidence on the opposite side.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I am not at all surprised at Mr. Westwood demurring to the belief that occasionally crossing the strain is advantageous or necessary with productions in a state of nature. The subject is only just alluded to in my volume on the “Origin of Species.”<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I do not pretend that I can prove the truth of the doctrine; but I feel sure that many important facts and arguments can be adduced in its favour. The ill effects of close inter-breeding between the nearest relations, especially if exposed to the same conditions of life, would be, I believe, the same under Nature as under domestication,—namely, some degree of sterility and weakness of constitution. Variability arises from quite independent causes, and is to a certain extent counteracted in its early stages by the free crossing of the individuals of the same species. Mr. Westwood misunderstands me if he supposes that it is my opinion that the Ibis, for instance, keeps true to its kind “by occasional crosses with individuals of the same species which have not sprung from the same grandfather or great-grandfather.”<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I only believe that if individuals of the Ibis did vary, such crosses would tend to keep the species true; and further, if the young from a single pair increased so slowly that they all continued to inhabit the same small district, and if brothers and sisters often united during successive generations, then that the Ibis would rapidly deteriorate in fertility and constitution. Mr. Westwood advances the hive-bee, as probably a case of constant intercrossing. Andrew Knight, however, who specially attended to this point, has published his belief (Whether founded on sufficient evidence I will not pretend to say) that the queen-bee commonly unites with a drone from another community.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Charles Darwin</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Down, Bromley, Kent.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f10"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter responds to a note published in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’</hi> <hi rend="italic">Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette </hi>(see n. 2, below) and was itself published in the following number of the journal. It is reprinted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 31–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Obadiah Westwood</ref> published a notice in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’</hi> <hi rend="italic">Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 14 January 1860, p. 26, entitled ‘Doubtful permanence of cross-breeds’. He stated his belief that plants of hybrid or mongrel origin would ultimately revert to their original type and suggested that this was ‘at once contradictory to the theory of progressive development’. In his closing remarks, Westwood stated that he hoped to induce a discussion on ‘these and other questions raised by Mr. C. Darwin in his very remarkable volume lately published’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Westwood referred to the search under way to find a substitute for the Swedish turnip, which was rapidly deteriorating despite the efforts of agriculturalists to keep it true-breeding. The report was printed in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural</hi> <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi>, 10 December 1859, p. 997.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD discussed crossed breeds of sheep that remain true in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 95–6. The pigs are the breed known as the Improved Essex, bred by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4327.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Sherard</ref>, Earl of Harborough (H. D. Richardson 1847, p. 37).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Cottagers’ kale is produced by crossing common kale with Brussels sprouts and then recrossing the progeny with purple broccoli. It was reported to breed true (<hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 10 February 1858, p. 128).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2736.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gärtner 1849</ref>. CD studied this work closely when compiling the manuscript of his species book (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 5 and 6). His notes on the book are in DAR 116. CD discussed <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Friedrich von Gärtner’s</ref> assertion that plants of hybrid origin were not variable in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 265.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 96–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Westwood had asserted: ‘To say that wild animals or plants which keep true to their kind—as, for instance, the Egyptian Ibis (Which is still identical with the individuals found in the mummy pits)—are only enabled to do so by occasional crosses with individuals of the same species which have not sprung from the same grandfather or great-grandfather is fallacious.’ (<hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 14 January 1860, p. 26). He further maintained that even if only two Ibises were left, they would breed true for the next 4000 years without needing to cross-breed with a dissimilar strain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4407.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Knight 1828</ref>, p. 319.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Westwood’s reply to CD’s letter appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’</hi> <hi rend="italic">Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 11 February 1860, p. 122. He emphasised the point that ‘progressive development’ could not take place while there was such a pronounced tendency for the reversion of varieties and mongrels back to the original type.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>