<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-222">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Caroline Darwin   23 [October 1833]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5055</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-222 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-222.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-222.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 154: 39</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi>: 92</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 342</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 223</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>223: 19</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>
                <date when="1833-10-23">23 [Oct 1833]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1208.xml">Darwin, C. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes his trip to north of Santa Fé, his illness, and return by boat to Buenos Aires – which he found in the throes of a revolution. Covington is cut off from the town, which some expect to be plundered.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Buenos Aires</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Santa Fe</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">boat</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>
                    <date>September 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></date>
                    <salute>My dear Caroline</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>A vessel will sail in an hours time to Liverpool, &amp; I will write as much as I can.— I have just returned from an adventurous tour.— I think I mentioned my intention of starting to the Northern parts of this Province.— I by chance procured Capt. Head’s peon &amp; arrived after a rapid gallop at St. Fe about 300 miles to the North— it was an interesting ride &amp; good opportunity of seeing the real sea-like Pampas. at St Fe I was most unfortunately, rather unwell, so as to be unable to ride.— I crossed over to the Bajada the Capital of Entre Rios &amp; there staid some days, but finding so much time lost I was obliged to embark on board a vessel down the Parana— This immense river, with its islands full of Tigers &amp; Capinchos,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> is so very great, as to appear only like an oblong lake.— When we arrived near Buenos Ayres, I left the vessel with the intention of riding into town.— The minute I landed I was almost a prisoner, for the city is closely blockaded by a furious cut-throat set of rebels.— By riding about (at a ruinous expence) amongst the different generals, I at last obtained leave to go on foot without passport into the city: I was thus obliged to leave my Peon &amp; luggage behind; but I may thank kind providence I am here with an entire throat.— Such a set of misfortunes I have had this month, never before happened to poor mortal. My servant (Covington by name &amp; most invaluable I find him) was sent to the Estancia of the Merchants whose house I am staying in.— he the other day nearly lost his life in a quicksand &amp; my gun completely.—</p>
<p>We now here the house is ransacked (&amp; probably his clothes all stolen!) Communication with the country is absolutely cut off, he cannot come into town, &amp; the Beagle before long sails to the South.— Here is a pretty series of misfortunes, &amp; there are plenty of smaller ones to fill up the gaps.—</p>
<p>I drew a bill a month ago for 80£. I am very sorry to say I shall be obliged from these great unexpected misfortunes to draw another one.— After my Fathers first great growl is over, he must recollect we shall be now 8 months to the South, where as last time I can neither spend or draw money.—the only security, I can give which will be trusted.—</p>
<p>Independent of all these uncommon mortifications &amp; my illness at St Fe preventing my return by the Rio Uruguay, through a most interesting Geo- logical country.—the tour answered well.— It is quite magnificent when I consider I have ridden nearly 800 miles in a North &amp; South direction &amp; the greater part through country most imperfectly known.—</p>
<p>We are in a pretty state in this nice city.— they think nothing of cutting the throats of 30 prisoners, whom they happened to take the other day:—and they are right; for what is it, to quietly stabbing all the Indian women above 20 years old or younger if ugly.— Oh these Creoles are such a detestably mean unprincipled set of men, as I hope this world does not contain the like.— There literally is only one Gentleman in Buenos Ayres, the English Minister.— He is has writt〈en〉 to or〈der〉 the Beagle up.— But we sail under such particular instructions I know not whether the Captain will come.— If he does all will be right about Covington.—otherwise I shall be obliged to send some small vessel or boat to smuggle him off the Coast.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>In fact I am in a pretty pickle.— I wish the confounded revolution gentlemen would, like Kilkenny Cats, fight till nothing but the tails are left.— Some of the good people expect the town to be plundered.— Which will a very amusing episode to me.—</p>
<p>dear Caroline. Yours Chas. Darwin</p>
<p>I will write again.—</p>
<p>I sent home by the Capt: Beaufort about 2 or 3 months ago—some more of my journal. Be sure acknowledge it, &amp; in more than one letter.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.3 Northern] ‘N’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘n’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.10 great] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘im’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.10 to] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘on’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.11 we] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘I’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.11 with] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘in’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.14 amongst] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘with’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">1.19 whose] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘house’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.2 from … misfortunes] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">5.2 whom they] ‘they’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">5.3 Indian] <hi rend="italic">final</hi> ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">5.3 years old] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">5.4 ugly] ‘u’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">5.6 English] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">5.8 whether] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘he will’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">5.10 or boat] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">6.3 good] ‘d’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘g’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">7.1 dear Caroline. Yours] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">9.1 Capt: ] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">9.1 some] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.6 ‘Pampas.’; 1.17 ‘happened’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">‘September 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.—’ was written by CD. ‘September’ has been deleted and ‘October 1833’ inserted, in what appears to be another hand, to correct CD’s error.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Jaguars (Spanish ‘tigres’) and capybaras.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_468.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">‘Beagle’ diary</hi></ref>, p. 191: ‘These disturbances caused me much inconvenience; my servant was outside, I was obliged to bribe a man to smuggle him in through the belligerents. His clothese, my riding gear, collections from St Fe were outside, with no possibility of obtaining them. I was, however, lucky in having them all sent to me at M. Video.’ See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Lumb, 13 November 1833</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>