<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10735">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. M. Heckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>     27 December 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14323</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10735 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10735.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10735.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 128</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 128</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2197.xml">Heckel, E. M.</persName>
                <placeName>Grenoble</placeName>
                <date when="1876-12-27">27 Dec 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has read and greatly admires CD’s latest book, <hi rend="italic">Cross and self-fertilisation</hi>; seeks permission to translate it into French and to add some annotations. [EMH’s translation was published in 1877.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cross and self-fertilisation</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">French</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive self-criticism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Grenoble</placeName>
                    <date>le 27 X<hi rend="superscript">bre</hi>. 1876</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai recu et lu déja votre tres remarquable livre sur <hi rend="underline">la fécondation croisée et directe dans le regne végétal</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f2"/>   permettez moi de vous remercier de ce gracieux envoi et de vous dire, Monsieur, que ce nouveau travail a excité en moi, comme toutes vos oeuvres, une admiration profonde pour votre génie—</p>
<p>Il me parait que les consequences de ces recherches sont pleines d’intérêt autant pour les philosophes que pour les practiciens (horticulteurs, agriculteurs), et qu’il y a portant le plus grand urgence à mettre votre livre a la portée de tous ceux qui en France, (et ils sont nombreux) peuvent avoir profit à tous lire. Je viens donc Monsieur vous demander l’autorisation de traduire votre dernièr livre, et si vous le permettez, d’y ajouter quelques annotations. J’ai en effet recueilli dans mes voyages de circomnavigation quelques observations sur la fecondations croisee et directe, qui ne font que corroborer les vôtres et que je serais heureux de placer sous le patronage de votre grand nom.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Veuillez, je vous prie, Monsieur, quelle que soit votre decision me honorer d’une réponse et dans le cas de l’affirmative permettez moi de vous demander la faveur de soumettre mon manuscrit avant la publication, car je serai aussi bien assuré de ne pas avoir faussé vos savantes interpretations.</p>
<p>Veuillez agreer, Monsieur, mes salutations les plus respectueuses | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. Heckel | professeur de botanique à la Faculté des Sciences de Grenoble (Isère)</p>
<p>P.S. Je me suis dejá adressé à M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Reinwald qui est n’hésitant à entreprendre la publication que je lui propose, mais que j’en suis sûr, Monsieur n’hesitera plus après un mot de vous autorisant la traduition d’un livre qui est le complément indispensable de la <hi rend="underline">Fécondation des Orchidées</hi><ref target="#foot.f4"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Grenoble</placeName>
                    <date>27 December 1876</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have received and already read your very remarkable book on <hi rend="underline">cross- and self-fertilisation in the vegetable kingdom</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> allow me to thank you for kindly sending it and to tell you, Sir, that this new work, like all your writings, has aroused in me deep admiration for your genius—</p>
<p>It seems to me that the results of this research are full of interest as much for philosophers as for practitioners (horticulturalists, agriculturalists) and that it brings to bear the greatest urgency to put your book within reach of all those in France, (and they are numerous) who can profit from reading everything. Therefore, Sir, I ask you for authorisation to translate your latest book, and if you will permit, to add some annotations. I have in fact collected in my circumnavigatory travels some observations on cross- and self-fertilisation, which can only corroborate your own and which I would be happy to place under the patronage of your great name.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Would you please Sir, whatever you decide, honour me with a reply and in the case of an affirmative one grant me the honour of submitting my manuscript before publication, for I will be sufficiently reassured that I have not distorted your wise interpretations.</p>
<p>I remain, Sir, most respectfully yours | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. Heckel | Professor of Botany in the Faculty of Sciences at Grenoble (Isère)</p>
<p>P.S. I have already approached M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Reinwald who is hesitant about undertaking the publication I suggested to him, but I am sure he will not hesitate any longer after a word from you authorising the translation of a book which is the indispensible complement to the <hi rend="underline">Fécondation des Orchidées</hi><ref target="#foot.f4"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. 403.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Heckel’s name is on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (see Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Heckel’s French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (Heckel trans. 1877) was published in 1877. He added a translator’s introduction and additional footnotes signed ‘(Traducteur.)’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3970.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles-Ferdinand Reinwald</ref>, CD’s French publisher, had published a translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> (Rérolle trans. 1870).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>