<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11084">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alphonse de Candolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   31 July 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14132</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11084 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11084.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11084.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (French) †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Baehni (1955): 146</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 21</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 21</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml">Candolle, Alphonse de</persName>
                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                <date when="1877-07-31">31 July 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for <hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi>.</p>  
<p>In his <hi rend="italic">Monographiae phanerogamarum</hi> [vol. 1 (1878)] he discusses transitional forms of dioecism in three genera of <hi rend="italic">Smilax</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Criticises CD’s use of the words "purpose" and "end", but acknowledges that in English they can mean both cause and effect.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Smilax</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Forms of flowers</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Monographiae phanerogamarum</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Candolle, Alphonse de 1878</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">causation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">definitions (will revert to tyd)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">intermediate forms, gradation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monoecious or dioecious plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative self-criticism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Genève</placeName>
                    <date>31 Juillet 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je vous remercie extremement de votre volume sur les <hi rend="underline">Forms of flowers</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> C’est un exposé très curieux de faits observés d’abord par vous et ensuite par d’autres, avec des comparaisons et reflexions d’un grand intérêt.</p>
<p>La question de l’origine probable des plantes uni et bisexuelles s’est presentée à moi en travaillant les Smilacées. Je regrette de n’avoir pas eu votre ouvrage avant l’impression des premières feuilles de notre volume de Monographies où j’en ai parlé. Quand vous recevrez ce volume, en automne, vous verrez mes conjectures sur l’apparition et la dispersion géographique des trois genres de Smilacées proprement dites, l’un dioique, sans trace d’organes avortés (Heterosmilax), un second dioique, avec filets d’etamines stériles dans les fleurs femelles (Smilax), le 3<hi rend="superscript">ème</hi> hermaphrodite (Rhipogonum).<ref target="#foot.f3"/> La forme la moins compliquée, Heterosmilax, m’a paru probablement la plus ancienne; ensuite les commencements d’etamines des Smilax se seraient formés, et enfin l’anthère serait venue, dans les Rhipogonum. Ce qui m’a fait incliner vers cette hypothèse (je ne l’ai pas expliqué expressement dans l’imprimé et j’ai eu tort), c’est que les feuilles se developpent sur la plante dans cet ordre. Le cotyledon et les premières feuilles de chaque rameau sont composées seulement de la gaine ou partie inférieure de la feuille; ensuite au milieu se developpent les feuilles pourvues de limbe. Dans le bourgeon floral, c’est la même chose: les sépales et petales sont des feuilles réduites à la base, et les petales manquent même dans les Heterosmilax; enfin les feuilles centrales sont plus developpées sous forme souvent d’etamines, pourvues d’anthères (limbe), mais pas toujours.</p>
<p>Dans le genre le plus developpé, Rhipogonum, une espèce de la Nouvelle Zelande m’a offert quelque chose de bien rare, qu’on n’avait pas remarqué. La fleur n’est jamais fermée en bouton. Les plus jeunes montrent déjà des etamines à découvert, sans préfloraison. C’est le contraire de la Cleistogamie. Qu’en resulte-t-il pour la fécondation? Je ne sais. Les ètamines des Rhipogonum, en particulier de celui-ci, contiennent peu de pollen. Le Rhip. scandens est imparfaitement hermaphrodite, plus encore que les autres. Il est vrai qu’il se reproduit énormement par les pousses venant des rhizomes, comme c’est le cas de beaucoup de Smilax du Bresil, qui fleurissent rarement. Le pollen des Smilacées est hérissé de petites papilles, de sorte que la fécondation doit se faire plus par les insectes que par le vent.</p>
<p>Dans les Rhipogonum les papilles sont très courtes, le pollen est presque volatil. Comme ils sont hermaphrodites, cela rentre dans vos idées. La fècondation se ferait d’une plante à l’autre malgré l’hermaphroditisme apparent, sans quoi (direz-vous) les produits auraient moins de vigueur.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>En lisant votre page 11 je remarque que les Smilacées dioiques ne sont pas comme les Restiacées dont vous parlez. Les pieds males et femelles sont impossibles à distinguer, autrement que par les fleurs ou fruits, à moins que l’elévation (la taille) ne soit différente selon le sexe, ce qu’on ne voit pas dans les herbiers.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Plusieurs passages de votre dernier ouvrage et des précédents m’ont fait faire une recherche linguistique, d’après laquelle il parait que les mots <hi rend="underline">purpose</hi>, <hi rend="underline">end</hi>, n’ont pas en anglais le sens précis que nous donnons en francais aux mots <hi rend="underline">but</hi>, <hi rend="underline">fin</hi>. Je me disais en lisant au haut de la p. 7 “their corollas have been increased in size for this special <hi rend="underline">purpose</hi>, et p. 9, vers le bas, “subserve any special <hi rend="underline">end</hi>”. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin, dont l’esprit philosophique poursuit methodiquement les causes et les effets, aurait mieux fait de dire: their corollas being increased in size the <hi rend="underline">consequence</hi> is, etc, et p. 9 au lieu de subserve any special end … have any <hi rend="underline">effect</hi>, car l’observation ne montre que des formes et des conséquences ou effets, non des buts ou intentions. Nos mots <hi rend="underline">but</hi>, <hi rend="underline">fin</hi> supposent une intention, une volonté extérieure, ou pour connaitre une intention, il faut questionner celui au quel on l’attribue ou l’entendre s’expliquer, ce qui n’arrive pas dans les phénomènes naturels. Que diraient des francais ou des hollandais s’ils lisaient dans un livre de géologie: “à la fin de l’epoque tertiaire la vallée de la Tamise s’est abaissée dans le <hi rend="underline">but</hi> que Londres eut un commerce immense etc,” ou … “les côtes de France se sont élevées dans le but que les Français ne fussent pas navigateurs”— Ils diraient assurement: qu’en sait-on? L’auteur a pris des consequences pour des buts, des effets pour des causes. Mais ces doutes et ces critiques de mon esprit sont tombés en ouvrant mon dictionnaire anglo-francais, de Spiers:<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Purpose</hi>. But, fin, effet, intention, dessein, usage.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">End</hi>. Bout, extrémité, fin, but, objet, cause.</p>
<p>Ainsi, chacun de ces mots anglais a deux sens contradictoires, tantot un but prémédité, tantot un effet—tantot une cause, tantot un resultat. Je doute que vos traducteurs aient fait attention à cette difficulté et je crains que l’ambiguité de ces mots anglais ne conserve dans le public anglais une certaine confusion d’idées peu philosophique. En tous cas si je vous ai critiqué dabord <hi rend="underline">in petto</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> c’etait ma faute; je n’avais pas compris le vague inévitable determiné par la langue.</p>
<p>Mon fils qui comte comme un de ses bons jours, celui que vous avez bien voulu lui accorder, se rappelle à votre souvenir.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Dites, je vous prie, à M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Francis Darwin, que M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Delpino a été plus heureux que nous en observant des Smilax. Je soupconnais une excretion de l’extremité des feuilles et nous ne l’avions pas vue, moi à Genève sur le Smilax excelsa, et M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Francis à Kew sur des Smilax probablement en serre, mais les pieds observés n’etaient pas dans des conditions ordinaires de climat et végétation. A Gênes, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Delpino a vu, sur deux espèces (S. aspera et bonanox) une matière sucrée produite par le tissu glandulaire qui se trouve au bout de la feuille, du côté extérieur, surtout dans les jeunes feuilles des pousses annuelles.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Cette matière sucrée est recherchée par les fourmis. D’après les échantillons d’herbiers, la secretion doit être plus forte dans certaines espèces de Chine, du Bresil, etc. Delpino, tout pénétré des anciennes théories sur les causes finales, cherche le <hi rend="underline">but</hi>, <hi rend="underline">l’intention</hi> pour les quels la secretion et l’abord des fourmis existent dans ce cas. Il croit, en général, que les fourmis arrivent <hi rend="underline">afin</hi> de débarrasser les arbres des larves d’insectes nuisibles. J’aimerais mieux l’hypothèse que les matières sécrétées ont pour but de nourrir les fourmis. Les jardiniers ont une troisième manière de voir, qui est de considérer les fourmis comme un fléau, dont il faut se débarrasser le plus possible. Enfin, je préférerais aux hypothèses une bonne expèrience; dans une rangée de cerisiers ou autre arbre frequenté par les fourmis, enduire quelques troncs de coal tar de manière à empêcher la visite de ces insectes, et voir si la végétation, floraison et fructification seraient differentes sur les arbres avec et sans fourmis. On saurait alors les conséquences, les effects, au lieu de faire des suppositions de toute nature sur des intentions!</p>
<p>Je me suis laissé entrainer au plaisir de causer avec vous. Il ne me reste qu’à vous prier de m’excuser de la longueur et d’agréer, mon cher Monsieur, l’assurance de tout mon dévouement | Alph. de Candolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>4.3 l’autre … l’hermaphroditisme] <hi rend="italic">bracketted by crosses, pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                    <date>31 July 1877.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Thank you very much for your book on the <hi rend="underline">Forms of flowers</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is a very curious account of facts observed first by you and then by others, with comparisons and thoughts of great interest.</p>
<p>The question of the probable origin of uni- and bisexual plants occurred to me when I was working on the Smilaceae. I regret not having had your work before the printing of first pages of our volume of monographs, where I spoke of it. When you receive this volume, in the autumn, you will see my conjectures on the appearance and geographical distribution of three genera of Smilaceae, strictly speaking, one dioecious, without a trace of aborted organs (Heterosmilax), a second dioecious, with sterile staminal filaments in the female flowers (Smilax), the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> hermaphrodite (Rhipogonum).<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The least complicated form, Heterosmilax, seemed to me probably the most ancient; then the beginnings of the stamens of Smilax were formed, and finally the anther will have appeared, in Rhipogonum. What inclined me towards this hypothesis (I did not explain this specifically in print, and I was wrong), was the fact that the leaves develop on the plant in this sequence. The cotyledon and the first leaves of each branch are composed only of the sheath or lower part of the leaf; then, in the middle, the leaves develop provided with a blade. In the floral bud, it is the same: the sepals and petals are leaves reduced to the base, and even the petals are missing in Heterosmilax; finally the central leaves are more developed, often, in staminal form, equipped with anthers (blade), but not always.</p>
<p>In the most developed genus, Rhipogonum, a New Zealand species afforded me with something very rare, which no one has noticed. The flower is never closed in the bud. The youngest ones already display uncovered stamens, without anthesis. This is the opposite of cleistogamy. What does this mean for fertilisation? I do not know. The stamens of Rhipogonum, especially this one, contain little pollen. Rhip. scandens is imperfectly hermaphrodite, even more than the others. It is true that it reproduces hugely by shoots from the rhizomes, as is the case with many of the Smilax of Brazil, which rarely flower. The pollen of the Smilaceae is spiked with small papillae, of the kind that necessitates fertilisation by means of insects rather than by wind.</p>
<p>In Rhipogonum, the papillae are very short, the pollen is almost volatile. As they are hermaphrodites, this idea fits with your ideas. Fertilisation takes place between one plant and another, in spite of apparent hermaphroditism, without which (you say) the offspring would be less vigorous.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Reading your page 11, I notice that the dioecious Smilaceae are not like the Restiaceae you mention. The male and female plants are impossible to distinguish, other than by the flowers or fruits, unless the elevation (height) is different according to sex, which would not be seen in herbaria.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Several passages in your last work and the preceding ones induced me to do some linguistic research, according to which it seems that the words <hi rend="underline">purpose</hi>, <hi rend="underline">end</hi>, do not have in English the precise sense that we give in French to the words <hi rend="underline">but</hi>, <hi rend="underline">fin</hi>. I was saying to myself when reading at the top of p. 7, “their corollas have been increased in size for this special <hi rend="underline">purpose</hi>, and p. 9, near the bottom, “subserve any special <hi rend="underline">end</hi>”. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin, whose philosophical spirit pursues causes and effects methodically, would better have said: their corollas being increased in size the <hi rend="underline">consequence</hi> is, etc, and p. 9 in place of subserve any special end … have any <hi rend="underline">effect</hi>, since observation only shows forms and consequences or effects, not goals or intentions. Our words <hi rend="underline">but</hi>, <hi rend="underline">fin</hi> assume an intention, an external will, either, to know an intention, one must question the one to whom one attributes it, or hear the explanation, which does not happen with natural phenomena. What do the French or Dutch say when they read in a book of geology: “at the end of the Tertiary epoch the valley of the Thames was deepened in <hi rend="underline">order</hi> that London should have immense commerce etc,” or … “the coast of France was elevated in order that the French should not be seafarers”— They will assuredly say: what do we know? The author has taken the consequences for the goals, the effects for the causes. But these doubts and criticisms of my spirit collapsed when I opened my English-French dictionary, of Spiers:<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Purpose</hi>. But, fin, effet, intention, dessein, usage.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">End</hi>. Bout, extrémité, fin, but, objet, cause.</p>
<p>Thus, each of these English words has two contradictory senses, sometimes a premeditated goal, sometimes an effect—sometimes a cause, sometimes a result. I doubt that your translators have paid attention to this difficulty and I am afraid that the ambiguity of these English words maintains in the English public a certain unphilosophical confusion of ideas. In any case if I have criticised you first <hi rend="underline">in petto</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> it was my own fault; I had not understood the inevitable vagueness determined by language.</p>
<p>My son, who counts as one of his good days, that which you were kind enough to grant him, asks to be remembered to you.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Please tell M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Francis Darwin that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Delpino was luckier than us in his observations of Smilax. I suspected that there was an excretion from the apex of the leaves and we had not seen it, I at Geneva on Smilax excelsa, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Francis Darwin at Kew on Smilax plants probably in a greenhouse, but the plants observed were not in ordinary conditions of climate and growth. At Genoa, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Delpino saw, on two species (S. aspera and bonanox) a sugary substance produced by the glandular tissue which is found at the tip of the leaf, on the outside, especially in the young leaves of annual shoots.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> This sugary substance is sought after by ants. Specimens from herbariums show that the secretion must be stronger in certain species from China, Brazil, etc. Delpino, totally immersed in ancient theories of final causes, seeks the <hi rend="underline">goal</hi>, <hi rend="underline">the aim</hi> for which the secretion and the approach of the ants exist in this case. He believes, in general, that the ants come <hi rend="underline">in order to</hi> rid the trees of harmful insect larvae. I would prefer rather the hypothesis that the matter secreted has the nourishment of ants as its goal. Gardeners have a third way of seeing it, which is to consider the ants as a scourge, which must be removed far as possible. In the end, I would prefer a good experiment to hypotheses; in a row of cherry trees or other trees visited by ants, to coat the trunks with coal tar in order to prevent the visits of these insects, and see whether the growth, flowering and fruiting were different in the trees with and without ants. One would then know the consequences, the effects, in place of making assumptions of any kind about intentions!</p>
<p>I have allowed myself to ramble on in my enjoyment of chatting with you. Nothing remains but to beg you to excuse me for the length, and to assure you, my dear Sir, of all my devotion | Alph. de Candolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Candolle’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref> (see Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See A. de Candolle and Candolle eds. 1878–96, vol. 1. The first three volumes of this work are in the Darwin Library–Down. Candolle worked on the publication with his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_811.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Casimir de Candolle</ref>. Smilaceae is a synonym of Smilacaceae (the family of greenbrier).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See A. de Candolle and Candolle eds. 1878–96, 1: 26–7. Candolle suggested that dioecious species of <hi rend="italic">Smilax</hi> with sticky pollen must be pollinated by insects. The pollen of the monoecious <hi rend="italic">Rhipogonum</hi>, however, was easily transported by the wind, which Candolle thought supported CD’s views on the advantages of cross-fertilisation.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 11, CD commented that differentiation of the sexes in the Restiaceae (a large family of rush-like flowering plants of the southern hemisphere; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, [before 17 January 1877]</ref> and n. 3) had affected the whole plant, not just the flowers, to such an extent that botanists were sometimes unable to match up male and female forms of the same species. See A. de Candolle and Candolle eds. 1878–96, 1: 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Spiers’s</ref> English–French dictionary was published in many editions; see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9565.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spiers 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">In petto</hi>: in private, in secret (Italian).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_811.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Casimir de Candolle</ref> was in England in January 1877 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10759.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alphonse de Candolle, January 1877</ref>); it is not known when he met CD.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref> published on <hi rend="italic">Smilax</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1880</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Smilax bononox</hi> is now usually rendered as <hi rend="italic">S. bono-nox</hi>. In his paper on <hi rend="italic">Acacia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cecropia</hi>, Francis mentioned Delpino’s view that sweet fluid secreted anywhere other than nectaries was to attract ants (see F. Darwin 1876d, p. 408).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>