<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5475F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. W. Nägeli<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   31 March 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21647</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5475F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5475F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5475F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Draft</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="Draft">1p</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">On permanent loan to KULTURAMA Zurich (Inv. 5109_L)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_481.xml">KULTURAMA, Zurich</repository>
                    <idno>Inv. 5109_L</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3473.xml">Nägeli, C. W.</persName>
                <date when="1867-03-31">31 Mar 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Summarises his 12-page letter in which he responds to CD’s criticisms of his theory of ‘perfectibility’.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-04-08" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-04-08" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-04-08" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>31 Mars 1867</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">12 pages</seg>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>sur sa critique de ma theorie du perfectionnement deux choses à distinguer:</p>
<p>1) la relation entre la morphologie et la physiologie. Il y a certaines lois morphologiques qui sont données par la nature de la cellule végétale et qui sont tout à indépendantes de l’utilité (Position des feuilles, <hi rend="underline">position des cellules</hi> etc.) Ceci est sur.</p>
<p>2) la relation entre la morphologie et le perfectionnement, qui est discutable. Je crois que les lois morphologiques impliquent le perfectionnement, savoir la transformation dans un organisme plus compliqué.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>sur mon travail sur les Hieracium: méthode</p>
<p>les Hieraciums et le transformation; plusieurs procès de transmutation avant les périodes glaciales.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Resumé de mes mémoires (que je lui envoie)<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Collections de Hieracium.</p>
<p>J’aimerais avoir un correspondant en Angleterre qui pût me procurer toutes les formes britanniques.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>avec Mittheilungen 18–29</p>
<p>Entstehung der Art II</p>
<p>Photographie<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>31 March 1867</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">12 pages</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In his critique of my theory of perfectibility two things to differentiate:</p>
<p>1) the relation between morphology and physiology. There are certain morphological laws which are given by the nature of the plant cell and which are completely independent of utility (Position of leaves, <hi rend="underline">position of cells</hi> etc.) This is certain.</p>
<p>2) the relation between morphology and perfectibility, which is debatable. I believe that morphological laws imply improvement, that is to say transformation into a more complex organism.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>on my work on the Hieracium: method</p>
<p>Hieraciums and transmutation, several processes of transmutation before the ice ages.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Summary of my papers (which I am sending him)<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Collections of Hieracium.</p>
<p>I would like to have a correspondent in England who could procure all the British varieties for me.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>with Mittheilungen 18–29</p>
<p>Entstehung der Art II</p>
<p>Photograph<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I. It appears to be a resumé of a much longer (twelve-page) letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. 476.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had responded to Nägeli’s theory of species formation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Nägeli 1865</ref>) in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter of 12 June [1866]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 14). Nägeli regarded natural selection as one mechanism of species development, but maintained that it was insufficient by itself to explain various features of plants. He argued that ‘higher’ species evolved through the operation of a ‘perfectibility principle’ (‘<hi rend="italic">Vervollkommnungsprincip</hi>’): a tendency within each organism to develop more complicated structures. Nägeli claimed that this principle operated in conjunction with the natural selection of useful variations (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Nägeli 1865</ref>, pp. 16–17, 28–30). CD admitted that he could not explain many morphological peculiarities, such as the arrangement of leaves or position of ovules, but added, ‘I hardly see how they support the doctrine of some law of necessary development for it is not clear to me that a plant with its leaves placed at some particular angle or with its ovules in some particular position, thus stands higher than another plant.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Nägeli had been working on <hi rend="italic">Hieracium</hi> (the genus of hawkweeds) for four years (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5488.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 5 April [1867]</ref>). In a paper on intermediate forms in plant species (Nägeli 1866d), Nägeli recognised that some plant genera seemed to have an abundance of intermediate forms, which pointed to the relatedness of these hawkweed species and showed that species in general were not absolutely differentiated and could have developed from a common source or one from another (Nägeli 1866d, p. 190). Nägeli further tried to develop a method of distinguishing between intermediate species and hybrids.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Nägeli discussed variation in <hi rend="italic">Hieracium</hi> in ‘Ueber die systematische Behandlung der Hieracien rücksichtlich der Mittelformen’ (On the systematic treatment of Hieracium with regard to intermediate forms; Nägeli 1866a), ‘Ueber die systematische Behandlung der Hieracien rücksichtlich des Umfanges des Species’ (On the systematic treatment of Hieracium with regard to the range of species; Nägeli 1866b), and ‘Ueber die Innovation bei den Hieracien und ihre systematische Bedeutung’ (On innovation in Hieracium and its systematic significance; Nägeli 1866c). See n. 6, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5488.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Joseph Dalton Hooker of 5 April [1867]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15), CD passed on Nägeli’s request for a complete set of British forms of <hi rend="italic">Hieracium</hi> in exchange for a large set of German and Alpine forms.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Nägeli had included several of his papers on intermediate species of <hi rend="italic">Hieracium</hi> in the second volume of his <hi rend="italic">Botanische Mittheilungen</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9455.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Nägeli 1863–81</ref>; included were Nägeli 1866a, 1866b, and 1866d). CD’s heavily annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9455.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Nägeli 1863–81</ref> vol. 2, with the first two papers, 16 and 17, removed, is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi> 1: 625–30). Nägeli also sent the second edition of his <hi rend="italic">Entstehung und Begriff der naturhistorischen Art</hi> (The origin and concept of natural historical species; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Nägeli 1865</ref>) and his photograph (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15, letter to C. W. von Nägeli, [after 8 April 1867]).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>