<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11942">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   17 March 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5452</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11942 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11942.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11942.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B17–18</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B17–18</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-03-17">17 Mar 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Had doubts about excerpt from Anna Seward’s book [<hi rend="italic">Life of Dr Darwin</hi>]. Sends slightly enlarged version of his "Erasmus Darwin". Includes footnote denouncing Seward’s book.</p>  
<p>Finds that part 2 of ED’s <hi rend="italic">Botanic garden</hi>, 2d ed. (1790), appeared before part 1 (1791).</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Botanic garden</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Life of Dr Darwin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Darwin, Erasmus 1790</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Seward, Anna 1804</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-05" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-18" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-19" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-07-19" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00152_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00152_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        <surface n="B:17r" xml:id="i152">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00152.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00152_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00152.dzi" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:17v" xml:id="i153">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00153.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00153_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00153.dzi" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:18r" xml:id="i154">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00154.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00154_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00154.dzi" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:18v" xml:id="i155">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00155.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00155_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00155.dzi" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 17 Maerz 79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Während ich eben im Begriffe war, die kleinen Zusätze abzuschliessen, welche theils eine bessere Gruppirung des Stoffes, theils einige Ergänzungen bezwecken, traf Ihr freundliches Schreiben vom 14<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi>. C. ein, welches mir eine grosse Befriedigung gewährt.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich hatte nämlich alsbald bei der Lecture des ausführlichen Auszuges aus dem Buche der Miss Seward, welchen die Edinburgh Review von 1804 heraus brachte, zu bemerken geglaubt, dass die Verfasserin unlautere Nebenzwecke verfolgt habe, und manche ihrer Geschichten auf Klatschereien beruhen müssten, so namentlich eine Anecdote über einen Rausch, die wenn überhaupt wahr, nicht der Erwähnung werth war, und Aehnliches.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Es scheint mir daher um so weniger nothwendig, dieses Buch zu lesen, als es bei diesem Essay viel weniger darauf ankommt, Einzelnheiten ueber Erlebnisse aufzufrischen, als vielmehr einen Beitrag zur Geschichte der Naturphilosophie und des Evolutions-Gedankens zu geben. Deshalb erlaube ich mir nun Ihnen den nur wenig erweiterten Aufsatz einzusenden, insbesondre auch, weil ich befürchte, dass eine noch weitere Text-Vermehrung die Aufnahme in eine Revue erschweren würde. Sollte mir später, sei es durch Ihre gütige Vermittlung, sei es sonstwoher weiteres zuverlässiges Material zu Händen kommen, so liesse sich jederzeit auf eine englische und deutsche Buchausgabe zurückkommen und dieselbe könnte durch längeres Sammeln nur gewinnen. Ich dachte darin als weitern Hintergrund die Anschaungen Linné’s, Buffon’s u. der französischen Encyclopädisten, sowie ferner diejenigen von Leibnitz, Haller, Göthe, also der ganzen Epoche <hi rend="underline">vor</hi> Lamarck wiederzugeben.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Aber die Verwirklichung dieses Planes wird noch mancherlei Vorstudien erfordern.</p>
                    <p>Nachdem ich von Ihnen nun eine Bestätigung meines Eindruckes von der Seward’schen Arbeit erhalten habe, scheint es mir nothwendig, dieselbe in einer Anmerkung zu discreditiren, und habe ich sogleich ein Paar diesbezügliche Worte hinzugesetzt.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Noch wirksamer würde es natürlich sein, wenn Sie diese Anmerkung selbst machen und unterzeichnen wollten. Doch überlasse ich diese, wie alle sonstigen Anordnungen völlig Ihrem Ermessen, ebenso, wie ich Sie herzlich bitte, die englische Uebersetzung, falls sie zu Stande kömmt, vor dem Druck noch einmal eingehend prüfen zu wollen. Den botanischen Garten besitzt die hiesige Königliche Bibliothek in einer Ausgabe, wobei der erste Theil (in <hi rend="underline">zweiter</hi> Ausgabe) die Jahreszahl 1791 trägt, während der zweite Theil schon 1790 in zweiter Ausgabe erschienen ist. Es wäre nun möglich, dass der zweite Theil der zuerst gedichtete wäre, von welchem einzelne Nachrichten angeben, dass er schon 1781 vorgelegen habe.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Mancherlei innere Gründe scheinen mir dafür zu sprechen, dass, wie ich auch im Texte erwähnt habe, “the loves of plants” nicht im unmittelbaren Anschlusse an den ersten Theil verfasst seien, vielleicht erklärt sich das so, dass sie gleichsam als eine poëtische Bearbeitung von Linné’s nuptiae plantarum früher vollendet wurden, als der später hinzugefügte erste Theil. Da das aber nur eine Vermuthung und ohne weitere Wichtigkeit ist, so habe ich davon nichts erwähnt, und nur die unsichere Jahreszahl 1781 weggestrichen.</p>
<p>Indem ich Sie, hochverehrter Herr, noch bitte, mir falls die Uebersetzung zu Stande kommt, einen Abdruck sichern zu wollen, zeichne ich | Mit den herzlichsten Wünschen für Ihr Befinden | Ihr | dankbar ergebener | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
             
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>17 March 79.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>As I was just about to finish the minor additions, partly to give the material a better structure, partly to complete it in a number of respects, your kind letter of the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of this month arrived, which gave me great satisfaction.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> For I had noticed immediately, when reading the detailed excerpts from the book by Miss Seward in the Edinburgh Review of 1804, that the author pursued dubious secondary aims, and that some of her tales must be based on gossip, particularly the anecdote about a drunken bout that, if true at all, was not worth mentioning, and similar things.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Hence it now seems to me all the less important to read this book, since the point of my essay is not to polish up details about adventures, but rather to contribute to the history of natural philosophy and evolutionary thought. For this reason I venture to send you the essay now, only slightly augmented, in particular also because I fear that further expansions will make it more difficult to get it accepted by a periodical. If, whether through your kind offices, or from wherever else, further reliable material should come into my hands, it would be possible at any time to come back to an English and German book edition, and this could only profit from further collecting. In this respect, I was thinking of giving as further background an account of the views of Linné, Buffon, &amp; the French encyclopaedists, and further those of Leibnitz, Haller, Göthe, that is, of the whole epoch <hi rend="underline">prior to</hi> Lamarck.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> However the realization of this project will of course require still further preliminary study.</p>
                    <p>Since you confirmed my impression of the Seward book, it struck me that I ought to discredit it in a footnote, and I added a few words to this effect at once.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It would be even more effective, of course, if you made these remarks yourself under your own name. However, I leave this matter, as all other arrangements, entirely to your discretion; just as I beg you most cordially to closely inspect the English translation once again, should it come about, before it goes to press. Our Royal Library here has an edition of the botanic garden whose first part (in the <hi rend="underline">second</hi> edition) bears the date 1791, while the second part came out in the second edition as early as 1790. It seems possible that the second part was written first, and according to a few reports it was already in existence in 1781.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> A number of internal reasons seem to me to indicate, as I mentioned also in the text, that “the loves of plants” was not written immediately after the first part; this may perhaps be due to the fact that the, as it were, poetic treatment of Linné’s nuptiae plantarum<ref target="#foot.f7"/> was completed before the first part, which was added later. However, since this is mere conjecture and without further implications, I have not said anything about it and only deleted the uncertain date of 1781.</p>
<p>With the additional request, most esteemed Sir, to be sent an offprint of the English translation, should it come about, I remain | With the most cordial wishes for your health | Yours | gratefully devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 14 March 1879</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">An essay review of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the life of Dr. Darwin</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>) was published in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> 4 (1804): 230–41. No anecdote concerning a bout of drunkenness is recorded in this review, but Seward did write of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>’s drunkenness on a boating trip to Nottingham, during which he allegedly stepped overboard, swam to shore, and walked into the town, where he addressed working men on the benefits of fresh air and sobriety (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>, pp. 64–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2942.xml">Carl von Linné</ref> (Linnaeus), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_714.xml">Georges Louis Leclerc</ref> (comte de Buffon), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2872.xml">Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2069.xml">Albrecht von Haller</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2786.xml">Jean Baptiste de Lamarck</ref>. The French encyclopaedists were the authors who contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie</hi> edited by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7549.xml">Denis Diderot</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7007.xml">Jean le Rond D’Alembert</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9239.xml">Diderot and Alembert eds. 1751–65</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Krause did not include a footnote to discredit Seward in the published version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The earliest publication date for the second part  (<hi rend="italic">The loves of the plants</hi>) of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref> was 1789. For the complete publication history, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml">King-Hele 1999</ref>, p. 401.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Nuptiae plantarum</hi>: marriages of plants (Latin); the term was used by Linnaeus in <hi rend="italic">Systema naturæ</hi> in his key to the sexual system of plants (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4797.xml">Linnaeus 1758–9</ref>, 2: 837).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>