<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4934">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   11 November 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5277</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4934 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4934.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4934.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 13</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 40</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 40</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="high">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1865-11-11">11 Nov 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has heard from Huxley that CD has been ill.</p> 
<p>Progress on his book [<hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie</hi> (1866)] has been slow.</p> 
            <p>Has been named "ordentlicher Professor". Has 150 listeners in his lectures on CD’s theory.</p>
            <p>Thanks CD for copy [of "Climbing plants"].</p> 
<p>Sends his book [<hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Naturgeschichte der Hydromedusen</hi>, 1. Heft: <hi rend="italic">Die Familie der Rüsselquallen (Geryonidae)</hi> (1865)] and two articles.</p> 
            <p>Calls attention to a new rhizopod from Nice.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term ref="#">rhizopod</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbing plants</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Beitrage zur Naturgeschichte der Hydromedusen</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die Familie der Russelquallen (Geryonidae)</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Generelle Morphologie</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2486">Huxley, T. H.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Nice</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1865a</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1866</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">professorship at Jena</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>11. November 1865.</date>
                    <salute>Mein hochverehrter theurer Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Nach längerer Zeit des Schweigens darf ich wohl wieder Ihre kostbare Zeit zum Lesen eines Briefes von mir in Anspruch nehmen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Durch Herrn Huxley habe ich zu meinem grossen Bedauern erfahren, dass Sie leider wieder sehr krank gewesen sind.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ich hoffe, dass es Ihnen wieder besser geht, und dass Sie der Wissenschaft und uns noch recht lange erhalten bleiben.</p>
<p>Leider ist mein Buch, welches Ihre Theorie ausführlich behandelt, immer noch nicht vollendet, trotzdem ich es schon vor einem halben Jahre fertig zu sehen hoffte.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ich habe aber diesen ganzen Sommer mit Arbeiten am zoologischen Museum verlieren müssen;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> da ich nämlich vor 6 Monaten hier zum ordentlichen Professor der Zoologie ernannt worden bin, nachdem ich eine Berufung nach Würzburg abgelehnt hatte.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Indessen hoffe ich das Buch bis nächsten Weihnachten vollenden zu können und werde es Ihnen sogleich nach Vollendung zusenden.</p>
<p>In diesem Winter hatte ich hier wieder öffentliche Vorlesungen “<hi rend="underline">über Darwins Theorie</hi>”, welche die besuchtesten von <hi rend="underline">allen</hi> Vorlesungen sind, die an der hiesigen Universität gehalten werden.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Ich habe über 150 Zuhörer, und das grösste Auditorium unserer Universität ist gefüllt. Sie können daraus ersehen, welches ausserordentliche Interesse hier an unserer kleinen Universität für Sie und Ihre Theorie herrscht und wie lebhaft die Theilnahme an der grossen Reform der Wissenschaft ist, welche Sie begonnen haben, und welche durchführen zu helfen die grösste Aufgabe meines Lebens ist. Meine Zuhörerschaft ist sehr gemischt, es sind darunter ausser vielen Medicinern und Naturforschern auch viele Historiker und Studenten der Philosophie; selbst einige Theologen und Juristen fehlen nicht!</p>
<p>Für die Übersendung Ihres schönen Aufsatzes “on the climbing plants” sage ich Ihnen meinen herzlichsten Dank.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Ich habe ihn mit grossem Interesse gelesen.</p>
<p>Hoffentlich werden Sie mein Buch über die Geryoniden (mit 6 Tafeln), sowie einen Aufsatz “über fossile Medusen” und einen anderen über “Rhizopoden Sarcode” richtig erhalten haben.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Ich hatte Herrn Engelmann in Leipzig beauftragt, Ihnen diese Arbeiten sogleich zu senden.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Unter den neuen Rhizopoden aus Nizza wird Sie der “Protogenes primordialis” (Fig 1, 2) vielleicht interessiren, als eines der allereinfachsten Geschöpfe, ein Organismus ohne Organe, durchaus homogen!<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Die Generatio aequivoca eines solchen lebenden Eiweiss-Klumpens liesse sich schon allenfalls denken, und damit wäre der Descendenz-Theorie über Ihren schwierigen Anfang hinweggeholfen.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>So oft ich Ihnen schreibe, mein theurer Herr, muss ich Ihnen den wärmsten Dank wiederholen für die unerschöpflische Quelle der Geistesthätigkeit und der lebendigen Anregung, welche Ihre classische Theorie für mich ist. Seitdem mir durch den Tod meines innigst geliebten Weibes alles Leben des Gemüthes abgeschnitten und getödtet ist, ist mir das Streben, mit dem geschärften Verstande die wahre Natur und den Zusammenhang der natürlichen Dinge zu erkennen, allein übrig geblieben.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Dieses Streben beschäftigt mich in meinem Einsiedlerleben Tag und Nacht, und dieses Streben verdanke ich nur Ihrem Wercke!</p>
<p>Mögen Sie uns noch lange in frischer Kraft erhalten bleiben, um die von Ihnen begonnene Reform der Biologie durchgeführt zu sehen und die Früchte Ihrer grossen Geistesthat selbst zu pflücken. Das ist der herzlichste Wunsch Ihres aufrichtig Ihnen ergebenen | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>11 November 1865.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed, dear Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>After a long period of silence, I hope I may take up your valuable time again with one of my letters.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> To my great regret I heard from Mr. Huxley that unfortunately you have been very ill again.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I hope you are feeling better now and that you will remain with us and science for a long time yet.</p>
<p>Unfortunately my book, which deals in detail with your theory, is still unfinished, although I had hoped to complete it half a year ago.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> However, I was forced to give up the whole summer in order to work at the zoological museum;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> you see, I was made a full professor of zoology 6 months ago, after I turned down the offer of a chair at Würzburg.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Still, I hope to be able to complete the book by next Christmas and I will send it to you as soon as it is finished.</p>
<p>This winter I am giving public lectures “<hi rend="underline">on Darwin’s theory</hi>” again, which are the most popular of <hi rend="underline">all</hi> lectures given at this university.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have over 150 attendants and the largest lecture theatre of our university is packed. This gives you an idea of how exceptional the interest in you and your theory is here at our small university and how much support there is for the great reform of science that you have begun and that it is the greatest task of my life to realise. My audience is very mixed; in addition to many students of medicine and the sciences it includes numerous historians and students of philosophy; there are even a few theologians and lawyers!</p>
<p>My most heartfelt thanks to you for sending your beautiful essay “on the climbing plants”.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have read it with great interest.</p>
<p>I hope you received my book on Geryonidae (with 6 plates) in good order, as well as a paper “on fossil Medusae” and another one on “Rhizopodean protoplasm”.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I instructed Mr Engelmann in Leipzig to send you these works without delay.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Among the new Rhizopoda of Nice the “Protogenes primordialis” (fig. 1, 2) might interest you as one of the simplest of all creatures, an organism without organs, homogeneous throughout!<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The <hi rend="underline">generatio aequivoca</hi> of such a living gelatinous mass is at any rate conceivable, and this would help the theory of descent with the difficulty of explaining the first origin.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Whenever I write to you, dear Sir, I must reiterate my warmest thanks for the unfailing inspiration and the vigorous stimulus that your classical theory gives me. Ever since the death of my most dearly beloved wife put an end to and destroyed my emotional life, all I have left is the aspiration to employ the keenest intellect in understanding the true nature and continuity of natural things.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> This aspiration occupies me in my hermit-like existence day and night, and I owe this aspiration solely to your work!</p>
<p>May you long remain in vigorous health, so as to witness the reform of biology which you began, and to enjoy the fruits of your great intellectual achievement. This is the most heartfelt wish of your sincerely devoted | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 302–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haeckel’s last known letter to CD is dated 26 October 1864 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12); however, CD received a copy of Haeckel 1865b in May 1865 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4827.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 4 May [1865]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haeckel refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>. On CD’s health, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4921.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 22 and 28 [October 1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The book was eventually published as <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>. In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 9 [July 1864]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12), Haeckel had claimed that in his next book he would show that the theory of descent threw ‘light on every single chapter’ of the history of creation and unified them ‘in the most perfect harmony’. See also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 26 October 1864</ref>. CD’s annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref> is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 355–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel succeeded <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1834.xml">Carl Gegenbaur</ref> as director of the Zoological Museum in Jena in 1862, and began a programme of improvement and acquisition. In the summer of 1865, Haeckel successfully petitioned the Weimar state ministry to finance a complete reorganisation of the collection, a new hall to house acquisitions, and instruments for research. Haeckel was able to obtain government funding by establishing a separate Zoological Institute within the Museum. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Uschmann 1959</ref>, pp. 48–58.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel received a full professorship at Jena on 15 May 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Uschmann 1959</ref>, p. 50). Five days previously, he had been offered a full professorship at Würzburg, but declined. The terms of the Würzburg position stipulated that control of the zoology museum and examinations remain with another, more senior, zoology professor (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 51).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The popularity of Haeckel’s course on ‘Darwins Theorie’ is described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Uschmann 1959</ref>, p. 44. Since 1862, Haeckel had also given a separate annual lecture on CD’s theory, and had devoted part of his zoology course to the topic (see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 43–4, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 9 [July 1864]</ref>). On the reception of CD’s theory in Germany, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Huxley, 29 May 1865</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>. No presentation list for the paper has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Haeckel refers to his monograph on the Geryonidae (now called Geryoniidae), a family of medusae (Haeckel 1865a), and to Haeckel 1865c and 1865d. A copy of Haeckel 1865a is listed in the 1875 catalogue of CD’s library (DAR 240); however, it is not recorded in later catalogues and has not been found in the Darwin Library–CUL or at Down. A lightly annotated copy of Haeckel 1865d is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The Leipzig firm <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7215.xml">Wilhelm Engelmann</ref> had published Haeckel 1865a, and was also the publisher of <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für wissenschaftsliche Zoologie</hi>, in which Haeckel 1865c and 1865d appeared.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Haeckel described <hi rend="italic">Protogenes primordialis</hi> as the simplest type of Rhizopoda; a protoplasmic aggregate, without differentiation, organisation, or nucleus, it was able to surround and assimilate foreign bodies and to reproduce by simple division (Haeckel 1865d, pp. 360–3). In his later book, <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie der Organismen</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>, 2: XXII–XXIII), Haeckel created a new classification for the organism within a phylum he named the Monera, within the kingdom Protista, arguing that the Rhizopoda had possibly evolved from a <hi rend="italic">Protogenes</hi> species. The organism is not recognised in modern taxonomic literature.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Generatio aequivoca</hi> or equivocal generation: ‘the (supposed) production of plants or animals without parents; spontaneous generation’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). Haeckel did not discuss <hi rend="italic">Primogenes primordialis</hi> (an unpublished taxon) as a case of spontaneous generation (Haeckel 1865d); however, in <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie der Organismen</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>, 2: 174), he did speculate more generally on the possibility of spontaneous generation. For discussions of Haeckel’s theories of protoplasm and the development of living organisms from inorganic matter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6585.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rehbock 1975</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6787.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rupke 1976</ref>. On the Victorian debates over spontaneous generation, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Strick 2000</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Haeckel’s wife, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5816.xml">Anna Sethe</ref>, had died on 16 February 1864; Haeckel discussed her death and its significance for his scientific work in his letters to CD of 9 [July 1864], 10 August 1864, and 26 October 1864 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>