<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4839">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. D. Walsh   29 May 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7965</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4839 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4839.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4839.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp inc †, CD note</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 47: 179, 179a; DAR 207: 18</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>47: 179–9a,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>207: 18</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4944.xml">Walsh, B. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Rock Island, Ill.</placeName>
                <date when="1865-05-29">29 May 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses several subjects, including examples of "Unity of coloration",</p>
            <p>the origin of gall-producing poison,</p>
            <p>Wagner’s theory of viviparous larvae,</p>
            <p>and stridulation in insects.</p> 
<p>Sends a reference supporting CD’s statement in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> that flies check propagation of horses and cattle.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cattle</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">flies</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">horses</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Wagner</term>
                <term type="organism" ref="#">gall</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">larvae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rock Island. Illinois.</placeName>
                    <date>May 29, 1865</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas. Darwin Esq</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                
<p>Many thanks for your letter of March 27.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I fear, in the present state of your health, I am troubling you too often with my scribblings; but the remedy is an easy one &amp; in your own hands—throw them in the fire.</p>
<p>I was delighted with your <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Primula</hi> papers, &amp; also with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Scott’s paper on <hi rend="underline">Primulaceæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> What a remarkable fact that is which he brings out, that the red variety of the common Primrose <hi rend="doubleUnderline">absolutely refuses</hi> to intercross with the normal form.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Such facts as these, it seems to me, knock the ground away completely from under the Creative Theory.</p>
<p>As to “Unity of Coloration” you have yourself given one very good example in the stripes which re-appear more or less in the several species of the genus <hi rend="underline">Equus.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f4"/> Another instance is found in the fawn of our common deer being <hi rend="underline">spotted</hi> like many adult fallow deer, &amp; Prof. Haldeman<ref target="#foot.f5"/> writes me word that he has remarked on the rump in <hi rend="underline">cervus</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">antelope</hi> “being frequently of a lighter tint than the general color”. (<hi rend="underline">Freshwater Univalve Mollusca</hi> N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 7. Jan 1844 Planorbis p. 5)<ref target="#foot.f6"/>   There is another most remarkable one in the Owlet-moths (<hi rend="underline">Noctuadæ</hi>), in almost every genus of which the “orbicular” &amp; “reniform” spots are found, besides five transverse lines of color which Guenée calls respectively the “basal”, the “transverse anterior”, the “transverse posterior”, the “subterminal” &amp; the “terminal”.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> From the enormous number of species in Insects, an Entomologist is naturally led to notice such things more than other Naturalists. I am not sufficiently familiar with exotic species of Insects to say whether or not genera inhabiting two continents “sometimes display a somewhat different type of coloring”.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> But ever since I have been collecting in this country I have been struck almost every day by the same genera on both sides the Atlantic displaying the same coloration. For example, I have two N.A. species of <hi rend="underline">Panagæus</hi> in my collection, (<hi rend="underline">P. fasciatus</hi> Say, &amp; <hi rend="underline">cruciger</hi> Say) which imitate your <hi rend="underline">P. crux-major</hi> both in design &amp; color; yet with the exception of the <hi rend="underline">Lebia</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Bembidium</hi> groups, almost all other <hi rend="underline">Carabidæ</hi> are of plain colors. If then there is no genetic connection between the N.A. &amp; European species of <hi rend="underline">Panagæus</hi>, &amp; if (as I think we must concede) coloration is independent of structure, why should <hi rend="underline">Panagæus</hi>, <hi rend="doubleUnderline">on both sides of the Atlantic</hi>, have four more or less confluent large red spots arranged in a quadrangle on its elytra?</p>
<p>My idea as to the mode in which <hi rend="underline">Cecidomyia</hi> acquired its gall-producing poison,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> is that originally they were all without it, as are to this day the Hessian fly (<hi rend="underline">C. destructor</hi>) &amp; the Wheat-midge. (<hi rend="underline">Cec. tritice</hi>). But that individuals by Variation acquired the power of secreting a minute portion of poison so as to irritate the plant slightly &amp; cause a slight additional flow of sap, &amp; a better nidus for the future larva,, whereby they gained an advantage over their fellows &amp; so on according to your theory. Whether the Guest-flies are degraded Gall-flies, or in an incipient state of perfection, is perhaps a doubtful point, though I rather incline to the former hypothesis.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>As to Wagner’s theory of Viviparous larvæ,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> allowing it as you say to be a form of gemmation, ought we to expect to find a mode of reproduction characteristic of the Vegetable Kingdom, &amp; hitherto only met with in Animals of very low type, in such highly organized &amp; intellectual beings as Insects? Taking everything into consideration, I think Insects are superior to Fish, &amp; could you yourself swallow down gemmiparous Fish without very good Ichthyological authority? I couldn’t. Now if a Fish, which has no “penis intrans”,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> which inhabits the water still &amp; which still breathes through gills, is not found to be gemmiparous, I am loath to believe that an insect can be so. Still, facts are stubborn things, &amp; it may turn out that Wagner &amp; Co are right, though I still believe he was deceived by parasitic larvæ.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>In a brief review of Wagner’s book which I have lately seen reference is made to a genus <hi rend="underline">Daphnia</hi> &amp; Family <hi rend="underline">Daphnidæ</hi>, in which <hi rend="underline">both males &amp; females</hi> are said to produce parthenogenic eggs in the summer, &amp; another kind of eggs called “ephippia” in the winter.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> To what class do these extraordinary animals belong? Can it be possible that true males generate eggs?</p>
<p>I bought a few weeks ago Lyell’s Book on the Antiquity of Man,<ref target="#foot.f15"/> &amp; was highly delighted with it. I had no idea that Prof. Owen was capable of making such an ass of himself as he has done<ref target="#foot.f16"/> 〈<hi rend="underline">section excised</hi>〉</p>
<p>You have referred in the “Origin” to a (dipterous?) fly checking the propagation of cattle &amp; horses in the southern parts of South America.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I find that in Gen. Páez’s book on South America (p. 58) he says that in the Northern parts (Venezuela &amp;c) a fly called ‘gutano’ oviposits in the umbilicus of newly born foals so constantly, that the herdsmen have to examine all the young foals &amp; remove the larva, or otherwise the foal is sure to die.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> May we not account for the extinction of the Horse in America by some such means as this?</p>
<p>Ever yours very truly, | Benj. D. Walsh</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">section excised</hi>〉 the so-called 〈<hi rend="underline">remainder of line excised</hi>〉 I am as unwilling to believe in gemmiparous insects as in hermaphrodite insects. Both seem to me low forms of reproduction derived originally from the Vegetable Kingdom &amp; dropped in the march of development at an early period.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>4.1 My idea … larvæ. 5.11] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>8.3 he says that … as this? 8.7] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi>; ‘Struggle for Existence’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">On separate sheet</hi>: ‘Unity of colour in Bembycidæ— | Panagæus in N. America coloured as in Europe—good | Law of Variation | My analogy of variation is nearly same as Walsh law of equable coloration, only I refer only to Variation’<ref target="#foot.f19"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had sent Walsh copies of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4778.xml">letter from B. D. Walsh, 1 March 1865</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref>), and, evidently, an offprint of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">John Scott</ref>’s study of reproduction in the Primulaceae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7021.xml">Scott 1864b</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In Scott 1864b, pp. 97–102, Scott gave the results of experiments with <hi rend="italic">Primula vulgaris</hi>, the common primrose, and a red and a white variety of primrose. His results suggested that the red primrose was infertile with pollen from the common and the white primrose, but fertile with its own pollen. If established, this would have been evidence in favour of CD’s views on the origin of species. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, in several publications (most recently in T. H. Huxley 1863b), had argued that CD’s views would not be beyond doubt until he could demonstrate ‘the possibility of developing from a particular stock, by selective breeding, two forms, which should either be unable to cross one with another, or whose cross-bred offspring should be infertile with one another’ (T. H. Huxley 1863b, p. 146). CD had also thought that Scott’s results were remarkable (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4611.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 13 September [1864]</ref>). However, he was unable to corroborate Scott’s results regarding the sterility of the red variety when pollinated by the common primrose when he repeated the crossing experiments in 1865 and 1866 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 109 n. and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Illegitimate offspring of dimorphic and trimorphic plants’</ref>, p. 420). CD’s notes on these experiments are in DAR 108 and DAR 110. For further discussion of CD’s and Scott’s experimental work on intra-specific sterility, prompted by Huxley’s challenge, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 10–12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For CD’s interest in Walsh’s law of unity of coloration, see his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Walsh of 27 March [1865]</ref> and nn. 5 and 6. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 163–7, CD gave examples of the tendency of a number of species in the horse genus to develop stripes, especially in young animals and hybrids, and hypothesised that this was because they were descended from a striped ancestor. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 7–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2056.xml">Samuel Steman Haldeman</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his <hi rend="italic">Monograph of the freshwater mollusca of the United States</hi>, Haldeman, in a discussion of <hi rend="italic">Planorbis</hi>, a genus of pond-snails, commented: ‘Certain uniform colors, lines, or spots, mark genera and families; in Cervus and Antilope the rump is frequently of a lighter tint than the general color’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3299.xml">Haldeman 184[2–]5</ref>, ‘Genus Planorbis, <hi rend="italic">Müller</hi>’, p. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Walsh probably refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2012.xml">Achille Guenée</ref>’s three-volume monograph on the <hi rend="italic">Noctuadae</hi> or ‘<hi rend="italic">Noctuélites</hi>’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1852</ref>). Guenée’s terminology for describing the spots and lines of colour on the wings of this family of moths appears in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1852</ref>, 1: xlii–xliv and 3: fig. 1; however, Walsh appears to have translated Guenée’s terms into a nomenclature of his own.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref> and nn. 8 and 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For CD’s query as to whether guest-flies may have developed from gall-flies, and for Walsh’s subsequent discussion in Walsh 1866, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">For CD’s comment on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6942.xml">Nikolai Petrovich Wagner</ref>’s observation of paedogenesis (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8030.xml">Wagner 1862</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8031.xml">1863</ref>), see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref> and nn. 15 and 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Penis intrans</hi>: internal penis (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4733.xml">C. T. Lewis and Short 1969</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">For Walsh’s eventual conclusion regarding paedogenesis, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 19 December [1865]</ref>, and Walsh 1866, p. 288.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The reference is to the review of Wagner’s article on viviparous gall-forming midge larvae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1865</ref>) in the May 1865 issue of the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi>, pp. 362–3 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5471.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Minor 1865</ref>). Walsh was misled by a mistake in translation in the review. Wagner had drawn an analogy between the two phases of reproduction in <hi rend="italic">Aphis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Daphnia.</hi> In both genera, males and females are produced asexually by parthenogenetic eggs in summer; they are also produced sexually in winter from eggs carried by the female in a pouch, or ephippia (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1865</ref>, pp. 110–11). The review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1865</ref>, however, mistranslated reproduction ‘of both males and females’ as reproduction ‘in both males and females’, thus implying that males produced eggs (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5471.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Minor 1865</ref>, p. 362).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Walsh probably refers to the second American edition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Antiquity of man</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5029.xml">C. Lyell 1863d</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">In <hi rend="italic">Antiquity of man</hi>, Lyell reviewed the long-running controversy between <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> and, principally, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> about the comparative anatomy of human and simian brains (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5026.xml">C. Lyell 1863a</ref>, pp. 480–93). On the so-called hippocampus controversy, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1982</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6790.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rupke 1994</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8419.xml">L. G. Wilson 1996</ref>. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 9–11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Walsh refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6469.xml">Ramón Páez</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Wild scenes in South America, or life in the llanos of Venezuela</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paez 1863</ref>, pp. 58–9). Páez was a son of General <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6468.xml">José Antonio Páez</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4934A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. D. Walsh, 12 November 1865</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">On Walsh’s law of unity of coloration, see n. 4, above. For CD’s discussion of analogous variation (the tendency of descendants of a common ancestor to vary in similar ways), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 159–70, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 348–52. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 351–2, CD mentioned Walsh’s ‘Law of <hi rend="italic">Equable Variability</hi>’: ‘if any given character is very variable in one species of a group, it will tend to be variable in allied species; and if any given character is perfectly constant in one species of a group, it will tend to be constant in allied species’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8145.xml">Walsh 1863</ref>, p. 213); adding that this law was similar to his statement in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> that generic characters were less variable than specific characters (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 168). CD also comments on Walsh’s law of equable variability in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 187.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>