<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13185A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   31 May 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20493</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13185A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13185A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13185A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">inc (German trans)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 410–11</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Möller, Alfred 1915–21 2: 410–11</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Blumenau, Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1881-05-31">31 May 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has just received CD’s letter of 12 April [<hi rend="doubleUnderline">13113</hi>]. To answer CD’s query, <hi rend="italic">Heteranthera reniformis</hi> is an amphibious plant that grows as well on moist ground as it does in ditches filled with water.</p>  
<p>For the past few weeks has been observing <hi rend="italic">Phyllanthus</hi> plants that had shown the irregular movement in leaves returning from the positions assumed at night, but none has repeated the irregularity. Perhaps the progeny from the seeds he has collected will inherit the tendency for irregular movement.</p>  
<p>Describes his observations of the power of movement in <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi>, and a few other plants.</p> 
            <p>Paul Mayer has identified seven new species of insects FM found in nine different species of figs.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">13113</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Cassia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Desmodium</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">figs</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Phyllanthus</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3242">Mayer, Paul</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number of species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-12-10" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-23" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-31" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Blumenau, Sa. Catharina, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>31. Mai 1881.</date>
                    <salute>Verehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>Ihr freundlicher Brief vom 12. April ist grade angekommen, und ich will sofort Ihre Frage über Heteranthera reniformis beantworten.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Es ist eine amphibische Pflanze, welche in stehendem Wasser von Sümpfen und Gräben ebenso gut wächst wie ausserhalb des Wassers an feuchten Stellen. …</p>
<p>Während ich bei einer Pflanze von Phyllanthus viele Wochen lang täglich beobachtete, dass an einem oder mehreren Zweigen ihre Blätter bei der Rückkehr aus der Nachtstellung den falschen Weg eingeschlagen hatten, so war es mir nicht möglich, ein zweites Beispiel dieser Unregelmässigkeit bei Hunderten von Pflanzen derselben Art aufzufinden, die ich seitdem darauf untersucht habe. Nur einmal vor ein paar Tagen an einem kalten Morgen sah ich 3 Blätter, welche auf der richtigen Seite zurückgekommen waren, aber ohne sich zu drehen, so dass ihre Unterseiten nach oben gekehrt waren. An den folgenden Tagen zeigten sie die normale Stellung. Von der Pflanze mit den abnorm sich bewegenden Blättern habe ich einige Samen gesammelt; vielleicht werden einige ihrer Nachkommen jene Unregelmässigkeit ererben.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Was die Bewegung der Blätter bei Cassia, Desmodium und einigen anderen Pflanzen angeht, die sie ausführen, wenn man sie schüttelt oder anschlägt, so glaube ich, dass Sie mit der Vermuthung recht haben, es geschehe, um die Regentropfen wegzuschnellen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Heute regnet es schon länger als 5 Stunden, und ich bin grade durch meinen Garten gegangen, um zu sehen, welche Stellung die Blätter der Cassia u. s. w. angenommen haben. Die Cassia-Blätter haben eine Stellung, die zwischen der Tag- und Nachtstellung in der Mitte liegt; die Fläche der Blättchen liegt in einer verticalen Ebene, senkrecht zum Blattstiel (und so liegen die beiden Blättchen jedes Paares in derselben Ebene); die Oberseiten sind nach der Spitze des Blattstieles gerichtet; gleichzeitg sind die Blättchen abwärts gebogen, so dass die beiden Mittelrippen jedes Paares ungefähr einen rechten Winkel bilden. Bei sehr heftigen Regengüssen nehmen die Blätter dieser Cassia ihre Nachtstellung an.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Die Blätter einer Acacia sind in einer der nächtlichen sehr ähnlichen Stellung. Die Blätter von Schizolobium (doppelt gefiedert, wie diejenigen von Acacia, aber sehr gross), haben kaum ihre Tagstellung verändert, während sie bei sehr schwerem Regen sich ziemlich ähnlich so stellen wie die Cassia-Blätter des Nachts. Die Blätter zweier Arten von Desmodium haben ihre Nachtstellung eingenommen, während diejenigen einer dritten Art die Tagstellung festhalten. Die Blättchen von Oxalis sepium hängen senkrecht herunter, wie sie gewöhnlich (aber nicht ohne Ausnahme) des Nachts thun. — Die Blätter von Phyllanthus compressus haben sich nicht bewegt; bei Ph. consanguineus stehen die Blattflächen beinah in einer senkrechten Ebene, etwas abwärts gebogen, und die Mittelrippen bilden einen Winkel von ungefähr 30<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> mit dem Horizont; bei einer dritten Art von Phyllanthus mit sehr abweichender nyctitroper Bewegung haben die Blätter nichtdestoweniger eine ganz ähnliche Regenstellung eingenommen wie bei der vorhergehenden; nur sind sie noch etwas mehr abwärts gebogen, und es bilden die Mittelrippen mit dem Horizont einen Winkel von etwas mehr als 45°.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Die Blättchen von Oxalis sepium und diejenigen von Schizolobium sind sensitiv, obwohl in geringem Grade; bei Oxalis biegen sie sich, wenn sie gestossen werden oder wenn die Pflanze geschüttelt wird, ein wenig abwärts. Wenn bei Schizolobium ein einzelnes Blättchen wiederholt mit dem Finger geschlagen wird, so bewegt es sich sehr langsam gegen die Spitze des Blattstieles und dreht sich gleichzeitig ein wenig. …</p>
<p>Ich habe jetzt die Hymenopteren-Bewohner von 9 verschiedenen Feigenarten gesammelt; unter den Insecten, welche in den Feigen eines einzigen Baumes gesammelt wurden, hat Dr. Paul Mayer nicht weniger als 7 verschiedene Arten unterschieden, und dazu sind die Männchen einer dieser Arten dimorph oder sogar trimorph. Wie ich von Mayer höre, wird die Abhandlung über Caprification wahrscheinlich nächsten Herbst erscheinen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Glauben Sie, werther Herr, dass ich mit der grössten Hochachtung treulichts der Ihrige bin | Fritz Müller.</p>
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
                       
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Blumenau, Sa. Catharina, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>31 May 1881.</date>
                    <salute>Esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Your kind letter of 12 April has just arrived and I will reply to your query about Heteranthera reniformis right away.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is an amphibious plant that grows equally well in the stagnant water of swamps and ditches and outside the water in humid locations. …</p>
<p>Whereas over many weeks I daily observed in a plant of Phyllanthus that the leaves on one or several branches had turned the wrong way when returning from the nocturnal position, I was unable to find a second example of this irregularity among hundreds of plants of the same species that I have since investigated in this regard. Only once a few days ago on a cold morning I saw 3 leaves that had returned to the right side but without turning over, so that their underside was facing upwards. On the subsequent days they showed the normal position. From the plant with the abnormal leaf movements I collected a number of seeds; perhaps some of its descendants will inherit that irregularity.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Concerning the movement of the leaves in Cassia, Desmodium and a few other plants that you elaborate on, if one shakes or taps them, I believe that your supposition is correct, that it happens in order to throw off raindrops.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Today it has been raining for more than 5 hours already, and I have just walked through my garden in order to see what position the leaves of Cassia etc. have assumed. The Cassia leaves are in a position midway between the diurnal and the nocturnal position; the surface of the leaflets lies in a vertical plane, perpendicular to the leaf stalk (and thus both leaflets of each pair lie on the same plane); the upper surfaces are turned towards the tip of the leaf stalk; at the same time the leaflets are bent downwards, so that the two mid-ribs of each pair form roughly a right angle. During very heavy downpour the leaves of this Cassia assume their nocturnal position.— The leaves of an Acacia are in a very similar position to the nocturnal one.— The leaves of Schizolobium (doubly pinnate, like those of Acacia, but very large), have hardly altered their diurnal position, while during very heavy rain they assume a position quite similar to that of the leaves of Cassia at night.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The leaves of two species of Desmodium have assumed their nocturnal position, while those of a third species have kept the diurnal position. The leaflets of Oxalis sepium are hanging down vertically, as they commonly do at night (but not without exception). The leaves of Phyllanthus compressus have not moved; in Ph. consanguineus the leaf surfaces stand in an almost vertical plane, bent downwards a little, and the mid-ribs form an angle of around 30<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> with the horizon; in a third species of Phyllathus with very atypical nyctitropic movement, the leaves have nonetheless assumed a rain position quite similar to the preceding; only they are tilted even somewhat further downwards, and the mid-ribs form an angle with the horizon of just over 45°.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>The leaflets of Oxalis sepium and those of Schizolobium are sensitive, though to a minor degree; in Oxalis they bend down slightly when prodded or when the plant is shaken. When a single leaflet of Schizolobium is repeatedly tapped with a finger, it moves very slowly towards the tip of the leaf stalk and at the same time turns a little. …</p>
<p>I have now collected the Hymenoptera-inhabitants of 9 different species of fig; among the insects that have been collected from the figs of a single tree Dr Paul Mayer has distinguished no less than 7 different species, and in addition the males of one of these species are dimorphic or even trimorphic. As I hear from Mayer, the treatise on caprification will probably appear next autumn.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Believe me, dear Sir, that I remain with the greatest respect Yours truly | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I. According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref>, all <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>). Möller also found final drafts of some Müller letters among the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> papers and included these in their original English form (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 2: 72 n). Where the original English versions are missing, the published version, usually appearing in German translation, has been used.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of the original German of the published source of this letter, see Transcript. According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref>, all <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (Möller ed. 1915–21). Möller also found final drafts of some Müller letters among the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> papers and included these in their original English form (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 2: 72 n). Where the original English versions are missing, the published version, usually appearing in German translation, has been used.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13113.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 12 April 1881</ref> and n. 5. CD had received seeds of <hi rend="italic">Heteranthera reniformis</hi> (kidneyleaf mudplantain) from Müller.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had suggested that Müller make further observations on the movement of leaves of <hi rend="italic">Phyllanthus</hi> (the genus of leaf flower; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13064.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 23 February 1881</ref> and n. 2). A short article with a figure of the atypical leaf movement of the plant in Müller’s garden was published in the April issue of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11328.xml">F. Müller 1881b</ref>; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13117.xml">letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 14 April [1881]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13113.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 12 April 1881</ref> and n. 7. <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi> are genera in the family Fabaceae (peas and legumes).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Acacia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Schizolobium</hi> (Brazilian firetree) are genera in the family Fabaceae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Oxalis sepium</hi> is a tropical species in the family Oxalidaceae. <hi rend="italic">Phyllanthus compressus</hi> has a native range from Mexico to Peru, while <hi rend="italic">P. consanguineus</hi> is native to Réunion.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Caprification is the process of hanging clusters of wild fig (caprifig) flowers in edible fig trees in order to facilitate the transfer of pollen by fig wasps. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3242.xml">Paul Mayer</ref> reported on the specimens in alcohol sent by Müller in his paper ‘Zur Naturgeschichte der Feigeninsecten’ (On the natural history of fig insects; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11313.xml">Mayer 1882</ref>, pp. 572–6); the paper was published in September 1882. Müller summarised <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11313.xml">Mayer 1882</ref> in a review in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>, January 1883 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11314.xml">F. Müller 1883</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>