<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11849">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. F. Batalin<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   29 January 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9321</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11849 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11849.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11849.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp † (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 209.14: 178</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>209.14: 178</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_7258.xml">Batalin, A. F.</persName>
                <placeName>St Petersburg</placeName>
                <date when="1879-01-29">29 Jan 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for CD’s interest in his paper on plant movements ["Über die Ursachen der periodischer Bewegungen der Blumen und Laubblätter", <hi rend="italic">Flora</hi> 56 (1873): 433–41, 449–55]. AFB concentrated on clear cases, though he knows there are others.</p>  
<p>Experiments on function of movement: <hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi> leaves, held so they cannot move, die.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Mimosa</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Flora</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Batalin, A. F. 1873</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">death</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-11">Facsimile information added by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-02-13">Link to Batalin nreg updated by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2017-05-25" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-15" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-01" status="editorResponseCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-05-24" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-24" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
    <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00387_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00387_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="178ar">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00387.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00387_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00387.dzi" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="178av">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00388.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00388_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00388.dzi" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="178br">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00389.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00389_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00389.dzi" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="178bv">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00390.jpg" rend="portrait" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00390_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00390.dzi" width="5625px" height="8618px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>St Petersburg,</placeName>
                    <date>Januar 29. 1879.</date>
                    <salute>Sehr geehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Zuerst erlaube ich mir Sie zu danken für die Acht, welche Sie für meine Arbeit über die Bewegungen der Blätter erwiesen haben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Was die Bewegungen der Blätter von Impatiens parviflora, Imp. noli tangere, Polygonum aviculare und Sida Napaea betrifft, so kann ich darüber folgendes sagen. Bei Impatiens-Arten sinken sich die Blätter nachts fast vertikal abwärts, so dass sie beinahe 90° machen. Die Blätter von Polygonum aviculare (und nicht P. Convolvulus, wie Sie schreiben) machen auch sehr große Bewegungen, beinahe 70° (aufwärts); die von Sida Napaea—bedeutend weniger, aber wie viel—kann ich mich nicht erinnern.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Wenn ich meine Untersuchung über die Bewegungen der Blätter schrieb, so wählte ich als Beispiele nur solche Pflanzen, bei welchen die Bewegungen sich deutlicher erwiesen haben,—um die Missverständniße zu verminden, da meine im Aufsatze gegebene Erklärung der Erscheinung überhaupt ganz neu war; ich denke, daß ich der erste auf das Existenz derartigen Bewegungen bei den Laubblättern hingewiesen habe. Deswegen erwähnte ich nicht über die Fälle der unbedeutenden Bewegung, aber ich erinnere mich ganz bestimmt, daß solche Fälle nicht zu selten waren,— aber bei welchen Arten habe ich sie beobachtet—dass habe ich leider vergessen.</p>
<p>Über das Vorhandensein der Kissen bei Sida-Arten kann ich Ihnen folgendes mittheilen. So viel ich mich erinnern kann, besitzt Sida Napaea kein solches, welches vom bloßen Auge deutlich sichtbar ist; möglicherweise ist auch bei dieser Art die Krümmungsstelle des Blattstieles von kleinzelligem Gewebe gebaut, wie Sie es bei Sida coronifolia gefunden haben,—aber ein deutliches Kissen existirt bei S. Napaea nicht.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Nachdem ich Ihres Schreiben bekommen habe, suchte ich in Gewächshäusern des hiesigen botanischen Gartens frische Blätter von Sida Napaea und leider nicht gefunden, so dass ich nicht im Stande bin bestimmt zu sagen, existirt oder nicht ein solches kleinzelliges Gewebe auch bei Sida Napaea. Ich habe im reichen Herbarium des botan. Gartens alle Sida-Arten durchgesehen und gefunden, dass bei einigen Arten ein deutliches Kissen vorhanden ist, bei anderen—kaum erkennbar, und bei noch anderen—existirt gar kein; zu der letzten Kategorie gehört Sida Napaea. Das Vorhandensein und Nichtexistenz des Kissens ist an trockenen Blättern noch zu erkennen.</p>
<p>Im vorigen Sommer habe ich einige Versuche gemacht um die Frage zu lösen: was für Vortheile Mimosa und ähnliche Pflanzen durch die Bewegungen ihrer Blätter erwerben—und kam zu wenigen Resultaten.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Es ist nur zu erwähnen, daß die Blättchen (kleine Lamina) bei Mimosa bald sich entfärben und zu Grunde gehen, wenn die <hi rend="underline">Blättchen</hi>, ohne sie zu schädigen, so festgehalten sind, daß sie ihre Bewegungen nicht ausfüllen können. Was ist die Ursache dieser Erscheinung—weis ich nicht.</p>
<p>Zuletzt bitte ich Sie um die Entschuldigung, daß ich Ihnen deutsch antworte. Im englischen Schreiben bin ich nicht ganz fest.</p>
<p>Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung | bleibt | Ihr ganz ergebener | A Batalin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>St Petersburg,</placeName>
                    <date>January 29. 1879.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Let me first of all thank you for the attention you gave to my work on the movements of leaves.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Regarding the movements of the leaves of Impatiens passiflora, Imp. noli tangere, Polygonum aviculare and Sida Napaea, I can tell you the following: in Impatiens-species, the leaves drop downwards almost vertically at night, forming an angle of almost 90°. The leaves of Polygonum aviculare (not P. convolvulus as you write) also make considerable movements, almost 70° (upwards); those of Sida Napaea— significantly less, but how much—I cannot recall.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>When I wrote my study on the movements of plants, I chose for my examples only those plants in which movements have clearly manifested themselves,—in order to avoid misunderstandings, for the account of this phenomenon in my paper was wholly new; I think that I was the first to point to the existence of such movements in leaves. For this reason I said nothing about the cases of negligible movement, but I recall for certain that such cases were not rare,— however, in which species I observed them—that I have unfortunately forgotten.</p>
<p>Regarding the existence of pulvini in species of Sida I can tell you the following. As far as I can recall, Sida Napaea does not have one that is clearly visible to the naked eye. It is also possible that in this species the point of curvature in the leaf stalk consists of an aggregate of small cells, like the one you discovered in Sida coronifolia—but a definite cushion cannot be found in S. Napaea.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> After I received your letter, I went to look for fresh leaves of Sida Napaea in the greenhouses of the botanical gardens here but unfortunately I found none, and so I am unable to tell you definitely whether or not such an aggregate of small cells exists also in Sida Napaea. In the plentiful herbarium of the botan. garden I checked through all the Sida species and found that in a few species there is a definite pulvinus, in others—it can barely be made out, and in others again—there is none at all; Sida Napaea belongs in the last category. Whether there are or aren’t any cushions can be determined even from dry leaves.</p>
<p>Last summer I undertook a number of experiments to answer the question of what advantages Mimosa and similar plants derive from the movements of their leaves—but with few results.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> All that can be said is that the leaflets (small lamina) in Mimosa soon lose their colour and perish, if the <hi rend="underline">leaflets</hi>, without being damaged, are restrained in such a manner that they cannot carry out their movements. About the cause of this phenomenon I know nothing.</p>
<p>Lastly I beg you to excuse me for replying in German. My written English is not quite reliable.</p>
<p>With highest respect | I remain | wholly devoted | A Batalin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter to Batalin about his paper, ‘Ueber die Ursachen der periodischen Bewegungen der Blumen- und Laubblätter’ (On the causes of the periodic movements of petals and leaves; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_426.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Batalin 1873</ref>) has not been found. CD’s annotated copy of the paper, with a separate sheet of notes, is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL; CD cited it in <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, pp. 113, 229, 283, 321–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Impatiens parviflora</hi> is smallflower touch-me-not; <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> is western touch-me-not. <hi rend="italic">Polygonum aviculare</hi> is prostrate knotweed; CD cited Batalin for information on this plant in <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, p. 387. <hi rend="italic">Polygonum convolvulus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Fallopia convolvulus</hi> (black bindweed). <hi rend="italic">Sida napaea</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Napaea dioica</hi>, glade mallow; CD cited Batalin for information on the plant in <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, pp. 321–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD cited Batalin on the absence of a pulvinus (a cushion or joint-like swelling at the base of some leaf-stalks) in <hi rend="italic">Sida napaea</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, p. 322. <hi rend="italic">Sida coronifolia</hi>, a name otherwise not found, may have been <hi rend="italic">S. rhombifolia</hi> (arrowleaf sida; see <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, pp. 322–3; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11950.xml">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 24 March 1879</ref>). There is note on the pulvinus of a <hi rend="italic">Sida</hi> in DAR 209.14: 123, in amongst notes, some of which are dated 1878, on what is presumably the same plant, referred to as <hi rend="italic">S. coronifolia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">S. corylifolia</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">S. subcordata</hi>) or <hi rend="italic">S. cordifolia</hi> (great-leaved sida), and finally as <hi rend="italic">S. rhombifolia</hi> (arrowleaf sida) (DAR 209.14: 114–25).</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi> is the genus of sensitive plants; CD worked on the movement of leaves in this genus (<hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>