<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12995">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From James Torbitt   8 January 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14634</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12995 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12995.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12995.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 172</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 172</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4777.xml">Torbitt, James</persName>
                <placeName>Belfast</placeName>
                <date when="1881-01-08">8 Jan 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Report on the progress of his experiments with potatoes; some varieties spoilt by an apparently hereditary disease.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">potatoes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">degeneration</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-08-13" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-06" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-12-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00791_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00791_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="172:1r" xml:id="i791">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00791.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00791_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00791.dzi" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="172:1v" xml:id="i792">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00792.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00792_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00792.dzi" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="172:2r" xml:id="i793">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00793.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00793_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00793.dzi" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="172:2v" xml:id="i794">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00794.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00794_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00178-000-00794.dzi" width="5511px" height="9183px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>58 North Street Belfast</placeName>
                    <date>8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Jany. 1881</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Charles Darwin Esq’r | Down.</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have been unwell for some time and have had very little energy, but I have not neglected the work in hand: on the contrary, in view of your great interest in it, and also that of the subscribers, and of my own, I have last season grown 7,000 new varieties of the plant in place of the usual 5,000.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>They are thrice crossed, and many hundreds of them are sound, and appear to be valuable, and of these I shall send you a specimen tomorrow.</p>
<p>Some of the previous year’s varieties (seedlings of 1880) were also thrice crossed and some few hundreds of them also are sound, and seem to be valuable, and of these I shall send specimen also.</p>
                    <p>And this brings me to the varieties (seedlings of 1880) which I sent you last spring in small paper bags:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> such of these as were round red or round white (and they were almost all so) were all of one particular cross (a second cross) which divided itself into varieties of three types—one nondescript and valueless, one round red, and the other round white as above described. And the selected varieties of the last two types, and of which yours were part, were all of most vigorous growth, each seed producing a plant having numerous tall strong stems, broad dark green leaves, and a large crop of sound tubers: they were apparently the best I had ever grown, and as such I sent them to you. Of this cross, I planted many hundred varieties last spring, in fact a whole acre full, and excepting 37, all these varieties produced plants, having only one, two, or three, small feeble stems, with yellowish green, small curled up leaves, and no tubers of any value—in one year the seemingly best varieties became utterly worthless, and unluckily I sent some of them to you and to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farrer and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Caird as specimens of my work.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The cause of the change I believe to be this—some three or four years ago I sent you a few tubers of a variety, some tubers of which produced most vigorous plants, having broad dark green leaves and an immense yield of both fruit and tubers, while other tubers produced plants having narrow pale green leaves, a much smaller yield of smaller tubers, and no fruit at all; and the tubers which produced the bad plants, were to my eye indistinguishable from the tubers which produced the good plants, and you Sir, after having grown this variety wrote to me that it “seemed to be affected by some constitutional malady”.</p>
<p>Now I, having for the moment forgotten all about hereditary disease—I crossed some plants of this variety, and the specimens which I sent you, and the acre which I planted, are results of that cross: it seems to me to be disease in the variety, transmitted by seminal reproduction, and should you believe the matter to be worth your attention I shall be happy to send you one tuber (or the whole) of each of the 37 varieties of this cross which remain healthy, and I propose myself to plant some of each of them in order to see how they turn out.</p>
<p>The tubers in the small linen bag which I sent you last spring were each of a different, twice crossed variety, and from what I have seen, I hardly think any of them were of any value. I am pleased only with the thrice crossed varieties of ’80 and ’81, and curiously, with some 5 uncrossed varieties of 1875.</p>
<p>A large agriculturist (as well as a considerable landowner) says he has obtained, last season, at the rate of 16 tons per acre, off unreclaimed Irish bog land, the government valuation of which is less than one shilling per acre: this is a variety of of 1875 uncrossed, and I send a sackful of a ’75 variety of the same type as specimen of quality, it is stored on a loft, and exposed to the air more than it should be, but is still good.</p>
                    <p>I am about to try this government for assistance, in accordance with the resolution they have carried in the House of Commons, and shall lose no time in letting you know the result (witholding your name in the first instance, as instructed.)<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>There is no disease here this year, of importance, either in mine or the common varieties, excepting in certain early ones which are always diseased and expected to be diseased.</p>
<p>I have made only a few crosses last season which are fourth crosses but in them, like all the others, I have used pollen gathered promiscuously and no doubt specific breeding should be resorted to.</p>
<p>Trade seems at last to be coming a little better, and I have good hope that in a few months I shall be able to return the subscribers money and with most sincere thanks.</p>
<p>With apologies for the awful length of this letter and with best good wishes I am | My dear Sir | most respectfully &amp; faithfully yours | James Torbitt</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
         
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had informed Torbitt that £90 was available from subscribers for his potato experiments (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12966.xml">letter to James Torbitt, [5] January 1881</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Torbitt occasionally sent CD seedlings and tubers of his more successful potato varieties (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12020.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 30 April 1879</ref>); no details about  potatoes sent in the spring of 1880 have been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_788.xml">James Caird</ref> had helped to raise the subscription for Torbitt’s experiments (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12395.xml">letter from T. H. Farrer, 2 January [1881]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12974.xml">letter from James Caird, 3 January 1881</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">A select committee had reported to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7863.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">House of Commons</ref> in July 1880 on the best means of reducing failures in the potato crop; it recommended Government support for experiments to breed new potato varieties (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11316.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report from the Select Committee on Potato Crop</hi></ref>). Torbitt had sent CD copies of his letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1883.xml">William Ewart Gladstone</ref>, requesting government assistance (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12915.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 15 December 1880</ref>). CD had asked Torbitt not to mention that he had helped raise money for the potato experiments (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to James Torbitt, 16 June 1880</ref>).</note>
           
            
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>