<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11977">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Reginald Darwin   4 April 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19882</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11977 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11977.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11977.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 153: 97</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>153: 97</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1879-04-04">4 Apr 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1236.xml">Darwin, Reginald</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has been "deeply interested by the great book" [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">11966</hi>]. Asks permission to publish extracts.</p> 
            <p>Did Dr Darwin go to Edinburgh when his son, Charles, died? Asks whether RD has ever heard a story about Dr Darwin that had been told to CD by the Galtons.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1210">Darwin, Charles</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Darwin, Erasmus’s son</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Edinburgh</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-11" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-03" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-07" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-02" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by Liz Smith. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2018-08-02" status="copyedited">Copyedited by Samantha Evans. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down,</placeName>
                    <date>April 4, 1879.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Cousin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have been deeply interested by the great book which you have so kindly lent me.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Reading and looking at it is like having communication with the dead. I will venture to keep the book for a week or 10 days longer, as my son George is greatly interested about all old things and will return it in a few days from Algiers.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The book has taught me a good deal about the occupations and tastes of our grandfather. I have copied out the address to an atheist,—the hymn,—part of a letter about a case of infanticide,—the agreement with Bolton which I suppose was a joke,—professional income at Lichfield and some doggrel verses about a hare hunt. I cannot tell at present what I shall like to insert in my preliminary notice; but if at the time it seems desirable should you object to my using any of the above specified extracts? I fear it would be too absurd to use the doggrel verses, which bring in Erasmus when 9 years old.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have two questions to ask:–</p>
                    <p>The Galtons have told me a curious story about a jockey coming to our grandfather at night in Newmarket, did you ever hear Sir Francis tell this story?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Our grandfather was certainly on the road to Margate and I cannot make out why he should have passed through Newmarket; can you throw any light on this?</p>
                    <p>I suppose you do not know whether our Grandfather went to Edinburgh when Charles died there: I ask because late in life he sent to my Father a cypher woven out grass collected on Charles’ tomb; and I want to know whether he gathered the grass himself.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Many thanks for your offer of a photograph of the house in Full St.; but I think it would be sufficient to give the two drawings before alluded to.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have a rough drawing of the Priory copied by Mrs Bort from a lithograph by Miss V. Darwin; and if I could borrow this lithograph, it could be reduced and engraved and would do very well.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have been much amused by many of the scraps at the end of the book which you depreciate: I was once at Sydnop and this makes me feel all the more interest about the place.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>With many thanks. | Yours affectionately | Charles Darwin</p>
                    <p>P.S. What a curious story that is about the Cotton M.S. I will get George to go to the Br. Mus. and try to discover the entry.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> Commonplace book (Down House MS; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11966.xml">letter to Reginald Darwin, 1 April 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The copyist probably made a slip and wrote ‘return it’ rather than just ‘return’; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> arrived back from Algiers, where he had been since late January, before 17 April, when he left Down for Cambridge (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD included all these items in the first version of his sketch of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> life; three copies of these first proofs exist in DAR 210.11: 45–7, and this version is reproduced in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10753.xml">King-Hele ed. 2003</ref>. However, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Litchfield</ref> edited this version before publication, and only the extracts from Erasmus’s ode on the folly of atheism, his letter about infanticide, the humorous agreement with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8434.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Matthew Boulton</ref>, and the records of his income from his medical practice in Lichfield, appeared in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 25–6, 28–9, 43–4, and 121.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The story of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> being woken at night in a Newmarket hotel to be given a betting tip by a jockey whose seriously ill mother had been treated kindly by Erasmus was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 63–4. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5088.xml">Elizabeth Anne Wheler</ref>, a sister of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1797.xml">Francis Galton</ref>, first told CD the story in her <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11953.xml">letter of 25 March 1879</ref>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1221.xml">Francis Sacheverel Darwin</ref> was Reginald’s father.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> did travel to Edinburgh and reached the city before his eldest son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1210.xml">Charles Darwin</ref>, died (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 83; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4364.xml">King-Hele ed. 1981</ref>, p. 87). It was probably his second son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8435.xml">Erasmus</ref>, who collected the grass from Charles’s tomb to make a plaited cross; it was found in his possession at the time of his death in 1799, and given to CD’s father, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin</ref>, in April 1802 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 76; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4364.xml">King-Hele ed. 1981</ref>, p. 89).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11968.xml">letter from Reginald Darwin, 2 April 1879</ref>. In the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11966.xml">letter to Reginald Darwin, 1 April 1879</ref>, CD had mentioned that he thought he would include woodcuts of Elston Hall and Breadsall Priory (the birth and death places of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>) in his biographical account.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The lithograph was made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1242.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Violetta Harriot Darwin</ref>. The copy was made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8689.xml">Ann Boott</ref> (née Haden), who, before her marriage, was a neighbour of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> in Full Street, Derby. The copyist wrote ‘?Boot’ in the margin opposite the mention of ‘Mrs Bort’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Sydnope Hall near Matlock, Derbyshire, was purchased by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1221.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Sacheverel Darwin</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1236.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reginald Darwin’s</ref> father, in the 1820s, and sold after his death in 1858 (‘Sydnope Hall’, Historic England, https://historicengland.org.uk/listing/the-list/list-entry/1001273 (accessed 9 August 2017)).  CD had visited Sydnope with his cousin <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Darwin Fox</ref> when they were Cambridge undergraduates (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2208.xml">letter to W. D. Fox, 31 January [1858]</ref> and n. 9). Among the newspaper clippings stuck in the back of the Commonplace book by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1236.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reginald Darwin</ref>, there are two taken from the <hi rend="italic">Derby Mercury</hi> of 25 March and 8 April 1874, describing <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1221.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Sacheverel Darwin’s</ref> life at Sydnope Hall and the hunt he organised in 1837 to kill the last wild boar of his herd. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1236.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reginald Darwin</ref> felt that he had ‘desecrated’ <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> Commonplace book by pasting in later newspaper cuttings (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11960.xml">letter from Reginald Darwin, 29 March 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">At the beginning of the proofs of the first version of the preliminary notice of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, CD mentioned in a footnote that a rare book on the history of Lichfield, found by a Mr Darwin in the thatch of a house and presented to the antiquary <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5452.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Bruce Cotton</ref> (according to an inscription by Cotton), was in the Cotton collection in the British Museum (DAR 210.11: 45–7; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10753.xml">King-Hele ed. 2003</ref>, p. 7). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> visited the British Museum to transcribe Cotton’s inscription (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10753.xml">King-Hele ed. 2003</ref>, p. 100). In DAR 210.11: 45, the sections to be omitted are marked in red crayon, but the footnote about Cotton’s book and the paragraph to which it refers has not been marked; evidently CD decided to leave them out later.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>