<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6452">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   9 November 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5287</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6452 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6452.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6452.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) damaged</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 50</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 50</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1868-11-09">9 Nov 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for comments [on <hi rend="italic">Entstehung des Menschengeschlechts</hi>].</p> 
            <p>Comments on Goethe and Kant as early evolutionists.</p>
            <p>Describes birth of his son. Mentions child’s "atavisms".</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Entstehung des Menschengeschlechts</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1904">Goethe, J. W. von</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A.’s son</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2641">Kant, Immanuel</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>9 Nov. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Theurer, hochverehrter Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>So eben erhalte ich Ihrern freundlichen Brief vom 7. Nov. und will ihn sogleich beantworten, um Ihnen für die Freude zu danken, welche Sie mir damit gemacht haben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Es kann für meine Arbeiten keinen besseren Lohn geben, als wenn dieselben Ihren Beifall haben, und so hat es mich sehr gefreut, dass Sie mit meiner kleiner Arbeit über den Stammbaum der Menschen zufrieden sind.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Es würde mich sehr glücklich machen, wenn auch die “Schöpfungsgeschichte” Ihnen gefallen würde.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In dem historischen Theil ist Ihnen vielleicht von Interesse, was <hi rend="underline">Goethe</hi> über die beiden Bildungstriebe (<hi rend="underline">Anpassung</hi>=Umbilding der Metamorphose) (<hi rend="underline">Vererbung</hi>=Specificationstrieb, p. 75) und <hi rend="underline">Kant</hi> über die Dessendenz theorie (p. 83) gesagt haben, beide schon 1790!--<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Ich habe schon längst Ihnen schreiben wollen, bin aber immer durch die wichtigen Veränderungen abgehalten und in Anspruch genommen worden, welche in dem letzten Vierteljahre in meiner Familie sich ereignet haben. Am 29<hi rend="underline">sten</hi> Sept. ist mir nämlich ein kräftiger gesunder <hi rend="underline">Knabe</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/> geboren worden und ich empfinde zum ersten Male, wie gross die <hi rend="underline">Vaterfreuden</hi> sind. Sowohl meiner Frau<ref target="#foot.f7"/> als dem Kleinen geht es sehr gut. Sie können aber denken, dass ich jetzt wenig zum Arbeiten komme und um so mehr in meiner Familie lebe. Nach dem vielen Kummer und Schmerz, den ich seit 1864 durch den Tod meiner ersten unvergesslichen Frau<ref target="#foot.f8"/> hatte, ist mir diese Freude jetzt doppelt werthvoll und hat mich wieder mit neuer Kraft und Wärme an das Leben gebunden.</p>
<p>Sie können sich de〈nken〉 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 ich jetzt bin, ob die 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 sich an dem kleinem lieben Weltbürger recht bewähren werden. Vorläufig erinnert er mich durch die atavistischen Bewegungen, die er greifend mit der grossen Zehe der Füsschen macht, sehr an unsere “<hi rend="underline">quadrumanen</hi>” Vorfahren aus der Tertiärzeit. Im Übrigen zeigt er zu meiner grossen Freude keine pithekoiden Atavismen, und sieht im Gegentheil mit seinen grossen blauen Augen so verständig und klug in der Welt sich um, dass ich die beste Hoffnung habe, aus ihm einen recht tüchtigen Naturforscher und natürlich einen rechten “<hi rend="underline">Darwinisten</hi>” zu machen! Es ist doch wirklich eigen, wie durch die Geburt einer 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 alle Thätigkeit und all〈    〉 im Hause verändert wird 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 soweit ich sehe, dop〈pelt〉</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">1 line missing</hi>〉 es mir jetzt recht 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 Vorlesungen sind sehr 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 machen mir viel Freude. Meine Gesundheit, die durch die Arbeit des Sommers etwas angegriffen war, habe ich durch eine Reise in die Tyroler Alpen<ref target="#foot.f9"/> (im August) neu gestärkt. Dass ich jetzt nicht zu viel arbeite, dafür wird schon der kleine Knabe sorgen!</p>
<p>Meine Frau, welche über Ihren Brief sich mit mir freute, dankt Ihnen sehr für Ihren Gruss und verspricht, mich nicht zu viel arbeiten zu lassen.</p>
<p>Hoffentlich sind Sie mit Ihrer Gesundheit, von der Sie nicht schreiben, jetzt ganz zufrieden. Ihrer Frau 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 bitte ich, ebenso wie Ihrer 〈<hi rend="underline">2 or 3 words missing</hi>〉 meine ergebensten 〈<hi rend="underline"> <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> line missing</hi>〉</p>
<p>〈  〉tigsten Verehrung und | 〈    〉 wie immer, | 〈    〉 treuer | Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>9 Nov. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Dear, most esteemed friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have just received your kind letter of 7. Nov. and wanted to answer it immediately to thank you for the pleasure that it brought me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> There can be no better reward for my endeavours than for them to meet with your approval, and so I was delighted that you were pleased with my little work on the genealogy of man.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It would make me very happy if you also liked the “Schöpfungsgeschichte”.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In the historical part you might be interested in what <hi rend="underline">Goethe</hi> had to say about the two formative drives (<hi rend="underline">adaptation</hi>=the transformation of metamorphosis) (<hi rend="underline">heredity</hi>=propensity for specification, p. 75), and what Kant had to say about the theory of descent (p. 83), both as early as 1790!—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I have wanted to write to you for a long time but I have been constantly hindered and kept busy by the important changes that have taken place in my family in the last three months. On 29th Sept. a strong, healthy <hi rend="underline">boy</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/> was born to me and for the first time I feel how great the <hi rend="underline">joys of fatherhood</hi> are. Both my wife<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and the little one are doing very well. But you can imagine that I’m not getting much work done at present and that I spend more time with my family. After all the sorrow and pain that I have been through since 1864 as a result of the death of my first, unforgettable wife,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> this joy is doubly precious and has committed me to life with new strength and warmth.</p>
<p>You can imagine 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 I now am, whether the 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 will be confirmed with the dear little citizen of the world. For the moment he really reminds me of our “<hi rend="underline">quadrumane</hi>” ancestors of the tertiary period with the atavistic movements that he makes gripping with the big toe on his little feet. By the way, to my great joy, he shows no sign of pithecoid atavisms, but rather looks so knowledgeably and cleverly at the world with his big blue eyes that I have high hopes of making him into a really competent naturalist and of course a real “<hi rend="underline">Darwinist</hi>”! It is however truly singular how through the birth of a 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 all activity and all 〈    〉 in the house is changed 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 as far as I can see, doubles</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">1 line missing</hi>〉 is to me now quite 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉</p>
<p>lectures are very 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉 give me much joy. My</p>
<p>health, which was somewhat affected by the work last summer, has</p>
<p>been restored by a trip to the Tyrolian Alps<ref target="#foot.f9"/> (in August). The</p>
<p>presence of my little boy will now ensure that I do not work too much!</p>
<p>My wife, who enjoyed your letter with me, thanks you very much for the greetings and promises not to let me overwork.</p>
<p>Hopefully you are now content with your health, which you do not mention. I ask your wife 〈<hi rend="underline">1 or 2 words missing</hi>〉, also your 〈<hi rend="underline">2 or 3 words missing</hi>〉 my most humble 〈<hi rend="underline"> <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> line missing</hi>〉</p>
<p>〈    〉 respect and | 〈    〉 as ever, | 〈    〉 devoted | Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see part II: 837–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6450.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 7 November 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haeckel 1868b. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6450.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 7 November 1868</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel 1868c. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6450.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 7 November 1868</ref> and n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel referred to a poem written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref> in 1820, ‘Metamorphose der Thiere’, but did not refer to any other specific work by Goethe, in his discussion of Goethe’s concepts of adaptation and heredity (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Goethe 1988</ref>, pp. 498–500, 1089–91, and Haeckel 1868c, pp. 74–5). In Haeckel 1868c, pp. 82–4, Haeckel quoted a passage from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Immanuel Kant’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Critik der Urtheilskraft</hi> (Critique of the power of judgment, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4289.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kant 1790</ref>; for an English version of the quoted passage, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4291.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kant 2000</ref>, p. 287). For more on the developmental theories of Goethe and Kant, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4686.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lenoir 1984</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5819.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walter Haeckel</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Agnes Haeckel</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anna Haeckel</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The Tyrolian Alps are in western Austria, extending into southern Germany in the north and Italy in the south (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref> s.v. Tyrol).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>