<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10986">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. J. Romanes   6 June 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15509</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10986 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10986.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10986.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">encl ALS and AmemS 7pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">E. D. Romanes 1896, p. 53; DAR 47: 139–42</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">E. D. Romanes 1896, p. 53; DAR 47: 139–42</bibl>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>47: 139–42</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1877-06-06">6 June 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends MS notes on intercrossing.</p>
            <p>Describes different reactions of rabbits and guinea-pigs to stinging nettles.</p>
            <p>Has made a number of grafts at Kew.</p>
            <p>Encloses notes on natural selection; discussion of factors mitigating the swamping influence of intercrossing on incipient variations.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">guinea-pigs</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">nettles, stinging</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Kew</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">grafting</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>June 6, 1877.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very glad you sent me the extract from Lamarck, for I had just been to the R.S., hunting up several of the older authors to see whether any mention had been made of the theory before Spencer wrote.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>While at Down I forgot my speculations about inter-crossing, and, therefore, although I do not think they are much worth, I send you a copy of my notes.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The ideas are not clearly put—having been jotted down a few years ago merely to preserve them—but no doubt you will be able to understand them. Do not trouble to return the MS.</p>
<p>I had intended to ask you while at Down if you happen to know whether stinging nettles are endemic plants in South America.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The reason I should like to know is, that last year it occurred to me that the stinging property probably has reference to some widely distributed class of animals, and being told—rightly or wrongly, I do not know—that ruminants do not object to them, I tried whether my tame rabbits would eat freshly plucked nettles. I found they would not do so even when very hungry, but in the same out-house with the rabbits there were confined a number of guinea-pigs, and these always set upon the nettles with great avidity.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Their noses were tremendously stung, however, so that between every few nibbles they had to stop and scratch vigorously. After this process had been gone through several times, the guinea-pig would generally become furious, and thinking apparently that its pain must have had some more obvious cause than the nettles, would fall upon its nearest neighbour at the feast, when a guinea-pig fight would ensue. I have seldom seen a more amusing spectacle than twenty or thirty of these animals closely packed round a bunch of nettles, a third part or so eating with apparent relish, another third scratching their noses, and the remaining third fighting with one another. But what I want to ask you is this. Does it not seem that the marked difference in the behaviour of the rabbits and the guinea-pigs points to inherited experience on the part of the former which is absent in the case of the latter? If nettles are not endemic in South America, this inference would seem almost irresistible. Dr. Hooker<ref target="#foot.f5"/> tells me nettles grow there now, but he does not know whether they did so before America was visited by Europeans. Possibly there might be some way of ascertaining.</p>
<p>I have now made a number of grafts at Kew. In about a month, I should think, one could see which are coming up as single and which as double sprouts.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If, therefore, Frank is going to work in the laboratory in July,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> he might perhaps look over the bed (which is just outside the door), and reject the double-stalked specimens. I could trust him to do this better than any one at Kew, and if the useless specimens were rejected, there would afterwards be much less trouble in protecting the valuable ones. But do not suggest it unless you think it would be quite agreeable to him. If he is in town within the next fortnight, I wish he would look me up.</p> 
                </div>
                  
            </div>
<div type="enclosure" subtype="other">

    <div type="transcription">
    <p>Natural Selection of Organic Types</p>
    <p>The only serious difficulty which the theory of natural selection has yet encountered, is that which was originally raised &amp; admirably rendered by a writer in the <hi rend="underline">North British Review.</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/> This difficulty, as all who are in any degree acquainted with the literature of the subject must be well aware, is that of the swamping influence of intercrossing upon individual variations. Of course this difficulty could be removed if any cause could be suggested sufficient to account for numerous individuals varying in the same direction at the same time. A paragraph in <hi rend="underline">First Principles</hi>, although not originally written with any such purpose, seems in this way partly to remove the difficulty. (See pp. 444–447.) <ref target="#foot.f9"/> The substance of this paragraph is, that geological changes, by successively altering in a given area the conditions of life under which the organisms upon it exist, successively modify the character of these organisms in virtue of the <hi rend="underline">direct</hi> influence of the changes themselves, &amp; altogether apart from the <hi rend="underline">indirect</hi> influence of natural selection. Now, although I cannot agree with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Spencer when he says, “in the absence of these successive changes of conditions, ‘natural selection’ would effect comparatively little”;<ref target="#foot.f10"/> still I think that such successive changes might in some cases materially assist the influence of natural selection, by causing similar variations to arise in a number of individuals simultaneously.</p>
    <p>The question as to the relative importance of the direct action of the environment in calling forth responsive changes in the organism, &amp; the indirect action of survival of the fittest, is a question which the present generation can scarcely hope to see answered. I may observe, however, that to Darwinists in general the chief value of the passage above aluded to will be felt to consist in the increase which it affords to the sphere of natual selection’s agency. For, in whatever degree geological changes exert an influence of the direct kind, they must also increase, in a high proportional degree, the indirect influence of natural selection, by increasing at the same time the variability of the organisms &amp; the severity of the struggle for existance to which the organisms are exposed. Thus, remembering that increase of <hi rend="underline">area</hi> does not necessarilly belong to geological change, I believe that the principal effect of the latter in modifying species is probably that of intensifying the influence of natural selection, &amp; hence that the converse of the above-quoted sentence is most likely to be true, namely, that in the absence of natural selection, geological changes would effect comparatively little.</p>
    <p>Still, as it is manifestly desirable to seek for additional causes which may be supposed to mitigate the swamping influence of intercrossing upon incipient variations, I venture to suggest the following possibilities, which although of a purely speculative character, nevertheless to my mind appear entitled to rank as <hi rend="underline">à priori</hi> probabilities of no inconsiderable weight.</p>
        <p>For the sake of clearness, let us suppose that England and Scotland are slowly rising, that they are seperated from one another by a narrow strait, &amp; that each of the two resulting islands contains a peculiar variety of the same terrestrial species. Let us further suppose that of these two varieties the more northern one is the better fitted to survive; &amp; for the sake of allowing the smallest amount of strength to the influence of natural selection, &amp; so the greatest amount of strength to the swamping influence of intercrossing, let us lastly suppose that the superiority of the northern type over the southern one is of a kind which natural selection cannot effect at all when acting in the ordinary way—i.e. that the superiority of the <hi rend="underline">type</hi> is of such a kind that it confers no benefit upon the <hi rend="underline">individual</hi>. Now the question is, when the elevation of the British Islands proceeds sufficiently far to unite England with Scotland &amp; the two varieties are thus allowed to intermingle, is there any possibility of the superior variety supplanting the inferior? Of course at first sight it seems that the only answer open to us is an unequivocal negative; for the only probality seems to be that the two types would merely intermingle upon their common border-land, &amp; that in time they would undergo more or less of mutual diffusion. That is to say, survival of the fittest appearing to have no basis of operation supplied to it—the superiority of the northern <hi rend="underline">type</hi> being supposed to confer no benefit upon its constituent <hi rend="underline">individuals</hi>,—amalgamation of the two varieties by free intercrossing appears to be the sole possibility. And so it undoubtedly is, if we grant that survival of the fittest can only act on individuals. I believe, however, that survival of the fittest may possibly act in the interest of varieties, quite independently of benefit to individuals, or even in opposition to such benefit. To take the simplest case I can think of: great expenditure in reproduction is certainly of benefit to such species as exhibit this character, while it is no less certainly detrimental to their constituent individuals.</p> 
        <p>How then was the character acquired? There seems to be only one answer possible, viz. that throughout the life-history of the species, those individuals which produced most young had always the best chance of leaving offspring to inherit a peculiarity, which, although detrimental to themselves, was notwithstanding of benefit to their species. I say this is the simplest case I can think of; let us then apply it to our illustration, &amp; suppose that the advantage which the Scottish type has over the English one consists in its possessing a higher degree of fertility. Now, when the two types begin to emigrate into each other’s territory, it is manifest that the northern one would have more penetrating power, so to speak, than would the southern one; for the superiority of the former over the latter would assert itself in two ways at the same time: it would <hi rend="underline">prevent</hi> immigration of the English type, &amp; it would <hi rend="underline">assist</hi> emigration of the Scottish one; for whenever any representatives of the English type passed into Scotland &amp; there crossed with endemic type, the resulting progeny would not have so good a chance of perpetuating their mixed chararacters as would any of the other progenies around it have of perpetuating their pure character; while, contrariwise, whenever an individual of the Scottish breed crossed with English blood on English soil, the progeny would have the very best chance of perpetuating their hybrid type; &amp; so in all proportions of admixture. Hence, if we suppose the struggle for existence to be tolerably severe, it is quite conceivable that the diffusive power of the one variety over the other might be very considerable. But now, would not the Scottish type, after it had affected the English one over a comparatively narrow band of territory, become lost by intercrossing? Not necessarily. Imagine a band of country 50 miles wide, stretching across the North of England &amp; occupied by the offspring of the various intercrosses between English &amp; Scottish blood. Above the northern limit of this band—i.e., slightly north of the border-line between the two countries—the Scottish type is still quite pure; the diffusive power of the English one having been but slight. On the other hand, the further South we go from the border-line, the more diluted does the Scottish type become. What then should we expect to ensue? Surely that the Scottish type should penetrate still further into England. Each of the types is subject to a greater or less degree of pressure—each would multiply itself indefinitely if only supplied with a large enough area free from opposition,— Hence it seems but natural that the Scottish type should extend itself in the line of the least resistance—i.e. progressively creep over the 50-mile band of territory, in its advance both purifying the previously mixed breed, &amp; extending the latter further south. In this way I think there might be a continual gravitation of the one variety into the area previously occupied by the other—the rapidity of the process being determined by the intensity of the struggle for existence in relation to the intensity of what we may term the specific pressure. And that the line of least resistance in such a case would probably be well pronounced is evident, if we remember how keen the struggle for existence generally is between closely allied types.</p>
    <p>In this way I think that the Northern variety might either extirpate the Southern one altogether, or supplant it over a large portion of its territory. During this process, however, new variations would be arising in the Northern type, spread as it now is over a larger area, &amp; subject to numerous &amp; important changes in its conditions of life. Some of these variations would almost certainly be in the direction of increased fertility; &amp; if in any one part of the now greatly increased area occupied by the Northern type, a comparatively large number of individuals varied in this direction at the same time (in consequence of increased food or other local influence) so as to give rise to a local variety in this respect; then this local variety might serve as a new centre from which there might radiate a further modification of the entire specific type. And by a series of such processes taking place either successively or simultaneously, one species might sooner or later become transmuted into another; for, as survival of the fittest is in this case selecting large numbers of individuals collectively, specific characters might be changed by a comparatively small number of stages.</p>
        <p>How far this theory may seem probable at first sight, I do not know; but we must remember that, as a matter of fact, most species <hi rend="underline">do</hi> exhibit local varieties; that even slight geographical changes must frequently bring strongly pronounced varieties into collision; &amp; that in such cases numerous species might be thus undergoing transmutation at the same time. In some cases, too, a small amount of sterility (or in the case of the higher animals, of sexual aversion) between members of the two varieties, would greatly assist the process. Moreover, the example which for the sake of simplicity I have chosen—viz. fertility—is not in other respects a good one; for it depends so much upon the mere doctine of chances. If, however, natural selection ever operates in the way now suggested, it must do so most energetically when in association with the principle acting in the ordinary way; for then the two methods of action would mutually assist each other.</p>
    <p>G. J. Romanes</p> 
    
</div>
        </div>
        </div>
        
        
        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had sent an extract from Jean Baptiste Lamarck’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophie zoologique</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lamarck 1830</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10983.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. J. Romanes, 5 June 1877</ref> and n. 2). R.S.: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref>. In a lecture delivered at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7845.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Institution of Great Britain</ref> on 25 May 1877, Romanes had discussed <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer’s</ref> theory of the genesis of nerve-fibres from undifferentiated protoplasm ‘by a process of integration which is due simply to use’ (see G. J. Romanes 1877b, p. 232; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7369.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer 1864–7</ref>, 2: 372–5). For more on Romanes’s research on the formation of the nervous system in medusae, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11105.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. J. Romanes, 13 August 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Romanes had visited Down House on 30 May 1877 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). For the notes, see the enclosure. Another note on intercrossing by Romanes, undated and evidently not enclosed with this letter, is in DAR 47: 143–4. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Urtica dioica</hi> (stinging nettle or common nettle) is not native to South America, but has been naturalised there.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The guinea pig (<hi rend="italic">Cavia porcellus</hi>) originates from the Andean region of South America.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Romanes had been doing grafting experiments at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew to test CD’s hypothesis of pangenesis (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10524.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. J. Romanes, 1 June 1876</ref> and n. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> had been assisting CD with observations on dimorphic and trimorphic plants at Kew (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 25 January [1877]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In his review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2552.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Charles Fleeming Jenkin</ref> had argued that natural selection would be unable to operate on individual variations, because these would be lost through blending and swamped within a larger population (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Jenkin] 1867</ref>). For CD’s response to Jenkin, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 104–5, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, letters to A. R. Wallace, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6567.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 January [1869]</ref> and n. 7, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6591.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">2 February [1869]</ref>. For more on Jenkin’s review, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hull 1973</ref>, pp. 344–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Romanes refers to the second edition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">First principles</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7371.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer 1867</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7371.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer 1867</ref>, p. 447 n.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>