<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8546">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. T. Moggridge   6 October 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">18043</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8546 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8546.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8546.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 216</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 216</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3353.xml">Moggridge, J. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
                <date when="1872-10-06">6 Oct 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>He will send his book [<hi rend="italic">Harvesting ants and trap-door spiders</hi> (1873)]. Describes two new types of trap-door spider nests.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Harvesting ants and trap-door spiders</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Moggridge, J. T. 1873</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nesting and other home-making or web-making behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>2 Montague Villas | Richmond | (<hi rend="print">Surrey</hi>)</placeName>
                    <date>6 Oct. | 1872 </date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am now on the point of leaving England for Mentone (we start on Wednesday next), &amp; I am anxious before going to ask your permission to be allowed to send you a copy of a little book, which I have been engaged during the past summer in preparing, on the <hi rend="underline">Habits &amp; dwellings of the Harvesting Ants &amp; Trap-door spiders of the Riviera.</hi><ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>You were so good as to express some interest in my observations, reported to you in a letter last year, on these seed-carrying ants, which are, contrary to the general belief of naturalists, common objects in the south—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> If you will accept this little publication you will see that I have been able to collect several details as to the manner in which these creatures cut, carry &amp; store their harvest, their manner of life &amp; relations to other ants.</p>
<p>The true harvesting ants are, as far as I have yet seen, easily known by their habits; but there are other species of ant which, though clearly dependent in the main upon sweet secretions &amp; animal matter for their living, do occasionally collect a few seeds &amp; thus shew a trace of this instinct.</p>
<p>The great majority of species in the neighbourhood of Cannes &amp; Mentone are not collectors of seed, &amp;, indeed, there are but three species to which the name of harvester can properly apply—</p>
<p>These three species are however very common, &amp; two of them may frequently be seen by the road side or crossing the paths in long lines, &amp; are very familiar objects.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The trap-door spiders have been forced upon my attention by my attention by a friend, &amp; I am now most deeply interested in their structure &amp; habits—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Up to the present time only one type of nest has been described in Europe, namely that in which the cylindrical silk-lined tube is closed by a solid door composed of layers of earth &amp; silk &amp; which fits into the aperture of the tube much as a cork does into the neck of a bottle (<hi rend="underline">Fig.</hi> A).</p>
<p>To this type I am now able to add two others, &amp; these posess two doors, one at the surface of the ground &amp; one some inches below (Fig<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. B &amp; C.).</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>In these nests the surface door is always thin &amp; wafer-like &amp; merely serves to conceal the aperture of the tube upon which it is laid, while the lower door is solid &amp; capable of offering mechanical resistance.</p>
<p>I will not however trouble you with further details, as I hope to explain these fully in the book which should appear in the end of next month.—</p>
<p>I have drawn the plates &amp; nearly completed the MS., but am anxious to make a few additional observations at Mentone before going to print.</p>
<p>I am indebted to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pickard Cambridge for the names &amp; descriptions of the four species of Trap-door spider found on the Riviera, &amp; Prof. Ausserer has also been so good as to give his opinion as to their proper naming.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I greatly regret however that I have hitherto been unable to discover the males of any one of these spiders &amp; it would seem that they are either very scarce or exceptionally well concealed—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>This letter need not require an answer; at least if I do not receive one I shall take it for granted that I may send my book— | Believe me | Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. very sincerely | J. Traherne Moggridge.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Owing to chronic ill health, Moggridge spent most winters at Mentone (now Menton), a town on the French Riviera near the Italian border (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1994</ref>). CD’s annotated copy of <hi rend="italic">Harvesting ants and trap-door spiders</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1873</ref>) is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 589).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7788.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. T. Moggridge, [before 22] June 1871</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7830.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. T. Moggridge, 22 June [1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1873</ref>, pp. 15–16, Moggridge named the three harvester ant species, <hi rend="italic">Atta barbara</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Messor barbarus</hi>, the Mediterranean harvester ant), <hi rend="italic">A. structor</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Messor structor</hi>), and <hi rend="italic">Pheidole megacephala</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1873</ref>, p. 79 n., Moggridge wrote, ‘This priority [of new observations on the habits of trap-door spiders] belongs to the Hon. Mrs. Richard Boyle, to whom I owe it that I ever took up the subject.’ He refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7089.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eleanor Vere Boyle</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The species descriptions in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1873</ref>, pp. 89–90, 92–4, 101–3, and 108–11, were written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_796.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Octavius Pickard-Cambridge</ref>. Moggridge also included an appendix of species of Territelariae of Europe and the Mediterranean region identified by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5630.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anton Ausserer</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 143–4). The Territelariae spiders described in the appendix are now classified within the families Ctenizidae, Nemesiidae, Atypidae, Idiopidae, Hexathelidae, Barychelidae, and Theraphosidae within the suborder Orthognatha, mygalomorph spiders.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Moggridge later discovered the male of a species first identified by him, <hi rend="italic">Nemesia eleanora</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1873</ref>, pp. 109–10).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>