<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8214">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Anton Dohrn   15 February 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16335</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8214 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8214.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8214.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Groeben (1982): 38</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 208</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 208</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml">Dohrn, F. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Naples</placeName>
                <date when="1872-02-15">15 Feb 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>AD is sorry CD thinks publication of <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> a mistake. The excitement shows it was necessary for someone to speak plainly.</p> 
            <p>His great difficulties (Italian indolence, dishonesty, hatred) in establishing zoological station. Can at last start construction.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Italians</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative self-criticism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Naples zoological station</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Naples. Palazzo Torlonia.</placeName>
                    <date>15.2.1872.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>There must have been some benevolent spirit somewhere, who knew, that I should be very proud to get a letter from You, and who knew also, that You would be so kind as to write even on behalf of such an insignificant thing, as that article of mine in “Das Ausland.”<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I am innocent of troubling You with my wisdom on Your great theory, and would never have sent that third hand article myself. But since somebody else must have done it, I am exceedingly thankful, that You noticed it, and wrote me Your kind letter in reply.</p>
<p>I infer from Your silence on it, that Your health is at present not a bad one, and that You are going to give us some new book out of the immense store-house of Your experience and speculation, and though You will perhaps know it best Yourself, I believe, whatever You would publish, will give a signal to new fighting on the new and the old grounds.</p>
<p>I am sorry, You think the publication of the Descent of Man a mistake,— the excitement produced by it shows, how utterly necessary it was, that You spoke plainly on the matter of Man’s descent.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have been burying myself for longtime in the history of our great literary epoch from Lessing to the Romantic School, including all the greatest Genius, Germany perhaps produced for the past as well as for the future. And the greatest lucubrations of Lessing, Goethe, Kant, Beethoven<ref target="#foot.f3"/> were almost without exception received with little or no consent from the side of the critics and with great alarm from the public. The single individual is perhaps standing to near, to view the whole importance of such productions, by and by he gets better acquainted with it, and—the excitement passed,—he is more ready to acknowledge and to do justice. I wished Goethe was still alive, and had seen the Revolution, Your books have worked,— no greater satisfaction he could have felt than that.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I shall be very proud, if You will send me a copy of the next edition of the Origin with the addition of the Chapter on the Incipient Structures;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> it will always remind me of the great obligation, we all have against You.</p>
<p>If I may be allowed to speak of my things, I cannot say much about the progress of the Station,—only it <hi rend="underline">is</hi> to be done.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The difficulties in this country are something quite unheard of for all of us northern people. The indolence, dishonesty, hatred even against a good and disinterested enterprise, are quite regular qualities with this people, and it wants one’s last resources of nervous energy to overcome the physical hindrance and the moral disgust, it fills one with. I am now so far, that I can begin the construction, having happily wrought me out of all dishonest elements, which first clung to my affair.</p>
<p>I hope that I shall be able to give some more specialized information on the way I intend to build and to organize the Station in one or two other articles in “Nature”, where also some woodcuts will illustrate the whole.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I shall be very sorry to miss Professor Huxley on his return home.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> It is almost certain, that I am to pass March and April in Germany as well for finishing some observations on fish-Embryology as for the sake of the Station.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I hope his health will be fully restored by his journey,— I remember last time, when I stayed with him at St. Andrews I viewed his position quite so as it has turned out.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> And I believe, there are struggles for him in store, for which he will want all his energies to fight them through. Practical life is Scylla and Charybdis at once,—and he may easily meet stronger opponents than Miss Helen Taylor.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Ray Lankester, who is staying with me since October wishes to be remembered to You most kindly. He works at Cephalopoda and Sipunculus.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> With my best compliments to Mrs. Darwin and Your son,<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Believe me, my dear Sir | Yours most sincerely | Anton Dohrn</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Anton Dohrn, 3 February 1872</ref> and n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Anton Dohrn, 3 February 1872</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gotthold Ephraim Lessing</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Immanuel Kant</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6336.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig van Beethoven</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Many German researchers, and notably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref>, saw Goethe as a precursor to CD (see Haeckel 1868, pp. 59–79).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Anton Dohrn, 3 February 1872</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Building of the zoological station at Naples was delayed, but started in March 1872 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 114–20).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Dohrn’s article on the founding of the zoological station appeared in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 8 February and 4 April 1872 (Dohrn 1872a). A longer essay on the purpose of the station appeared in <hi rend="italic">Preussische Jahrbücher</hi> (Dohrn 1872b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> was returning from Egypt via Naples. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Anton Dohrn, 3 February 1872</ref> and n. 3. Huxley stayed at Dohrn’s house in Naples from 27 March 1872 until the beginning of April (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1979.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1994–7</ref>, 2: 34).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Dohrn spent March and April in Stettin (now Szczecin in Poland) and returned to Naples in May 1872 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 118–19).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Huxley had stayed in St Andrews, Scotland, in September 1871 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1979.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1994–7</ref>, 2: 24).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Dohrn alludes to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4669.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Helen Taylor’s</ref> article ‘The new attack on toleration’, which appeared in the December 1871 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly Review</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7633.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Taylor 1871</ref>); in it, Taylor criticised Huxley’s article ‘Administrative nihilism’ (T. H. Huxley 1871c) in the November 1871 issue of the same journal.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester</ref> studied development in the squid genus <hi rend="italic">Loligo</hi> (Cephalopoda), and the histology of <hi rend="italic">Sipunculus nudus</hi>, an unsegmented marine worm of the family Sipunculidae (see Lankester 1873).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Dohrn had visited CD on 26 September 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, p. 108). It is not known which of CD’s sons Dohrn met.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>