<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9991">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Anton Dohrn   24 May 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16349</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9991 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9991.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9991.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Groeben (1982): 63</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Bayerische Staatsbibliothek München (Ana 525. Ba 1122)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_36.xml">Bayerische Staatsbibliothek</repository>
                    <idno>(Ana 525. BA 1122)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1875-05-24">24 May 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml">Dohrn, F. A.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks AD for his <hi rend="italic">Ursprung</hi> [<hi rend="italic">der Wirbelthiere</hi> (1875)], which astonished CD. AD’s views, if accepted by competent authorities, will show how much we have to learn about the history of every animal. Suggests caution on "degradation principle". Comments on other views in the work. Has long seen importance of the principle of "Functionswechsel" [transfer [change!?] of function], but never enunciated it as a distinct principle.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Ursprung der Wirbelthiere</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Dohrn, F. A. 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">degeneration</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">exclamations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>May 24 | 1875</date>
                    <salute>My dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dohrn</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very much obliged for the present of your “Ursprung &amp;c”.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have read the whole, so far as my shameful ignorance of German has permitted me. It has interested me extremely, &amp; has astonished me not a little. Your views seem very ingenious, but I have not knowledge enough of comparative anatomy to form a judgment of any value. Should your views be even partially accepted by competent authorities, it will shew how much we have to learn about the history of every animal. May I venture to caution you not to extend too far the degradation principle.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Nothing has surprized me so much as your belief in the changed position of the mouth of vertebrates, &amp; of the œsophagus having aboriginally passed between the 2 main nerve-chords<ref target="#foot.f3"/>   I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be greatly pleased if your explanation of the development of our limbs from branchiæ is true, for I never dreamed of their origin being explained. I have for a long time seen the full importance of the principle of Function wechsel; though I never enunciated it as a distinct principle.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>With all good wishes | I remain my dear Sir | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>P.S | Please to give my thanks to Prof: Claus. for the present of his memoir on the “Arguliden”, which I hope to read immediately<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s lightly annotated copy of <hi rend="italic">Der Ursprung der Wirbelthiere und das Princip des Functionswechsels</hi> (The origin of vertebrates and the principle of change of function; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Dohrn identified homologies in the basic structure of annelids and vertebrates, from which he concluded that both had developed from a segmented ancestor. Dohrn refined his theory on the ancestry of vertebrates by proposing that similarities to vertebrates in both ascidians and <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus</hi> (the lancelet; now <hi rend="italic">Branchiostoma lanceolatum</hi>) were the result of degeneration from a vertebrate form (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>, pp. 32–60). For more on the controversy surrounding Dohrn’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5158.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maienschein 1994</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9845.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Anton Dohrn, 7 February 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>, pp. 7–9. Dohrn proposed that the original mouth (which in annelids is dorsal to the brain) was replaced in vertebrates by a new ventrally situated mouth, formed from the fusion of two gill slits (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>, pp. 13–15. Dohrn proposed, in accordance with his principle of <hi rend="italic">Functionswechsel</hi> (change of function), that posterior gills developed a secondary function of helping with movement, and that these eventually disappeared to leave only the gill arches, which would become ribs and later fins. Dohrn also devoted a section of his monograph to explaining <hi rend="italic">Functionwechsel</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 60–76), the principle that organs tended to possess secondary functions as well as a main function; these could develop over time, leading to a shift in the main function. He saw it as a counter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart’s</ref> objection in <hi rend="italic">Genesis of species</hi> that rudimentary organs would be functionless (Mivart 1871, p. 38; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>, p. 61).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD’s copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_955.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Friedrich Claus’s</ref> paper ‘Ueber die Entwickelung, Organisation und systematische Stellung der Arguliden’ (On the development, organisation, and systematic place of the Argulidae; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8651.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claus 1875</ref>) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Claus had been at Naples from 20 March until 14 April 1875 and had promised CD a copy of this paper (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9203.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from F. M. Balfour, [20 March – 14 April 1875]</ref>). Argulidae is the family of fish lice.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>