<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6512">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. D. Hooker   25 December [1868]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">4623</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6512 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6512.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6512.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 151: 200</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 375</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 94: 105–7</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>94: 105–7</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1868-12-25">25 Dec [1868]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Is working on new edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> [5th (1869)].</p> 
            <p>Asks JDH’s assistance on a problem posed by Nägeli on morphological differences that are of no utility to plants and hence could not be selected. CD wants to show that these differences do not support the idea of progressive development as Nägeli suggests.</p> 
<p>Owen pitches into CD and Lyell in third volume of <hi rend="italic">Anatomy of vertebrates</hi> [1866–8].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Anatomy of vertebrates</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3051">Lyell, Charles</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1342">Nageli, C. W. von</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Owen, Richard 1866–1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative self-criticism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down</placeName>
                    <date>Dec 25</date>
                    <salute>My dear Hooker</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Thanks for the interesting letter; I can however hardly believe that each Var. of the grasshopper has always been bred in its own district. What a pity she did not enclose under glass, living specimens on differently coloured surfaces.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I am very glad to hear that you are going on with y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> flora.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> W<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> it be worth while my looking through my M.S index of Gardener’s Chron. for any <hi rend="underline">little</hi> facts for you.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Now I want to beg for assistance for the new Ed. of Origin.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Nägeli justly urges that plants offer many morphological differences, which from being of no service cannot have been selected, &amp; which he accounts for by an innate principle of progressive development. I find old notes about this difficulty, but I have hitherto slurred it over.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Nägeli gives as instances the alternate &amp; spiral arrangement of leaves, &amp; the arrangement of the cells in the tissues.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> W<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> you not consider as a morpholog. difference the trimerous tetramerous &amp;c divisions of flowers,—the ovules being erect or suspended, their attachment being parietal or placental,—&amp; even the shape of the seed when of no service to the plant.</p>
<p>Now I have thought, &amp; want to show, that such differences follow in some unexplained manner from the growth or development of plants which have passed thro’ a long series of adaptive changes. Any how I want to shew that these differences do not support the idea of progressive development.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Cassini states that the ovaria on the circumference &amp; centre of Compos. flowers differ in essential characters, &amp; so do the seeds in sculpture.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> The seeds of umbelliferæ in the same relative positions are coelospermous &amp; orthospermous.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> There is a case given by Aug. S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Hilaire of an erect &amp; suspended ovule in the same ovarium, but perhaps this hardly bears on the point.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The summit flower in Adoxa &amp; rue differ from the lower flowers;<ref target="#foot.f12"/> What is difference in flowers of the Rue? how is the ovarium? especially in the rue? as Aug. S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Hilaire insists on the locularity of the ovarium varying on the same plant in some of the rutaceæ.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Such differences do not speak, as it seems to me, in favour of progressive Development.—Will you turn subject in your mind, &amp; tell me any sure facts.— Differences in structure in flowers in different parts of same plant, seem best to show that they are result of growth or position or amt of nutriment.—</p>
<p>I have got your Photograph over my chimney-piece &amp; like it much;<ref target="#foot.f14"/> but you look down so sharp on me that I shall never be bold enough to wriggle myself out of any contradiction—</p>
<p>Yours affect. | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Owen pitches into me &amp; Lyell in grand style in last chapt of vol. 3 of Anat. of Vertebrates.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> He is a cool hand— he puts words from me in inverted commas &amp; alters them.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">3.5 arrangement of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.9 What … Rue? 4.10] <hi rend="italic">added in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.12 Such…them.— 7.3] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">5.2 bold] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">5.2 to] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6550.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. D. Hooker, 13 January 1869</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to a paper by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_271.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Elizabeth Barber</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [23 December 1868]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [23 December 1868]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s manuscript index of <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> has not been found, but a later index, in the hand of an amanuensis, is in DAR 222. CD’s annotated copies of <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> are in the Cory Library, Cambridge Botanic Garden.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD started work on the fifth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> on 26 December 1868 (see ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Wilhelm von Nägeli’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Entstehung und Begriff der naturhistorischen Art</hi> (The origin and concept of natural historical species; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nägeli 1865</ref>) was about the mechanisms and principles operative in the development and transmutation of species. CD’s copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nägeli 1865</ref> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL is heavily annotated, and there is a partial manuscript translation, beginning on page 15, of the German text, along with a page of notes by CD, also in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nägeli 1865</ref>, pp. 28–30. Nägeli argued that while the function of leaves could be modified, their arrangement, which, he claimed, had no value in terms of ‘usefulness’, could not be altered. He also claimed that the arrangement of cells and organs in a plant was its most constant feature.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Nägeli had augmented what he termed the theory of ‘usefulness’ (‘Nützlichkeitstheorie’, that is, CD’s theory) with his own theory of perfectibility (‘Vervollkommnung’), which posited an inner tendency towards a more complex organisation. Nägeli then argued that CD’s theory could only operate on functional characteristics, while his own would account for most morphological features (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5780.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nägeli 1865</ref>, p. 29). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 6 January [1868]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_854.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Cassini</ref> made these observations in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1312.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cassini 1826–34</ref>, 1: 216–19.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Coelospermous: ‘Hollow-seeded; having the seed, or seed-like fruit, hemispherical, and excavated on the flat side, as in coriander’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). Orthospermous: ‘Of certain umbellifers: having carpels with the albumen flat on the inner face; (of a carpel) having the albumen distributed in this way’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Auguste de Saint-Hilaire</ref> noted the case in the genus <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus</hi> in Saint-Hilaire 1841, p. 548. CD’s annotated copy of the book is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 733–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Adoxa</hi> (moschatel) is characterised by inflorescences consisting of five flowers, one of which faces upwards while the other four are arranged facing outwards below it. CD also refers to <hi rend="italic">Ruta</hi> (rue). In common rue, <hi rend="italic">Ruta graveolens</hi>, the central flower of each cluster has five rather than four petals.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">For Saint-Hilaire’s remarks on locules of the ovarium, see Saint-Hilaire 1841, pp. 477, 481–7, and 550–8. No comment on some members of the family Rutaceae having varying numbers of locules on the ovaria of the same plant has been found. However, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 155–6, CD referred to Saint-Hilaire’s discussion of the ovaria of <hi rend="italic">Zanthoxylon</hi>, a member of the Rutaceae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD refers to a photograph of Hooker taken by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_798.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julia Margaret Cameron</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6321.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 17 [August 1868]</ref>). The photograph is at Down House. See plate facing p. 630.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, and the last part of <hi rend="italic">On the anatomy of vertebrates</hi> (Richard <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6113.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Owen 1866–8</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. H. Darwin, 8 December 1868</ref>, n. 6). For Owen’s criticism of Lyell, see Richard <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6113.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Owen 1866–8</ref>, 3: 801.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>