<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13122">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alexander Agassiz   16 April 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20236</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13122 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13122.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13122.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_39.xml">G. R. Agassiz ed. 1913</ref>, pp. 281–2</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Agassiz, G. R. 1913: 281</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_41.xml">Agassiz, Alexander</persName>
                <placeName>Tortugas</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-16">16 Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Is mapping coral distribution on the Tortugas reef. His observations on the Florida peninsula suggest that it was built up from the debris of animal remains and was not elevated.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Florida peninsula</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Tortugas reef</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">death</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-11" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-07" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="smallCaps">Tortugas</hi></placeName>
                    <date>April 16, 1881.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>It is very natural you should be in my mind, as I am in the midst of corals. I came down here about six weeks ago to study the surface fauna of the Gulf Stream. The Coast Survey placed a small launch at my disposal to go out and scour the surface when the weather is favorable. Unfortunately thus far I have had little chance to accomplish what I started to do, as I find is nearly always the case on the seashore— you never can do what you wish, but have to be satisfied with what turns up. Thus far I have only found the more common things with which I was familiar from my former Blake experience and from meeting them late in the fall at Newport.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>I took advantage of bad weather to finish up a lot of drawings and notes on Velella and Porpita, and have some interesting things about the post-embryonic stages of both, which I hope to publish next summer if I get time to finish the drawings.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The greater part of my time I spend in running round inside the reef in the launch and getting at the distribution of the different genera of corals. The number of species here is not great, so it makes their mapping out a simple matter. The Tortugas being the very last of the Florida reefs I find much that has not been noticed before and helps to explain, somewhat differently from what was done by Father, the formation of the reefs.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> On my way here I went across the northern base of the Peninsula of Florida—from Jacksonville to Cedar Keys, and found halfway across a series of hammocks and old coral reefs, such as are found in the Everglades at the southern extremity. In tracing the growth of the reefs and the formation of the Peninsula, I have come across no signs of any elevation. Everything, on the contrary, tends to show that the immense plateau which forms the base upon which the Peninsula of Florida is formed, was built up by the débris of animal remains,— Mollusks, Corals, Echinoderms, etc. (after it had originally reached a certain depth in the ocean), until it reached the proper height for corals to flourish. This here is not much deeper than seven to eight fathoms; generally six fathoms marks the limit. To the westward of this group of reefs is a coral reef starting on a bank at a depth of seven fathoms.</p>
                    <p>I expect to publish a small map of the distribution of the corals of the Tortugas as soon as I return home, in my report of work (not done) to the Superintendent of the Coast Survey. I shall, however, have first to finish reading the proofs of the Challenger Echini, the last pages of which I expect to find awaiting my return home, and I trust you will see that Memoir out during the summer.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For Agassiz’s dredging missions aboard the US coast survey steamer <hi rend="italic">Blake</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11236.xml">A. Agassiz 1888</ref>. During his 1881 visit to the Tortugas, Agassiz also further developed his theory of coral reef formation; in opposition to CD’s deductive subsidence theory, he argued from empirical evidence that coral reefs began to grow on banks that were rising not because of elevation but through the accumulation of animal remains (mainly plankton) on mudbanks (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2067.xml">Dobbs 2005</ref>). Agassiz had established a laboratory at Newport, Rhode Island, in 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_39.xml">G. R. Agassiz ed. 1913</ref>, pp. 153–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Velella</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Porpita</hi> are genera in the hydrozoan family Porpitidae. Agassiz published a study of the species found in the region in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11237.xml">A. Agassiz 1883</ref>; he included twelve plates, figuring the morphology and anatomy of specimens at various stages of development.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_41.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Agassiz</ref> argued that the accumulation (through the action of waves and winds) of the remains of pelagic creatures on parts of the seabed provided areas at the right depths for corals to grow and reefs to develop. In contrast, his father, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml">Louis Agassiz</ref>, had believed that reefs must have been formed by shifts in the relative levels of land and sea; on this view, no new reefs were likely to form in the deep water off the coast of Florida because these relative levels were no longer changing. Extracts from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz’s</ref> report on the topography of Florida, including coral reefs, were published in 1851, but did not appear in full until Alexander published them in 1880 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11399.xml">L. Agassiz 1851</ref>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11238.xml">L. Agassiz 1880</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_41.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Agassiz’s</ref> own results were published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11405.xml">A. Agassiz 1882</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">No map appeared with Agassiz’s report to the superintendent (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11240.xml">A. Agassiz 1881a</ref>) but several were included in his article on the Tortugas and Florida reefs (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11405.xml">A. Agassiz 1882</ref>). Agassiz’s report on the Echinoidea (the class of heart urchins, sand dollars, and sea urchins) collected during the <hi rend="italic">Challenger</hi> expedition was published in 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11239.xml">A. Agassiz 1881b</ref>). There is a copy of this report in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>