<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13203">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francisco de Arruda Furtado<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   13 June 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16916</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13203 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13203.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13203.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp (French)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Tavares (1957): 296</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11431.xml">Constância ed. (2002)</ref>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 159: 114b, 114c</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>159: 114b, 114c</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_160.xml">Arruda Furtado, Francisco de</persName>
                <placeName>Azores</placeName>
                <date when="1881-06-13">13 June 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Offers his services to CD as an observer in the Azores. Has studied the local natural history and is a great disciple of CD’s.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Arruda Furtado, Francisco d’</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Azores</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive self-criticism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-02-25" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-03" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-05-29" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00578_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2984px" height="5149px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00578_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="2984px" height="5149px"/>
        <surface n="114b:1r" xml:id="i578">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00578.jpg" width="2984px" height="5149px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00578_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2984px" height="5149px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00578.dzi" width="2984px" height="5149px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="114b:1v" xml:id="i579">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00579.jpg" width="2984px" height="5188px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00579_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2984px" height="5188px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00579.dzi" width="2984px" height="5188px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="114b:2r" xml:id="i580">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00580.jpg" width="5747px" height="5118px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00580_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5747px" height="5118px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00580.dzi" width="5747px" height="5118px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="114b:2v" xml:id="i581">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00581.jpg" width="3070px" height="5227px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00581_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3070px" height="5227px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00581.dzi" width="3070px" height="5227px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="114b:1v-2r" xml:id="i582">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00582.jpg" width="2980px" height="5227px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00582_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2980px" height="5227px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00582.dzi" width="2980px" height="5227px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="114c:1r" xml:id="i583">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00583.jpg" width="2983px" height="5182px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00583_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2983px" height="5182px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00583.dzi" width="2983px" height="5182px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="114c:1v" xml:id="i584">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00584.jpg" width="2983px" height="5182px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00584_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2983px" height="5182px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00159-000-00584.dzi" width="2983px" height="5182px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Ile St. Michel (Açores)</placeName>
                    <date>13 June 1881</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>très honoré Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Je suis né et je vis sur ces îles volcaniques où les faits de distribution géographique des mollusques terrestres sont une intéressante preuve en faveur de la théorie à qui on a donné votre nom mille fois célèbre et respectable.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Après la lecture de votre livre “The origin of species”, sur ce qui touche aux iles océaniques, ma vocation naturelle pour la zoologie s’est trouvée toute occupée de ces faits malacologiques, de la difficulté d’introduction des espèces, du transport dans les pattes des oiseaux &amp; et j’ai entrepris de faire ma petite œuvre sur ce sujet.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> J’ose placer entre vos mains deux petits travaux de ce genre et je possède bon nombre de dessins et de notes sur des espèces dont l’anatomie interne est encore inconnue. Mon but est de comparer avec la faune continentale américaine et européenne, afin de jetter quelque lumière sur <hi rend="underline">l’origine des espèces</hi> açoréannes.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>En même temps je cherche à vulgariser, dans ces parages exilées du monde scientifique, votre théorie, en donnant à mes petit écrits cette forme de transition indispensable dans ce milieu où il faut que la réaction soit le plus vivement excitée; et je cherche aussi à ne perdre un seul fait qui puisse apporter une preuve quelque faible qu’elle soit à votre théorie.</p>
                    <p>Tout dernièrement j’ai fait une découverte intéressante:—dix exemplaires d’une Vitrine où je n’ai trouvé (dans 7 individus disséqués) aucun vestige d’appareil reproducteur! J’ai communiqué 3 individus à Mr. Miall, professeur de Biologie (Yorkshire College) et bienveillant traducteur de mon travail sur la <hi rend="underline">Viquesnelia atlantica</hi>, et il a trouvée <hi rend="underline">no trace of reproductive organs</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Je cherche à établir les circumstances détaillées du fait, afin de connaître s’il s’agit bien d’un hybride et quelles sont les espèces qui ont du le produire.</p>
                    <p>Dans ces conditions, entouré de cette nature si intéressante et, il faut le dire, très incomplètement étudiée, et sachant que toujours le savant le plus éminent est le plus bienveillant pour ceux qui font les premiers pas, je me suis decidé à avoir l’hardiesse de vous offrir mes premières études et toute la faiblesse de mes services, si vous me jugerez digne de vous recueillir quelques faits, de faire des observations sur le transport des vagues, des oiseaux, et., enfin de faire quelque chose utile à la Science, entreprise imprudente sans se demander le secours bienveillant du Maître.</p>
                    <p>L’etude des araignées des Açores, autre celle des mollusques, est une étude intéressante. Mr. Eugène Simon a voulu bien se charger de la determination d’une soixantaine d’espèces que j’ai recueillies à St. Michel. Beaucoup d’espèces nouvelles ont été trouvées, quoique la faunule se rattache intimement aux formes circaméditerranéennes.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Une espèce très voisine d’une autre de St. Helène a été trouvée—<hi rend="underline">Ariamnes delicatulus</hi>, E. Simon (sp. nov.)<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Mr. Lédillot<ref target="#foot.f8"/> prépare un travail sur des coléoptères et des hémiptères provenant aussi de mes excursions.</p>
                    <p>En rendant ces faibles services à ces naturalistes, comment pourrais-je etre silencieux devant vous, Monsieur, quand je relis tous les jours quelque page de votre livre, quand je sais que les Açores ne vous sont pas du tout indifférents et quand j’ai le suprême bonheur de me trouver un de vos disciples? Certes je ne pourrais le faire. Je ne pourrais que penser toujours à obéir à vos ordres toutes les fois que vous m’en jugerez digne.</p>
                    <p>Mes services n’auront peut-être aucune valeur, mais je ne vivais sans vous communiquer que vous aviez aux Açores un disciple des plus reconnaissants et que vous pourrez en faire un serviteur des plus devoués.</p>
<p>Arruda Furtado.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>São Miguel Island (Azores)</placeName>
                    <date>13 June 1881</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>Very honoured sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
                    <p>I was born and live on these volcanic islands where the facts of geographical distribution of land molluscs are an interesting proof in favour of the theory that has made your name a thousand times renowned and respected.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>After reading your book “The origin of species”, on that which dealt with oceanic islands, my natural vocation for zoology has been totally devoted to these malacalogical facts, on the difficulty of the introduction of species, on the transportation on the  feet of birds &amp; and I have undertaken my small contribution on the subject.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I venture to send you two small works of this sort and I have a good number of drawings and notes on species whose internal anatomy is as yet unknown. My goal is to compare these with the fauna of continental America and Europe, in order to throw light on <hi rend="underline">the origin of species</hi> of the Azores.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>At the same time I hope to popularise your theory on these shores, exiled from the world of science, by giving my little offerings this transitional form, which is indispensible in this environment where the response must be more keenly excited; and I also hope not to lose a single fact that could provide a proof, no matter how weak, of your theory.</p>
                    <p>Recently I made an interesting discovery:—ten specimens of Vitrina where I found (in 7 dissected individuals) no trace of reproductive organs! I sent 3 individuals to Mr. Miall, professor of Biology (Yorkshire College) and generous translator of my work on <hi rend="underline">Viquesnelia atlantica</hi>, and he found <hi rend="underline">no trace of reproductive organs</hi>. I hope to establish the circumstances of this fact in detail, in order to assess whether it is a case of a hybrid and what the species are that produced it.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>In these conditions, surrounded by this nature so interesting, and, it must be said, very incompletely studied, and knowing that the most eminent scholar is always the most generous to those taking their first steps, I decided to be so bold as to offer you my first studies and all the limitations of my services, should you consider me worthy of gathering a few facts for you, of making observations on the transportation by waves, birds, and, thus to do something useful for Science, a foolish enterprise without seeking the Master’s gracious help.</p>
                    <p>The study of the spiders of the Azores, besides that of molluscs, is an interesting study. Mr. Eugène Simon agreed to undertake the identification of sixty species that I collected on St. Michel (São Miguel). Many new species have been found, although the faunule is intimately linked to forms of the Mediterranean region.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> One species very close to another on  St. Helène has been found—<hi rend="underline">Ariamnes delicatulus</hi>, E. Simon (sp. nov.)<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Mr. Lédillot<ref target="#foot.f8"/> is preparing a work on beetles and Hemiptera, which also come from my excursions.</p>
                    <p>By providing these meagre services to these naturalists, how could I be silent before you, Sir, when I am always re-reading some page of your book, when I know that the Azores are not without interest for you and when I have the extreme pleasure of being one of your disciples? I certainly could not do it. I could not but think of always following the orders that you judge me worthy to carry out.</p>
                    <p>My services may not perhaps be of value, but I could not live without telling you that you have a most appreciative disciple in the Azores and that you could make use of a most devoted servant.</p>
                    <p>Arruda Furtado.</p> 
                </div>   
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had discussed geographical distribution on oceanic islands in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 389–406. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For more on Arruda Furtado’s work in malacology, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9809.xml">Felismino <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2016</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s inscribed offprint of ‘Indagações sobre a complicação das maxillas de alguns helices (Enquiry on the complexity of the jaws of some Helixes; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9813.xml">Arruda Furtado 1880a</ref>) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Arruda Furtado probably also sent ‘A proposito da distribuição dos molluscos terrestres nos Açores’ (On the distribution of terrestrial molluscs in the Azores; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11430.xml">Arruda Furtado 1880b</ref>), but no copy has been found in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3313.xml">Louis Compton Miall</ref> had translated Arruda Furtado’s anatomical study of the terrestrial gastropod <hi rend="italic">Viquesnelia atlantica</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Plutonia atlantica</hi>) in <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</hi>, March 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9814.xml">Arruda Furtado 1881a</ref>). Miall later translated Arruda Furtado’s work on the abortion of the reproductive organs in <hi rend="italic">Vitrina</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9810.xml">Arruda Furtado 1882</ref>). Although Arruda Furtado had concluded that the specimens might be hybrids, Miall, in a note added to the paper, suggested that the complete absence of reproductive organs in the individuals that he dissected was more likely due to a parasitic attack. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Arruda Furtado had written to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9301.xml">Eugène Simon</ref> in June 1880 describing his collection of spiders and asking whether Simon would be interested in describing them (for all of his correspondence with Simon, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11431.xml">Constância ed. 2002</ref>, pp. 23–50). Simon agreed and the description of species appeared in his memoir on the spiders of the oceanic islands of the Atlantic (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11433.xml">E. Simon 1883</ref>). A faunule is the fauna of a specified small habitat.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Ariamnes delicatulus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Rhomphaea nasica</hi>) was first described by Simon in 1873 as <hi rend="italic">Ariamnes nasica</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11434.xml">E. Simon 1873</ref>, pp. 152–4). He later described it as a new species, <hi rend="italic">Ariamnes delicatulus</hi>, from a specimen sent by Arruda Furtado, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11433.xml">E. Simon 1883</ref>, pp. 272–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">For Arruda Furtado’s  correspondence with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9302.xml">Maurice Sédillot</ref>, see Constância ed. 2002, pp. 65–73.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>