<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8080F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. E. Darwin   22 November 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21715</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8080F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8080F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8080F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
                <relatedItem type="publication">
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 24: 525</bibl>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Cornford Family Papers (DAR 275: 47)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                        <collection>DAR</collection>
                        <idno>275: 47</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">Darwin, W. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Bank, Southampton</placeName>
                <date when="1871-11-22">22 Nov 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends back proofs. Praises CD for calm treatment of Mivart. Looks at duck’s mouth. Asks whether CD has seen Snow’s article in the Spectator.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">duck</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_6226">Lucretius</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3350">Mivart, St G. J.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_5011">Wedgwood, F. J.</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Bank, Southampton,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Nov 22 <hi rend="print">18</hi>71</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I sent you to day a fresh lot, as it was chiefly manuscript, I thought it just worth registering.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>It is delicious the calm way you jaw up the imposter M.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I got your card as to not marking injured letters.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I was looking today from curiosity into a duck’s mouth, I should have thought from the neat way in which the fringed tongue fits in against the roof of the mouth that the slightest grooves would begin to act as a filter.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I send you the Saturday review. Did you read the quotation from Lucretius in Snow’s article in Spectator Nov 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Mivart delights in putting up a dummy which he pretends to be you, and then knocking it down in the most light &amp; easy style, to the admiration of those he can gull.</p>
<p>Your affect son | W E Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">William was correcting the proofs of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed. (see this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8041F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. E. Darwin, [19 November 1871]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD responded to various criticisms of the theory of natural selection that had been made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart</ref> in chapter 7 of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s postcard has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In response to Mivart’s objection that the large plates of baleen in whales could not have evolved gradually through natural selection, CD suggested that the early progenitors of whales might have possessed mouths like the lamellated beaks of ducks that enabled them to sift mud and water (<hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed., pp. 183–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Snow was the nickname of Frances Julia Wedgwood. In her unsigned article, ‘The natural and the supernatural’ (<hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>, 4 November 1871, pp. 1340–42), she compared CD’s theory of natural selection with the views of Lucretius. She paraphrased Lucretius (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 1341): <quote>We see that many conditions are necessary in order that a race should be perpetuated, and among all the animals which have existed, some have been brought into the world unfitted for these; others, again, have perished from being unprovided with any peculiar advantage in the struggle for existence. For races are preserved in this struggle either by their own craft, strength, or at least activity, on the one hand, or else by being useful to us, many different races of animals being secured from extinction by the guardianship of man.</quote> The text is from Lucretius, <hi rend="italic">De rerum natura</hi> 5: 849–59.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>