<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1914">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To T. H. Huxley   1 July [1856]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3286</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1914 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1914.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1914.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 166</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 175, 37–9)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 175, 37–9</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1856-07-01">1 July [1856]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Asks for information on geographical distribution of ascidians; are any closely allied species or genera found in north and south temperate zones that do not have representatives in the tropics?</p>
            <p>Answers some questions on [cirripede] antennae.</p>
            <p>If THH ever sees a tree washed ashore, will he observe whether any earth is embedded between roots?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ascidians</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cirripedes</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">trees, drifted</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">temperate zone, north</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">temperate zone, south</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">tropics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">close species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dispersion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">representative species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>July 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Huxley</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>The Society for Prevention of Cruelty to animals ought to be at me, for troubling you, overworked &amp; unwell as you are; but I do cruelly want one question answered; &amp; you can lay aside <hi rend="underline">for present</hi> the remarkable case, of “Darwin, an absolute &amp; eternal hermaphrodite”<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Have you published a Catalogue of the Ascidians in B. Mus;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> if so &amp; you could lend it me for a few days, I daresay my question would be answered.— My question is, are there any Ascidian genera, with closely allied species in the northern &amp; southern cold or temperate seas, but such genera <hi rend="underline">not</hi> found anywhere in the Tropical seas.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have some vague idea that there are some genera of compound Ascidians in this predicament.— But it is very likely that the subject has been so neglected that even if you knew of a genus in north &amp; south, yet you could not form any opinion whether or no it occurred in Tropics. The best chance would be in very northern genera.— I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. like to quote you as authority</p>
<p>Hoping for forgiveness | Yours most truly | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Thanks for the last lecture,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> which as all the others have done, has interested me much.—</p>
<p>You pay me a grand compliment, far more than I deserve; but this did not lessen my satisfaction.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>What success with Examinership?<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>P.S. | Two closely allied genera, one in north &amp; the other in south, with <hi rend="underline">no</hi> closely allied in Tropics, is almost equally a case in point. I think it quite possible that Ascidians in spirits may be hardly recognizable, &amp; if so my queries are unanswerable.—</p>
<p>P.S. 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.— | I see I have not answered your question about the antennæ.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> It is mere chance whether easy or excessively difficult to detect antennæ, depending on nature of surface &amp; amount of cement poured out. Generally young are best. It is easy in some cases for reasons I cannot explain. The best specimens are young attached to calcareous substances which can be dissolved. But you must remember these organs very small. For months, at first, I only obscurely made them out, &amp; could never conceive what they were! How I have puzzled over them!</p>
<p>As you will be a good deal of sea-side for next few years,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I wish you would remember to observe, sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> you chance ever to see a tree washed on shore, will you carefully observe whether any earth, ever so little, is embedded between roots—on account of transport of plants.—</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">P.S. 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> </hi> | You have some slides with cement-glands of sessile cirripedes in London, please do not destroy them; as I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. like sometime to have them back.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I have antennæ preserved, sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. you ever wish to see them.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 are;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon over colon</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.3 answered;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon over colon</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.7 Ascidian] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.7 &amp; southern] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.8 such] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘not’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.1 Thanks] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">6.2 almost] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is indicated by CD’s use of information in this letter in chapter 11 of his species book (see n. 4, below), which was completed late in the summer of 1856 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 531).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had asked Huxley to give him examples of organisms that were truly hermaphrodite, that is, in which cross-fertilisation seemed anatomically impossible. (The joke apparently arose through Huxley entering this request in his diary in the form CD quoted.) Such examples would disprove CD’s belief that all hermaphrodites could, and occasionally did, cross. The issue is discussed at length in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 44–6. CD refers to Huxley’s observations on ascidians which, though hermaphrodite, were thought by Huxley to release their spermatozoa and ova at different times, thereby being functionally unisexual (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 45). He also mentions having asked Huxley whether he knew of ‘any animals whose structure was such that an occasional cross was physically impossible’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 46). See also letters to T. H. Huxley, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">8 July [1856]</ref>, and to J. D. Hooker, 13 July [1856].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Huxley endeavoured to compile a catalogue of the ascidians in the collection of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3994.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1852</ref>). The catalogue, however, was never completed by Huxley.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Huxley’s reply has not been found, but CD cited it in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 556: ‘In the Ascideae, the genus Boltenia has allied species in the arctic &amp; antarctic seas, &amp; Prof. Huxley thinks that the genus is not Tropical; but here again from our ignorance much caution is requisite.’ See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 8 July [1856]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD refers to Huxley’s lectures on general natural history, delivered at the School of Mines, that were published serially in the <hi rend="italic">Medical Times &amp; Gazette</hi> beginning with the issue of 3 June 1856 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1856–7</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In Huxley’s fifth lecture, published on 21 June 1856 and covering the Actinia, Huxley founded his discussion of the coral-forming actinians on CD’s <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>, warmly praising the work ‘as a striking example of the manner in which Geology and Natural History may be made to elucidate one another.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1856–7</ref>, 12: 623).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See letters to T. H. Huxley, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1878.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">27 May [1856]</ref>, and to J. W. Lubbock, 27 May [1856]. Huxley was appointed examiner in comparative anatomy and physiology at the University of London. The appointment was announced in the <hi rend="italic">Medical Times &amp; Gazette</hi> 13 (1856): 103.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD refers to the antennae of sessile cirripedes. Huxley discussed this group of Crustacea in his twelfth lecture on general natural history. For earlier correspondence between CD and Huxley concerning cirripede anatomy, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Huxley had visited Tenby in the summers of 1854 and 1855 to carry out researches on marine invertebrates. He returned there again in September and October 1856 (L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 143).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">A set of slide specimens of cirripede parts prepared by CD is in the Cambridge Zoology Museum.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>