<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5960">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. T. Stainton   29 February 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16203</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5960 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5960.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5960.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="inc">†, encl 4pp † &amp; ACC 7pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy"><bibl>NHM Gen. lib. MSS/DAR: 22</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 85: B52-3; DAR 86: A16;</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>85: B52–B53,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>86: A12–A13, A16</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_288.xml">NHM</repository>
                    <idno>Gen. lib. MSS/ DAR : 22</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4514.xml">Stainton, H. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Lewisham</placeName>
                <date when="1868-02-29">29 Feb 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Replies to CD on proportion of sexes in butterflies, coloration of moths, and courtship. Encloses copies of letters on these subjects between HTS, Henry Doubleday, and John Hellins.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">butterflies</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">moths</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Mountsfield, | Lewisham. | S.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>February 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1868</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I now reply <hi rend="underline">seriatim</hi> to the points noted in your letter of the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>1. The Males of the Emperor &amp; Brimstone butterflies are <hi rend="underline">visibly</hi> more numerous than the females—but with me that is no evidence that their numbers are really greater—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Doubleday says of the Emperor moth (<hi rend="underline">Saturnia carpini</hi> or <hi rend="underline">Pavonia-Minor</hi>) he breeds more males than females, but I doubt whether you would find that the general experience.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>2. With reference to <hi rend="underline">Pamphila Actaeon</hi> I can give no information.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>3. In many genera of moths the males have whiter underwings that the females— this renders them much more conspicuous in the evening dusk— The common <hi rend="underline">Agrotis exclamationis</hi> is a good instance of this.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>With reference to the <hi rend="underline">Oenistis quadra</hi> I have no information.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>4. I cannot call to mind that I ever noticed an instance of courting in the <hi rend="underline">Fritillaries</hi> or <hi rend="underline">Vanessæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I have seen it in the white butterflies but then the female was sitting down calling the male— whether there had been any preliminary stages I cannot say.</p>
<p>5. I am not aware of any moths in which the underside is more conspicuous than the upper side (of which in Butterflies we have such a striking instance in the Green Hair Streak <hi rend="underline">Thecla Rubi</hi>)— the underside of the Red Underwing is very conspicuous but not more so than the upper side.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>6. With a few exceptions all the most gaily coloured moths are diurnal in their habits.</p>
<p>7. Generally speaking there are no strongly marked sexual differences in the <hi rend="underline">Tineina</hi>   in a few cases we have apterous females, then females with abbreviated wings as in <hi rend="underline">Chimabacche Fagella</hi> <ref target="#foot.f9"/>— the differences in colour &amp; marking are most conspicuous in the genus <hi rend="underline">Elachista</hi>—but the long-horned moths of the genera <hi rend="underline">Adela</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Nemotois</hi> <ref target="#foot.f10"/> are the most singularly different—whilst the differences are very slight in the wings— the antennae, eyes, palpi &amp; clothing of the head are quite different.</p>
<p>Towards the end of April &amp; beginning of May a little whitish moth <hi rend="underline">Elachista rufocinerea</hi> flies along the hedge-bottoms towards dusk— these are the males on search for the female. By looking carefully on the blades of grass a female may be seen at rest— she is at once recognised by her whiter &amp; rather more pointed wings— not unfrequently the female will be found not at rest, but sitting with her wings expanded &amp; her body raised, fluttering her wings—&amp; this may be noticed when there is no male near.— the males flying along the hedge-bottom come to such a female &amp; congregate round her perhaps as many as 12 or 20— one pairs with the female &amp; the rest fly onwards in search of other females.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>In reference to your letter of Feby 21 I cannot say whether the artificial condition of life of a caged caterpillar in any way affects the sex—but I strongly incline to the belief that if collected in the pupa state the majority would still be females.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I enclose you copies of some correspondence I had just had with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Doubleday &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hellins on this subject, which I thought would interest you.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Many years ago I had much diversion with the Scotch form of <hi rend="underline">Lasiocampa Quercus</hi> &amp; almost any number of males might be caught by taking a bred female on to the moors they frequented.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> but yet I never knew the slightest difficulty in breeding a female if 2 or 3 pupæ were obtained &amp; as M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hellins well puts it if you had only one pupa it was far more likely to produce a female than a male.</p>
<p>You will find mention of the assembling propensities of the males <hi rend="underline">Bombycidae</hi> in Westwood’s Introduction to the Modern Classification of Insects vol II p. 384<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>I do not think that a male insect serves more than one female</p>
<p>I would in conclusion throw out the suggestion that you should call the attention of Entomologists to points (on which you want information) to be observed during the coming season.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f17"/></ab>
      
          <div type="transcription">
  
<p>H. T. Stainton to Henry Doubleday, Esq. Epping</p>
              <p rend="right"> Feb. 25, 1868</p>  
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin is at present collecting information as to the relative numbers of the sexes in insects.</p>
<p>I have told him that my experience as a <hi rend="underline">breeder</hi> is directly opposed to my previous experience as an insect–collector, as in breeding I find the females predominate.</p>
<p>I should be glad if you would give me any details of your experience, especially where you have reared an entire brood of a species.</p>
<p>Even in the Bombycidae of which the males swarm round a female I fancy the bred females preponderate.</p>
<p>Pray excuse my troubling you with this query, but your experience in breeding <hi rend="underline">Macros</hi> <ref target="#foot.f18"/> has been so great &amp; so long continued, that your observations will be most valuable.</p> 

<p>Henry Doubleday to H. T. Stainton</p>
<p rend="right">Feb. 26, 1868</p>  
<p>I received your welcome letter this morning &amp; beg to assure you that I am always glad to give you any information that I can upon Entomological subjects.</p>
<p>I am decidedly of the opinion that the males of all insects are more numerous than the females, &amp; I do not recollect a single instance among the <hi rend="underline">MacroLepidoptera</hi> when I have reared whole broods, in which the females were more numerous than the males. —some years since I reared a large number of <hi rend="underline">Selenia Ilustraria</hi> <ref target="#foot.f19"/> from the eggs &amp; I think two-thirds of them were males—it was the same with broods of <hi rend="underline">Orgyia gonostigma</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Saturnia Carpini</hi> &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>I have never reared whole broods of any of the <hi rend="underline">MicroLepidoptera</hi>.</p>
<p>I think the males of <hi rend="underline">Gonepteryx Rhamni</hi> <ref target="#foot.f21"/> for instance, must be far more numerous than the females, as when they re-appear in the spring, none of the common White Butterflies are out &amp; you certainly see a dozen males to one female.</p>
<p>I have seen many hundred male <hi rend="underline">Miana fasciuncula</hi> but not more than half a dozen females, two of which I took last May.</p>
<p>The females of <hi rend="underline">Miana strigilis</hi> are common enough but not quite as abundant as the males.<ref target="#foot.f22"/></p>
<p>I shall have much pleasure in answering any more questions upon this subject.</p> 

<p>H. T. Stainton to the Rev. J. Hellins, Chaplain’s House, County Recson,<ref target="#foot.f23"/> Exeter</p>
<p rend="right">Feb. 25, 1868</p>  
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin is busy collecting information as to the relative numbers of the sexes in insects. Now my experience as a breeder of Micros is that the females preponderate—as you must have had considerable experience by this time in breeding Macros I should be glad to hear what you have found to be the case, more especially in those instances in which you have reared an entire brood.</p>
<p>If you have had sufficient experience of insect collection in the pupa state I should be glad to learn whether in those cases the females do not also preponderate.</p>
<p>Pray excuse the trouble I am giving you.</p> 

<p>Rev. J. Hellins to H. T. Stainton</p>
<p rend="right">February 26, 1868</p>  
<p>My <hi rend="doubleUnderline">impression</hi> is decidedly that as a rule I breed more female moths than males–a rule not without striking exceptions—still holding so generally good, that if I had one egg—one larva and one pupa—I should expect to breed a female moth; or if I had two or three—still I should not quite expect to get a male: i.e. trusting only to chance.</p>
<p>When I dug pupae I fear I didn’t keep account—but if you will give me ten days I will look up my note books &amp; see what I can find out.</p>
<p>I understand that those who keep <hi rend="underline">poultry</hi> expect more cocks than hens, &amp; such people have been surprised to hear me say what I found in the case of my insects.</p>
<p>Also—my children have been keeping guinea–pigs for the last two years &amp; certainly the “old mother” who was the foundation of their stock &amp; has gone on having broods ever since, has produced more sons than daughters!</p>
<p>You know I don’t often rear <hi rend="underline">large</hi> broods—because I don’t care for heaps of specimens, only to watch the transformations &amp; six larvae are much more likely to thrive than sixty.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I now … 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. 1.1] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 2. With … <hi rend="italic">Vanessæ</hi>. 6.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 3. In … dusk— 4.2] ‘But differences not very conspicuous’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.2 <hi rend="italic">Agrotis exclamationis</hi> 4.3] ‘V’ <hi rend="italic">added blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 5. I … different 10.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.7 the males flying … 20— 11.8] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi>; <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>12.1 In reference … interest you. 13.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>16.1 I do not … call 17.1] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘No of sexes’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure, 4th letter</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 I … insects. 3.2] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 Also … daughters! 4.3] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 I don’t care … sixty. 5.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi>; ‘so he wd probably collect larger caterpillars’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5890.xml" resp="#automat">letter to H. T. Stainton, 18 February [1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5890.xml" resp="#automat">letter to H. T. Stainton, 18 February [1868]</ref> and n. 2. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5903.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. T. Stainton, 20 February 1868</ref>, in which Stainton claimed that accurate information on the proportion of the sexes could only be obtained from insects bred in captivity.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 311, CD reported that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1360.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Doubleday</ref> and some other entomologists maintained that they had reared from the egg and caterpillar stages a larger proportion of males than females. The emperor moth is now <hi rend="italic">Saturnia pavonia</hi> (family Saturniidae); it is mentioned in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 311, 398.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5890.xml" resp="#automat">letter to H. T. Stainton, 18 February [1868]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD cited Stainton’s remarks on <hi rend="italic">Agrotis exclamationis</hi> (the heart and dart moth) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 398–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Oenistis quadra</hi> (the large footman) is now <hi rend="italic">Lithosia quadra</hi> (the four-spotted footman). Stainton described the different coloration in the sexes in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7405.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stainton 1867</ref>, pp. 155–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5890.xml" resp="#automat">letter to H. T. Stainton, 18 February [1868]</ref> and nn. 5 and 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 397, CD stated on Stainton’s authority that in moths the under surface of the wings was very rarely more brightly coloured than the upper side. <hi rend="italic">Thecla rubi</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Callophrys rubi.</hi> The red underwing is <hi rend="italic">Catocala nupta.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Chimabacche fagella</hi> (the March dagger) is now <hi rend="italic">Diurnea fagella.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Nemotois</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Nemophora.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Stainton’s description of <hi rend="italic">Elachista rufocinerea</hi> is given in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 311.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5907.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. T. Stainton, 21 February [1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See enclosure. Stainton refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hellins</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5907.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. T. Stainton, 21 February [1868]</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Stainton refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8305.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Westwood 1839–40</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Stainton announced CD’s interest in various aspects of sexual selection involving coloration at the 2 March 1868 meeting of the Entomological Society of London (see <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</hi> (1868): xiv).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">The enclosure is a copy, in an unknown hand, of Stainton’s correspondence with Doubleday and Hellins.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Stainton refers to macrolepidoptera: those families of butterflies and moths whose members are large enough to be of interest to the majority of collectors (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Probably <hi rend="italic">Selenia illunaria</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">S. dentaria</hi>), the early thorn moth (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fletcher 1979</ref>, p. 188).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><hi rend="italic">Orgyia gonostigma</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">O. antiqua</hi>) is the scarce vaporer moth. For <hi rend="italic">Saturnia carpini</hi>, the emperor moth, see n. 3, above..</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21"><hi rend="italic">Gonepteryx rhamni</hi>, the brimstone butterfly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22"><hi rend="italic">Miana fasciuncula</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Oligia fasciuncula</hi>, the middle-barred minor; <hi rend="italic">Miana strigilis</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Oligia strigilis</hi>, the marbled minor.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">The address is probably a copyist’s error: Hellins was chaplain of the Exeter county house of correction.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>