<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9999">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. F. Segrave   28 May 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10702</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9999 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9999.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9999.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 131</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 131</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4281.xml">Segrave, W. F.</persName>
                <placeName>British Consulate, Stockholm</placeName>
                <date when="1875-05-28">28 May 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has heard from Italian minister that the inhabitants of the Japanese island of Saghalien [Sakhalin], lately ceded to Russia, have their bodies covered with hair, like the gorilla, and are supposedly the remnant of the aboriginal population of the Japanese islands.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">gorilla</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">aboriginal population</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Sakhalin inhabitants</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Italian minister</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Japanese island</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Russia</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Saghalien</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">British Consulate Stockholm</hi></placeName>
                    <date>28 May 1875</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The Italian Minister here, who served for some time in Japan, informs me that the Inhabitants of the Island of Saghalien, lately ceded to Russia, are covered with hair, even as the gorilla,<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>He tells me that this interesting people are supposed to be the remnant of the aboriginal tribes who inhabited Japan before the advent of its present population.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Only a small remnant now survive who will probably not long outlive Russian improvements.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I have no means of testing the accuracy of Mons dela Tours information, and indeed, I may say that I am disposed to question it, as I cannot at this moment call to mind that you have noticed the fact, if fact it be, in any of your works.</p>
<p>If there be any foundation for the statement, I am sure that you will agree with me that it is of the highest interest and importance from a scientific point of view, and well worthy of investigation</p>
<p>I therefore make no apology for bringing the subject to your notice and Remain | Dear Sir | Your faithful serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> | W. F. Segrave | H.M. Counsul</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The Italian minister was Comte <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7604.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vittorio Sallier de la Tour</ref>. The Ainu people of the Island of Saghalien, now known as Sakhalin island, were renowned for their hairiness (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8858.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Batchelor 1892</ref>, pp. 17–18; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8859.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Savage Landor 1893</ref>, pp. 85, 88, 142, and 145); in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 601–2, CD suggested that greater hairiness in certain races might be due to reversion. The Russians had established a penal colony in northern Sakhalin in 1857, but the Japanese held the southern part until August 1875, when, with the signing of the Treaty of Saint Petersburg (the Russo-Japanese Sakhalin, Kuriles Exchange Treaty), Russia gained sovereignty over all of Sakhalin in exchange for the Kurile Islands (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8857.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gentes 2002</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In the early part of the nineteenth century, the Japanese had subjected the Ainu to forced labour and resettlement; from the 1850s, they attempted to integrate them into Japanese culture. This policy of assimilation transformed the Ainu from barbarians into a ‘primitive race’, doomed to die out because it was unable to progress to higher levels of civilisation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8876.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Siddle 1997</ref>, 22–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In 1875, following the Treaty of Saint Petersburg, 841 Ainu from southern Sakhalin were removed by the Japanese to the island of Hokkaido, but many others remained on Sakhalin under Russian rule. Russia appropriated Ainu land on Sakhalin for agriculture in the hope of making their penal colony self-sufficient. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howell 2005</ref>, pp. 186–9.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>