<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6213">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Friedrich Rolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   28 May 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10563</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6213 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6213.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6213.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 204</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 204</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4067.xml">Rolle, Friedrich</persName>
                <placeName>Bad Homburg</placeName>
                <date when="1868-05-28">28 May 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Questions CD’s view in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> that <hi rend="italic">Torfschwein</hi> formerly ranged from Europe to China.</p> 
            <p>Cites numerous German publications relating to CD’s theory.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Torfschwein</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">China</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Europe</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Homburg vor der Hoehe | bei Frankfurt am Main</placeName>
                    <date>28 Mai 1868</date>
                    <salute>Geehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Entschuldigen sie mich, dass ich erst so spaet Ihnen meinen Dank für die Zusendung der Uebersetzung Ihres neuen Werks sage. Ich erhielt Theil II, Heft I. soeben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Theil I habe ich eifrig studirt. Sie erwarten kein Lob von mir: Sie wissen, dass ich bemüht bin, Ihren Schritten zu folgen! Um so mehr bemühte ich mich, neues Material für Sie zu sammeln und meine Einwaende gegen Einzelheiten Ihres Werks zu notiren.</p>
<p>Ich opponire gegen Ihre Ansicht, dass das <hi rend="underline">Torfschwein</hi> ehedem wild von Europa gegen China gereicht habe. (Darwin. Das Variiren I. pag 86)<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Ich sagte 1863 (Rolle. Ch Darwin’s Lehre pag 127) ich glaube dass das Torfschwein als gezaehmtes Thier aus Osten (Asien) nach Europa gebracht wurde, in Europa (Schweiz) darnach <hi rend="underline">verwilderte</hi> (wie das Schwein so oft in Colonien!) und dann wild ausgerottet wurde (durch Anwachsen der menschlichen Bevölkerung.)— Beweis dafür ist, dass das Torfschwein der sicher wilden europaeischen Diluvialfauna fehlt— es ist also vom Menschen importirt; nicht autochthon.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> 1866 wiederholte ich dies (Rolle. der Mensch. pag. 329 N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 4)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Auch Andre sind dieser Ansicht bereits D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="underline">R. Pallmann</hi> schrieb ein Werk gegen <hi rend="underline">Rütimeyer</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Desor</hi> u. <hi rend="underline">Keller</hi> (in reactionaerem Sinn, oft mythisch) ((<hi rend="underline">R. Pallmann</hi>. Die Pfahlbauten. Greifswald 1866.))<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Ich liebe dieses Buch nicht. Es ist zum Wohlgefallen der preussischen Orthodoxie u. der Mythologen geschrieben. Aber <hi rend="underline">Pallmann</hi> theilt meine Meinung über das Torfschwein. In seinem Buch 1866. pag. 199. N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 92 sagt er dasselbe sei asiatisch und (von Phoeniciern oder Massalioten) in Westeuropa importirt worden. Ich glaube, dass diese Ansicht richtig ist und <hi rend="underline">Rütimeyer</hi> eine verwilderte Rasse für ein wildes autochthones Thier nahm.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Betreffs des Hundes im Verhaeltniss zu Wolf und Schakal sowie der Hauskatze gegen die Wildkatze bemerke ich dass <hi rend="underline">Blasius</hi> (Fauna der Wirbelthiere Deutschlands 1857. Theil I. Saügethiere) sehr reiches Material hat, namentlich fur die Ermittlung des anatomischen Verhaltens.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Er stellt den Hund durchaus dem Schakal am naechsten—weniger dem Wolf— am entferntesten dem Fuchs.) Ich benutzte <hi rend="underline">Blasius</hi> auch 1863 (Darwin’s Lehre.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> pag. 177) über die Ratten u. Mäuse)</p>
<p>Ueber das Verhaeltniss des Pferdes zum pliocaenen Hipparion (Hippotherium) finden sie reichlichen Aufschluss in <hi rend="underline">R. Hensel</hi>. Ueber Hipparion mediterraneum. Abhandlungen der Berliner Akademie 1860. (auch als Separatwerk erschienen) Hipparion verknüpft das Pferd mit den normalen Pachydermen. Auch kommen Monstrositaeten des Fusses beim Pferde vor, welche die Abstammung erweisen<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Das vortreffliche Werk. <hi rend="underline">Ernst Haeckel</hi>. Generelle Morphologie der Organismen nach der von Ch. Darwin reformirten Descendenz-Theorie Berlin 1866. 2 Baende (Es hat VIII genealogische Tabellen) werden Sie wohl schon kennen.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Er leitet Equus von Hipparion—von Anchitherium u. Tapirus ab</p>
<p>Vielleicht kennen sie auch das Werk von <hi rend="underline">Ed. von Martens</hi> (einem Würtemberger der die preussische Seefahrt nach Ostasien begleitete.) Er muss viel über Hausthiere beobachtet haben, denn <hi rend="underline">Weinland</hi> ermunterte ihn dazu.— Eine Correspondenz von <hi rend="underline">Martens</hi> in <hi rend="underline">Weinland</hi>’s “Thiergarten” 1864. pag 116 sagt, dass <hi rend="underline">Martens</hi> nie Sus pliciceps, das Faltenschwein, in China u. Japan traf und dass er es für eine Culturform haelt, die nirgens wild lebt.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> <hi rend="underline">Weinland’s</hi>, “Thiergarten” 1864 enthält auch pag. 103–105 einen Aufsatz von <hi rend="underline">E v. Martens</hi> über Pfauen, Pavo japanicus, und P. cristatus.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> (Er hat die Pfauen in Japan u. China studirt)</p>
<p>In Tschudi “Thierleben der Alpenwelt”. (edit. V.) 1860<ref target="#foot.f14"/> p. 283 finde ich folgende Stelle, die Sie interessiren wird. <quote type="quote"> “Die <hi rend="underline">Bettwanze</hi> (Ac. lectul.) traf Prof. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Heer</hi> auf der oberen Stafel der Alp Seetz in dem Neste einer Moos-Hummel<ref target="#foot.f15"/> weit entfernt von der menschlichen Wohnung—was diesem Gelehrten mit gegen die Annahme zu sprechen scheint, dass jener Parasit fremden (indischen) Ursprungs sei.” </quote></p>
<p>—Ich glaube dagegen, dass die Wanze auf der Alpe sich verirrt hat—und andre Nahrung suchte—Insecten ansaugte, wie ihre ersten Vorfahren!— von Professor <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> in Wien erschien eine Serie Aufsaetze “Botanische Streifzüge auf dem Gebiete der Culturgeschichte” in den Sitzungsberichten der K. K. Akademie (naturwiss. mathemat. Klasse) 1857–1859 (und vielleicht noch spaeter.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>der 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Theil enthaelt “Die Nahrungspflanzen des Menschen” Sie führt eine Erdkarte mit den “bromatorischen Linien” welche <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> aufstellt.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> Die oestliche bromatorische Linie geht von England deutlich bis zu den Molukken die westliche Halbkugel zeigt keine so deutliche Linie, am meisten tritt noch der Zug von Mexiko bis Brasilien hervor.</p>
<p>Diese Carte wird Sie interessiren. Es knüpft sich die Frage <hi rend="underline">warum</hi>? daran; warum gibt es grosse Linien in welchen die Pflanzen <hi rend="underline">reichlich</hi> Nahrungsstoffe <hi rend="underline">aufspeichern</hi>?!— Ich glaube aber, Sie werden eher gegen <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> opponiren oder zweifeln! Australien hat nach <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> nur an der Südspitze Nahrungspflanzen (also wohl nur Colonisten!?— die alte autochthone Flora von Australien würde dann total <hi rend="underline">abromatorisch</hi> sein.</p>
<p>(Der 2<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>. u. 3<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>. Theil der “Streifzüge” werden Sie minder interessiren.) Um so mehr der 4<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>. Theil “Die Pflanzen des alten Aegyptens” mit IX Tafeln Copien aegyptischer Pflanzen-Bilder zB. Lotus, Cyperus, Vitis etc.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>Vielleicht interessirt Sie auch <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi>, Beiträge zur Physiologie der Pflanzen (Sitzungsberichte Band XXV. 1841.) N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. VIII behandelt Kalkauscheidung, N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. IX die Wachsauscheidung. N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> X den Hönigthau in Aegypten durch Aphis (von Calotropis) erzeugt.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>Ebenso bemerke ich Ihnen die neuen Arbeiten von D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Kerner</hi> in Innspruch (Tirol) über Cultur der Alpenpflanzen und Umwandlung in Sorten des niedren Landes. Ich habe das Buch zwar nicht gelesen, aber gehoert dass <hi rend="underline">Kerner</hi> 5 alpina durch Cultur in sogenannte andre Arten (der Niederung) umwandelte Auteralpinus, Potentilla frigida u. a. (<hi rend="underline">A. Kerner</hi>. Die Cultur der Alpenflanzen, Innsbruck 1864)<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>Noch bemerke ich dass ich beim Studium Ihres Werkes zur Ansicht gelangte dass</p> 
<table>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">die Ratafia-Kirsche</cell>
            <cell rend="left">(</cell>
            <cell rend="left">das</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Variiren.</cell>
            <cell rend="left">pag. 439)</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">le griottier de Toussaint</cell>
            <cell rend="left">(</cell>
            <cell rend="centre">"</cell>
            <cell rend="centre">"</cell>
            <cell rend="left">pag. 440)</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
 
<p rend="left">eins ist und gleich Prunus (cerasus) semperflorens Ehrh.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> diese Variatät kennt <hi rend="underline">J. L. Christ</hi> schon 1794, (Der beste unserer älteren Pomologen.) Er erhielt sie 1794 aus Frankreich als Cerise de la Toussaint<ref target="#foot.f22"/></p>
<p>Endlich notire ich noch D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="underline">G. Jaeger’s</hi> thiergeographische Arbeit in “<hi rend="underline">Ausland</hi>” 1867 N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 6. pag 121.) Er lehrt, “Die Salamandrinen haben gemeinsame nordische Abkunft zusammen mit der miocaen-Flora von Europa, Nordamerika, Japan. Die 3 Stufen Perennibranchiaten, Derotremen, Salamandrinen leben beisammen aber nur noch in der Nordost-Amerika-Provinz von Canada bis Mexiko. (In Europa u. Japan ist heute die Stufenreihe schon gesprengt!)”<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p>
<p>Indem ich mich Ihrer Güte empfehle | Geehrtester Herr | Ihr hochachtungsvoller | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Rolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.1 Ich … N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 4) 3.7] ‘Disbelieves Torf-schwein was wild’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.4 Beweis … N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 4) 3.7] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.7 Auch … worden. 3.13] ‘Several disbelieve’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Ueber … Pachydermen. 5.4] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Hipparion] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.6 <hi rend="italic">Weinland’s</hi> … Pfauen, 7.7] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>15.1 Noch … Ehrh. 15.4] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>16.3 Die 3 … Mexiko. 16.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘&amp; about Cherries’ <hi rend="italic">pencil, circled ink</hi>; ‘only’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Homburg vor der Hoehe | near Frankfurt am Main</placeName>
                    <date>28 May 1868</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Please forgive me for taking so long to thank you for sending the translation of your new work. I just received part II, issue I.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have studied part I avidly. You expect no praise from me; you know that I am keen to follow your steps! All the more I have endeavoured to gather material for you and to note my objections to details in your work.</p>
<p>I oppose your opinion that the <hi rend="underline">Torfschwein</hi> (turbary pig) formerly lived in the wild from Europe almost to China (Darwin. Das Variiren I, p. 86)<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I said in 1863 (Rolle. Ch. Darwin’s Lehre, p. 127) that I believe that the Torfschwein was brought from the East (Asia) to Europe as a tamed animal, afterwards in Europe (Switzerland) it <hi rend="underline">became wild</hi> (as the pig so often does in colonies!) and then was eradicated in the wild (through the growth of the human population).— The proof for this is the absence of the Torfschwein from the undoubtedly wild European diluvial fauna—it was therefore imported by humans; not indigenous.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In 1866 I repeated this statement (Rolle. der Mensch. p. 329 No. 4).<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Others also have already taken this view D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="underline">R. Pallmann</hi> wrote a work against <hi rend="underline">Rütimeyer</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Desor</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Keller</hi> (in a reactionary and often mythological way) ((<hi rend="underline">R. Pallmann</hi>. Die Pfahlbauten. Greifswald 1866.))<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I don’t like this book. It is written in order to satisfy the Prussian orthodoxy and the mythologists. But <hi rend="underline">Pallmann</hi> shares my opinion on the Torfschwein. In his book (1866. p. 199. No. 92) he states that it is Asian and that it was imported into Western Europe (by the Phoenicians or the Massaliotes). I think this view is correct and that <hi rend="underline">Rütimeyer</hi> mistook a feral race for a wild indigenous animal.<ref target="#foot_trans.f7"/></p>
<p>Concerning the dog in relation to the wolf and the jackal and the domestic cat compared with the wild cat, I notice that <hi rend="underline">Blasius</hi> (Fauna der Wirbelthiere Deutschlands 1857. Part I. Mammals) has an abundance of material, particularly for the determination of the anatomical behaviour [relation].<ref target="#foot.f8"/> He puts the dog definitely closest to the jackal—less so to the wolf— furthest away from the fox.) I used <hi rend="underline">Blasius</hi> also in 1863 (Darwin’s Lehre.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> p. 177) on rats and mice)</p>
<p>There is an abundance of information on the relation of the horse to the Pliocene Hipparion (Hippotherium) in <hi rend="underline">R. Hensel</hi>. Ueber Hipparion mediterraneum. Abhandlungen der Berliner Akademie 1860. (has also appeared as a reprint) Hipparion links the horse with the normal pachyderms. Also, monstrosities of the foot occur in the horse, which prove the descent.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>You will already know the excellent work. <hi rend="underline">Ernst Haeckel</hi>. Generelle Morphologie der Organismen nach der von Ch. Darwin reformirten Descendenz-Theorie Berlin 1866. 2 vols. (It contains VIII genealogical tables).<ref target="#foot.f11"/> He derives Equus from Hipparion—from Anchitherium and Tapirus</p>
<p>You may also know the work by <hi rend="underline">Ed. von Martens</hi> (a native of Würtemberg who accompanied the Prussian maritime expedition to East Asia.) He must have observed much regarding domestic animals, since <hi rend="underline">Weinland</hi> encouraged him to do so. Correspondence from <hi rend="underline">Martens</hi> in <hi rend="underline">Weinland’s</hi> “Thiergarten” 1864. p. 116 says that <hi rend="underline">Martens</hi> never encountered Sus pliciceps, the Japan pig, in China or Japan, and that he considers it a domestic variety that lives nowhere in the wild.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> <hi rend="underline">Weinland’s</hi> “Thiergarten” 1864 also contains on pp. 103–105 an essay by <hi rend="underline">Ed. Martens</hi> on Peacocks, Pavo japanicus, and P. cristatus.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> (He studied peacocks in Japan and China.)</p>
<p>I find in Tschudi “Thierleben der Alpenwelt”. (edit. V.) 1860<ref target="#foot.f14"/> p. 283 the following passage, which will interest you. <quote type="quote"> “Prof. Dr. Heer encountered the <hi rend="underline">bedbug</hi> (Ac. lectul.) on the upper alpine pastures of Seetz in the nest of a moss carder-bee<ref target="#foot.f15"/> far away from a human settlement—which seems to this scholar also to go against the assumption that every parasite is of foreign (Indian) origin.” </quote></p>
<p>—I think, on the contrary, that the bedbug went astray on the pasture—and was looking for other food—sucking from insects, as its first ancestors did! —a series of essays by Professor <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> in Vienna, “Botanische Streifzüge auf dem Gebiete der Culturgeschichte” have appeared in the Sitzungsberichte der K. K. Akademie (scientific-mathematical class) 1857–1859 (and perhaps even later).<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>The 1st part contains “Nutritional plants of man” It contains a map of the earth with the “bromatorische Linie” that <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> formulated.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> The eastern bromatorial line clearly goes from England to the Moluccas. The western hemisphere shows no such clear line, the clearest line is one from Mexico to Brazil.</p>
<p>You will be interested in this map. The question presents itself <hi rend="underline">why?</hi>; why are there these big lines in which plants <hi rend="underline">store</hi> nutriments <hi rend="underline">in abundance</hi>?!-- But I think you will rather oppose <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> or doubt! According to <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi> Australia has nutritional plants only on its southern tip (and thus only colonists!?— the old indigenous Australian flora would thereby be completely abromatorial.</p>
<p>(The 2nd and 3rd part of the “Streifzüge” will be of less interest to you.) Even more so part 4 “The plants of ancient Egypt” with IX illustrations with copies of Egyptian plant images, e.g. Lotus, Cyperus, Vitis etc.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>You may perhaps also be interested in <hi rend="underline">Unger</hi>, Beiträge zur Physiologie der Pflanzen (Sitzungsberichte vol. XXV. 1841) No. VIII on the secretion of lime, No. IX the secretion of wax. No. X the honey dew created by Aphis (from Calotropis) in Egypt.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>I also mention the recent works by Dr. <hi rend="underline">Kerner</hi> in Innsbruck (Tyrolia) on the cultivation of Alpine plants and their transmutation into lowland varieties. Although I haven’t read the book I have heard that <hi rend="underline">Kerner</hi> transmuted 5 alpina by cultivation into so-called other species (of the lowlands) Aster alpinus, Potentilla frigida etc. (<hi rend="underline">A. Kerner</hi>. The cultivation of Alpine plants, Innsbruck 1864)<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>Further, I mention that I have arrived at the following opinions through reading your work:</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>the Ratafia cherry (Variation. p. 439)</p>
<p>le griottier de Toussaint (" " p. 440)</p> </figure> 
<p>are one and the same with Prunus (cerasus) semperflorens Ehrh.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> <hi rend="underline">J. L. Christ</hi> (the best of our older pomologists) already knew this variety in 1794. He obtained it in 1794 from France as Cerise de la Toussaint<ref target="#foot.f22"/></p>
<p>Finally I mention Dr. <hi rend="underline">G. Jaeger’s</hi> zoogeographical work in “<hi rend="underline">Ausland</hi>” 1867 No. 6 p. 121.) He shows that “The salamandrians share the same northern ancestry with the Miocene flora of Europe, North America, Japan. The 3 levels perennibranchiates, derotremes, salamandrians still live together only in the Northeast-America-region from Canada down to Mexico. (Today in Europe and Japan the graduated series has already broken up)”<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p>
<p>With kind regards | most honoured Sir | Yours sincerely | Dr.  Rolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see part I: 546–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Rolle refers to the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Victor Carus</ref> (Carus trans. 1868). The first volume was published in December 1867 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5726.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Eduard Koch, 11 December 1867</ref>), and the second in July 1868; however, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2732.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eduard Koch</ref> told CD that he had published the first twenty sheets of the second volume earlier, so that German subscribers would not have to wait for too long (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6284.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Eduard Koch, 21 July 1868</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 68, where CD suggested that the wild <hi rend="italic">Sus Indicus</hi>, a group of which he believed <hi rend="italic">Sus scrofa palustris</hi>, the Torfschwein (turbary pig), was a member, formerly ranged from Europe to China. CD omitted this suggestion in the second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 1: 71).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6704.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rolle 1863</ref>, pp. 127–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rolle 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Rolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig Rütimeyer</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Desor</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6040.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferdinand Keller</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6474.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reinhold Pallman</ref>. Pallman’s book on Pfahlbauten (lake-dwellings) was Pallman 1866.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Rolle refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rütimeyer 1861</ref>, pp. 33ff. Massaliots: natives or inhabitants of Massalia (modern Marseilles), a Greek colony founded around 600 <hi rend="smallCaps">BCE</hi> on the Mediterranean coast of southern France (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f7">Rolle refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rütimeyer 1861</ref>, pp. 33ff. Massaliots: natives or inhabitants of Massalia (modern Marseilles), a Greek colony founded around 600 <hi rend="smallCaps">bce</hi> on the Mediterranean coast of southern France (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 15–48. Rolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_487.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Heinrich Blasius</ref> and to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Blasius 1857</ref>. ‘Anatomischen Verhaltens’ (anatomical behaviour) was evidently a slip of the pen for ‘anatomischen Verhaeltniss’ (anatomical relation).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6704.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rolle 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 50. Roller refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hensel 1860</ref>. This was also published by the Berlin Academy of Sciences as a separate work in 1860.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Rolle refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4973.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 11 January 1866</ref>, n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Rolle refers to Martens 1864b. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5046.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Friedrich Weinland</ref> was editor of the periodial, <hi rend="italic">Der Thiergarten.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 290–2. Rolle refers to Martens 1864a. <hi rend="italic">Pavo cristatus</hi> is the Indian peafowl. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eduard von Martens</ref> argued that <hi rend="italic">P. muticus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">P. japanicus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">P. javanicus</hi> were synonyms. He also considered that <hi rend="italic">P. japanicus</hi> was an improper name, as peafowl were not found wild in Japan. <hi rend="italic">Pavo muticus</hi> is the green peafowl.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tschudi 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><hi rend="italic">Acanthia lectularia</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Cimex lectularius.</hi> The moss carder-bee is <hi rend="italic">Bombus muscorum.</hi> Tschudi referred to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oswald Heer</ref>. ‘Seetz’ is probably Séez, a village near Bourg St Maurice in the Alps of south-eastern France (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7766.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Times atlas</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Rolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Franz Unger</ref> and Unger 1857a, 1857b, 1858, and 1859 (Botanical expeditions in the field of cultural history).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Bromatorische linie: bromatorial line. ‘Bromatorische’ was a neologism derived from the ancient Greek ‘broma’ (food) and ‘horos’ (boundary or limit). See Unger 1857a, p. 253.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><hi rend="italic">Cyperus</hi>: the papyrus genus. <hi rend="italic">Vitis</hi>: the vine genus.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Rolle refers to the last part of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Unger 1854–61</ref>, in particular to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Unger 1854–61</ref>, pp. 519–30 (the volume number is in fact 43). Unger referred to <hi rend="italic">Calotropis procera</hi>, the mudar tree (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Unger 1854–61</ref>, pp. 528–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Rolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2677.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anton Kerner von Marilaun</ref> and Kerner von Marilaun 1864.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">Rolle refers to Carus trans. 1868, 1: 439, 440. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 347–8. <hi rend="italic">Prunus cerasus</hi> L. var. <hi rend="italic">semperflorens</hi> (Ehrh.) is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. cerasus</hi>, the dwarf cherry.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Rolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Ludwig Christ</ref> and probably to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1395.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christ 1794</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">Rolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Jäger</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4125.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jäger 1867</ref>. However, the quotation is at best a paraphrase from the specified publication; it is also inaccurate. Derotreme: one of the Derotremata, ‘a group of urodele batrachians, having gill-slits or branchial apertures, instead of external gill-tufts’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). Perennibranchiate: tailed amphibians that retain their gills throughout life; the division Perennibranchia or Perennibranchiata is now obsolete.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>