<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5226">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   1 and 3 October 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19612</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5226 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5226.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5226.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp inc †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> Möller (1915–21) 2: 93–4 (German translation) </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 142: 99; DAR 157a: 103</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>142: 99,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>157a: 53</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Desterro, Brazil</placeName>
            <date when="1866-10-01">1 Oct 1866</date>
            <date when="1866-10-03">3 Oct 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses dimorphism of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi>; one form has 99% sterile anthers. Has found three kinds of fertile anthers.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oxalis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro, Brazil</placeName>
                    <date>Octbr. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1866.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In your last letter (of May 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>) you wished me to observe whether Oxalis here exhibits different forms.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I already wrote you that in one of our species I found the relative lengths of the styli and stamens to be variable; I have now satisfied myself that this species is dimorphic.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In both the forms the stigmas reach to, or project a little beyond, the mouth of the calyx and the longer stamens are fully one third longer than the styli. The shorter stamens in one form are about half as long, whereas in the other they are about as long as the styli.— Thus far the species offers no particular interest; but there is one circumstance which renders it highly curious. At least 99 per cent of the plants of the second form have perfectly sterile anthers, not producing a single pollen-grain. Specimens of this form having all the anthers of all their flowers fertile are extremely rare. There are three different estates of the anthers: with good pollen—with small aborted pollen-grains—and without pollen; they blend into one another by insensible steps; (thus you may find anthers with only two or three good pollen-grains); but notwithstanding they are generally to be distinguished even without the aid of the microscope, the fertile anthers being bright yellow, those with aborted pollen-grains pale yellow and the pollen-less anthers white.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Now in nine stalks the flowers showed the following combinations of the different anthers:</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>In the first form the anthers are always fertile; but even here, as in the fertile anthers of the second form there is among the good pollen a large amount of aborted pollen-grains.</p>
<p>In some rather rare specimens of the second form,—but only, as far as I know, among those with sterile anthers,—the length of the stamens is very variable; (such were casually the few plants, which I had examined, when writing my last letter).<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Sometimes, in a single flower the longer stamens are hardly as long, and the shorter ones half as long as the styli; but even in those specimens the stamens and styli of the majority of flowers use to show the characteristic lengths of the form.</p>
<p>It is not very rare to find one or two of the white pollen-less anthers transformed into small leaflets, and I met with a single plant, (now in my garden), in which all the anthers are transformed into petala-like leaves, sometimes exceeding ten in number; the ovaries form five open leaves with green stigmas on the tip, but without ovula, and in the midst of these ovarial leaves there is a great number of petala-like leaves, among which sometimes some sepala may be distinguished.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Although the plant is extremely common (thousands flourishing in the very streets of our town) I have not yet been able to find a single seed-capsule. This sterility may be owing in part to the circumstance of the two forms but seldom growing mingled.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> You may find your way bordered, for a mile or more, by one of the two forms exclusively, which then suddenly is substituted by the other.</p>
<p>A second very common species of <hi rend="underline">Oxalis</hi>, with small yellow flowers, is monomorphic, the styli reaching to the level of the longer stamens; this species produces plenty of seed-capsules.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Of a third species with fine crimson flowers, ressembling in shape, size and colour those of Linum grandiflorum, I have as yet seen only one plant, in which the styli were intermediate in length between the two sets of stamens; although the stigmas of all the flowers were densely covered with pollen, I found no seed-capsules; thus I am inclined to think that it will prove dimorphic or trimorphic.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>In short, I hope to have an opportunity of examining a fourth species of Oxalis with woody stem.—</p>
<p>To the list of dimorphic plants I may add a <hi rend="underline">Cordia</hi>, of which I enclose a short- styled as well as a long-styled specimen; as soon as they are ripe, I shall send you seeds of either form.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>In my last letter (of Aug. 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>) I alluded to the circumstance of brightly coloured seeds remaining attached to the valves of the capsules after their opening.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I have since found two more plants, in which this is the case. One is a twining Leguminosa, perhaps a Rhynchosia, with black and red seeds. The other is a tree, probably belonging to the Mimoseae, which after the opening of the seed-capsules presents a truly magnificent aspect, being covered over and over with large and elegant curls of pale yellowish silk, (the spirally contracted valves) beset with brilliant red pearls.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Octbr. 3.</hi> Yesterday I procured to calculate the number of seeds contained in a large capsule of an Orchid (Maxillaria?); the seeds weighed 42<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> grains; I extended half a grain of the seeds into a narrow heap and by counting a small portion I found them to be 20661, so that the capsule would contain the prodigious quantity of 1.756.440 seeds!<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>Hoping that this will find you in good health I am dear Sir with the most sincere respect | Yours very truly | Fritz Müller</p>
<p>Do the aërial roots of all the species of Catasetum grow perpendicularly upwards into the air, as they do in our Cat. mentosum?<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.5 the longer stamens … the styli.— 1.7] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.10 Specimens of … anthers white. 1.17] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 In the first … pollen-grains. 3.3] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.2 —the length … variable;] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.2 very] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.2 small leaflets] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.2 I have not … seed-capsule.] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.4 You may … the other. 6.5] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 A second] ‘[’ <hi rend="italic">added before, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 monomorphic 7.2] <hi rend="italic">underl red &amp; blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.3 seed-capsules.] ‘]’ <hi rend="italic">added after, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 Of a third … form.— 10.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>10.1 To the list … form.— 10.3] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon, crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>12.1 <hi rend="italic">Octbr. 3.</hi> … very truly 13.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 23 May 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 2 August 1866</ref> and n. 2. After further observations, Müller later came to regard this species of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> as trimorphic (see n. 6, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his work on dimorphic and trimorphic flowers, CD noted any differences in the pollen of different forms of flowers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>). CD had recently been interested in the observations made by his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Erasmus Darwin</ref> on the differences in the size of pollen-grains in <hi rend="italic">Rhamnus cathartica</hi>, but was unsure of the significance of such differences. William had suggested that <hi rend="italic">R. cathartica</hi> was an example of a dimorphic species becoming dioecious (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5131.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 22 June [1866]</ref> and n. 3). CD included Müller’s description of this species of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 180–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Müller initially had noted considerable variation in the length of the styles, even in flowers of the same plant (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 2 August 1866</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 180, CD mentioned that the stamens in some of the flowers were ‘partially converted into petals’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Müller eventually reinterpreted the cause of sterility in this species of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi>, as well as its dimorphic status, in light of CD’s experimental results with the illegitimate offspring of various heterostyled species. He concluded that the plants might be the variable and sterile offspring of a single form of a trimorphic species, accidentally introduced and afterwards propagated asexually (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 180–1; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 31 October 1868</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 6439).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD discussed this monomorphic species of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 181–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 180, CD referred to a trimorphic <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> with red flowers that, according to Müller, had never produced seed.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The specimens have not been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, [before 10 December 1866]</ref> and n. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD cut out the following paragraph and pasted it into his Experimental notebook along with his own notes on brightly coloured seeds (DAR 157a: 80; the fragment has since been moved to DAR 157a: 103). For Müller’s earlier comments on the topic, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 2 August 1866</ref> and nn. 14 and 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Müller evidently sent specimens of these seeds, but they have not been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5295.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 5 December [1866]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, [before 10 December 1866]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The sketch is reproduced at approximately 80 per cent of its original size.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><hi rend="italic">Catasetum mentosum</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">C. atratum.</hi></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>