<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5478">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Joseph Trimble Rothrock to Asa Gray   31 March 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10576</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5478 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5478.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5478.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †, † (by CD)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 218</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 218</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4089.xml">Rothrock, J. T.</persName>
                <placeName>McVeytown, Pa.</placeName>
                <date when="1867-03-31">31 Mar 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Answers to CD’s questions on expressions among the Atnah and Espyox Indians of Nass River [see <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>, pp. 22, 232, 252, 260].</p> 
            <p>Discusses the debate in America over the relationship among Indian tribes. JTR does not believe Indians are all of one race; they are as varied as Europeans.</p>
            <p>[Forwarded to CD by Asa Gray.]</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Atnah Indians</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Espyox Indians</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Europeans</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Indian tribes</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Nass River</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Veytown [Pennsylvania]</placeName>
                    <date>Mch 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1867</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Doctor</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Some of Mr Darwins questions I feel safe in answering, Such only I attempt Any reply to.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> all parties add that the Answers apply especially to the Atnahs and Espyox tribes on the Nasse River of North So Western N.Aa.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Neither tribe had much previous acquaintance with the Whites.— in fact the Espyox had not previous to my going among them seen half a dozen whites. You will observe I found the indians much like other men. I must say I nowhere saw the ideal, taciturn immovable indian of Mr Coopers conception.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>Question 1. Yes</p>
<p>"  2 —</p>
<p>"  3 Many of them do, Not all</p>
<p>"  4 Yes</p>
<p>"  5 —</p>
<p>"  6 Yes</p>
<p>"  7 Sometimes. Generally in fact. Among the</p>
<p>Siceanees<ref target="#foot.f4"/>—a tribe adjoining the</p>
<p>Atnahs Question 8 Yes, decidedly<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>"  9 —</p>
<p>"  10 —</p>
<p>"  11 Exactly So.</p>
<p>"  12 Laughter is often excessive, tho I know of but one instance in which tears were shed from that cause, real or feigned grief produce them often enough from the women. Question 13 —</p>
<p>"  14 Yes, just as a white child<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>"  15 Yes, and these knowing indians, look for these</p>
<p>signs</p>
<p>"  16 —</p>
<p>17 Vertical nod is usual, lateral not so common though I have seen it.</p> </figure> 
<p><hi rend="underline">Mr Darwin may depend on the correctness of these Answers, I am sure of them</hi></p>
<p>On my return home from the North West, I was unable to reconcile my views with those of the late D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morton, but disliked to adopt those opposed to his. I knew him to be an authority on the subject, and therefore kept the matter in a mental status quo. He says that “sixteen years of almost daily comparisons have only confirmed him in the opinions announced in his Crania Americana, that all the American nations are of one race (excepting the Esquimaux) and that this race is peculiar and distinct from all others.”<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Col Hamilton Smith says it is vain to assert that all American races excepting the Esquimaux have sprung originally from one stock.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>If by this Smith means that Indians differ from one another as much as Europeans do, I at once adopt his view. J Aitken Meigs of Philad in a paper Read before the Philadelphia Acad. of Nat. Sci. May 1866 to my mind completely upsets Mortons opinion, and is I think in the main correct. If M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> D. has not this paper I am sure he would be interested in it.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Meigs is unable to understand why the Stickine river indians and some of those farther north do not always flatten the infant skull. The reason is plain, these tribes are warlike, and come south among the flat-headed tribes for slaves. Finding their captives regard the compressed skull as a mark of aristocratic blood; they (the Northern tribes) in contempt flatten the heads sometimes of their own female children, and usually the heads of both sexes when born in slavery. Hence the deformed cranium among them is the mark of inferiority and the sign of a slave.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Should there happen to be any other facts in my possession relating to the ends, which would interest you or Mr D. I beg that you will command them. Did you receive about 150 Species of NW. plants from me some months ago? I sent them by Adams Express.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Yours Always | J. Trimble Rothrock</p>
<p>I shall soon have some answers from Wyman—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> from memory— And he will send copies of your queries South to trusty persons</p>
<p>A.G.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.2 Atnahs] ‘Atnaks?’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
                <note>1.3 Espyox] ‘Espyox(?)’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
                <note>1.3 Nasse] ‘Nasse?’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Keep 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Page for Descent of Man<ref target="#foot.f13"/> | cause of not flattening the Head’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Rothrock refers to CD’s queries about expression. CD evidently sent a copy of the queries to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> with a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5424.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 28 February 1867</ref>, but that letter has not been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5462.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 26 March 1867</ref>). In his letter of 26 March 1867, Gray told CD that he recently had fifty copies of the queries printed. Rothrock probably had a handwritten copy of the queries. For a later, printed, version of the queries, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, Appendix IV. Rothrock had been in British Columbia as a member of the Western Union Telegraph Expedition from 1865 to 1866 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1727.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DAB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The Nass river of western British Columbia, Canada, flows about 236 mi (380 km) south-west through the Coast Mountains to the Pacific Ocean north of Prince Rupert. The name ‘Atnah’ is recorded as a synonym for the Shuswap (Secwepemc) nation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3701.xml">Hodge ed. 1907–10</ref>, 2: 561), but their territory was in south-central and eastern British Columbia. ‘Espyox’ may refer to the Kispiox (Gitanspayaxw) tribe of the Gitksan nation, who had territories on the upper Nass (Sterritt <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1998, p. 99). Much of the land around the Nass river was the territory of the Nisga’a nation. For more on tribal boundaries in this area, see Sterritt <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1998.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Rothrock refers to the characterisation of Native Americans in the novels of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1061.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Fenimore Cooper</ref> (for more on Cooper’s portrayal of Native Americans, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3880.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">House 1965</ref>, pp. 47–71).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘Siceanee’: probably the Sekani; the Long Grass band of the Sekani had territory near the headwaters of the Nass river, and were known to intermarry with the Kispiox (Sterritt <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1998, pp. 54–5). CD noted Rothrock’s information on sneering in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 252 and 260.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 232, CD cited Rothrock on the expression of determination or obstinacy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 233, CD noted the affirmative reply about pouting in children, but did not cite Rothrock by name.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3419.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel George Morton</ref> had written a monograph, <hi rend="italic">Crania americana</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">S. G. Morton 1839</ref>), in which he argued that there was only one distinct American race, based on an analysis of human skulls. The statement quoted by Rothrock was made in an article, ‘Some observations on the ethnography and archæology of the American aborigines’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">S. G. Morton 1846</ref>, p. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Hamilton Smith</ref> argued in <hi rend="italic">Natural history of the human species</hi> that several migrations of people from different Old World origins to America had occurred (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7255.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. H. Smith 1848</ref>; for the statement paraphrased by Rothrock, see p. 251). ‘Esquimaux’ refers to Inuit people.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In a paper reviewing the ethnological literature on American races and reporting on his examination of the skulls in Morton’s collection (Meigs 1866), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Aitken Meigs</ref> challenged Morton’s view of a single cranial type for all Americans. CD’s annotated copy of an offprint of Meigs 1866 is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Meigs described the ‘Stikanes or Cowitchins’ (Cowichan tribe or Quw’utsun’ people) of Vancouver Island as practising a form of head-binding resulting in a conical head shape (Meigs 1866, p. 212). Rothrock evidently thought Meigs was referring to people from the area of the Stikine River (Tahltan nation) in north-western British Columbia. For more on the practice of slavery among Native American tribes in British Columbia, see Hodge ed. 1910, 2: 598; for the practice of head-flattening, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1: 96–7, 465.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Adams Express Company.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The postscript to CD was added by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>. No record of answers from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jeffries Wyman</ref> to the queries has been found, nor was Wyman mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Expression.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD used Rothrock’s answers to the queries about expression in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, which had originally been planned as a part of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5420.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 26 February [1867]</ref> and nn. 5 and 6).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>