<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5662">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Benjamin Clarke<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   1 November [1870]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14879</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5662 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5662.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5662.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">AL incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="AL">inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 261.11: 26 (EH 88206077)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>261.11: 26 (EH 88206077)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_944.xml">Clarke, Benjamin</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1870-11-01">1 Nov [1870]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends CD some Indian corn seeds to demonstrate the extreme effect sometimes producible on progeny by the mutilation of a parent.</p>
            <p>Writes of a recent book.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">corn</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">India</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>November 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I wrote the foregoing letter before I received yours of Oct. 20 containing the Post Office Order for 10s.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> &amp; I have now only to add that if the Zoological part of the work appears to you of any value you will be receiving back a part of that which you gave when you subscribed to the Relief Fund of the Royal Society.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I enclose to you a few seeds of a plant of Indian Corn which was 3-stemmed without a trace of a male flower, the central stem terminating in a soft slightly hooked spine &amp; one if not both the lateral terminating in cobs. It was artificially fertilised &amp; ripened 10 cobs growing in somewhat unfavourable circumstances being shaded &amp; sparingly watered.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It belongs to the continental 6-weeks variety procured by Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Gibbs &amp; Co.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> &amp; was raised from seed produced last year by cutting off the entire of the male flowers of one plant about a week before flowering &amp; fertilising the plant with the flowers of another. This was done with a view of producing varieties by pruning or mutilation as it may be called &amp; it appears that <hi rend="underline">the extreme effect can be produced in one year</hi> on some of the plants although on a very few; while some of the progeny show no diminution of male flowers;—in these latter there was apparently increased vigour of growth. I will only add that if you grow this seed you will I expect have an opportunity of witnessing this phenomenon &amp; by repeating the experiment increase the number of female plants in the progeny.</p>
<p>You will observe at the back of the title page that science does not in any degree diminish my faith in the bible &amp; that in fact science &amp; the New Testament are according to my views quite in harmony—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> My reason for placing <hi rend="underline">Man</hi> in the system of the Mammalia is given at page 44.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The correspondent is identified from the handwriting, and from the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Benjamin Clarke, 12 March 1867</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The year is established by the reference to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3828.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Post Office</ref> order (see n. 3, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The letters have not been found. CD recorded a payment in his Account books–cash account (Down House MS) of 10<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> under the heading ‘B. Clarke. Syst. Bot. &amp; Zooly.’ for 20 October 1870.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Clarke refers to his <hi rend="italic">On systematic botany and zoology</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clarke 1870</ref>). The botanical part of the work had already been published as <hi rend="italic">A new arrangement of phanerogamous plants</hi> (Clarke 1866); the zoological part was ready for the press in early 1867 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Benjamin Clarke, 12 March 1867</ref>) but not published until 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clarke 1870</ref>). CD’s donation to the Relief Fund of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref> is referred to in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5460.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Benjamin Clarke, 25 March 1867</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15). For a brief history of the Royal Society’s Scientific Relief Fund, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6563.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Record of the Royal Society of London</hi></ref>, p. 111.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his letter of 25 March 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15), Clarke had outlined a procedure for breeding a predominantly female variety of maize by emasculating the breeding stock repeatedly for several years.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Thomas Gibbs and Company were seedsmen; they had premises on the corner of Piccadilly and Halfmoon Street, London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1870).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">On the verso of the title page of Clarke 1866 is a poem on the splendour of God as manifest in tropical vegetation. A further poem referring to the ‘power of God’ was added to the 1870 publication. Both poems were signed B.C.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Clarke qualified his classification of humans among the Mammalia as follows (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clarke 1870</ref>, p. 44): <quote type="quote"> By including Bimana in this classification it is not intended to say that man was derived from Quadrumana as the other orders of Mammalia it is understood were derived from the Orders below them; Jeremiah, Chap. I, v. 5, is clearly opposed to such a supposition; the angelic host would, if incarnate, of course be classed with Bimana. </quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>