<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4934A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. D. Walsh   12 November 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20773</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4934A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4934A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4934A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago (Riley bequest of 1948)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_133.xml">Field Museum</repository>
                    <collection>Riley bequest of 1948</collection>
                    <idno/>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4944.xml">Walsh, B. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Rock Island, Ill.</placeName>
                <date when="1865-11-12">12 Nov 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Acknowledges CD’s paper on "Climbing plants".</p> 
<p>Mentions Asa Gray’s complimentary notice in Silliman’s Journal [<hi rend="italic">Am. J. Sci. and Arts</hi> 2d ser. 40 (1865): 273–82].</p>  
<p>His difficulty in understanding how males of <hi rend="italic">Daphnia</hi> or any other genus can produce eggs. If there is no impregnation, how can there be sexual organs? Why call one form male and another female?</p> 
            <p>He has sent CD his paper on "the new Potato Bug".</p>
            <p>Will soon send "On Phytophagi Species &amp; Unity of Coloration". [phytophagic!?]</p>
            <p>Complaints about practices of the English Post Office.</p> 
<p>His current research and description of the <hi rend="italic">rationale</hi> of his experiments.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Daphnia</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">potato bug</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbing plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Am. J. Sci. and Arts</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1865</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Silliman, Benjamin, Sr 1865</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">eggs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Post Office</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rock Island. Illinois U.S.</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 12, 1865</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas. Darwin Esq.</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I have not answered sooner your letter of July 9 because, as your health was so poor, I was afraid of worrying you by frequent scribbling.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I received your Paper on Climbing Plants &amp; was very much interested in it.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I had always supposed that Climbers had some unknown means of perceiving where there was a twig, or other support suitable for them to grasp, &amp; went straight to their mark as a wolf goes straight at a deer. But this discovery of their sweeping circles &amp; groping in the dark for support, like a blind Cyclops, is very astonishing. And yet, when we consider that plants have no eyes, it is evidently the only possible way, &amp; like the other ways of Nature so beautifully simple. The gradations too that you trace between the different kinds of Climbers are of high philosophical interest. Don’t be afraid that I shall ever find anything which you publish “not worth reading”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> How you manage to get through such an amount of work is a mystery to me. If I did not know that you had been my Contemporary at college, I should suppose that you must be at least a hundred years old.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> An ordinary life-time seems too brief for what you have accomplished.</p>
<p>I conclude that you are aware that there was a long notice of your Paper in Silliman’s Journal by Asa Gray—the July number if I recollect right.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> He speaks of it in very high terms.</p>
<p>The extract I sent you as from a work by <hi rend="underline">Gen. Paez</hi> was, I find, from a work by <hi rend="underline">a son of Gen. Paez.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/> My memory played me false.</p>
<p>I don’t see—with my entomological ideas—how it can be possible for the <hi rend="underline">males</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Daphnia</hi> or any other genus to produce eggs. There may be dimorphous female forms in the genus, both of which produce eggs, but to call a form which oviposits a male seems to me simply an abuse of language. According to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Minor, quoting from Wagner, both male &amp; female <hi rend="underline">Daphnia</hi> oviposit “without sexual influence”, i.e. as I understand it without copulation or any other mode of impregnation.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Why then call one form a male &amp; the other a female? If there is no impregnation, I don’t see how there can exist any male sexual organs; for, if they had primordial existence, they would have long ago been obliterated by disuse. But probably this may be all very plain to you, though to me, who know but little of Natural History out of my own special department, it is unintelligible. Please, if not too much trouble, lighten my darkness. Perhaps the supposed males are really hermaphrodites.</p>
<p>I sent you a few days ago a Paper of mine on “the new Potato Bug”, out of which you may possibly glean a useful fact or two.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have another Paper just ready for the Press “On Phytophagic Species &amp; Unity of Coloration”, which will perhaps be of more interest to you. As soon as printed, I shall of course do myself the pleasure to forward you a copy.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> By the way I was vexed at finding out some months ago, that your Post-office is so rigidly stringent, that they do not allow simple errors of the press to be corrected in MS. in the margin without charging letter postage;<ref target="#foot.f10"/> &amp; that I had in this way, through my thoughtless ignorance, put M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bates to some trouble.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I shall know better for the future. Here every body does it, &amp; everybody puts as many Pamphlets as they please under a single stamp, provided they don’t exceed the just weight. Whereas I find your Post office requires a separate package &amp; separate stamp for every Pamphlet, even if they each contain but four pages.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I have been continuing this year my investigations into the Dimorphism of <hi rend="underline">Cynipidæ</hi>, &amp; though there are many mysteries still to solve, yet I think I have thrown some additional light upon the question.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I find that (unless I am mistaken) the agamous dimorphous ♀ form <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> o.s. produced galls out of which came many specimens of the same agamous female form, (A single ♀ of course out of a single gall, this gall being monothalamous,) &amp; also one ♀ specimen of the copulative ♀ form <hi rend="underline">spongifica.</hi> Assuming the truth of the above—and to be quite certain of the truth I have been repeating my experiments this autumn—two consequences follow:—1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. that <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">spongifica</hi> are necessarily the same species, (as I had concluded from other evidence,) since one gives birth to the other, &amp; 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. that an agamous ♀ form may generate the same agamous ♀ form for at least two successive generations &amp; probably for more. My present idea is, that the supposed agamous <hi rend="underline">Cynipidæ</hi> generate only agamous ♀ ♀ for an indefinite series of years, say 4 or 5 or 8 or 10, &amp; that then comes forth a brood ♂ ♀ of the copulative dimorphous form. There is an analogy to this in <hi rend="underline">Aphis</hi>, some species of which produce a long series of agamous apterous ♀ generations all through the summer &amp; then in the autumn the winged copulative ♂ ♂ ♀ ♀, while others produce the copulative &amp; the agamous forms promiscuously all through the season.</p>
<p>You may perhaps like to know the <hi rend="underline">rationale</hi> of my experiments. They proceed upon a postulation, which I have ascertained by long observation &amp; which you must take my word for, viz. that <hi rend="underline">Cynips</hi> scarcely ever fly at all but breed from year to year on the same tree. A tree that is infested by a particular species one year, will always have more or less galls of the same species on it the following year; &amp; in the case of those particular kinds of gall (such as <hi rend="underline">spongifica</hi>, <hi rend="underline">ficus</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">poda</hi>) which hang on the tree more than 12 months, the particular boughs which bear the old galls are very generally, as I have repeatedly noticed, those which bear the new galls.</p>
<p>First, then, I select Black Oak Trees, which are isolated from others, &amp; which I know have borne no <hi rend="underline">spongifica</hi> galls the preceding year. Then in the autumn I place upon each of these trees 8 or 10 lively <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi>, sometimes as high up as I can reach on the trunk, sometimes on the overhanging boughs, taking notes in my Journal of the particular trees &amp; where I placed the insects. Of three trees experimented on thus last autumn, one bore no galls at all, one, a rather small tree, where I had put the insects on the trunk, was covered all over with the galls this spring, so that I had to climb to get them, &amp; the third—a very large tree with overhanging boughs, where I had put all the Cynips on certain particular boughs—had about a dozen galls on these particular boughs, which formed perhaps <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>20</mn></mfrac></math></formula> part of the whole tree, &amp; none whatever on any of the other boughs. Of course, if these galls had been made, not by my bred <hi rend="underline">Cynips</hi>, but by wandering individuals, the chances are some 19 to 1 against their selecting the same particular boughs as I did.</p>
<p>I carefully preserved alive the dimorphous ♀ agamous forms raised in each of these cases, &amp; have placed them this autumn on isolated oaks again, so as to find out what they will produce next year. It is tedious having to wait so long for the fruits of one’s labor, but it seems to me the only possible way of solving the enigma. I have tried enclosing the insects on the trees in gauze bags, &amp; the hateful boys will not let them alone.</p>
<p>But I shall tire you to death. Adieu, &amp; may your health soon improve. | Yours ever very truly, | Benj. D. Walsh</p>
<p>P.S. Has M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lubbock arrived at any conclusions on this subject?<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4867.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 9 July [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had sent Walsh his paper <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> earlier in the year (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4867.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 9 July [1865]</ref>). No presentation list for the paper has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4867.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 9 July [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4778.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. D. Walsh, 1 March 1865</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The first part of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray’s</ref> review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> appeared in the September 1865 issue of the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3042.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1865–6</ref>). The journal was also known as ‘Silliman’s Journal’ after its founder, Benjamin Silliman. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4930.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 6 November 1865</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4839.xml">letter of 29 May 1865</ref>, Walsh had discussed a passage from <hi rend="italic">Wild scenes in South America, or life in the llanos of Venezuela</hi> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6469.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramón Páez</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paez 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Walsh refers to the review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1865</ref> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6346.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Chester Minor</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5471.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Minor 1865</ref>). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. D. Walsh, 29 May 1865</ref> and n. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8151.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walsh 1865</ref>. Walsh’s article ‘The new potato bug, and its natural history’ described a beetle, <hi rend="italic">Doryphora decemlineata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Leptinotarsa decemlineata</hi>, the Colorado potato beetle), that had recently migrated from the Rocky Mountain region into the state of Illinois. Walsh suggested that the insect fed on wild species of <hi rend="italic">Solanum</hi>, and had migrated eastward as cultivated varieties of <hi rend="italic">Solanum</hi>, such as domestic potatoes, were introduced into the Plains region. For a discussion of Walsh’s research on the potato beetle, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7340.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sorensen 1995</ref>, pp. 121–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The second part of Walsh’s article ‘On phytophagic varieties and phytophagic species’ was published in the December 1865 issue of <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Philadelphia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walsh 1864–5</ref>). CD’s heavily annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Walsh had sent CD the first part of the paper earlier in 1865 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4778.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. D. Walsh, 1 March 1865</ref> and n. 14); for CD’s comments on it, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref> and nn. 3 and 5. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. D. Walsh, 29 May 1865</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For periodicals carrying the newspaper stamp, British postal regulations prohibited any writing or other marks on the publication, except for the name and address of the recipient; an additional postage of 2<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> was charged for a breach of the rule. Each publication had to carry a separate stamp. Offprints of articles, and periodicals published at intervals greater than thirty days, would usually travel by book post. A book packet could contain any number of separate publications, but no letters or ‘communication of the nature of a letter’; packets containing such communications were charged additional postage (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">British postal guide</hi></ref>, 1 July 1865, pp. 10–14).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Walter Bates</ref>. Walsh had sent copies of some of his papers to Bates earlier in the year (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4792.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. W. Bates, 22 March 1865</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See n. 10, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Walsh had sent CD an article on dimorphism in <hi rend="italic">Cynips</hi> in 1864 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4477.xml">letter from B. D. Walsh, 29 April – 19 May 1864</ref>, and letters to B. D. Walsh, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4640.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 October [1864]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4695.xml">4 December [1864]</ref>). Walsh argued that the gall insect <hi rend="italic">Cynips quercus aciculata</hi>, hitherto regarded as a distinct species, was a dimorphic female form of <hi rend="italic">C. q. spongifica</hi> (Walsh 1864a, pp. 447–8). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4478.xml">letter from B. D. Walsh, 1 March 1865</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 27 March [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD had forwarded Walsh 1864a to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref>, who wrote a brief notice of the paper in the January 1865 issue of <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>, pp. 138–41. Lubbock thought the evidence for dimorphism in <hi rend="italic">Cynips</hi> was inconclusive (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4653.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Lubbock, 3 November 1864</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>