<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9009F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   14 August [1873]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21498</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9009F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9009F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9009F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 26</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 26</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Pantlludw</placeName>
                <date when="1873-08-14">14 Aug [1873]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has found <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus maritima</hi> on the cliffs near Barmouth.</p> 
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Pantlludw | Machynlleth</placeName>
                    <date>Aug 14</date>
                    <salute>Dear Father</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Ruck knew where the Lathyrus maritima grew so Amy &amp; I railed off there; it is near a little place called Llwyngwril near Barmouth on the cliffs— We found it growing in tangled masses—most lovely tho’ it was rather passed. They have the nectar holes just like the ones in the everlasting pea—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I saw a bee going to them &amp; he went to a hole bitten in the base of the keel   Amy &amp; I examined 24 flowers &amp; found in 23 of them this hole was present &amp; on the right hand side (looking at the flower from above). We therefore looked at the nectar holes of 24 of them and in 16 of them the right hole was biggest, in 2 equal or doubtful and in 6 the left bigger   The reason the right is bigger is that the pod in growing out of the stamen tube goes to the right of the loose stamen; and we think the reason of that is that the pod has a slight bend with the convexity towards the right. The right nectar holes is bigger than the left even before the splitting up caused by the growth of the pod. In the everlasting pea, the pod we think also goes to the right of the loose stamen, but the right hole we <hi rend="underline">think</hi> isnt bigger till the splitting begins but we will look at a lot. Why should the bees bite the Maritima but go in the proper way pressing down the keel, in Everlasting Peas—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> They bite quite young buds in Maritima perhaps Maritima has honey in younger buds than the bee can get at in the legitimate way? I suppose you know all this, but it has been great fun discovering it— The droseras had their feed of bread yesterday— I have put bread on the damp moss beside them to compare— I shall look tomorrow.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Tell Jim no family should be without his worm-garden— we have grt fun with ours— we take notes and take tracings of their burrows<ref target="#foot.f5"/>   I think they will lay their eggs as I have two worms and they are in full breeding condition— We find they make a very curly burrow with a blind end and then somehow turn round with their heads towards the entrance   I think we shall make them out— They have made <hi rend="underline">no</hi> castings in the surface of the earth but <hi rend="doubleUnderline">very</hi> small ones in the burrow itself</p>
<p>My love to mother &amp; thank her for her letter— We send you a Maritima | Yrs affec F Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.10 loose stamen] ‘(not always)’ <hi rend="italic">interl pencil</hi></note>
                <note>1.18 The droseras … Darwin 2.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Lathyrus Maritimus’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, 15 August [1873]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Lathyrus maritimus</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">L. japonicus</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">maritimus</hi> (the sea or beach pea). It is found rarely on shingle on the east and south coast of England (for distribution in the British Isles, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Randall 1977</ref>). Francis later found that the species he described was actually <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus sylvestris</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9012.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [16 or 17 August 1873]</ref>). The everlasting pea is either <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus latifolius</hi> (the broad-leaved everlasting pea) or <hi rend="italic">L. sylvestris</hi> (the narrow-leaved everlasting pea; now often called the flat pea); <hi rend="italic">L. sylvestris</hi> is native to the British Isles, while <hi rend="italic">L. latifolius</hi>, a popular garden plant, is naturalised in places (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3801.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Hooker 1870</ref>, p. 104). Francis also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4118.xml">Mary Anne</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1205.xml">Amy Ruck</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">It is now common to describe the orientation of flowers (right, left) from the viewpoint of a legitimate pollinator (that is, one that gets access to pollen and nectar in a way that results in the cross-pollination of flowers). Access to nectar through a hole would not result in pollination, so such visits are referred to as illegitimate. In papilionaceous flowers like those of <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus</hi>, the petals are specialised. Two carina or keel petals form a boat-shape that encloses the sexual parts of the flower; two alae or wing petals are attached to the sides of the keel, and a large central vexillum or standard petal with line and colour guide-marks directs insects to the correct landing position to effect the transfer of pollen. For a detailed description of the floral morphology and kinetics of <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus latifolius</hi> and its insect visitors, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8291.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Westerkamp 1993</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had resumed his experimental work on <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> in mid-June (see ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)). He was studying the powers of digestion of <hi rend="italic">D. rotundifolia</hi> and its reaction to various substances (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9005B.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Mary Treat, 12 August 1873</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">‘Jim’ was a nickname for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref> (letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1205.xml">Amy Ruck</ref> to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref>, [23 April 1873] (DAR 258: 790)). Amy had sent CD information on wormcastings in 1872 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1205.xml">Amy Ruck</ref> to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8168.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[20 January 1872]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8193.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[1 February 1872]</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>