<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11209">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Saville-Kent   25 October 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17722</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11209 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11209.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11209.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 6</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2665.xml">Saville-Kent, William</persName>
                <placeName>Jersey</placeName>
                <date when="1877-10-25">25 Oct 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Enlists CD’s support for a marine biological research institution to be built soon on Jersey.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Jersey</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">marine biological research institution</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>4 Marine Terrace S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Clements | Jersey,</placeName>
                    <date>Oct 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1877.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">To Charles Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>. F.R.S.—</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You will I think be pleased to hear that I have at length a definite prospect of carrying the proposition submitted to you last spring, &amp; the accomplishment of which I may say has been the main object of my ambition during my several years “<hi rend="underline">Apprenticeship</hi>” as Naturalist to the leading English Aquaria—Namely—the establishment of an Institution specially devoted to the interests of Marine Zoology &amp; Pisciculture &amp; that shall place at the disposal of British Naturalists those facilities for pursuing Marine Biological Research which under existing auspices can be obtained no nearer than Naples.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>It would certainly have been more to the credit of the Country &amp; more to my own satisfaction if such an Institution could have been established by Private Munificence instead of through the medium of a Public Company—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Science, however, must nowadays make the most of such opportunities as present themselves &amp; I am only too glad to be able to report to you that the undertaking as set forth in the accompanying Prospectus is on the eve of being carried into execution.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The Society was in fact Registered by the Jersey States<ref target="#foot.f4"/> last Saturday &amp; by January next I anticipate we shall be in a position to commence active building operations. Numerous promises of support have already been received &amp; I am hoping that the Members of the various Scientific Societies will take, if even ever so little, an interest in it. With the view of enlisting such aid I issue the circular letter enclosed—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> As a sure <hi rend="underline">guarantee</hi> that the premises of the Institution shall be used only for <hi rend="underline">Scientific</hi> purposes I may refer you to Clause N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 7 of the accompanying Memorandum of Association.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Should the object &amp; intention of this Institution as now submitted to your notice meet with your approbation to an extent justifying your support of it in any way—or your favourable mention of the same to others interested in the advancement of Marine Biological Science I need scarcely say how grateful I shall be. If again you should at any time have works or papers bearing upon the subject of Marine &amp; general Biology—more especially when edited by <hi rend="underline">yourself</hi>—to spare, your contribution of the same to our Library will be greatly appreciated. In return I shall hope at an early date to be able to render you some assistance through the medium of our Dépôt (see <hi rend="underline">Prospectus</hi>) by the transmission of living or carefully preserved specimens for Museum or other purposes that you may in future require &amp; of which the Channel Islands produce so luxuriant a variety— Assuring you that when in need of such desiderata either personally or for friends my best services will be always at your command.</p>
<p>I remain, My dear Sir | Yours very truly | W Saville Kent.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">P.S</hi> | I am hoping by &amp; by for the full development of the Scientific advantages that this Institution will have to offer, to add to the present <hi rend="underline">Working Committee</hi> a second <hi rend="underline">Technical</hi> one consisting of the more eminent Biologists of the day. Such a Technical Committee should direct the special branches of Scientific investigation pursued in the Laboratories, receive &amp; utilise the Periodical Reports, &amp; by the weight of their authority secure to the Institution that prominent Scientific position I am ambitious that it should eventually attain— Perhaps when the time for the election of such a Technical Committee arrives you might be induced to concede to the Society the lustre &amp; advantages of your high talent as a <hi rend="underline">member</hi> of the same.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Saville-Kent had requested CD’s support to establish an aquarium on Jersey (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10915.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from William Saville-Kent, 26 March 1877</ref>). He had previously worked at the Brighton aquarium and the Manchester aquarium. The <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3478.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Naples Zoological Station</ref> with its large aquarium provided facilities for visiting researchers (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 156–7 and 164). CD had provided substantial support for the Naples station (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9338.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Anton Dohrn, 7 March 1874</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had declined to have his name attached to a proposal for a commercial aquarium, but had offered to consider subscribing to one established purely for scientific purposes (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10917.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to William Saville-Kent, 28 March [1877]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The prospectus has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The States of Jersey is the parliament and government of the British Crown dependency of Jersey in the Channel Islands. In October 1877, Saville-Kent had registered his company under the name of the Channel Island Zoological Station, Museum &amp; Institute of Pisciculture Society Limited (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10406.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harrison 1997</ref>, p. 34).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">This circular has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">This memorandum of association has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>