<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10643">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Moritz Wagner   13 October 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13765</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10643 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10643.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10643.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">2pp inc</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 158</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 148: 198; <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 159 <ref target="#foot.f8"/></bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>148: 198</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Bassett Down letterhead</placeName>
                <date when="1876-10-13">13 Oct 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4916.xml">Wagner, M. F.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on essays by MW [<hi rend="italic">Das Ausland</hi>, May 1875]. Criticises his theory of isolation as source of species change: "But my strongest objection to your theory is that it does not explain the manifold adaptations in structure in every organic being". Believes MW has misunderstood his views: "I believe that all the individuals of a species can be slowly modified within the same district … I do not believe that one species will give birth to two or more new species, as long as they are mingled together within the same district."</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Das Ausland</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Wagner, M. F. 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">individuals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, | Beckenham, Kent [Bassett, Southampton.]</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 13. 1876</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have now finished reading your essays, which have interested me in a very high degree, notwithstanding that I differ much from you on various points.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> For instance several considerations make me doubt whether species are much more variable at one period than at another, except thro’ the agency of changed conditions,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I wish however that I could believe in this doctrine, as it removes many difficulties. But my strongest objection to your theory is that it does not explain the manifold adaptations in structure in every organic being,—for instance in a Picus for climbing trees &amp; catching insects,—or in a Strix for catching animals at night, &amp; so on <hi rend="underline">ad inifinitum</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> No theory is in the least satisfactory to me unless it clearly explains such adaptations. I think that you misunderstand my views on isolation. I believe that all the individuals of a species can be slowly modified within within the same district, in nearly the same manner as man effects by what I have called the process of unconscious selection; as has happened with our <hi rend="underline">English</hi> race horse or our English pointer-dogs.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I do not believe that one species will give birth to two or more new species, as long as they are mingled together within the same district. Nevertheless I cannot doubt that many new species have been simultaneously developed within the same large continental area; and in my ‘Origin of Species’ I endeavoured to explain how two new species might be developed, although they met and intermingled on the <hi rend="underline">borders</hi> of their range.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It would have been a strange fact if I had overlooked the importance of isolation, seeing that it was such cases as that of the Galapagos Archipelago, which chiefly led me to study the origin of species.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In my opinion the greatest error which I have committed, has been not allowing sufficient weight to the direct action of the environment, <hi rend="underline">i.e.</hi> food, climate, &amp;c., independently of natural selection. Modifications thus caused, which are neither of advantage nor disadvantage to the modified organism, would be especially favoured, as I can now see chiefly through your observations, by isolation in a small area, where only a few individuals lived under nearly uniform conditions.</p>
<p>When I wrote the ‘Origin,’ and for some years afterwards, I could find little good evidence of the direct action of the environment; now there is a large body of evidence, and your case of the Saturnia is one of the most remarkable of which I have heard.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Although we differ so greatly, I hope that you will permit me to express my respect for your long-continued and successful labours in the good cause of natural science.</p>
<p>I remain, dear Sir, yours very faithfully, | C<hi rend="smallCaps">harles</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">arwin</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had received a copy of Wagner’s multi-part essay on species formation in September 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9387.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1875</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Karl von Scherzer, 22 September 1876</ref> and n. 1). CD’s heavily annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Wagner, in line with his primary claim that isolation was the efficient cause of speciation, argued that the variability of species was greater when the opportunities for migration, both active and passive, were increased (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9387.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1875</ref>, pp. 451–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Picus</hi> is a genus of woodpeckers; <hi rend="italic">Strix</hi> is a genus of owls.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD discussed the process of unconscious selection in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 34–40, using English pointer dogs, racehorses, and other domesticated animals as examples.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 173, CD discussed cases in which allied species met and intermingled at the limits of their geographical range, and yet remained distinct. In such cases, he argued, one species did not give rise to the other, but rather both were descended from a common stock.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">On the role of the Galápagos islands, especially its species and varieties of birds, in shaping CD’s views on transmutation, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8848.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">M. J. S. Hodge 2010</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Wagner gave the case of cocoons from a moth, <hi rend="italic">Saturnia luna</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Actias luna</hi>, the luna moth), that were transported from Texas to Switzerland, and developed into adults with a completely different colour pattern. Wagner believed that a new species had thus been formed and gave it the name <hi rend="italic">Saturnia bolli</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9387.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1875</ref>, pp. 491–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The text of this letter down to ‘simultaneously’ is from an incomplete copy in DAR 148: 198; the rest is from the published version in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 3: 159.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>