<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2927A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles Lyell<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   25 September 1860</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20468</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2927A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2927A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2927A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="CC">10pp inc</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 383–6</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The University of Edinburgh Centre for Research Collections (Lyell collection Coll-203/A3/7: 3–12)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_124.xml">Edinburgh</repository>
                    <collection>Lyell</collection>
                    <idno>Coll-203/A3/7 3–12</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
                <date when="1860-09-25">25 Sept 1860</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Returns "excellent" MS in which CD favours hybrid origin of domestic dog, which CL believes strengthens case for common progenitor of wild species.</p>
            <p>Doubts CD’s authorities for antiquity of dingo.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> will raise many points for investigation.</p> 
            <p>"Leporine" hare–rabbit hybrid should be investigated.</p> 
<p>Has re-read passages in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> that CD suggested.</p>  
<p><hi rend="italic">Annals of Natural History</hi> would probably reprint Gray’s review of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> at their own expense.</p> 
            <p>CD’s thought that modern reptiles could not develop into existing Mammalia but only into another high form is a "grand notion" compatible with "the infinite capacity of the creative power".</p>
            <p>Comments on New Guinea marsupials.</p>
            <p>Still thinks that the Australian genera and species are so well fitted for extraordinary droughts that they would get the better of the dingo.</p>
            <p>Suggests that once there were more races of man, though from common stock. Competition and then hybridity checked divergence.</p>
            <p>Falconer’s views on elephant classification. CL attaches little value to Falconer’s objection that mastodons and elephants do not come in chronologically, as they should in CD’s view.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">"Leporine"</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">dingo</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">dog</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">elephant</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">hare</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Mammalia</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">marsupials</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">mastodons</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbit</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">reptiles</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Annals of Natural History</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1585">Falconer, Hugh</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Australia</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">New Guinea</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1860a</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">divergence</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">multiple origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">struggle for existence</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>25. Sept. 1860</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I return the M.S. on dogs which I think excellent.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The case you make out seems very strong not only of crosses from distinct living species having blended into the dog, but in favour of diff<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> savage races having domesticated different canine types, wolves, jackalls &amp;c by domestication in accordance with the hypothesis of Pallas having eliminated the dislike to cross with other species as well as the tendency of such crosses to sterility.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>All this helps the doctrine of the several so blendible wild species having themselves come down from a common remote progenitor &amp; I suppose you will say in reply to Quart. Review that the only reason that pigeons have not so mixed is that Man had not the same motive to cross them with other species distinct from the Rock pigeon.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I think the subject too important to bear shortening. As to the antiquity of the Dingo I have turned up to your two references in Quart. G. S. Journal &amp; they by no means bear out your inference.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The fossils occurred in a cave in the basalt &amp; were certainly posterior probably very long so, &amp; there is no evidence as caves are gradually choked up that the Dingo was not one of the last creatures whose bones were introduced. I asked Falconer yesterday<ref target="#foot.f6"/> &amp; he said, ‘let him take care he does not get himself into the same scrape which Owen did about Strzelecki’s Australian Mastodon;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I read the papers about Dingo &amp; thought they had no proof.’</p>
<p>Falconer knows of no fossil, rodent or bat in Australia. He says Strzelecki’s Mastodon was from S. America.</p>
<p>It seems strange that the question whether any Newfoundland dogs are semi-web-footed or not sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be so doubtful, also gestation of jackall. On these and many points y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> book will draw forth a number of facts for the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Ed<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Some one sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> go at once to Angoulême &amp; see into that question of the Leporine.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> If true, it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. take away the antecedent improbability of Pallas’ hypothesis of dogs when domesticated losing sterility &amp;c. Bartlett says, at Zool. Gardens, that we must wait till next spring for good experiments.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> He ought to have as many as possible to start with.</p>
<p>The chapter on dogs makes me wish yr book soon out. That &amp; the pigeons &amp; the Tables of large &amp; small genera w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> alone make a useful beginning.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>You conclude yr. letter received this morning by doubting whether I care for so speculative a way of dealing with the question. It is just what I wanted &amp; not more conjectural than my letter, much of which I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not of course touch or venture on in print, nor wish shown to third persons, more especially as one may alter one’s speculations the day after. I have referred to the pp. you allude to of Origin with much profit, tho‘ I remembered them all, but they contain such a condensation of matter that they require to be often re-read.</p>
<p>I have been too deeply interested &amp; taken up with the Dogs to have done with Asa Gray, but see enough to wish it to appear in Annals of N. H. &amp; cannot but think they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> print it for their own sake &amp; not require you to pay.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Tell them that the addition of A. Gray’s name w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> give a wholly new value to it instead of its appearing anonymously    I want to buy it, for one.</p>
<p>I think you have understood my point &amp; the idea that if the original type of Mammalia had been lost &amp; the reptilian had been greatly raised in grade, they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have produced some other great class as high perhaps or higher but not the existing Mammalia, is a grand notion &amp; believing as I do in the infinite Capacity of the creative power, inherent in the organic world, worked out by variation &amp; natural selection, I do not think it an extravagant speculation at all. You might say the same if some monotreme, instead of a reptile, was improved into a mammal, by a series of changes independent of those which gave rise to the first mammal. Possibly birds may be an instance of such a class, though I fear that would not do, because however low the Monotreme, it must perhaps rank typically before birds &amp; birds therefore must have preceded in order of development.</p>
<p>I am glad you reminded me of the N. Guinea Marsupials. I had imagined that there was a larger admixture of placentals. I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. think still the Australian genera &amp; species were so well fitted for the extraordinary droughts that they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. get the better of the Dingo had he run wild as in Juan Fernandez. The Brazilian case does not tell for much as that country has in the Marsupial line turned out nothing but opossums.</p>
<p>The case of nat<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. grafting stated by Göppert Überwallung der Tannenstöche, Bonn 1842, where silver fir borrows from roots of Pinus abies is the more analogous to grafting as being one conifer borrowing from another.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Plants of other divisions w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> do the same probably if near enough to allied trees, which owing to rotation may not be often at hand. If the genus were remote, it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. fail.</p>
<p>Do you not think when Man was less advanced 50,000 years or generations back &amp; tribes more isolated there must have been rather more races than now. tho’ of course at a remoter period much fewer, &amp; originally only one, &amp; that one lower intellectually than any one now existing. In proportion as more powerful &amp; more cosmopolite races arose they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> exterminate inferior ones &amp; also there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be more mixture &amp; a check to divergence into species or the centripetal force of hybridity (excuse the use of the phrase) would come into play.</p>
<p>Falconer has been holding forth today on the diff<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, Mastodons &amp; Elephants not coming in chronologically as they sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> do, according to yr views, but when one sees the new Maltese dwarf intermediate between E. antiquus &amp; E. meridionalis &amp; Anca’s new Sicilian cave elephant,<ref target="#foot.f14"/> a modification of the living Indian one leaning towards antiquus, &amp; when one thinks that Falconer can distinguish all American varieties of Mammals from all European fossil species, I confess I attach little value to the objection.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The text of the letter has been taken from a copy in Lyell’s scientific journal. It is also printed in Wilson ed. 1970, pp. 493–5. Lyell returned to London on 23 September following a six-week visit to the Continent (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 490 n. 88).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2895.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 11 August [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD described the ‘doctrine’ of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3654.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pyotr Simon Pallas</ref> concerning the origin of domestic breeds of dogs in a previous letter to Lyell (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2510.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 25 October [1859]</ref>): <quote type="quote"> He <hi rend="italic">hypothetically</hi> supposes that when long domesticated they lose their tendency to sterility when crossed with the other domesticated <hi rend="italic">species</hi>; &amp; by their crossing when domesticated he believes that all our domestic races have originated. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi> ridiculed CD’s example of the power of selection drawn from comparing the breeds of domestic pigeons, stating ‘this is all very pleasant writing, especially for pigeon-fanciers; but what step do we really gain in it at all towards establishing the alleged fact that variations are but species in the act of formation, or in establishing Mr. Darwin’s position that a well-marked variety may be called an incipient species?’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8372.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Wilberforce] 1860</ref>, p. 235). This passage and others relating to pigeons are heavily marked and annotated in CD’s copy of the review (Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Selwyn 1858 and 1860. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2925.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 23 [September 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Lyell visited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1585.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Falconer</ref> soon after returning to London to learn what progress had been made ‘on the great question at issue about the relation of certain elephant beds and the glacial epoch.’ (K. M. Lyell ed. 1881, 2: 337).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In 1844, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> had identified a fossilised molar tooth sent to him by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4598.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paul Edmund de Strzelecki</ref> as that of a mastodon. It was said to have been found in a cave in Australia (R. Owen 1844). Before then, the extinct mammalian fauna of Australia was believed to be exclusively restricted to marsupial forms. Falconer first questioned Owen’s identification in 1857; in 1863, he published a full history and refutation of Owen’s claim (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2427.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Falconer 1857–8</ref>, ‘Synoptical table of the species of <hi rend="italic">Mastodon</hi> and elephant’, facing p. 319; and Falconer 1863, pp. 96–101).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> usually referred to as the second was published in January 1860. Lyell evidently considered this to have been a corrected reprint and rather refers to the major alterations that CD was intending to incorporate into the third edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, published in 1861.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Lyell refers to the supposed hybrid between a hare and a rabbit said to have been bred in Angoulême, France. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2860.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 5 [July 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_300.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Abraham Dee Bartlett</ref> was superintendent of the zoological gardens in London. Lyell had seen the so-called leporines at the gardens early in July 1860 (Wilson ed. 1970, p. 465). Bartlett conducted many breeding experiments for CD at the gardens, but an account of this particular cross has not been located in the Darwin Archive.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD was preparing the first part (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>) of a substantial work, in which he planned to provide all the details and citations he had been unable to include in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2925.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 23 [September 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2917.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Göppert 1842</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_153.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anca 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Falconer was engaged in an extensive study of the fossil elephants and mastodons of Europe and America. He published a paper on the British and European species in 1857 and one on the American forms in 1863 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2427.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Falconer 1857–8</ref> and 1863). He had recently discovered a ‘small elephant, the size of a Shetland pony, in the small island of Malta.’ (K. M. Lyell ed. 1881, 2: 339). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 28 [September 1860]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>