<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8204">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From George Henslow   [<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 7 December 1876]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9393</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8204 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8204.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8204.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 149</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 149</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2232.xml">Henslow, George</persName>
                <placeName>London, Bentinck Terrace, 7</placeName>
                <date when="1876-12-07">[c. 7 Dec 1876]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Considers some flowers especially adapted for self-fertilisation, and believes all flowers are self-fertilising under some conditions. Gives examples of plants in which he believes all flowers are cleistogamous. Believes self-fertilisation is the primordial condition of flowering plants.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cleistogamous</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>7 Bentinck Terrace, Regents Pk.</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you very much for kindly ordering a copy of your new work to be sent to me, and which I have just received.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> There is so much matter in it, that it will take a long while to <hi rend="underline">digest</hi>; but I think from a few parts which I have read, that my conclusions—I gave in “Nature”—are <hi rend="underline">really</hi> in harmony with yours.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have paid no attention to <hi rend="underline">Conspicuous</hi> flowers, so that my term “self-fertilisation” had sole reference to small inconspicuous flowers; and as far as they are concerned your book certainly seems to corroborate me. I was hoping to find you had experimented on such flowers but you confess not to have done so. I mean to try next year to see what I can do.</p>
<p>In your list of plants fertile without insect-aid pp. 365–369 are included a few of those which I have noticed as being adapted for self-impregnation; &amp; of which I have detected the pollen-tubes: Thus. <hi rend="underline">Fumaria off<hi rend="superscript">s</hi></hi>: In this, the 3 Anther-cells of each group form a neat little 3-sided box into which the “horn”-like stigmas are shut, so that the pollen-tubes pour into it while the grains are still in situ. From this <hi rend="underline">I inferred</hi> (&amp; you have <hi rend="underline">proved</hi>) that it is self-fertilising.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have also detected the pollen-tubes in <hi rend="underline">Trifolium procumbens</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">minus.</hi><ref target="#foot.f5"/> <hi rend="underline">Nicotiana Tabacum</hi> as growing in the Kew Gardens seemed to be proterandrous, but <hi rend="underline">N. rusticum</hi> with smaller, greenish flowers was certainly fertilising itself.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have also noticed the pollen tubes in several small-fl<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. sp. of Veronica. With regard to sp: of <hi rend="underline">Solanum</hi> (Note p. 387) <hi rend="underline">S. nigrum</hi> I take to be decidedly self-f<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>. for the anther cells begin by pores, but slit all the way down &amp; so the pollen fall easily on the stigma, the flower being pendulous.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>The conclusion I drew was that these self-fertilising inconspicuous flowers, had acquired the habit—or rather <hi rend="underline">regained it</hi>, in consequence of the reduction of the corolla or by suppression of nectariferous affairs or both: for I found (as Bennett had also, though I was not aware of his observations at the time) that as the weather grows colder <hi rend="underline">Two</hi> Things followed; (1) buds have a tendency to remain closed (2) the corollas are dwarfed.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The former is seen well, e.g. in <hi rend="underline">Spergula arvensis</hi><ref target="#foot.f9"/> which goes on “budding” all through the winter but never “blossoming” &amp; yet produces an abundance of seed:— I therefore <hi rend="underline">greatly rejoiced</hi> when I came across the foot-note to p. 420—where you say:—“I am greatly surprized &amp;c for you include <hi rend="underline">Viola tricolor</hi> (p. 358) in your list of “Plants <hi rend="underline">sterile</hi> without insect aid” Now, these cases of <hi rend="underline">Delphinium</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Viola</hi> anticipate what I had determined to experimentize &amp; have already asked friends to help me:—viz. to see if flowers which are usually proterandrous will not become self-fertilising when their corollas are early removed; so far then, these cases quite corroborrate my deductions!<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>On p. 385. you speak of the reduction of the size of the corollas of some papilionacae species:— the <hi rend="underline">Cause</hi>, judging by analogy, I take to be <hi rend="underline">change of climate</hi>; for the reduction of temperature seems at once to affect &amp; reduce the size of the corolla or perianth. A case was mentioned a few weeks ago in the Gardner’s Chronicle where a Lapageria had a branch which had somehow escaped into the air—the blossoms on which only differed “in being smaller”.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Similarly I have noticed the corollas of conspicuous flowers get reduced in the autumn; but it would seem that the sexual processes are in no way interfered with. For example, I found last September &amp; October several plants of <hi rend="underline">Tradescantia erecta</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> <hi rend="underline">at Kew</hi> which earlier in the season produced conspicuous flowers, but in which the corollas were completely arrested, shriveled: the styles were consequently bent down on the side of the ovary &amp; the stigma thus kept in contact with the anthers. Not a bud expanded, though they were very numerous, yet <hi rend="underline">all</hi> set seed: &amp; I have preserved about 100 for next year’s sowing   the embryos are perfectly well formed!</p>
<p>You say you can hear of no instance of a species with <hi rend="underline">all</hi> its flowers rendered permanently cleistogamous:<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Perhaps the two following may prove to be so: <hi rend="underline">Cerastium glomeratum</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Corrigiola littoralis</hi><ref target="#foot.f14"/> Because, while <hi rend="underline">Spergula arvensis</hi> keeps its buds shut in cold weather, yet expands them on a warm sunny day, yet I have found Cer: glom: perfectly closed on a broiling hot day last June in an open hayfield. It grew abundantly, but not a single bud was expanded yet seed was shed in profusion. <hi rend="underline">Cor: litt:</hi> was quite closed <hi rend="underline">last Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> at Kew: whether it opens on hot days I can’t say.—</p>
<p>The fact that so many <hi rend="underline">Conspicuous</hi> flowers are self-fertilising, but benefitted by crossing; and that to be absolutely sterile with its own pollen is a fact decidedly in the minority, also seems to corroborrate my view that self-fertilisation was the primordial condition of flowering plants; but that in proportion as the corollas or perianths became conspicuous &amp; insect adaptation set in, sexual differentiations were set up &amp; self-fertilisation correspondingly “went to the wall”; but as species spread &amp; got into colder regions than their ancestors: the corollas were checked: &amp; self-fertilisation became again the rule for such inconspicuous flowers:</p>
<p>But I must not bore you with any more of my notions:</p>
<p>Again thanking you, | I beg to remain | Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> very truly | Geo: Henslow <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Ch. Darwin Esq F.R.S.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I have … can do. 1.8] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.5 the blossoms … smaller”. 4.6] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi>; ‘4’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.8 For example, … shriveled: 4.11] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.3 also seems … condition 6.4] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.3 self-fertilisation … condition 6.4] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘p 4.’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the references to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>; copies sent by J<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">ohn Murray</ref> were received around 7 December 1876 (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-10703.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. W. Bennett, 7 December 1876</ref>; CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (Appendix III)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Henslow’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See Henslow 1876b; see also letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2232.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Henslow</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">20 October 1876</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10652.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">24 October 1876</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10648.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to George Henslow, 23 October [1876]</ref>. Henslow published further on his thesis that self-fertilised plants were the fittest to survive in the struggle for life in Henslow 1877.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 366, CD noted that he had never seen an insect visit <hi rend="italic">Fumaria officinalis</hi> (common fumitory), and that covered-up and unprotected plants produced an equal number of capsules.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Trifolium procumbens</hi> and <hi rend="italic">T. procumbens</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">minus</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">T. campestre</hi>, field clover.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Nicotiana tabacum</hi> is the tobacco plant; <hi rend="italic">N. rustica</hi> is Aztec tobacco.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 387, CD noted that species of plants with small and inconspicuous flowers nevertheless continued to produce some flowers that opened and could intercross, and concluded that crossing must therefore be of some benefit to them. However, he added that he had not experimented on such flowers, and, in a footnote, suggested that it would be useful to try some species of <hi rend="italic">Solanum</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Solanum nigrum</hi> is deadly nightshade.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_389.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred William Bennett</ref> published on self-fertilisation in winter-flowering plants in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_547.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bennett 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Corn spurry.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 420 n., CD described experiments in which the corolla was removed from various flowers, which none the less yielded seeds. CD was not surprised that self-fertilised flowers produced seed in these circumstances, but was surprised that <hi rend="italic">Delphinium consolidum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Viola tricolor</hi> did so. In <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 358, CD listed <hi rend="italic">V. tricolor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">D. consolidum</hi> among plants that were sterile or significantly less fertile than usual when insects were excluded. See also Henslow 1876b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 4 November 1876, p. 588, contained a report of a white <hi rend="italic">Lapageria</hi> (the Chilean bellflower) that had sent a shoot between a door jamb and a wall; the shoot flowered outside, although the flowers were smaller than usual.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Tradescantia erecta</hi> is widow’s tears or false dayflowers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See n. 7, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><hi rend="italic">Cerastium glomeratum</hi> is sticky mouse-ear chickweed or clammy chickweed. <hi rend="italic">Corrigiola litoralis</hi> (‘littoralis’ is a misspelling) is strapweed.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>