<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-183">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Sarah Williams    26[–31] August 1832</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5121</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-183 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-183.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-183.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">31 AU</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 117</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 117</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2059.xml">Williams, S. H.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Belgrave St, 1</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1832-08-26" notAfter="1832-08-31">26[–31] Aug 1832</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Gives CD an "account of my life and adventures since we parted" and news of her family.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Williams, S. H. M.’s family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">news</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>1. Belgrave Street.</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday 26. August. | 1832.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>If you have ever thought of me I fear it has only been to upbraid me with forgetfulness of the promise I made to write to you. I assure you my own conscience has reproached me very very often, but I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> I need not say that forgetfulness of you did not cause my silence, indeed, my dear Charles, no day has elapsed without your occupying some of my thoughts, &amp; it was with very great pleasure I heard such good accounts had been received of you, Papa was <hi rend="underline">much pleased</hi> with your letter, which he had about a fortnight ago, &amp; I dare say has answered by this time. Susan tells me to direct to Monte Video, but I am afraid it may be very uncertain when this reaches your hands, whenever it does, I hope you will write &amp; tell me so, without waiting till you are at <hi rend="underline">Terra del</hi> <hi rend="underline">Fuego</hi> from whence you know you promised me a letter— I often think what a wonderful number of changes have taken place amongst your Friends, since you saw them.— Fanny’s marriage <hi rend="underline">must have surprised you</hi> not a little, then the “incomparable Charlottes”, &amp; her Brother, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> F. Wedgwood, I think your Cousin Hensleigh was <hi rend="underline">twined</hi> off before you sailed &amp; you must have been detained long enough at Portsmouth to hear that my <hi rend="underline">execution</hi> had actually taken place, since which awful time, I have, I assure you, been <hi rend="underline">as happy as a Queen</hi>, &amp; have really nothing left to wish for being sadly spoilt &amp; indulged by Edward, who is an Angel all but the Wings, (as Harry Wedgwood said of the “incomparable Charlotte’s husband)— I do think there <hi rend="underline">never</hi> was such a temper, <hi rend="underline">you</hi> may imagine its excellence, when I tell you that even one of the <hi rend="underline">Warlike race</hi> of Owen has never yet contrived to make a fight, or even a dispute, whether it is that the Owen blood is fast degenerating, I know not, but such is the fact.— I must try &amp; give you some account of my life &amp; adventures since we parted— When I married instead of going a shivering tour in the month of November, in search of the Picturesque, I declared I would instantly proceed on a romantic tour to London—where we arrived the day afterwards, that same evening I went to see Miss Fanny Kemble<ref target="#foot.f1"/> (Heavens &amp; Earth, I hear you exclaim,) &amp; continued my Theatrical Tour for a week or more; till I had visited every play house then open— We soon afterwards returned to Eaton, where we remained till the end of January, &amp; excellent fun we had, hunting almost every day with the Beagles—I mounted on a steady seasoned old Hunter, with as much sense as any Christian, he carried me most delightfully over most things, &amp; never gave me a fall, he has since become my own property, he has been at grass all summer, &amp; I hope to find him in hunting condition when the season begins— but to return to my story, we left Eaton the end of January &amp; went to stay at <hi rend="underline">my Brother</hi> Richard’s,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> in Pall Mall, whilst we were furnishing this house, which we took possession of the end of February, &amp; I have never left it since, except for a few day’s visit to the Bruces who have taken a place near Windsor— In March I had a very severe illness, which laid me up for some time, as soon as I was able, I thought a ride would do me good, &amp; accordingly mounted a 4 year old Grey Mare which Edward had bought for me from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gore 〈&amp;〉 we went into the Park, (it was my sec〈ond ti〉me of riding her) &amp; had just got opposite the Serpentine, when she started across the road at a Dog, turned short round, &amp; down I came, her feet were unluckily entangled in my habit, &amp; in trying to get away, she put her foot on my Ancle bone &amp; the caulking of her shoe took a piece <hi rend="underline">clear</hi> out, had it been half an inch lower, the Surgeons say I should have lost the joint— I jumped up directly, fancying I had only strained my ancle, &amp; Edward put me into the house belonging to the <hi rend="underline">Humane</hi> Society whilst he fetched the Carriage to take me home, that very evening Caroline &amp; Arthur arrived, poor Arthur to prepare for his Voyage &amp; the whole time he staid, I was never able to leave my bed the wound was so bad—it was 9 weeks before I was able to walk. I went about with a Crutch, &amp; was lifted in &amp; out of the Carriage— Edward would not consent to my riding this unlucky grey Mare any more, &amp; I was obliged to sell her, but have supplied her place by a very nice Bay, which exactly suits me— Poor Arthur sailed the middle of May, he took with him a most tremendous looking Bull Dog, rather an odd Dog to choose, I thought but he was told it would be more useful to him than any other— We heard from him at Madeira, &amp; he seemed to enjoy his voyage much poor boy, I hope he will be steady, when he arrives in India, &amp; then there can be little doubt of his doing well— Caroline went down for Fanny’s Wedding, &amp; then returned here with Mama, they staid 5 weeks with us, came up &amp; returned per <hi rend="underline">Wonder</hi>, which they say is the most delightful of earthly conveyances— I feel quite odd at being left by myself so many hours in the day, for Edward goes to <hi rend="underline">Shop</hi> about 11 &amp; seldom returns before 5 or half past, it is very provoking we are detained in London so late this year, owing to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Powell’s absence, but I hope to see Eaton about the second week in Sep<hi rend="superscript">tr</hi>. &amp; then we shall remain there till after Xmas— I never was so long in London before, but I am such a <hi rend="underline">thorough Cockney</hi> that I like it better than any other place, on the long run, &amp; am glad it is my fate to spend so much time in it— Fanny has been in Town for 3 weeks, but is now returned to Chirk Castle, which I fear she will not find very pleasant for some time to come, as M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> &amp; Miss Biddulph are there for a <hi rend="underline">few</hi> Months, &amp; she is sadly in awe of them both. Who would have thought she would have married so soon after that unfortunate Citadel Affair!!—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Caroline is now in possession of the title of <hi rend="underline">Miss Owen</hi>, I assure you she is much <hi rend="underline">come forward</hi> since she attained that dignity— Emma I suppose will make her <hi rend="underline">public</hi> appearance this Winter, I hear she is much improved lately, but it is more than 6 months since I have seen her— That “rising Star of Ton” Matty Cotton is also very flourishing— Of course all the other Shropshire Marriages have been announced to you—Miss Boughey &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. Fielding, Miss Parker,—&amp; Sir Baldwin—M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mainwaring’s <hi rend="underline">intended</hi> marriage to Miss Salisbury, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Henry Lloyd’s to a Bristol heiress, as soon as he gets a Living— If you do not make haste home, you will find nothing but <hi rend="underline">dead dogs</hi> in Shropshire— Clare Leighton is still Clare Leighton, &amp; I hear no <hi rend="underline">talk</hi> of her changing her name, I am sure you would be sorry to hear of poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Mathew’s sudden death. I do think nobody was ever so generally lamented, poor M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mathew is not likely ever to recover it I fear— Erasmus dined with us not long ago, &amp; I also met him at dinner at the Hollands—by the bye M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Holland is married &amp; done for since you went— I cannot say I much admire his choice though I am not so violent as Erasmus, who declares i〈f sh〉e was to offer him 5£ to give her a kiss, he would not— Catherine is now on a visit to the Hollands, in Gloucestershire— I shall be <hi rend="underline">most delighted</hi>, my dear Charles, to receive a letter from you, I have not forgotten the <hi rend="underline">solemn</hi> promise you made me to come to N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1 Belgrave S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> as soon as you arrived in London—dine with us, &amp; <hi rend="underline">go to the</hi> Play— I wonder when that day will come!! I hope you continue to like your “<hi rend="underline">Angel in the disguise of a</hi> <hi rend="underline">Sea Captain</hi>” as much as ever, have you made a large collection of Curiosities— I often laugh when I think of your very last <hi rend="underline">walk in the Forest</hi>, when you discovered &amp; rooted up those horrible funguses, &amp; <hi rend="underline">bottled</hi> them for the Professors at Cambridge— I should prefer <hi rend="underline">living</hi> curiosities such as Monkeys or Parrots, which I have a great fancy for— I have now got 3 Pets—a Bull finch, &amp; 2 nondescript little foreign birds. I had the 〈    〉 misfortune to lose poor Beppo, who was taken by some wretch in human form when he had been 3 weeks in Town— I like this house very much, it is so airy &amp; <hi rend="underline">quiet</hi> —you will laugh at this being a recommendation to <hi rend="underline">me</hi>, but you have no idea what a sober steady Matron I am become &amp; strange to say, I have <hi rend="underline">almost</hi> entirely lost my taste for gaiety &amp; going out— You will hardly believe it is <hi rend="underline">Sarah Owen</hi> who writes in this strain, but so it is— And now I fear I must bring this long scribble to a conclusion. Heaven knows <hi rend="underline">when</hi> or <hi rend="underline">where</hi> it may reach you, but whenever it does, I hope it will convince you that you are not &amp; never will be forgotten by one of your oldest Friends, who now remains very sincerely, &amp; affec<hi rend="superscript">tely</hi> Yours, | S. H. Hosier Williams | (how does it look)</p>
<p>A letter directed Belgrave S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. will always find me— God bless you, my dear Charles, I will write again 〈very〉 soon—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2655.xml">Frances Anne Kemble</ref>, actress then at the height of her success.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Williams</ref>, Sarah’s brother-in-law (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-37.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fanny Owen, [January 1828]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">An allusion to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3619.xml">Fanny Owen</ref>’s having been jilted by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2291.xml">John Hill</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>