<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1214">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Edward Forbes   [1 May – 5 June 1851]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13349</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1214 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1214.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1214.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 144: 131</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 131</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1851-05-01" notAfter="1851-06-05">[1 May – 5 June 1851] </date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1680.xml">Forbes, Edward</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on MS by C. S. Bate. Bate not aware of other work on <hi rend="italic">Cirripedia</hi>; cites Bate’s errors. Would Bate allow CD to use his drawings in <hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi>? [See <hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> 1: 9–16.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cirripedia</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_312">Bate, C. S.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnboro. Kent.</placeName>
                    <date>Thursday.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Forbes</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I have read with much interest, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bate’s paper &amp; admired his <hi rend="underline">beautiful</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">excellent</hi> drawings—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am sorry to say that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bates is not at all aware (as he suggests himself) how much has been published on the Cirripedia— I presume he would consider that the Chief Point in his paper is the fact that the metamorphosis commences under a quite different form (viz a six-legged little crustacean) compared with the last form described by V. Thompson;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> it must no doubt have been a great satisfaction to him having made out this important fact independently But Burmeister in his Beitrage zur an Rankenfüsse has published figures (poor) &amp; detailed description of the whole series of similar changes in the larva of Anatifa<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>And Goodsir in the Edin New. Phil. Journal. has done the same thing for Balanus—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Goodsir’s figures of the <hi rend="underline">first &amp; second</hi> (not the <hi rend="underline">last</hi>) stages are closely similar, but not identical with those of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates.— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B. does not seem aware of V. Thompson’s second Paper in Royal Soc Transt. on the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> (N.B. V. Thompson did not even conjecture there were two stages) stage of the larva of Anatifa;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> for he gives a copy of Thompsons figure copied by Prof<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Harvey of Dublin (not Capt<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>!) in his sea side book.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I will give some other authorities not known to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates, who speaks of the mature Cirripedes <hi rend="underline">not</hi> having eyes, which shows he has not heard of Prof<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Leidy’s discovery<ref target="#foot.f8"/> which I have repeatedly verified having found optic nerve &amp; ganglion &amp;c.— Kölliker has figured the spermatozoa of Cirripedia,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> but as far as I have seen M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates figures seem more accurate, than Kölliker, &amp; yet I hardly like to distrust on such a subject such an observer.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>When M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates speaks of the pulp (an inappropriate name I think) in the tubes of shell of Balanus being isolated, I conceive he is mistaken, as he would see if he read D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Coldstream’s paper in Encycp. of Anatomy—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> But the most valuable &amp; extensive paper unknown to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates is by Martin S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Ange read 16 years ago to the Acad: Sc: Paris, with excellent figures;<ref target="#foot.f12"/> if M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates had read this he would have seen that his figure Tab. V. is very erroneous; I can assure him I have <hi rend="underline">repeatedly</hi> verified S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Ange’s observations; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B. makes the two so called testes (really vesiculæ seminales, the testes being quite distinct) debouch at the anus! &amp; the alimentary canal debouch at the end of the probosciformed male organ or penis! My unpublished observations are of course of no authority but I see many points very different from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates, &amp; it would be unfriendly not to caution him that his description of the female parts of generation are <hi rend="underline">very</hi> far, as I believe from the truth.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Indeed S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Ange would show this in two leading points &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Ange has been confirmed by Rudolph Wagner<ref target="#foot.f14"/> and Lovèn<ref target="#foot.f15"/> in parts of his description—</p>
<p>I do not know whether M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates will think my advice uncalled for,<ref target="#foot.f16"/> but I would recommend him to publish only his observations on the larva out of Justice sake, alluding to Burmeister, &amp;, Goodsir’s previous discovery of the great fact of the complex metamorphosis of the Cirripedia— Perhaps he had better look at Goodsir’s figures (Edin: New. Phil. Journal. July 1843) &amp; see how near his are, &amp; allude to points of difference, some of which I consider of <hi rend="underline">very considerable</hi> interest I will add that letters of reference to each corresponding part would make his figures plainer in Tab I.— If I might venture to beg a favour it would be, <hi rend="underline">when M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates paper is published</hi>, if he would give me (supposing he has such) two or three specimens of the larva in the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> &amp; 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> stage as figured in Tab I. I should like to see rather a fuller description of the curious point on the basal segments of the legs, which Goodsir imperfectly figures—<ref target="#foot.f17"/> Would M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates permit me in my introduction to my systematic volume to be published this autumn in which I shall give an <hi rend="underline">abstract</hi> of my anatomical observations, to allude to his drawings of the early stages of the larva?<ref target="#foot.f18"/> One word more, would it not be advisable for M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates to give some measurements of the embryo figured 18–19, for they must be excessively minute—<ref target="#foot.f19"/> The fact of the 21 segments being reckonable is exceedingly curious— Forgive this long letter, but I did not like to say simply—that parts of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bates work had been forestalled without going into details—</p>
<p>Believe me dear Forbes with sincere thanks for your kind expressions about our bitter loss.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>Yours most truly. | C. Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date range is established by the reference to CD’s ‘bitter loss’ (see n. 20, below) and the letter of 13 June to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_312.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Spence Bate</ref>. The first Thursday after CD’s return from Malvern was 1 May, and 5 June is the last possible Thursday on which he could have written to Forbes and had a reply from Bate by 13 June.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s reference is to the manuscript of Bate’s paper, which was published in October 1851 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_428.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bate 1851</ref>). Bate described the two larval stages of five species of Lepadidae. CD cited Bate’s paper in the section on metamorphosis in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>8–28. The copyist frequently spelled the name ‘Bates’. Whether it was so spelled in CD’s original is not known.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4721.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Vaughan Thompson</ref>, who, through his observation of the metamorphosis of crustacea-like larvae into barnacles, was the first to point out that the Cirripedia were allied to the Crustacea (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thompson 1830</ref> and 1835). Thompson identified two distinct larval forms and thought one was the larva of pedunculated cirripedes and the other the larva of sessile cirripedes. In fact both forms, now referred to as nauplius and cyprid stages, are common to all cirripedes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1104.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burmeister 1834</ref>, the full title of which is <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Naturgeschichte der Rankenfüsser</hi> (Cirripedia). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_741.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Burmeister</ref> described what he took to be four developmental stages in the larvae of Lepadidae. CD’s annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1104.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burmeister 1834</ref> is in the Darwin library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2912.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Goodsir 1843</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7713.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thompson 1835</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Harvey 1849.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Leidy 1848.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Koelliker 1843.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD’s own description of the spermatozoa of Balanidae differed slightly from that given in Koelliker 1843 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_428.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bate 1851</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>98–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Coldstream 1836</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5274.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Martin-Saint-Ange 1835</ref>. In <hi rend="italic">Living</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cirripedia</hi> (1851): viii–ix, CD gave the date as 1834, the date it was read.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">For a discussion of CD’s interpretation of the female generative system, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1639.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crisp 1983</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8033.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wagner 1834</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Lovèn 1844.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Bate in large measure followed CD’s advice and concluded his paper with an expression of ‘thanks to Mr. Darwin, but for whose kindness I should have been guilty of publishing more than a single error.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_428.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bate 1851</ref>, p. 331).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">CD referred to Bate’s description of the spiny projections at the base of the legs of cirripede larvae in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">The permission was granted (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1340.xml" resp="#automat">letter to C. S. Bate, 13 June [1851]</ref>). CD referred to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_428.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bate 1851</ref> in the preface to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>ix, as a ‘valuable Paper’ and discussed his work further on pp. 9–16. CD reproduced figures from it in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>Plate XXIX, fig. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1340.xml" resp="#automat">letter to C. S. Bate, 13 June [1851]</ref>, in which CD suggested that Bate purchase a micrometer to fit into the eye-piece of his microscope.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">The death of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8647.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anne Darwin</ref>, 23 April 1851.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>