<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3019F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To David Forbes   11 December [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21210</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3019F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3019F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3019F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 185: 150</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>185: 150</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <date when="1860-12-11">11 Dec [1860]</date>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1678.xml">Forbes, David</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Encourages Forbes to publish his geological observations on Chile.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent.</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 11.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>Your letter has pleased me exceedingly.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> When I saw how much error you detected in d’Orbigny, I said to myself “Good Heavens my turn will come next”.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I hope that you will be able to send your observations on Chile &amp;c to Geolog. Soc. before your departure (which I am sorry to hear is so very soon); but of course if not written out already that will be quite impossible.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> On your return if you wish to publish in extenso, your case would be an excellent one for aid from the Government grant to Royal Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Pray bear this in mind.— You would get plenty of backers.— Your paper just sent to G. Soc. will at once put you in that position, that you might boldly demand aid.</p>
<p>I am sorry for my blunder about Andesite.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Have you ever reflected on the subject of plutonic rocks being same character throughout extensive areas at same epoch. I remember this subject treated of by (I think) Keilhau: it seems to me very mysterious &amp; indicating some great unknown class of facts.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>How curious I shall be at some future time to read about the Uspallata formation.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I know how busy you are &amp; must be; but it would be a <hi rend="underline">great favour</hi>, if you would write literally one line to me to say whether the great mound of detritus at Val del Yeso has any connection with ice-action; because I am preparing new Edition of my Origin of Species, &amp; if you say “no” I will strike out 3 lines; if you say “yes” I will leave them as they now stand.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I saw in the valley of Cauquenes boulders which I now think must have had some connexion with Glacial action.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>When in S. America, would it trouble you to make a few observations on Mules, as by enclosed paper, &amp; some time write me the results?<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>With every good wish for your success &amp; prosperity, &amp; with cordial thanks for your letter &amp; kind expressions. Believe me | My dear Sir | Yours very sincerely | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.4 one] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘case’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.6 now] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the references to Forbes’s paper on the geology of Bolivia and southern Peru (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2571.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Forbes 1860</ref>), which was read before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref> on 21 November 1860. A summary of this letter was published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 13, Supplement.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Forbes’s letter has not been found. The <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2621.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from David Forbes, [November? 1860]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8), which should now be dated [after 11 December 1860], is a reply to this letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2571.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Forbes 1860</ref>, in which Forbes challenged many of Alcide Charles Victor Dessalines d’Orbigny’s findings on the geology of South America (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6005.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Orbigny 1835–47</ref>; see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3006.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 4 December [1860]</ref>). For a summary of the differences between Forbes and Orbigny, see <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Geological Society of London</hi> 33 (1877): 44–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2571.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Forbes 1860</ref> was intended as the first part of a memoir that would include two further parts on the geology of Chile and the Argentine (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2571.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Forbes 1860</ref>, p. 62). However, Forbes read no further paper on the geology of South America to the Geological Society.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Forbes did not publish on the geology of Chile and Argentina with the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had described a volcanic rock that he found in the vicinity of the Beagle Channel as andesite (<hi rend="italic">South America</hi>, pp. 154–5 <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi>). Forbes had revised CD’s nomenclature, preferring to call it diorite on account of its similarity to European diorites (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2571.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Forbes 1860</ref>, p. 29).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had earlier been impressed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2651.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Baltazar Mathias Keilhau’s</ref> theory of the origin of rocks by heat-induced crystallisation (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4308.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Keilhau 1838–40</ref> and 1844, and <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-780.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Adolf von Morlot, 10 October [1844]</ref> and n. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD crossed the Uspallata pass and the Uspallata range in Argentina in 1835 (see <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed., pp. 331, 333; see also <hi rend="italic">South America</hi>, pp. 60, 175).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD described the geological features of the Yeso valley, in Chile, in <hi rend="italic">South America</hi>, p. 178. This may have been the source for the passage about the ‘vast mound of detritus’ in an Andean valley in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, p. 373. After receiving Forbes’s reply (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2621.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from David Forbes, [after 12 December 1860]</ref> [previously dated [November? 1860]), CD restated his conviction that the mound was due to glacial action (<hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed., pp. 403–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <hi rend="italic">South America</hi>, pp. 64–7. While a small number of boulders near Cauquenes in Chile had previously been described by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_655.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolphe Théodore Brongniart</ref> as erratics deposited by glaciers, CD argued that river action and uplift could have displaced them from their original strata (<hi rend="italic">South America</hi>, p. 66 and n.).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The enclosure listing questions for Forbes has not been found. By mules, CD probably means hybrids between goats and sheep. For Forbes’s reply, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2621.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from David Forbes, [November? 1860]</ref>, now redated [after 11 December 1860]. CD cited Forbes on the sheep of Chile in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 95, and considered the question of the possible relatedness of sheep to goats in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 94, 98–9, and 102.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>