<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4394">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Hermann Crüger   21 January 1864</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16574</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4394 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4394.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4394.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="12">12</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 278</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 278</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1100.xml">Crüger, Hermann</persName>
                <placeName>Trinidad</placeName>
                <date when="1864-01-21">21 Jan 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends his MS of orchid paper ["A few notes on the fecundation of orchids and their morphology", <hi rend="italic">J. Linn. Soc. Lond. (Bot.)</hi> 8 (1865): 127–35] for CD to send to an editor.</p>  
<p>CD was right about <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi> sexes.</p>  
<p><hi rend="italic">Ficus</hi> experiments fail.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Catasetum</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Ficus</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">J. Linn. Soc. Lond. (Bot.)</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4503">Cruger, Hermann</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Cruger, Hermann 1864</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Trinidad</placeName>
                    <date>21 Janry 1864.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am sending off by this mail a small box containing a bottle with various curiosities concerning the impregnation of Orchids. There are flowers of Coryanthes, Stanhopea, Gongora &amp; Catasetum. Further the insects which visit them a large humble bee &amp; a very brilliantly colored Euglossa I believe.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Further flowers of Schomburgkia &amp; the Epidendrum mentioned in former letters which does not open &amp; notwithstanding is always impregnated.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> One Coryanthes flower has the bee in the position it takes when forcing its way out.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> To fill up I have added some flowers of Norantea.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>With the humblebees with the pollinia of Catasetum on their back I have been unfortunate   I had three, two I tried to preserve dry which would not succeed, &amp; the third which I put into Rum lost its pretty appendage, as happened also with one with the same organ on its back from Coryanthes.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The notes I have taken on these things I have incorporated into a paper on the subject which you will find in the same box.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have added a few remarks on the morphology of Orchids &amp; the bearing the whole has on theory.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have also added a few sketches, illustrative of the subject.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> You will do with this paper what you think proper, if you think it worth publishing, it would perhaps best go to the “Natural History Review” which has some good botanists amongst its editors.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> If you think it is not fit for publication, I am still content. You will find perhaps that it is too full of Germanisms. I believe that the facts communicated in the paper are interesting although the deductions may be not approved of by all your countrymen.—</p>
<p>While reperusing the other day your book on Orchids,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I recollected that bees in Germany where certain orchids are very common suffer from a disease called the “Kolbenkrankheit” “club disease” which consists of their body being beset with pollen masses to such an extent as to impede their movements. Does this disease not exist in England?—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> One of the stalks of the Epidendron sent bears flowers which I recommend to your attention, the stigmatic cavity is quite terminal surrounded besides the anthers by five lobes of the column.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I am very sorry I did not see these flowers at an earlier stage.— In the observation of our orchids much remains to be done with regard to their insects, as the greater number of them live high up in the air the subject has its great practical difficulties   I do not think we know the insect which impregnates Stanhopea grandiflora.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>I have failed in my experiments with native Ficus.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Although I had them in very tight cambric bags the insects have found means to penetrate. I have not begun too late, as they were quite rudimentary &amp; completely covered by their bracts when I tied the Bags on. But they contain much fewer insects than those which were not covered. The insects which perform the act of caprification appear not well known, the insect book I have refer the insect of the European Figs to Cynips, ours certainly do not belong to that Genus.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> I think all our Figs have their own insects, &amp; some of them several species. In general I have had occasion again to verify what I advanced formerly that exotic figs have no insects &amp; produce no good seeds.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>From the paper I send you will find that some of my former notions about Catasetum were incorrect &amp; that you had hit the thing exactly.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I have looked in all these plants for nectar such as it is generally defined but I find none. I do not know if I wrote you in answer to your last,<ref target="#foot.f18"/> the surgeon you mention must be my friend Bradford,<ref target="#foot.f19"/> but he is certainly mistaken when he says that Catasetum tridentatum, ie the male flower bears seed.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> I consider it simply impossible for reasons specified in my paper. Monachanthus is in my opinion, as I said formerly the female form of both Catasetum &amp; Myanthus, &amp; it will be found that the Catasetum form, if really found on the same spike with Myanthus is the transition from Myanthus to Monachanthus.—</p>
<p>I forgot to tell you that I am getting a layer made for you of Norantea, which I intend to send to Kew, where you can claim it when arrived.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> I have seedlings but they take too much time to come to flower   a layer will flower in 2–3 years.—</p>
<p>Have you seen the paper by Mohl I refer to in my essay?<ref target="#foot.f22"/> I have lately examined the flowers of Ruellia clandestina   the small ones behave certainly as Mohl indicates in that class of dimorphic flowers he treats of.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> We have another Ruellia which does not flower now, but it also bears dimorphic flowers. I shall watch it. In General, as far as I can collect your ideas have not had the reception among German botanists which I thought I had a right to expect.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> But the younger men are nearly all given to specialities, &amp; the older such as Mohl &amp; others belong to the “Parti de resistance”. You will perceive that I have frankly accepted your theory, as the one which connects better than any other phenomena hitherto unconnected. On the other hand I differ from you in the explanation of the Orchidean flower, &amp; perhaps from all living botanists.<ref target="#foot.f25"/> In general I am afraid the present generation of Botanists are shy of discussions of a theoretical description.—</p>
<p>I have addressed the box to the Messrs G. Dunlop &amp; Co in Southampton,<ref target="#foot.f26"/> I know from experience that if not addressed to the care of somebody there things are apt to be lost. The bottle contains a larger humblebee, which sometimes visits Catasetum etc, but which is more timid than the other, &amp; driven away by it. The Euglossa I find appears to have a longer tongue in the living state, how is this to be accounted for?<ref target="#foot.f27"/> If my time &amp; money were not fully taken up by the “Amabilis”<ref target="#foot.f28"/> I should like to learn a little more about insects, I wish somebody would take up the subject in this island, there is no end of variety of them.— I need not tell you again that I am as heretofore quite at your disposal if you should like to have some other things from this island for your studies. I hope you will receive the box &amp; contents in safety, &amp; to learn from you how it pleases you.</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours | H Crüger</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>5.5 that Catasetum … paper. 5.7] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: <hi rend="italic">circle, red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 154 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 151), CD said that Crüger had sent him ‘specimens of the bees, belonging to three species of <hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi>, which he saw gnawing the inside of the labellum’ of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum.</hi> CD sent Crüger’s bee specimens to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> for deposit, and evidently for identification (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3365.xml">letter to Frederick Smith, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 17 February 1864?]</ref>). See also n. 3, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Crüger</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">23 February 1863</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">23 April 1863</ref>. CD discussed Crüger’s information about the self-pollination of unopening flowers (later called cleistogamic flowers) in his letter to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11), in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, pp. 152, 158–9 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 149, 155–6), and in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 147. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4184.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Hermann Crüger, 25 May [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD mentioned Crüger’s <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> specimen with the bee still within the flower in an addition to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 230; this passage (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 229–31) recounted Crüger’s observation of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> pollination from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref> in a section entitled: ‘Cases of special difficulty on the theory of natural selection’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 224–32). CD also mentioned the <hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi> specimens sent by Crüger in his discussion of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 157 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 153–4), and in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 175. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4410.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 17 February [1864]</ref> and n. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Crüger had discussed the pollination and form of <hi rend="italic">Norantea</hi>, a member of the Marcgraviaceae, in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4265.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 8 August 1863</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11). CD had already expressed an interest in observing members of the Marcgraviaceae in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 28 March [1863]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Crüger had observed pollinia of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi> attaching to a bee’s back while it gnawed on the labellum of a male flower; he speculated that they were then deposited on the stigma of a female flower when the bee was similarly attracted to the labellum (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 129; Crüger’s observation confirmed CD’s account of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi> pollination in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 211–13, 234–5 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4410.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 17 February [1864]</ref> and nn. 9 and 10). The pollination of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> was described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 130 (see n. 3, above, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 173–6, for CD’s published discussions of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> pollination).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD communicated the paper (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>) to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>, where it was read on 3 March 1864 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4410.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 17 February [1864]</ref>). See DAR 70: 144 and DAR 70: 145 for CD’s two annotated copies of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>; both copies have portions cut out of them. Another heavily annotated copy is in CD’s unbound issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>) 8 (no. 31) in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Crüger argued that the adaptations and the rarity of the necessity for self-pollination that he found in orchids supported CD’s theory of transmutation, noting ‘the harmony into which it has brought so many branches of natural history hitherto unconnected’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 131). For his discussion of the relation of the form of the orchid flower and its ‘history of development’ to theory, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 132–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Crüger’s sketches included a bee, its position in a female <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi> flower while pollinating it, and sketches of stages of development in <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, plate 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See n. 6, above. The botanists on the editorial board of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> in 1864 were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1164.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick Currey</ref>, a mycologist. Crüger may also be referring to the naturalist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5255.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Perceval Wright</ref>. CD referred the paper to Oliver, who passed it on to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref>, the president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4411.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Daniel Oliver, 18 February 1864</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Orchids.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. 418–38, CD included a chapter entitled ‘The habits of insects in relation to the fertilisation of flowers’; he discussed the pollination habits of bees that he had observed, but did not mention the condition described by Crüger.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 131, Crüger wrote that, in the Epidendreae, the highly viscous stigma was usually situated ‘immediately below the pollen-bed’, facilitating self-pollination. CD referred to Crüger’s observation of self-pollination in the Epidendreae in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 152 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 149), and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 147. See n. 2, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Crüger observed an insect visiting a <hi rend="italic">Stanhopea</hi> and caught it with the pollen-mass on its back, but did not think that it pollinated the flower; he noted that <hi rend="italic">S. grandiflora</hi> rarely bore seeds (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 130). CD attempted to pollinate <hi rend="italic">Stanhopea</hi> himself later in the year (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 3 November [1864]</ref>); he mentioned his and Crüger’s assessments of <hi rend="italic">Stanhopea</hi> pollination in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 153 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 150), and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 171.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Crüger was already convinced that figs (<hi rend="italic">Ficus</hi>) required insects for pollination, but had agreed to attempt an experiment suggested by CD to verify this (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1675.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1851</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Crüger, 23 April 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Caprification, a method of promoting the pollination and ripening of cultivated figs, entails hanging branches of caprifig, a wild fig, on cultivated fig trees. Gall-wasps, including the genus <hi rend="italic">Cynips</hi>, then emerge from the galls of the caprifig and fly to the cultivated fig to lay eggs, carrying pollen with them.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See n. 14, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 127. In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4008.xml">letter of 23 February 1863</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11), Crüger expressed the opinion that <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Myanthus barbatus</hi> were distinct species. CD had argued in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 236–48, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7750.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three sexual forms of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi>’</ref> that <hi rend="italic">Myanthus barbatus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Monachanthus viridis</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi> were, respectively, the hermaphrodite, female, and male forms of the same plant. <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Monachanthus viridis</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum macrocarpum</hi>, the jumping orchid; <hi rend="italic">Myanthus barbatus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum barbatum</hi>, the bearded catasetum. For CD’s references to Crüger’s conclusion, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 154 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 151), and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 197, 200, and 202. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4410.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 17 February [1864]</ref> and nn. 6–10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">This letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Bradford</ref>. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Bradford, 31 July 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4259.xml">letter of 31 July 1863</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Bradford</ref> disputed CD’s claims about <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi>, informing him that when collecting and cultivating orchids in Trinidad, he had found a dried specimen of the fruit with seeds. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 187–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">Layering was a method of propagating plants that involved pegging down shoots, runners, or stolons to a soil surface; adventitious roots and new plants then developed. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> offered to send CD a <hi rend="italic">Norantea</hi> specimen before Crüger’s arrived (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4404.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 9 [March] 1864</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5528.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mohl 1863</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 131). CD did read <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugo von Mohl’s</ref> paper on the small, unopening flowers (later called cleistogamic); Mohl claimed that these self-pollinating flowers contradicted CD’s assertion in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 359, that ‘nature … abhors perpetual self-fertilisation’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5528.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mohl 1863</ref>, p. 325, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 28 [November 1863]</ref>). There is an annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5528.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mohl 1863</ref> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">For Mohl’s discussion of <hi rend="italic">Ruellia clandestina</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5528.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mohl 1863</ref>, pp. 310–11, 327.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">For another report to CD on the reception of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in Germany, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3947.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Friedrich Rolle, 26 January 1863</ref>. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Junker 1989</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">While Crüger admired CD’s work on orchids, he differed from CD on some points of orchid morphology, particularly on the nature of the labellum; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, pp. 132–5, for his description of orchid morphology and its relation to theoretical considerations of development. See also n. 7, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">George Dunlop &amp; Company were general agents and shipping agents to two Royal Mail steam-packet companies (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6369.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office directory of Hampshire, Dorsetshire, and Wiltshire</hi></ref> 1867). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> asked her son William, who lived in Southampton, to send for the parcel and forward it by rail to the Down postman (letter from Emma Darwin to W. E. Darwin, [15 February 1864], in DAR 219.1: 79).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 131. The genus <hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi> is composed of bees from tropical South America that have a proboscis considerably longer than their body.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28">Amabilis: ‘Worthy of love’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>