<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-572">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. D. Fox   [7 June 1840]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7060</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-572 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-572.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-572.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">9pp inc</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 195</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Christ’s College Library, Cambridge (MS 53 Fox 60)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_83.xml">CCLC</repository>
                    <collection>MS 53</collection>
                    <idno>Fox 60</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                <date when="1840-06-07">[7 June 1840]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml">Fox, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Family news.</p>
            <p>CD’s health is improving, but he has scarcely put pen to paper in the last half-year, and everything in the publishing line is going backwards.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, good or improving</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1202">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">news</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Maer]</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">about seven lines missing</hi> 〉old friend much to endure in the ill-health of your wife.— There is a degree of anxiety about the health of 〈<hi rend="underline">about ten lines missing</hi> 〉<ref target="#foot.f2"/> boy—(William Erasmus,—proper <hi rend="underline">family </hi> names)—he is a prodigy of beauty &amp; intellect. He is so charming, that I cannot pretend to any modesty.— I defy anybody to flatter us on our baby,—for I defy anyone to say anything, in its praise, of which we are not fully conscious.—</p>
<p>He is a charming little fellow, &amp; I had not the smallest concepcion there was so much in a five month baby:— You will perceive, by this, that I have a fine degree of paternal fervour. And now for myself, about whom I can now give a very good account.— I have during the last six weeks been gradually, though very slowly, gaining strength &amp; health, but previous to that time I was for nearly six months in very indifferent health, so that I felt the smallest exertion most irksome. This is the reason I have been so long without writing</p>
<p>I had no spirits to do anything. I have scarcely put pen to paper for the last half year, &amp; everything in the publishing line is going backwards— I have been much mortified at this, but there is no help, but patience.—</p>
<p>My Father, who has certainly in a quite unexpected degree put me on the course in getting well, (having put a stop to periodical vomiting to which I was subject) feels pretty sure that I shall before long get quite well.— At present I only want vigour—in wanting which, however, one wants almost all, which makes life endurable.—</p>
<p>We came here the day before yesterday and are enjoying the delightful smell of the damp earth &amp; plants.— I think we shall never be able to stick all our lives in London, &amp; our present castle in the air is to live near a station in Surrey about 20 miles from Town.— We shall remain here about a month.— should my health continue getting stronger, I will, should all things be fitting with you, pay you a flying visit.— I want much to see your house.— it is always very pleasant to have a picture of a person’s residence rise before one, when one thinks of the person.— At present, however, I am determined to obey implicitly my Father &amp; remain absolutely quiet.— You speak in your letter of going with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Fox to the sea.— pray send me a short note before long, telling me your plans.— I hope M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Fox came home from Osmaston as well as could be expected after her confinement.— What an awful affair a confinement is: it knocked me up, almost as much as it did Emma herself.—</p>
<p>You ask about scientific news— I have none to tell, for I have of late literally seen no one except Lyell occasionally.— He is going to start immediately to examine Fren〈ch〉 Tertiary deposits—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have not seen Henslow for a long time, though I have occasionally heard from him. He likes his living exceedingly, &amp; is growing fat.— He is very active, giving scientific lectures to parish &amp; whole neighbourhood: displaying fire works, &amp; preparing for publication a continuation of Lindley &amp; Hutton’s fossil coal Flora.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Pray remember me most kindly to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Fox, &amp; believe me dear Fox, your’s affectionately | Chas. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.5 was] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘have been’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.8 in the publishing line] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.9 help] ‘p’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘f’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.4 wanting] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘saying’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">5.6 for publication] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">5.7 coal] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated from the postmark and the reference to William’s age as five months. CD’s ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, Appendix II) for 1840 reads ‘June 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Went to Maer &amp; paid a visit to Shrewsbury’, but the entry appears to be a mistake made in retrospect. A note on the letter in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin’s</ref> hand reads ‘W. D. Fox July 7 1840’, perhaps because the ‘Journal’ entry caused Francis to read the ‘JU’ in the postmark as an abbreviation for July. However, the date stamp for that month would have read ‘JY’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">All except the bottom few lines have been excised from the first and second pages.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Lyell left for France in July (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wilson 1972</ref>, pp. 490–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lindley and Hutton 1831–7.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>