<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11635">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Francis Darwin   30 July [1878]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19833</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11635 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11635.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11635.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 211: 41</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>211: 41</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-07-30">30 July [1878]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on function of bloom.</p> 
<p>Describes the effect of water shortage on sleep movements in <hi rend="italic">Porlieria</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Porlieria</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">bloom</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>July 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear old Backy</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am very sorry you have been again “slack”. Your 2 last letters very interesting &amp; valuable, &amp; you have got a fine lot of knowledge out of Sachs. But you are an impudent dog, as the beginning of your last note shows.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be very glad to see De Vries here, but we leave home on the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. &amp; shall be away about 3 weeks; though if Fanny Hensleigh sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. come here soon, we may, I suppose have to alter our plans. about returning.— Tell Vries this if you see him.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Observe, if you can, whether the water obtains anything from the <hi rend="underline">bloomless</hi> or cleaned petals of Helvingia.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> If you have any flowers, you might hang up a few cleaned &amp; uncleaned about relative shrivelling or drying.—</p>
                    <p>Sachs remark about the stomata seems very important; yet I can hardly understand how with M. Mer the leaves of so many plants kept alive for many days or even weeks when fairly immersed in water. I thought that each leaf chiefly depended on its own power of breathing &amp; nourishing itself. I wonder what Sachs w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. say to Mer’s statements.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>I quite agree with what Sachs says that certain actions of plants or effects on them are neither advantageous or disadvantageous: unless, for instance, light produced some tendency to move or some effect, there could have been no beginning to acquiring perfect heliotropism or apheliotropism.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>My Porliera was last watered on July 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; yesterday it seemed dying; but the leaves have never slept during the day, even not those on twig in bottle with quick-lime. It did not even sleep <hi rend="underline">last night</hi> from “dry rigidity”, but recovered when watered with wonderful quickness.— My notion now is that agitation from wind &amp; dryness is cause of the diurnal sleep.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Your affect Father | C. Darwin</p>
                    <p>Your observations on manner of growth of free &amp; coiled twiners seems <hi rend="underline">eminently</hi> well worth investigation.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>I wrote on double paper by mistake<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.3 about returning.—] <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.3 Tell … him.] <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.1 <hi rend="italic">bloomless</hi> or cleaned 3.2] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">5.1 or … them] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">5.3 or] <hi rend="italic">after del comma</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">5.3 there] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">6.2 in] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n8">6.3  last night] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi></note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n9">9.1 I … mistake] <hi rend="italic">added red crayon at top of letter</hi> </note>
            </div>
             
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11628.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 24 and 25 July 1878</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11628.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 24 and 25 July 1878</ref>, reporting being unwell and also his conversations with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref>. The second letter from Francis, with the impudent beginning, has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugo de Vries</ref> was working in Sachs’s laboratory in Würzburg. The Darwins visited family in Surrey and Staffordshire between 7 and 22 August 1878 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)). The only mention of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5010.xml">Frances Emma Elizabeth Wedgwood</ref> in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary for August 1878 is a note on 23 August recording ‘Fanny H. v. poorly’ (DAR 242). In the event, De Vries visited CD at the home of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref> in Abinger, Surrey (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11662.xml">letter to Hugo de Vries, [15] August [1878]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Sachs had shown Francis the fruit of <hi rend="italic">Helvingia ruscifolia</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Helwingia ruscifolia</hi>); Francis had suggested that the petals, which closed over the carpel, might be covered with bloom because they acted like a part of the fruit (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11623.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, [21 July 1878]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Sachs suggested that leaves wanted to keep dry in order to keep their stomata open to breathe (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11628.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 24 and 25 July 1878</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Émile Mer</ref> had suggested that submerged leaves could survive as long as they continued to produce starch, and that various factors such as species, age, temperature, etc., affected this ability (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mer 1876</ref>, pp. 257–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11628.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 24 and 25 July 1878</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Plants of <hi rend="italic">Porlieria</hi> in Würzburg were observed to sleep even during the day, while the plant CD borrowed from Kew did not. At first CD had assumed daytime sleep was caused by dry conditions, but his observations on the Kew plant did not support this view (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11628.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 24 and 25 July 1878</ref> and n. 1). Francis, having seen a twig sent by CD, suspected the plants in Würzburg were not the same species as the one from Kew (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11596.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, [after 7 July 1878]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">This may be a reference to the missing letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> (see n. 2, above).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD did not realise that two sheets were stuck together when he turned over the paper to write on what he thought was the verso of the first page. He then used the verso of the first two pages to write the remainder of his letter.</note>
                       
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>