<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4143">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. C. Ramsay   6 May 1863</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17934</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4143 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4143.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4143.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 11</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 11</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml">Ramsay, A. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Dolaucothy</placeName>
                <date when="1863-05-06">6 May 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Glad CD likes his Presidential Address to Geological Society [1863].</p>
            <p>Will continue the practice [of discussing the break in succession of strata].</p>
            <p>Has devised a diagram showing number of genera and species in each geological formation and the number that pass from formation to formation.</p>
            <p>Describes the glaciated terrain of S. Wales.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">break in succession of strata</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">glaciated terrain</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Wales, S.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Darwin, C. R. 1863a</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">imperfection of geological record</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number of species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Geological Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>DolauCothy, Llandielo</placeName>
                    <date>6 May 1863</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Having nothing to do I am so lazy that I have neglected for some days to answer your welcome letter.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In truth I have been here now 4 weeks trying to coax myself by idleness into my usual health. I have I hope partially succeeded but not thoroughly as yet. The prescription is however pleasant, viz a lovely place, old &amp; well beloved friends a good library including plenty of novels, some pretty girls, my wife &amp; one of my daughters,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> good trout streams and a horse to ride on when I want it.</p>
<p>I am very glad that you approve of my address.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I supposed that if properly treated the subject would be sure to interest you both as a geologist &amp; a Zoologist. Sir Charles Lyell writes me that he hopes I will continue the subject precisely as I began it if I continue President.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Such was my intention with possible additions in the summing up. Sir Charles wishes that experienced Surveyors all over the Continent would each do the same for their own Countries, but from what I have seen of Continental Surveys the mapping has not been done in sufficient detail to admit of it. Sella who reported to the Italian government on the Subject said to me that all the Continental surveys were done too <hi rend="underline">rapidly</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> For years I have had a diagram which I used in my lectures,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> something like one that you suggest, but with a considerable difference, &amp; I thought of using it in my next address if I can find time to correct it up to date.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>It is like this<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>It shows the number of species in each formation, the number of genera, &amp; also the number of genera &amp; species that pass from one formation to another, &amp; is very instructive.</p>
<p>Logan has a splendid Case in Canada of a cliff overlapped in the way you mention.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> All the rocks concerned in the question are Old Silurian &amp;c. I have no doubt he will send you a copy of the book when published.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I know of no positive case in England, but we have something like it too. “Creeps” are certainly often over the land.</p>
<p>You do me too much honour in supposing that I can give a satisfactory philosophical discussion on these &amp; the other points you mention, but it must be done some day, &amp; if I live &amp; thrive perhaps I may try my hand at it.</p>
<p>Have you seen Geikie’s new book on the Drift of Scotland?<ref target="#foot.f11"/> It seems excellent.</p>
<p>This South Welsh land is full of Scratched stones &amp; boulders. When I mapped it 20 years ago I knew the erratics when I saw them but I had then never seen a glacier &amp; was not up to the <hi rend="underline">Scratched</hi> stones.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> There is a good field here still remaining for any one to work out in that way. For want of clear sections I cannot say whether the detritus is all or mostly <hi rend="underline">iceberg</hi> work, or whether land ice did a deal of it. There are no <hi rend="underline">mountains</hi> here, but all the country is hilly.</p>
<p>Ever sincly | And<hi rend="superscript">rew</hi> C Ramsay</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-4131.xml" resp="#automat">Letter to A. C. Ramsay, 29 April [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Ramsay was staying at the house of his widowed friend <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2580.xml">John Johnes</ref> of Dolaucothy, Llandeilo, Carmarthenshire, Wales, who had one unmarried daughter, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2579.xml">Elizabeth</ref>; his other daughter was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2577.xml">Charlotte Anna Maria Cookman</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1596.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">County families</hi></ref> 1860–76; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2775.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geikie 1895</ref>, pp. 76, 278, 340). Ramsay and his wife Louisa had four daughters and one son (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4131.xml" resp="#automat">letter to A. C. Ramsay, 29 April [1863]</ref>. Ramsay gave his presidential address to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref> on 20 February 1863, taking as his theme breaks in succession in the British Palaeozoic strata (Ramsay 1863). Ramsay concurred with CD’s argument that the imperfection of the geological record explained the absence of transitional links between many species in successive geological formations (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2706A.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter from A. C. Ramsay, 21 February 1860)</ref>. In his address, Ramsay introduced the idea that the periods of time for which there was no stratigraphical evidence might be longer than the geological periods that were represented by stratified formations (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2775.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geikie 1895</ref>, pp. 357–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Ramsay was president of the Geological Society from 1862 to 1864 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). CD had also encouraged Ramsay to continue his discussion with reference to breaks in succession in other strata (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4131.xml" resp="#automat">letter to A. C. Ramsay, 29 April [1863]</ref>). See also n. 7, below. Ramsay’s presidential address for 1864 discussed breaks in succession in the British Mesozoic strata (Ramsay 1864).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Ramsay refers to the Italian geologist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4284.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quintino Sella</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6895.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sarjeant 1980–96</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Ramsay probably refers to the annual series of lectures that he delivered at the Royal School of Mines, where he was professor of geology.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4131.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Ramsay of 29 April [1863]</ref>, CD suggested that Ramsay publish a diagram of the physical breaks in the British geological record, indicating the percentage of fossils that continued to appear in the stratum above a break. Ramsay included tables showing the numbers and percentages of fossil species that passed from one formation to another in Mesozoic strata in his presidential address to the Geological Society in 1864 (Ramsay 1864).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The lines on the graph represent the number of genera and species found in each geological formation and (on the intersections with the vertical lines) the respective number surviving from each formation to the next. For clarity, the genera line has been depicted here as a grey line to distinguish it from the species line. The annotation of the graph is only complete with reference to the Devonian and Carboniferous formations. In the Devonian formation, for example, the number of species rises to a peak of 600 and the number of genera rises to a peak of 100. In passing from the Devonian to the Carboniferous, 50 genera and 10 species are common to both formations. The number of species common to two formations is invariably smaller than the number of genera because in the intervening period many species have become extinct, while different species of the same genera have arisen. Ramsay eventually chose a tabular rather than a diagrammatic format to represent changes in the occurrence of fossil genera and species between geological formations (Ramsay 1864).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The reference is to the Canadian geologist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2978.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Edmond Logan</ref>; the case referred to is described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4850.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Logan] 1863</ref>, pp. 295–7. In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4131.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 29 April [1863]</ref>, CD suggested that Ramsay might discuss creeps (slow, more or less continuous movements of rocks under gravitational stresses), and asked: ‘why do we not often find, old sea-cliff overlapped?’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Ramsay refers to a report of the Geological Survey of Canada (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4850.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Logan] 1863</ref>) summarising the work of the survey since 1843. CD does not appear to have received a copy of this publication.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geikie 1863</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1836.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Archibald Geikie</ref> was a colleague of Ramsay’s on the Geological Survey of Great Britain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">After joining the staff of the Geological Survey of Great Britain in 1841, Ramsay spent the first four years mapping the geology of South Wales (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). In the 1840s, the role of glaciation in shaping the landscape of Britain was only just beginning to be appreciated (see Davies 1969, pp. 266–316). Ramsay subsequently conducted fieldwork that used scratched stones and boulders as evidence of past glaciation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6516.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1855</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>