<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6129">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From George Thurber   18–20 April 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10980</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6129 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6129.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6129.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp ††</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 120</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 120</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent" subtype="personGrp">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4745.xml">Thurber, George</persName>
                
                <placeName>New York</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1868-04-18" notAfter="1868-04-20">18–20 Apr 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>About an American edition of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>
                    <date>April 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1868</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Mr Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Our Excellent friend Doctor Gray sent me your note to him of March 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. and added “you drop Darwin a line—it will be both well and pleasant, giving your address.”<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Assuming this to be a sufficient introduction, I will say that the publishing house is Orange Judd &amp; Company, 245 Broadway. Besides publishing the most extensively circulated popular Agricultural Journal in the country, they are also the largest publishers of Agricultural books. My position with them is that of managing editor of the paper &amp; general adviser with respect to books—</p>
<p>Although your book is a little out of the line of Agricultural works proper I had a strong desire that our house should republish it and had talked with the firm about making an arrangement with you through Gray.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Soon after, Gray happened along and proposed the same thing himself. There was some delay in deciding, as I was obliged to run the book through to be able to assure them that it was not likely to upset the whole social fabric—for those who never read a word of your writings sometimes have odd notions about them. When it was concluded to reprint it was thought best to push it as rapidly as possible &amp; we found that we could save time by transferring the cuts &amp; re-engraving them here— We find it very desirable to not have odd sizes among our books, &amp; yours is made of one of our standard sizes, a little smaller page. This involved changing the figures of the index—but I think it was accurately done— Though the volumes have not such a sumptuous air as the English they are very neat and I think you will not be displeased with them. They will sell at $6—while the imported is $14—</p>
<p>As to its sale, it is not easy to predict— The class of readers who are able to appreciate such a work is not proportionately so large with us as with you— The present work will not have the benefit of the abuse that fell to the Origin of Species—but I think that every one who has that would want this. I much hope it will be successful as I was mainly instrumental in its publication, as well as for the desire that something may accrue to you— I send some copies of our paper, the Agriculturist, that you may see something of what we are doing— You will find in the May Number—an illustrated notice of your work—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You will perhaps regard it as rather undignified— if you do, you must consider the very popular character of the Journal—and that knowing my readers I presented it in a way most likely to interest them. Today I got the sheets of reprint from Gray and your M.S. corrections. As both volumes were printed these have to go in on a page or two of corrigenda.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Should another edition be called for—they, with others, may be worked into the pages.</p>
<p>If you would care for it I should be pleased to continue to send the Agriculturist to you— It is the medium through which a large number of readers may be reached, and if you have occasion, as I see you do at home—to ask for information or observations on any particular points, I should be very glad to make your requests known—</p>
<p>Aside from an editorial interest in the matter, from a scientific point of view, I am delighted that we bring out your work— I have only read it, but intend to <hi rend="underline">study</hi> it— Pangenesis makes one hold his breath.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> My friends think me Darwin mad—</p>
<p>I had no idea of making so long a letter &amp; probably shall not have occasion to inflict you at such length again—</p>
<p>Allow me to present my sincere regards, and at the same time thank you for the instruction &amp; pleasure your writings have given me—</p>
<p>Yours | George Thurber <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">245 Broadway. | New York. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Apr— 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</p>
<p>I did not send the foregoing as I wished it to go by the same steamer with the book—which was delayed a little at the binders. We shall try to have the work well reviewed— Gray will see to having notices in Sillimans Journal &amp; Sprague will review it in the Atlantic.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I met a few evenings ago the editor of the North American Review at the Dickens dinner, &amp; he had already read the English edition &amp; was full of it.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The book &amp; papers will go by this weeks steam. If I can be of any service to you here please command me</p>
<p>G. T.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘Very kind &amp; pleasant letter &amp; for the copy of my Book. I most sincerely hope it may answer, but it is bold speculation. I am greatly indebted to you for your favourable opinion, which led to its publication in your country, which has naturally gratified me much.— | Pangenesis.— | Illustrations &amp; wonderful <hi rend="italic">[</hi>mass<hi rend="italic">]</hi> of miscellaneous matter— I certainly sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> much like to have copies for rest of year | Pike | Sexes’<ref target="#foot.f8"/> <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Asa Gray of 11 March 1868</ref> has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5921.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 24 February 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Thurber refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Thurber refers to the <hi rend="italic">American Agriculturist</hi>, a journal he had edited since 1863, and to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7753.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Thurber] 1868</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ANB</hi></ref>). No copies of the magazine have been found in the Darwin Library.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD probably sent corrections in late March (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 25 March [1868]</ref>). The ‘Author’s preface’ to the American edition is dated 28 March 1868; three pages of corrections are inserted following the preface (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7953.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> US ed.</ref> 1: i–iv).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Thurber refers to CD’s hypothesis of heredity (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 357–404).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Gray’s review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> had appeared in the 19 March 1868 edition of the <hi rend="italic">Nation</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[A. Gray] 1868</ref>). Thurber probably refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4501.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isaac Sprague</ref>. An unsigned review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> appeared in the July 1868 issue of <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> ([Sprague?] 1868). A brief notice of the publication of the American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> is in <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> 2d ser. 45 (1868): 411. The journal was popularly known as ‘Silliman’s Journal’ after its founder, Benjamin Silliman.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Thurber refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3560.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Eliot Norton</ref> and to a public dinner held on 18 April 1868 in New York in honour of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Dickens</ref>, who had been touring America since November 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Meckier 1990</ref>, p. 238). Norton had delivered a short speech at the dinner (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7947.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vanderbilt 1959</ref>, p. 103).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD’s annotations are notes for his reply to Thurber, which has not been found. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 14, CD cited an article in <hi rend="italic">American Agricultural</hi> (1868), p. 100, for information on the colours of male pike during the breeding season.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>