<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11426F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">From James Torbitt   15 March 1878</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">21844</idno>
                
                
                
                
                
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11426F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11426F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11426F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">Printed encl</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 140</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                        <collection>DAR</collection>
                        <idno>178: 140</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4777.xml">Torbitt, James</persName>
                    <placeName>Belfast</placeName>
                    <date when="1878-03-15">15 Mar 1878</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p>Enclosure: printed copies of letters from people who have grown his potato seed (pages from Torbitt 1876).</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="plants" ref="#">potato</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                
                
                <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" n="2">
                    
                    <div type="transcription">
                        
                        <p>Ground well ventilated and drained. Stable manure used.</p>
                        <p>Grown in hot-house and transplanted. Some of the tubers were full size. Sown in April, transplanted in June. No disease; but a few tubers were eaten by earth worms and slugs. I think the tubers will take the disease in the course of two or three years (see Mr. W. G. Smith’s report on the potato fungus.) [This report is reprinted in full above, J. T.] Some of the plants had very small foliage, and almost all flowered. A few had seed-apples, but they did not come to maturity. One, a white kidney, (the best of the fine sorts) was very small in the foliage.</p>
                        <p>Alfred L. M’Calmont.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>Moy, 10<hi rend="underline">th December</hi>, 1875.</p> </figure> 
                        <p>Seedlings were grown just beside diseased potatoes. Locality well ventilated. Farm yard manure used. Those planted in March grew larger, and resisted disease better. About eighty or ninety plants per hundred absolutely resisted the disease. Of the plants infected, about one tenth by weight of the tubers was infected. I have seedlings of three years’ age which give as large or a larger yield than the set.</p>
                        <p>Samuel Corrigan.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Grange, Portadown, 15<hi rend="underline">th December</hi>, 1876.</p> </figure> 
                        <p>Soil good rich clay with sand. Well ventilated. Stable Manure. Grown in field and thinned out. Sown 17th March and 15th April. 17th March, no disease; 15th April, disease hardly perceptible. Unimportant portion of the diseased tubers was infected. I believe that the seed when properly cultivated gives a larger yield than the varieties now grown from the set. I believe the disease may be extinguished by the means you propose. I <hi rend="underline">think the government should take it up.</hi></p>
                        <p>Richard Allen.”</p>
                        <p>“The seedlings were grown in boxes in my green-house in March, afterwards potted, afterwards planted out. About 9 out of 10 plants absolutely resisted the disease. Of the plants infected most of the tubers were infected. There were about 20 to 30 tubers per root (or seed) about as large as walnuts. I believe the set gives a larger crop than the seed. I think the disease is atmospheric, and do not believe growing potatoes from the seed will prevent it, any more than using sets.</p>
                        <p>J. W. Robinson.<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
                        <p rend="left">Tetton Hall, Wyberton, Boston, 10<hi rend="underline">th December</hi>, 1875.</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“<hi rend="underline">December</hi>, 1875.</p> </figure> 
                        <p>The seedlings were grown in next drill to diseased potatoes. Disease had always developed itself in the field since I got it five years ago. Soil old, rich and heavy. Ill ventiated. Farm yard manure used. Sown in April, and tubers attained about half size. I don’t know how many plants per hundred absolutely resisted the disease, but the greater number were affected. Of these, about one eighth by weight, of the tubers, was affected. I believe the means you propose is the only possible way of extirpating the disease, and I believe they will be successful. It is not my belief that researches such as these should be left to the unaided efforts of individuals.</p>
                        <p>Henry Mathers, <hi rend="underline">Newforge House, Maralin.</hi>”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>Ballynegh, 14 <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December</hi>, 1875. J. Torbitt, Esq. Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>I enclose you the paper you were so good as to send to fill up. I will pay more attention in the future as I am greatly interested. I am conscious I did not give half the attention I might have done to the culture of the potato seed you so kindly sent me; nor did I give it the observation I know now it is entitled to. All the excuse I can make to you is, my experience was young. I was ignorant altogether, not knowing even what the seed of the berry was like; and people I showed it to laughed at the idea of any sized tubers growing from such a small seed. It was only when the crop was coming to maturity we had any belief, and the results at raising time surprised us; and then one is so interested in the different sorts, and the different sorts of haulm likewise. I only sowed three perches of a drill and there were four sorts of haulm and the same of tubers. We had rather better than 21lbs. and more than we deserve, for I had no faith in them; but now I see my error, and that your time, trouble, expense and research, is a noble and good work, and deserves every consideration.</p>
                        <p>Yours respectfully, | Alexander Napier.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p><hi rend="underline">Report referred to by </hi>Mr. Napier<hi rend="underline">, in foregoing letter.</hi></p> </figure> 
                        <p>In the same field with the seedlings, we had Skerry Blues, which have been more diseased this year than in any of the previous eight years. In my opinion, in about six or eight years they will be as bad as the Rocks are now. The soil was kindly and dry, the field well ventilated, and we used farm-yard manure, sowed the seed in beginning of April; but weather turned in dry and cold, and it did not braird till the rain came, which was about a month after. I sowed the seed like turnip, in drills with deep track in centre; and when commencing to have good strong tops, raked down the shoulders of the drills, thinning afterwards about 9 inches apart [<hi rend="underline">about half the proper distance, J. T.</hi>], and there were a good number about the size of eggs, but far more numerous than any potatoes I have ever seen. About one plant in ten absolutely resisted the disease, and they kept quite green for weeks longer than any potatoes in the country, and this is interesting; for this year blight withered all sorts at the same time. Of the plants infected, I dare say about one pound of tubers in fourteen was affected; but on looking through them since, I find a very small per centage more affected. I find the plants that withered soonest are most diseased, in my opinion. I did not know what seed was till I received it from you. There was not one I showed it to, would believe I would have any tubers from it. They were as ignorant as myself; and the very persons who laughed at me were surprised to see the crop I had.</p>
                        <p>I have no hesitation in saying, and I believe it from my heart, that you will likely be the means, either directly or indirectly, of, at any rate, introducing a potato that will resist the disease for a time, and take the place of the Skerry, as I believe it is commmencing to fail; and I believe it will be a great national good. My opinion is, our Government should give every encouragement, pecuniary and other, to researches of the kind. No one for a moment would think you would get one individual in a thousand would do the same as you are doing, unaided, for the public good. Is not the potato everything, in a sense, to Ireland? When it completely failed, did not it cause famine in the land? I believe it to be a noble work of you, and that you are a benefactor to your country.</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“The Leuchold, Dalmeny Park, Edinburgh, <hi rend="underline">December</hi> 13<hi rend="underline">th</hi>, 1875. Dear Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>I regret to say that I have been most unfortunate in my experiment with the potato seed. I sowed about a quarter of an acre, in the centre of a large white crop field, and not one plant ever came up. I gave some seed to Lord —’s gardener for him to sow, he was equally unsuccessful. I sowed also a small bed in my own garden, with great care, and only three plants came up. These three grew very well—<hi rend="underline">immensely to shaws</hi> at least four feet in length; the tubers were, however, very small. One of the plants is of a distinctly different kind from the other two. The two appear to be coarse varieties, and would not suit us here. I am keeping the seeds carefully, and will plant them another season, which will better prove what they are, in respect to kinds. I think the ground being too dry must have been the cause of the seed not coming up last season.</p>
                        <p>I remain, dear Sir, your truly, | Peter Glendinning.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>Brown Farm, Biggleswade Beds, (<hi rend="underline">no date</hi>.)</p> </figure> 
                        <p>Seedlings and diseased potatoes were grown close to each other, in field diseased last season. Soil, gravel. Locality well ventilated. Manure, farm yard. Seed sown in rows in the usual manner [evidently in the field, like turnips, J. T.] in the middle of April. A little disease in the tops, none in the potato. I think your proposed plan of destroying all seedlings which become diseased, and propagating only from the tubers of those which do not become diseased, would make little or no difference in extinguishing the disease. It is my opinion it comes after thunder storms; rain alone will not produce it. I am very sorry to inform you of my loss. I had taken the greatest care of the tubers grown from the seed you sent me; they were large enough to plant next season, but I had them stored in the cellar, and the water came in very sudden and I could not get them out, so I have lost all my produce.</p>
                        <p>Yours faithfully, | John King.”</p>
                        <p>[I wrote Mr. King I should send him more seed, and I shall supply his loss with tubers grown from the seed last year, which were disease-proof here. I want to know if they will continue disease-proof in Bedfordshire, J. T.]</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Ballyclare, (<hi rend="underline">no date</hi>). Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>My garden contains 3 roods. It is a deep rich soil, which is heavily manured every year, with farm-yard manure. Every spot of it lies to the sun. I have laboured it for eleven years, and every year my potatoes were badly diseased. The seed you sent me, I sowed in the middle of March, and planted them in drills, with farm-yard manure, in the beginning of May. I never had stronger, healthier, or more beautiful plants. They were the admiration of every one; they could scarcely believe they were from the seed of the first year, and I thought they were going to resist the disease altogether, but alas it made its appearance on the leaves; but not very rapidly, and the haulm did not decay away like that of the old potato. The greater part of them blossomed and produced some seed, but not much. I raised them at the end of November. I had from 16 to 32 tubers from each seed. Not more than one-eighth were diseased, and those very slightly. The disease was almost confined to one variety, which, when cut, has black streaks.</p>
                        <p>Yours respectfully, Mary M’Fadden.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Castlewellan, <hi rend="underline">December</hi> 18<hi rend="underline">th</hi>, 1875. Sir—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>I sowed your seed in a garden sheltered by trees, where potatoes had been grown for the last 20 years, and with the half of the crop invariably bad. I transplanted the largest of the plants, and the produce amounted to about <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> cwt. to the square perch; and what was singular, I hadn’t a bad potato in the whole lot. I gave some of the plants to my neighbours, and they all report most favourably of them. Some of the plants blossomed, but none produced apples.</p>
                        <p>Yours respectfully, | Jas. O’Flinn.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Well House, Saltney, December 20th, 1875. Dear Sir.—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>The potatoes from your seed are blue-red in colour; nearly all looking like an early variety, very small, but no disease. Seeds from Patterson’s Victorias cropped rather better than yours, and are nearly all apparently the same kind as Patterson’s.</p>
                        <p>Yours very truly, | John Roberts.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Mount Hamilton, Clough Mills, 20th December, 1875. Dear Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>In the middle of April I sowed your seed in drills like turnips, only very thin, and thinned out the plants to a foot or so apart. In the whole there were not twelve diseased plants, although they grew in a garden, closely adjoining Black-hearts, which are attacked by the disease earlier than perhaps any other variety.</p>
                        <p>I am, very truly yours, | Thomas Gregg.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Dunfane, 1st January, 1876. Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>Miss Walker of Crebilly received a package of your potato seed from me on the 5th April. Some days after, she sowed it on a kind of hot-bed, and it came forward soon. She had it then transplanted to drills in a kind of boggy ground, proverbial for disease. The leaves of her seedlings were diseased, but the potatoes which were of various kinds, all resisted it; as did the haulms, and they were near diseased kinds without ditch or wall between them; and she states she had an average crop; tubers weighing 2, 3, 4, 5 ounces.</p>
                        <p>John Sloan.”</p>
                        <p>[This is the ex-Head Constable, R.I.C., writer of second report].</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“The Grange, Goole, Yorkshire. Dear Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>I have saved some of the best of those that entirely resisted the disease, and I trust the effort you are making, will be successful. If you cannot, by your plan, entirely eradicate the disease, you will, I have no doubt, raise some new and valuable varieties. My plants were sown in April, about two yards from diseased potatoes, on sandy loam, pretty well ventilated, and yard manure used. They were drilled on ridge, and thinned out. About 40 plants out of 100 absolutely resisted the disease. Of the infected plants, at some roots nearly all, at others half, and at a great many only a few—say one or two tubers at a root, were affected. I think the disease might be extinguished by your method, and I think it ought to be tried. I think the Government, or some of our great societies, ought to take up the matter.</p>
                        <p>Wishing you every success. I am, yours respectfully, | W. Smith.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“<hi rend="underline">December</hi> 25<hi rend="underline">th</hi>, 1875. Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>The plants grew very well until longer after the potatoes in the neighbourhood were diseased, and then the foliage of the seedlings became diseased also. They blossomed, but bore no ‘plums.’ They were sown on 11th and 13th March, close beside diseased potatoes, in a field in which the disease has always shown itself since it commenced; soil, loam; part well, part ill ventilated; manure, farm-yard and a little guano. A few tubers were nearly full size; about 70 plants per 100 absolutely resisted the disease. I believe that the disease might be extinguished. I think these researches should not be left to individuals.</p>
                        <p>Your obedient servant, | W. Lamont.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p><hi rend="underline">Report from</hi> J. Bailey, Esq., <hi rend="underline">Shirley, Southampton</hi>, per Mr. Blundell.</p> </figure> 
                        <p>“Seedlings were grown within about 30 feet of old diseased potatoes, and with nothing between them. Disease had developed itself in the garden each year; soil gravelly, well ventilated; seed sown 7th April. A few tubers attained full size, and about 80 per 100 plants resisted the disease absolutely.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“<hi rend="underline">Report.</hi></p> </figure> 
                        <p>Soil light sandy, pretty open though well sheltered; liberally manured in Autumn, with farm-yard manure; disease in the garden the year before; grown on a seed-bed about middle of April; transplanted, and only a few of the tubers were of a good size. Very few of them were at all touched by the disease, and those few were all white varieties. The plants being too close, they did not give this year so large a crop as the set. I think it is a likely way of extinguishing the disease. W. G.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Crossburn, Troon, 10<hi rend="underline">th January</hi>, 1876. Dear Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>I sowed the seed on a hot bed about the beginning of March, and planted out in a garden, on good horse manure, on the 4th of June, about 1,200 or 1,500 seedlings. I think the ground and the manure had been too strong, as the potatoes, which were not ready to lift till November, were so badly worm-eaten that it was impossible to say much about them; there seemed a great number of varieties amongst them, and a red kind in particular appeared more susceptible to disease than any of the others. Whereas a white kind which bulked well, though small, did not disease at all.</p>
                        <p>I am, yours faithfully, | W. Guthrie.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p><hi rend="underline">Report</hi>, Author <hi rend="underline">not known.</hi></p> </figure> 
                        <p>Sowed seed in a drill between cruffles and flounders on the 18th March, 1875. Had potatoes of different kinds, of which about one cwt. of twenty was diseased.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p><hi rend="underline">Report from</hi> S. Thompson, Esq., <hi rend="underline">Muckamore Abbey, Antrim.</hi></p> </figure> 
                        <p>“Sowed, part in seed-bed, part out, some tubers full size, grown in rich garden soil, in which there was disease this year, locality well ventilated, manure common. Fully 90 per cent. of the plants resisted the disease absolutely.”</p> 
                        <figure type="diagram"> 
                            <p>“Killinchy, Co. Down, 12<hi rend="underline">th March</hi>, 1876. Dear Sir,—</p> </figure> 
                        <p>I think it right to let you know how the potato seed you kindly sent me last year has turned out.</p>
                        <p>I sowed some in hot-beds and hardened them off, then transplanted them, in drills two feet apart, some I sowed in the open air, thinned them out to proper distances, and planted the thinnings; from all I had a tolerable fair crop, <hi rend="underline">not one diseased</hi>; but the seed from the hot-beds were the largest; I suppose because they had an earlier and better season to grow.</p>
                        <p>I have twelve distinct sorts. I have long ones as black as jet, something like what was called ‘Black Lords,’ long ago. I have evidently Kidneys, and round ones of various colours. I shall plant them all whole this season again; and if you have any hint to throw out for my guidance, it shall be carried out by yours very truly,</p>
                        <p>James M’Cann.</p>
                        <p>P.S.—You might send me a very small sample of seed. J. M’C.”</p>
                        <p>It is now 28th of March, the printer wants copy, and the seed should be in the ground at once; I must therefore record my own experience rapidly and without revision.</p>
                        <p>I sowed seed in a hot house 1st January, 1875; on a seed bed in the open, 24th March; in a conservatory without artificial heat on 4th April; again, some time in May, in the open air. The sowings of 1st January and 4th April were planted out about middle of May. The 4th April gave the better result, both as regards yield and resistance to disease. The sowing of 24th March, owing to cold winds (I suppose) did not give so good yield as the sowing of</p> 
                    </div>
                    
                </div>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
            </div>
            
          
        
            
          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>