<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7510">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   24 February 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5292</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7510 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7510.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7510.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 55</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 55</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1871-02-24">24 Feb 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Received copy of <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses CD’s comments on EH’s work.</p>
            <p>Speculates about reception by press and scientists.</p>
            <p>Remarks on sexual selection;</p>
            <p>on human relationship to catarrhine apes.</p>
            <p>Has rejected offer of chair at Vienna.</p>
            <p>Compares Jena to Down.</p>
            <p>Describes growth of his salary.</p>
            <p>Mentions birth of Emma Haeckel.</p>
            <p>A. M. Norman’s collection of calcareous sponges is very valuable.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">apes, catarrhine</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sponges, calcareous</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Haeckel, Emma</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3551">Norman, A. M.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4972">scientists</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Down</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Jena</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">professorship at Vienna</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">University of Vienna</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>24. Febr 71</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Sir | Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>Mein theurer, hochverehrter Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Gestern überraschte mich Ihr kostbares Geschenk, die zwei inhaltschweren Bände “The Descent of man”, und obwohl ich erst einen Theil des kostbaren Werkes gestern und heute habe durchgehen können, will ich doch nicht zögern, Ihnen sofort meinen <hi rend="underline">herzlichsten</hi> und <hi rend="underline">innigsten Dank</hi> abzustatten.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich brauche Ihnen nicht erst zu sagen, theurer Freund, wie <hi rend="underline">ganz ausserordentlich</hi> vor Allen grade mich Ihr Werk interessirt und entzückt. Sind ja doch die darin entwickelten und so meisterhaft ausgeführten Gedanken und Entwickelungs-Ideen dieselben, mit denen ich mich tagtäglich trage, für die ich kämpfe und arbeite, und für die ich die heftigsten Angriffe der Gegner beständig empfange.</p>
<p>Eine werthvollere Anerkennung meiner aufrichtigen Bestrebungen, ein glänzederen Triumph meiner Ansichten, ein schöneren Lohn für meine Anstrengungen, als Ihre Lobsprüche und Ihre Übereinstimmung, konnte mir <hi rend="underline">niemals</hi> zu Theil werden. Der gestrige Tag war für mich der Tag meines grössten wissenschaftlichen Triumphes!<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Nur fürchte ich, mein theurer Freund, dass Sie <hi rend="underline">allzu gütig</hi> und nachsichtig gegen mich gewesen sind, und meine Verdienste <hi rend="underline">allzu sehr</hi> überschätzt haben. Wenn Sie mir früher vorgeworfen haben, dass ich allzuviel Ehren und Auszeichnungen durch meine begeisterte Verherrlichung des Darwinismus auf Ihr Haupt häufe, so muss ich Ihnen jetzt diesen Vorwurf mit viel grösserem Rechte zurückgeben. Hoffentlich werde ich Ihr Lob später besser verdienen können!</p>
<p>Was wird aber Ihr Werk für einen <hi rend="underline">colossalen Eindruck und Erfolg</hi> haben! Mit welcher Spannung es schon längst von der Presse erwartet wurde, ahnen Sie nicht! Die meisten deutschen Blätter haben schon im Voraus über seinen Inhalt sich gestritten, und nicht wenige haben behauptet, dass der “besonnene, milde, unbefangene Darwin” die Anwendung seiner Theorie auf den Menschen nicht dulden, und namentlich den “<hi rend="underline">Hyperdarwinismus</hi>” des “leidenschaftlichen, übertriebenen, radicalen Haeckel” entschieden desavouiren werde!</p>
<p>Was wird der hochweise Pariser Central-Anthropolog, Msr. Quatefrages (—welcher Rückschlag in der Ahnenreihe!) dazu sagen? —und was der confuse Bastian?—und was Herr Rütimeyer, dessen linke Gehirnhälfte darwinistisch und dessen rechte (—nebst des ganzen Plexus choroidei—) orthodox pfäffisch ist?<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Welche Fülle von Belehrung und Genuss mir Ihre specielle Durchführung der <hi rend="underline">Selection sexual</hi> durch die ganze Thierreihe gewährt, hat mir schon die erste flüchtige Durchsicht gezeigt. Ich freue mich ungemein, diesen höchst wichtigen Gegenstand so unübertrefflich anschaulich und klar ausgeführt zu finden. Er gehört zu den interessantesten in der ganzen Biologie.</p>
<p>Dass Sie speciell die <hi rend="underline">Catarrhinen</hi> in Ihr Ahnen-Recht eingesetzt haben, ist mir die grösste Genugthuung! Es ist unglaublich, welche Opposition grade dieses so einfache und klare, aus logisch consequenter Systematik folgende Verhältniss hervorgerufen hat. Nicht allein kenntnisslose Laien, sondern sogar gelehrte Naturforscher, wollten lieber von den Ungulaten als von den Catarrhinen abstammen!<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Offenbar, weil das letztere Verhältniss zu einleuchtend ist!</p>
<p>Ich selbst bin jetzt noch fortdauernd mit der Monographie der Calcispongien beschäftigt, und hoffe sie in diesem Jahre zu beendigen. Um die letzten Untersuchungen an lebenden Grantien zu vollenden, gehe ich nächsten Mittwoch (1. März) nach Triest und Dalmatien, wo ich 2 Monat (bis Ende April) arbeiten werde.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Ihr kostbares Werk begleitet mich, und ich freue mich im Voraus, welchen Genuss mir die Lectüre der “Sexual Selection” in den Musse Stunden dort gewähren wird.</p>
<p>Die Kalkschwämme sind für die Descendenz Theorie <hi rend="underline">höchst interessant.</hi> Alle Systematik in gewöhnlichem Sinne hört hier auf, und man kann nur durch <hi rend="underline">genealogische</hi> Classification zum Verständniss kommen. Ich hoffe, dass Ihnen diese Darwinistische Monographie manche Freude machen wird.</p>
<p>Die letzten Monate waren für mich sehr unruhig und bewegt. Zu Weihnachten erhielt ich eine sehr ehrenvolle Berufung als Professor der Zoologie an die Universität zu <hi rend="underline">Wien.</hi> Die glänzenden Bedingungen—besonders ein marines Laboratorium und Aquarium in <hi rend="underline">Triest</hi>, die grossen Hilfsmittel und zahlreichen Zuhörer in <hi rend="underline">Wien</hi>—waren sehr verlockend.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Ich habe einen Monat lang geschwankt, mich aber dann doch entschlossen, hier zu bleiben. Die hiesigen Verhältnisse sind zwar viel kleiner und weniger glänzend; aber ich kann hier viel besser arbeiten und viel ungestörter der Wissenschaft leben. <hi rend="underline">Gegenbaurs</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/> Verkehr ist mir unersetzlich, und wir geniessen hier die grösste <hi rend="underline">Freiheit</hi> in jeder Beziehung.</p>
<p>Wenn man mir sagte: “Aber in Wien haben Sie einen viel grösseren Wirkungskreis!”—so antwortete ich: “Jena ist immer noch grösser als Down, und Darwin hat dort demnoch den grössten Wirkungskreis von allen heutigen Naturforschern!”</p>
<p>Da ich nun hier geblieben bin, haben sich auch meine materiellen Verhältnisse sehr gebessert. Ich bin jetzt zehn Jahre grade hier. In den ersten 5 Jahren hatte ich nur 50 £, in den letzten 5 Jahren 100 £ Gehalt. Jetzt ist nun mein Gehalt wieder verdoppelt worden, und ich bekomme 200 £ Sterl. Damit kann ich meine kleine Familie schon besser ernähren. Sie ist am 10. Januar um eine kleine Emma vermehrt worden.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Mein Walter, jetzt 2<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> Jahr alt, entwickelt sich sehr niedlich.</p>
<p>Ich hoffe, theurer Freund, dass es Ihnen gut geht, und dass Sie mit Ihrer lieben Familie recht wohl sind.</p>
<p>Gegenbaur bittet mich, Ihnen seinen herzlichen Dank und Gruss zu sagen.</p>
<p>Von mir selbst nochmals den Ausdruck des herzlichsten und innigsten Dankes für Ihr unschätzbares Werk</p>
<p>In unveränderter Anhänglichkeit | Ihr treulichst ergebener | Ernst Haeckel.</p>
<p>P.S. Die Kalkschwamm-Sammlung von Mr. <hi rend="underline">Norman</hi>, deren Benützung ich Ihren gütigen Fürsprache verdanke, war mir höchst werthvoll.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Ich werde sie nächsten Mai oder Juni zurückschicken.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>24. February 71</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Sir | Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>My dear, much esteemed friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Yesterday I was surprised by your precious gift, the two momentous volumes The Descent of Man, and while I have yesterday and today been able to look through the precious work in part only, I shan’t hesitate to convey to you at once my <hi rend="underline">cordial</hi> and <hi rend="underline">heartfelt</hi> thanks.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I need not tell you, valued friend, that your work more than any other interests and delights me <hi rend="underline">most exceptionally.</hi> For the thoughts and ideas about development that are developed and elaborated in such a masterly way in it, are precisely those that I myself have on my mind day in day out, for which I fight and labour, and for which I am constantly under ferocious attack by my opponents.</p>
<p>I could <hi rend="underline">never</hi> receive a more valuable acknowledgment of my sincere endeavours, a more brilliant triumph of my views, a finer reward for my exertions, than your praise and your agreement. Yesterday was for me the day of my greatest scientific triumph!<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I only fear, my dear friend, that you were <hi rend="underline">much too kind</hi> and lenient with me, and that you overestimated my merits <hi rend="underline">far</hi> too much. As you have previously remonstrated with me for bestowing far too many honours and distinctions on you, through my enthusiastic glorification of Darwinism, so must I now return this reproach with far greater cause. I hope to become more worthy of your praise in the future!</p>
<p>What a <hi rend="underline">colossal impact and success</hi> your work will have! You cannot imagine how eagerly the press has been expecting it for ages already! Most German papers had already argued over its contents in advance, and not a few of them have claimed that the “level-headed, mild and unbiassed Darwin” would not tolerate the application of his theory to man, and would decidedly repudiate in particular the “<hi rend="underline">hyper-darwinism</hi>” of the “passionate, extreme, radical Haeckel”.</p>
<p>What will the most wise Parisian central-anthropologist, Monsieur Quatrefages (—what a setback in his pedigree!) have to say?—and what the confused Bastian?—and what Herr Rütimeyer, whose left cerebral hemisphere is Darwinist, and whose right one (—along with the entire choroid plexus—) is orthodox-priestish?<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>What an abundance of instruction and enjoyment I will derive from your special application of <hi rend="underline">sexual selection</hi> to all the stages of the entire animal kingdom, I have realised already from my first fleeting glance at your work. I am inordinately pleased to find this most important matter presented in so matchlessly vivid and clear a manner. It is among the most interesting in the whole of biology.</p>
<p>That you have specifically inserted the <hi rend="underline">Catarrhines</hi> in their rightful place in your ancestral line gives me great satisfaction! It is incredible how much opposition this very relationship has encountered, which is so simple and clear and which follows logically from the systematics. Not only ignorant laypersons, but even educated natural scientists prefer to have descended from the Ungulata rather than from the catarrhines!<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Evidently because the latter relationship is too obvious!</p>
<p>I myself am still busy with the monograph on the calcareous sponges, which I hope to finish this year. To complete the final investigation of live Grantia, I shall leave for Triest and Dalmatia next Wednesday (1 March), where I will work for two months (until the end of April).<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Your valuable work will accompany me, and I am already looking forward to the pleasure I shall derive from reading “Sexual Selection” during my leisure hours there.</p>
<p>Calcareous sponges are of <hi rend="underline">great interest</hi> for the theory of descent. All systematics in the conventional sense end there, and an understanding can be achieved only through <hi rend="underline">genealogical</hi> classification. I hope you will enjoy this Darwinist monograph.</p>
<p>I have had a very restless and eventful time in recent months. At Christmas I received the very flattering offer of the professorial chair for zoology at the university of <hi rend="underline">Vienna.</hi> I was very tempted by the brilliant conditions—above all by the marine laboratory and aquarium at <hi rend="underline">Triest</hi>, as well as the considerable facilities and the large audiences at <hi rend="underline">Vienna.</hi><ref target="#foot.f7"/> I hesitated for a month, but in the end decided to stay. Conditions here are certainly on a much smaller scale and less splendid, but I can work far better here and live for science in peace and quiet. <hi rend="underline">Gegenbaur’s</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/> company to me is irreplaceable, and we enjoy the greatest <hi rend="underline">freedom</hi> in any respect here.</p>
<p>If I were told: “But at Vienna your sphere of influence would be so much greater!”—I would reply: “Jena is bigger than Down, and still Darwin has the greatest sphere of influence of all scientists today!”</p>
<p>Since I have been staying here, my financial circumstances have much improved. I have been here for ten years now. In the first 5 I had only 50 £, in the past 5 100 £. Now my income has again been doubled, and I receive 200 £ Sterling. With this I can really better sustain my little family. On 10 January it was increased by one little Emma.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> My Walter, who is now 2<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> years old, is developing very nicely.</p>
<p>I hope, dear friend, that you are in good health, and that you and your dear family are very well.</p>
<p>Gegenbaur asks me to convey his cordial thanks and greetings.</p>
<p>Let me again express my most cordial and heartfelt thanks for your invaluable work.</p>
<p>In unaltered affection | Your most loyal and devoted | Ernst Haeckel.</p>
<p>P.S.: The collection of calcareous sponges by Mr. <hi rend="underline">Norman</hi>, for the use of which I am indebted to your kind intercession, was very valuable to me.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I shall return it in May or June of next year.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haeckel’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> (Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 4, CD wrote of Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Haeckel 1868b; second edition Haeckel 1870): ‘If this work had appeared before my essay had been written, I should probably never have completed it. Almost all the conclusions at which I have arrived I find confirmed by this naturalist, whose knowledge on many points is much fuller than mine.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Armand de Quatrefages, while keeping up a cordial correspondence with CD, was sceptical of CD’s theory. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_309.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolf Bastian</ref> rejected the application of descent theory to humans (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tort 1996</ref>). Haeckel had fallen out with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig Rütimeyer</ref> in 1868 over a review of his <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Haeckel 1868b; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4494.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Krauße 1987</ref>, pp. 79–80, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3861.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hopwood 2006</ref>, pp. 283–5). The choroid plexus is an infolding of blood vessels projecting into each ventricle of the brain; they secrete the cerebrospinal fluid (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Dorland’s medical dictionary</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 196, CD classed human beings as an offshoot of the catarrhine (Old World) group of monkeys. The former order Ungulata is now divided into the orders Artiodactyla and Perissodactyla (even and odd-toed ungulates).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel’s work was published in Haeckel 1872a. For <hi rend="italic">Grantia</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 6 July 1870</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Despite being in Italy, Trieste was an Austrian city, and the University of Vienna maintained a marine zoological station there (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1898.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dean 1893</ref>, pp. 703–5; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Carl Gegenbaur.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Haeckel’s eldest daughter was Elisabeth Charlotte Emma <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Agnes Haeckel</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kornmilch 2009</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Haeckel refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3551.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Merle Norman</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6845.xml" resp="#automat">letter to A. M. Norman, 29 July [1869]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6848.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. M. Norman, 2 August 1869</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>