<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12075">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [after 2 June 1879]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9325</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12075 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12075.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12075.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp †, CD note, encl 2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 209.5: 230–2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>209.5: 230</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1879-06-03" notAfter="1882-12-31">[after 2 June 1879]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Geotropism.</p> 
<p>Experimenting on <hi rend="italic">Porlieria</hi> in damp and dry earth.</p> 
            <p>Hermann Müller has been ridiculed for teaching children "in the beginning was Carbon".</p>
            <p>Will ask about Ernst Krause.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Porlieria</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2758">Krause, E. L.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3069">Müller, H. L. H.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-11">Facsimile information added by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-11-01" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-13" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-13" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-08-13" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00484_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00484_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="230r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00484.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00484_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00484.dzi" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="230v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00485.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00485_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00005-000-00485.dzi" width="3195px" height="6298px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Here is an abstract about the firs: Stahl says it is impossible to be certain about your piece of wood but he thinks a little fir tree growing on a branch out of such a lump can be nothing but the Hexenbesen; there is mycelium in the wood you sent but that alone is not enough.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> He says there are lots of affected trees near Strassbourg &amp; he could easily send us a young tree with a hexenbesen on it in the autumn. Have you noticed the young shoots of scotch fir how vertically they grow up, while spruce buds curve downwards slightly like hazel buds. The Finlander is experimenting on the horizontal underground shoots of Scirpus &amp;c &amp; finds they have just the same instinct to grow horizontally as an ordinary shoot has to grow vertically—which is the much abused “transversal-geotropismus” of Frank only his transvers: geotr was with above ground things which are affected by light—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will ask more about Krause— Stahl who is not usually severe called him an “abscheulicher Mensch” but Stahl as <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> French hates Berliners: every one hates Kosmos I think as the organ of “uncultivated materialism”—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Hermann Müller has been christened Kohlenstoff Müller because he was complained of for teaching the boys in school that they should not believe “in the beginning was the word” but “in the beginning was Carbon”!<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>I have got two good Porlieras in a room where I can do what I like &amp; I will keep one in damp earth &amp; one in dry &amp;c &amp; make careful observ<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I am very glad you are done with old Eras<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>I am very sorry about poor Jimmys pit &amp; also for Pouts’ horse<ref target="#foot.f8"/> yrs affec | FD</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Bot Zeitung 1867 p257</p>
              <p>A de Bary Ueber den Krebs und die Hexenbesen der Weisstanne <hi rend="underline">Abies pectinata</hi><ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
              <p>The Krebs consists of a lump on the stem or branches, the swelling is about twice the diameter of the stem above &amp; below it. Remarkable for very thick bark which is externally deeply cracked. Ultimately the bark comes off the &amp; wood rots extensively. The wood &amp; especially bark is crowed with mycelium which is continued into the branches that grow out of the swellings &amp; reproduces itself in the young leaves. The branches growing out of the swellings are the little upright trees or Hexenbesen. He speaks also of hexenbesen growing out of the stem— {for Hexenbesen he quotes De Bary Ann Sc Nat 4 Sér, Tom XX p 90}.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> The fungus is <hi rend="underline">Æcidium elatinum</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f11"/> he speaks of the mycelium growing from a swelling into “<hi rend="underline">side branches</hi>” without producing reproductive organs, which latter are only in the true hexenbesen. The hexenbesen is only formed when the mycelium grows from the swelling into a <hi rend="underline">bud</hi> beginning to elongate   If it grows into already unfolded though still young shoots it does not produce a hexenbesen, only another swelling   One and the same swelling may produce hexenbesen and normal branches   Normal shoots free from mycel may come from hexenbesen. The hexenbesen are found all over the tree, most rarely at the summit of a young tree. The hexenbesen-shoots may either grow from the very first vertically up, or bend upwards with a bent piece. The first year they are simple shoots, &amp; form a winter bud at the top. The branches which grow from the main hexenbesen axis are like the primary branches of a young fir tree &amp; grow out on all sides</p>
<p>Hexenbesen—</p>
              <p>The leaves fall off in autumn &amp; are rather smaller than normal, “Krautartig-fleischig”<ref target="#foot.f12"/> &amp; light yellow green in colour. If the fungus does not fructify which is very rare they the leaves live over the winter   “The hexenbesen sits on the branches like a strange looking bush in winter bare, in summer light green”   Imitating a a little fir tree if it grows regularly or looking like a confused bush if it has grown irregularly. The hexenbesen are usually more regular in growth when only one grows out of a swelling. They usually die in a few years but may live in one case 16 years   In the hexenbesen, as in the swellings, the bark is very thick. “Very rarely one finds side shoots on the hexenbesen free from mycelium which then assume all the properties of normal fir branches”<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>(I dont understand this as I thought the side branches of the hexenbesen were always like normal branches of a young fir tree. F D)</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.4 He … Pouts’ horse 4.1] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure</hi>:</note>
                <note>3.12  <hi rend="italic">bud</hi> … elongate] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12078A.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 2 June [1879]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had sent Francis a twig of <hi rend="italic">Abies pectinata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">A. alba</hi>, silver fir) with a small swelling (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12078A.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 2 June [1879]</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4513.xml">Ernst Stahl</ref>, an assistant of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml">Julius Sachs</ref> at Würzburg, had worked on lichens and experimentally demonstrated their fungal character (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1402.xml">Cittadino 1990</ref>, pp. 83–4). <hi rend="italic">Hexenbesen</hi>: witches’ broom (German); a clump of densely branched small shoots that can result from various tree parasites, such as fungi, mistletoe, insects, or viruses (for more on the cause of witches’ broom in silver firs, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10695.xml">Schweingruber 2007</ref>, pp. 215–18). Mycelium is the vegetative part of a fungus, characterised by fine branching threads or hyphae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Scotch fir (Scots pine) is <hi rend="italic">Pinus sylvestris</hi>; spruce trees are in the genus <hi rend="italic">Picea</hi>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1485.xml">Fredrik Elfving</ref> was studying a problem suggested to him by Sachs, the tendency of the rhizomes of many plants to take up a horizontal position in the ground (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10696.xml">Collander 1965</ref>, p. 44). <hi rend="italic">Scirpus</hi> is the genus of bulrushes. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1738.xml">Albert Bernhard Frank</ref> had proposed that there were special forms of growth in plant organs, characterised by an inherent tendency to be horizontal or to be placed at a right angle to the direction of gravity or a light source; he referred to these as ‘Transversal-Geotropismus’ and ‘Transversal-Heliotropismus’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10698.xml">Frank 1870</ref>, p. 77). Frank’s thesis had been challenged by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4908.xml">Hugo de Vries</ref>, who argued the phenomenon could be explained as a sort of equilibrium between opposing heliotropic and geotropic forces in conjunction with epinastic and hyponastic movements (the bending down and up of an organ due to greater longitudinal growth on one side; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9677.xml">Vries 1872</ref>, p. 277). Frank had responded to De Vries’s criticisms with a more detailed experimental study of differences in movement that resulted from different tropic forces (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10699.xml">Frank 1873</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Abscheulicher Mensch</hi>: odious man (German). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Ernst Krause</ref> was the editor of the journal <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>, which promoted an evolutionary perspective in natural science.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Kohlenstoff</hi>: carbon (German). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Hermann Müller</ref> was a senior teacher of natural sciences at the Realschule in Lippstadt. Müller had briefly explained the case in a letter to CD and sent two articles written by Krause in his own and Müller’s defence (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11883.xml">letter from Hermann Müller, 14 February 1879</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">On the identification of plants as <hi rend="italic">Porliera hygrometrica</hi>, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12067F.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 29 May 1879</ref> and n. 3. In 1878, Francis had noted changes in movement that seemed dependent on the amount of water a specimen received (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 26, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11596.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, [after 7 July 1878]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12078A.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 2 June [1879]</ref>. CD had spent several weeks working on a biographical sketch to introduce an English translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Krause’s</ref> essay on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>). The translation appeared in November 1879 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Jimmy was a nickname for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml">Horace Darwin</ref>; Pout was a nickname for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml">Leonard Darwin</ref>. The pit and the horse have not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref>’s paper ‘Ueber den Krebs und die Hexenbesen der Weisstanne (<hi rend="italic">Abies pectinata</hi> DC.)’ (On the canker and witches’ brooms of the silver fir (<hi rend="italic">Abies pectinata</hi> DC.); <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10803.xml">Bary 1867</ref>) identified <hi rend="italic">Aecidium elatinum</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Melampsorella caryophyllacearum</hi>, fir broom rust) as the pathogen that caused cankers and brooms in <hi rend="italic">Abies pectinata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Abies alba</hi>, silver fir) and described the progression of disease in infected trees.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10803.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bary 1867</ref>, p. 260; Bary referred to his paper in the <hi rend="italic">Annales des sciences naturelles</hi>, ‘Recherches sur le développement de quelque champignons parasites’ (Researches on the development of some parasitic fungi; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10804.xml">Bary 1863</ref>). Bary noted that it was probable that in certain members of the Uredinales (the order to which <hi rend="italic">Aecidium elatinum</hi> belonged) the fungus alternately infested two types of host (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10804.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bary 1863</ref>, pp. 90–1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See n. 9, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Krautartig-fleischig</hi>: herbaceous-fleshy (German); see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10803.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bary 1867</ref>, p. 262.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10803.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bary 1867</ref>, p. 262. Bary noted that the infected needles of a witches’ broom were small, yellow, herbaceous-fleshy, and shed in late autumn, but in rare cases when the fungus had not fructified the branches might have normal needles.</note>       
        </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>