<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10990">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. F. Martins<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   7 June 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10094</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10990 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10990.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10990.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 63</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 63</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3197.xml">Martins, C. F.</persName>
                <placeName>Jardin des Plantes de Montpellier</placeName>
                <date when="1877-06-07">7 June 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>All young intelligent French naturalists support CD. But the professors are afraid of being called materialists, atheists, or communists.</p> 
<p>A paper of his ["Sur l’origine paléontologique", <hi rend="italic">C. R. Hebd. Acad. Sci.</hi> 84 (1877): 534–7] met with silence, except from Bureau. If only France had become Protestant!</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">C. R. Hebd. Acad. Sci.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">atheists</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">communists</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">French naturalists</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">materialists</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">professors</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">France</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Martins, C. F. 1877</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">exclamations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Bureau</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">protestantism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Jardin | des Plantes | de | Montpellier. Montpellier,</hi></placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="print">le</hi> 7 Juin 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Cher et illustre Maitre,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je suis hereux d’apprendre que la Traduction de vos Plantes insectivores en francais vous ait satisfait et j’ai transmis vos compliments à M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Barbier.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Vous trouverez ci joint un Compte rendu de votre ouvrage qui a paru dans le Journal le Temps sous le pseudonyme de A. Vernier.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> L’auteur est M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Auguste Laugel Ingenieur des Mines et Secretaire du Duc d’Aumale pendant son séjour en Angleterre.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Tous les jeunes Naturalistes français intelligens sont vos disciples mais les Professeurs officiels qui sentent bien combien vos idées sont justes se tiennent sur la reserve, ils n’osent aborde ces questions de peur d’etre accusés de materialisme, d’atheisme de communisme &amp;c &amp;c. Quand j’ai lu à l’Institut et à la Société botanique le Memoire que je vous ai envoyé sur les arbres et arbrisseaux qui gelent dans les grands hivers du Midi de la France, j’ai soutenu leur origine paléontologique, soutenu la continuité des creations, nié les revolutions du globe et la réalité de l’espèce; personne n’a fait d’objections mais personne ne m’a approuvé sauf M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bureau qui a dit que la végétation actuelle datait de l’epoque crétacée.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Tout cela tient à l’influence catholique et à la crise religieuse dont nous souffrons en ce moment.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> L’Angleterre a eu le bonheur dembrasser la reforme c’est le malheur de la France de ne pas l’avoir imitée.</p>
                    <p>Veuillez agréer cher Monsieur la nouvelle expression de ma profonde sympathie pour vos ecrits et votre personne |  Votre devoué | Ch: Martins</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Jardin | des Plantes | de | Montpellier. Montpellier,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>7 June 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Dear and illustrious Master,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am happy to learn that the translation into French of your Insectivorous plants has pleased you and I passed on your compliments to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barbier.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You will find enclosed a review of your work that appeared in the newspaper Le Temps under the pseudonym of A. Vernier.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The author is M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Auguste Laugel a mining engineer and secretary of the Duc d’Aumale during his stay in England.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>All the intelligent young French naturalists are your followers but the official professors, who know very well that your ideas are correct, reserve their judgment, they do not dare to approach these questions for fear of being accused of materialism, atheism communism &amp;c &amp;c. When I read at the Institute and at the botanical society the memoir I sent you on trees and shrubs that freeze in the severe winters of the Midi of France, I maintained their palaeontological origin, maintained the continuity of creations, denied the revolutions of the globe and the reality of space; no one objected but no one agreed with me except M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bureau, who said that current vegetation dated back to the Cretaceous epoch.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> All this stems from the Catholic influence and the religious crisis that we are suffering from at the moment.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> England has the good fortune to embrace reform it is France’s bad luck not to have imitated it.</p>
<p>Please accept sir the renewed expression of my profound sympathy for your work and yourself</p>
<p>Yours truly | Ch: Martins</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter to Martins has not been found. Martins had written an introduction to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edmond Barbier’s</ref> translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (Barbier trans. 1877). The French edition was published in May 1877 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10955.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C.-F. Reinwald, 9 May 1877</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> was published in <hi rend="italic">Feuilleton du temps</hi>, 22 May 1877, pp. 1–2; a clipping is in DAR 139.18: 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2828.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Auguste Laugel</ref> had written a review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Laugel 1860</ref>), and an article on CD’s French critics (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4607.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Laugel 1868</ref>). Henri Eugène Philippe Louis d’Orléans, duc d’Aumale, was exiled to England after the revolution of 1848; he returned to France in 1871 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Martins’s paper was read at the 19 March 1877 meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_15.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Académie des sciences</ref> (Martins 1877), one of five academies of the Institut de France, Paris. A summary of the paper was also given at the Société botanique de France on 23 March 1877 (<hi rend="italic">Bulletin de la Société botanique de France</hi> 24 (1877): 127). A longer version was published the previous year in <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de l’Académie des sciences et lettres de Montpellier</hi> (Martins 1876). For a discussion of Martins’s views on evolution, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rioux 2011</ref>, pp. 339–42. M. Bureau: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_733.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Édouard Bureau</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">On ultramontanism and the conflicts between Catholic, royalist, and republican allegiances in the early Third Republic, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10324.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Passmore 2013</ref>, pp. 21–37.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>