<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7028">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Camille Dareste<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   13 December [1869]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16670</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7028 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7028.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7028.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 46</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 46</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1196.xml">Dareste, G. M. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Lille</placeName>
                <date when="1869-12-13">13 Dec [1869]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD’s letter on his behalf made a great impression, but his candidacy nevertheless failed, largely owing to the hostility of Claude Bernard. CD’s opinion sustains his belief that his work will be a service to science.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_411">Bernard, Claude</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lille</placeName>
                    <date>13 décembre</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je vous suis bien reconnaissant de l’éclatant témoinage que vous avez bien voulu m’adresser sur mes travaux.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Il a produit un grand effet, et vivement impressionné tout les personnes qui avaient à voter sur ma candidature:</p>
<p>Je regrette d’avoir à vous apprendre que ma candidature, bien qu’appuyée de votre nom, a echoué.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Je suis arrivé aussi près que possible du bas; car j’ai eu, un très grand nombre de voix parmi les membres du Conseil acadèmique et de la faculté des Sciences qui dressaient leurs listes de présentation. Mais j’ai rencontré devant moi une hostilité qui s’est manifestée de la manière la plus enérgique; celle de Claude Bernard qui est aujourd’hui tout puissant même en dehors de la Science. Il n’admet pas que l’on puisse traiter la physiologie autrement qu’il ne la fait lui-même; c’est à dire en ne suivant pas la méthode des vivisections.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Il m’a donc combattu en criant très haut et partout que je n’étais pas physiologiste. Sans lui, j’aurais très certainement réussi.</p>
<p>Je suis donc retourné à Lille, très froissé, mais non découragé; et j’ai repris la serié interrompue de mes travaux.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> J’ai tout lieu de croire, par les resultats de mes expériences de l’année, que j’arriverai prochainement au terme d’une série de recherches qui m’occupent depuis près de dix-huit ans. Peut-être, lorsque je publierai mon travail d’ensemble, pourrai-je trouver dans mon pays un accueil plus favourable que celui que j’ai rencontré jusqu’à présent.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Du reste, si j’étais d’une façon quelconque, abattu par mon insuccès actuel, j’aurai, pour me relever, l’opinion d’un Savant comme vous; elle ne prouve que je n’ai point fait facille route; et qu’en cherchant à étudier par la méthode expérimentale, la production des monstrosités, je suis entré dans une carrière où je pourrai rendre de véritables services à la science de la vie, quoiqu’en dire Claude Bernard et son école si exclusive.</p>
<p>Veuillez recevoir, Monsieur, l’assurance de mon profond respect et de ma vive reconnaissance.| Camille Dareste</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener>
            <placeName>Lille </placeName>
            <date>13 December</date>
            <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <div type="transcription">
            <p>I am very grateful to you for the brilliant recommendation that you kindly sent to me about my work.<ref target="#foot.f3"/>  It produced a fine effect, and keenly impressed all those who voted for my candidature:</p>
            <p>I regret to have to tell you that my candidature, although  well-supported by your name, has failed.<ref target="#foot.f4"/>  I came as close as possible to the bottom; for I had a great many votes among the members of the Conseil Académique and the Faculté des Sciences who drew up their presentation lists. But I faced a hostility that was manifested in the most energetic manner; that of Claude Bernard, who is nowadays all-powerful even outside science. He does not allow that physiology can be treated in any other way than he does himself, that is to say following the method of vivisections.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Therefore he fought me by shouting very loudly and everywhere that I was not a physiologist.  Without him, I would have very certainly succeeded.</p>
            <p>I have since returned to Lille, very bruised but not discouraged; and I have resumed the interrupted course of my work.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have every reason to believe, from the results of my experiments this year, that I will soon reach the end of a course of research that has occupied me for nearly eighteen years. Perhaps, when I have published my work as a whole, I might find a more favourable reception in my country than that which I have encountered up to now.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Besides, if I have been to some degree disheartened by my current lack of success, I have the opinion of a scholar like you to lift my spirits; it just proves that I did not take the easy road; and that in seeking to study the production of monstrosities by the experimental method, I entered a career where I could render real services to the life sciences, whatever Claude Bernard and his very exclusive school may say about it.</p>
            <p>Please accept, dear Sir, the assurance of my profound respect and continuing regard. | Camille Dareste</p>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 521–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Camille Dareste, 20 November 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Camille Dareste, 20 November 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">On the position Dareste had been seeking, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6994.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Camille Dareste, 18 November [1869]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_411.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claude Bernard’s</ref> position in French science and philosophy, and for his promotion of vivisection, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3742.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Holmes 1974</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Dareste was a professor of zoology at the University of Lille (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DBF</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">For Dareste’s recent work on animal monstrosities, see Dareste 1862, 1863, and 1867. Dareste later published <hi rend="italic">Recherches sur la production artificielle des monstruosités, ou essai de tératogénie expérimentale</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1778.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dareste 1877</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>