<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8294F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To G. G. Leveson-Gower, Earl Granville   [before 19 April 1872]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21594</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8294F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8294F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8294F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Memorial</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="Memorial"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Correspondence between the Foreign Office and Her Majesty’s representatives abroad, and foreign representatives in England, on the subject of copyright: 1872–75. <hi rend="italic">House of Commons Parliamentary Papers</hi> session 1875 (1285) LXXVIII.233–4 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Correspondence between the Foreign Office and Her Majesty’s representatives abroad, and foreign representatives in England, on the subject of copyright: 1872–75. <hi rend="italic">House of Commons Parliamentary Papers</hi> session 1875 (1285) LXXVIII.233–4</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <date notBefore="1872-04-01" notAfter="1872-04-17">[before 19 Apr 1872]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4629.xml">Leveson-Gower, G. G.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Writes on behalf of British authors requesting improved copyright rights with respect to United States.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="italic">Memorial of British Authors to the Right Hon. Earl Granville, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, on the subject of Copyright in the United States.</hi></p>
<p>Looking forward with satisfaction to the prospect of harmonious relations being happily established between the United States and the United Kingdom, we, the undersigned, hope for a reconsideration of the policy in virtue of which British authors, as authors, enjoy no rights which American citizens are bound to respect.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Letters from influential Americans—one of them a leading New York publisher—which have recently appeared here, joined with the approval of them expressed in the journals of the United States, show the desire of the Americans for the conclusion of a Copyright Convention between their country and ours.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>We understand that the demands of publishers in this country have hitherto been the most formidable obstacles to the negotiation of a Copyright Convention. We are of opinion that the interests of our publishers in American copyrights are quite independent of the just claims of British authors; and that the latter may be fully admitted without recognition of the former. We think it would be a grave error if the settlement of this matter were retarded, or rendered impossible, in consequence of two classes of claims, which, in essence, are wholly distinct, if not antagonistic, being regarded by negotiators representing this country as identical and inseparable.</p>
<p>Americans distinguish between the author, as producing the ideas, and the publisher, as producing the material vehicle by which these ideas are conveyed to readers. They admit the claim of the British author to be paid by them for his brain-work. The claim of the British book-manufacturer, to a monopoly of their book-market, they do not admit. To give the British author a copyright is simply to agree that the American publisher shall pay him for work done. To give the British publisher a copyright is to open the American market to him on terms which prevent the American publisher from competing.</p>
<p>Without dwelling on the argument of the Americans that such an arrangement would not be free trade, but the negation of free trade, and merely noticing that further argument that, while their protective system raises the prices of all the raw materials, free competition with the British book-manufacturer would be fatal to the American book-manufacturer, it is clear that the Americans have strong reasons for refusing to permit the British publisher to share in the copyright which they are willing to grant to the British author.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>We venture to suggest, therefore, that, responding to the cordial feeling recently expressed by Americans on the subject, and duly appreciating the force of their reasons for making the above distinction, future negotiations should be conducted with a view to secure a copyright on the conditions they specify.</p>
<p>Without making it the foundation of a formal claim for reciprocity of treatment, we mention the fact, that American authors may, if they please, secure all the advantages of copyright in the United Kingdom which are enjoyed by native authors.</p>
<p>(Signed) HERBERT SPENCER (And 51 others.)<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">This memorial was forwarded to Earl Granville, the foreign secretary, on 19 April 1872, according to the letter that precedes it in <hi rend="italic">Parliamentary Papers</hi>. A version of it, also signed by CD, was presented at a meeting of publishers in New York on 6 February 1872 (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ and Stationers’ Weekly Trade Circular</hi>, 8 February 1872, pp. 91, 94–5; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_209.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Appleton 1877</ref>, pp. 247–8). The only significant difference between the version presented in New York in February and the version transcribed here is that the words ‘Looking forward with satisfaction to the prospect of’ were omitted from the beginning of the New York version, and the following text was added after the first sentence of the second paragraph: ‘They maintain that such a convention should provide for the vesting of the British author’s American copyright absolutely and inalienably in him. That condition appears to us both equitable and satisfactory.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">No copyright treaty existed between the United Kingdom and the United States, with the result that American publishers could reprint and sell British books without offering any recompense to the author or publisher (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7125.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Seville 2006</ref>, pp. 148–9). CD’s own books were by this time regularly published in the United States by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. Appleton &amp; Co</ref>, who paid CD a percentage out of courtesy and in the hope of receiving early copy to enable them to publish in advance of competitors (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2706.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 20 February 1860</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">There was correspondence on the subject of international copyright in <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> in October and November 1871; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_140.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Appleton</ref>, head of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. Appleton &amp; Co</ref>., had a letter published on 20 October 1871, p. 10 (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7125.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Seville 2006</ref>, p. 200 and n. 166).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">British printing costs were lower than US printing costs at this period; many US publishers were in favour of an international copyright treaty on condition that it covered only works wholly manufactured in the US (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7125.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Seville 2006</ref>, pp. 199–201).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For the full list of signatories, see the <hi rend="italic">Daily News</hi>, 6 May 1872, p. 6; CD, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_832.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Carlyle</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Henry Lewes</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3327.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Stuart Mill</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Tyndall</ref> were among them. What is probably an interim printed version of the memorial, containing twenty-nine printed signatures and CD’s handwritten signature, was advertised for sale by Pickering &amp; Chatto of New Bond Street, London, in their Bulletin 35 (March 2012).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>