<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6487">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. D. Hooker   2 December 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">4621</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6487 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6487.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6487.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 151: 199</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 373</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 94: 102–4</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>94: 102–4</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1868-12-02">2 Dec 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Enthusiastic about JDH’s plan for a British <hi rend="italic">Flora</hi> – "a grand idea to make a Flora a guide for knowledge already acquired &amp; to be acquired". Gives examples of subjects.</p> 
            <p>No work exists on various biological points in plants.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down—</placeName>
                    <date>Dec 2 1868.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Hooker</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is a splendid scheme, &amp; if you make only a beginning on a Flora, which shall serve as an index to all papers on curious points in the life-history of plants, you will do an inestimable good service.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Quite recently I was asked by a man how he c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> find out what was known on various biological points in our plants; &amp; I answered that I knew of no such book, &amp; that he might ask half a dozen botanists before one w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> chance to remember what had been published on this or that point.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Not long ago another man, who had been experimenting on the quasi-bulbs on the leaves of Cardamine wrote to me to complain that he c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not find out what was known on the subject.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>It is almost certain that some early or even advanced students, if they found in their Flora a line or two on various curious points, with <hi rend="underline">references</hi> for further investigation, would be led to make further observations. For instance a reference to the viscid threads emitted by the seeds of compositæ,—to the apparatus (if it has been described) by which oxalis spurts out its seeds,—to the sensitiveness of the <hi rend="underline">young</hi> leaves of oxalis acetosella with reference to O. sensitiva.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Under Latherus nissolia it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> better to refer to my hypothetical explanation of the grass-like leaves than to nothing.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Under a twining plant you might say that the upper part of the shoot steadily revolves with or against the sun, &amp; so when it strikes against any object it twines to the right or left, as the case may be.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If again references were given to the parasitism of Euphrasia &amp;c how likely it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be that some young man w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> go on with the investigation;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> &amp; so with endless other facts. I am quite enthusiastic about y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> idea; it is a grand idea to make a Flora a guide for knowledge already acquired &amp; to be acquired. I have amused myself by speculating what an enormous number of subjects ought to be introduced into a Utopian Flora,—on the quickness of the germination of the seeds, on their means of dispersal, on the fertilization of the flower, &amp; on a score of other points, about almost all of which we are profoundly ignorant. I am glad to read what you say about Bentham, for my inner consciousness tells me that he has run too many forms together.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Should you care to see an elaborate German pamphlet by Herman Müller on the gradation &amp; distinction of the forms of Epipactis &amp; of Platanthera?<ref target="#foot.f9"/> It may be absurd in me to suggest, but I think you w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> find curious facts &amp; references in Lecoq’s enormous book, in Vaucher’s 4 vols, in Hildebrand’s Geschlechter-Vertheilung &amp; perhaps in Fournier de la Fecondation.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I wish you all success in your gigantic undertaking; but what a pity you did not think of it 10 y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> ago, so as to have accumulated references on all sorts of subjects. Depend upon it you will have started a new era in the Floras of various countries. I can well believe that M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hooker<ref target="#foot.f11"/> will be of the greatest possible use to you in lightening your labours &amp; arranging your materials.</p>
<p>Yours affectionately | Chas. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6484.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of [28 November 1868]</ref>, Hooker had informed CD that he was going to write a ‘British Flora’ adapted to students’ purposes and containing references to papers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD may refer to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref>, who met him in London in November (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Farrer, 21 November 1868</ref> and n. 1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD may refer to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3861.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Price</ref>, who had worked on <hi rend="italic">Cardamine pratensis</hi> (cuckoo flower or lady’s smock). Price referred CD to articles he had written on the topic, but made no mention of experiments or of not being able to find out what was known on the subject (see letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3861.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Price</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5982.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">5 March 1868</ref> and n. 4, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6434.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">28 October 1868</ref>). For Price’s discussion of the ‘plumule and radicule’ shooting from the base of leaflets of <hi rend="italic">C. pratensis</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6426.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Price 1863–4</ref>, pp. 348–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The family Compositae is now Asteraceae; <hi rend="italic">Oxalis acetosella</hi> is wood sorrel; <hi rend="italic">O. sensitiva</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Biophytum sensitivum</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had hypothesised that the legume <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus nissolia</hi> (grass vetchling or pea), which has grass-like leaves and is the only <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus</hi> without tendrils, had developed from an ancestor in which the tendrils were not highly developed, and was a reversion to a primordial ancestor without tendrils (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi></ref>, pp. 114–15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">For CD’s description of the revolving movement in twining plants, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi></ref>, pp. 2–25.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Euphrasia officinalis</hi> (eyebright) is a hemiparisite that grows on the roots of many grass species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mabberley 1997</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">For Hooker’s assessment of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Handbook of the British flora</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_576.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1865</ref>), see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6484.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [28 November 1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller’s</ref> paper on Westphalian orchids (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1868</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2854.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Lecoq</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lecoq 1854–8</ref>, to Jean Pierre Etienne Vaucher and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7956.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vaucher 1841</ref>, to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Hildebrand</ref> and Hildebrand 1867a, and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5683.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eugène Fournier</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fournier 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frances Harriet Hooker</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>