<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-660">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. S. Henslow   [22 January 1843]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">811</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-660 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-660.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-660.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno/>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1843-01-22">[22 Jan 1843]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml">Henslow, J. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on JSH’s botanical work with his parishioners. Lyell will be pleased that he has done some fossil botanical work.</p>
            <p>Describes a Geological Society meeting about Edward Charlesworth’s complaints.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_890">Charlesworth, Edward</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific controversy, confrontation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Geological Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday Morning</date>
                    <salute>My dear Henslow</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you for a “muckalereous” newspaper,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> as well as your letter &amp; two sermons— As far as I have read in the latter, it appears to me full of most wise advice, &amp; &amp; I shall finish it this evening.— Your fears about the dunghill made us laugh— I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> like to know, who your bigoted mathematical friend is, who sneers so severely on Leibig<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; Co.— Your lectures must do good, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> think, in stirring up all the farmers; but as for hoping to get tabulated results from them, if you succeed you will either prove yourself a magician or that your Suffolk farmers are very different from the Shropshire ones, whom I have been accustomed to.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Lyell &amp; co will be delighted to hear of your having actually finished some fossil Botanical work.— I have heard many a groan over you &amp; your pursuits; &amp; the worst of it is, that your pursuits are so evidently excellent, that one cannot have the pleasure of abusing you. I hope indeed, you will find leisure from your weightier occupations to go on with your fossil work, &amp; I must put in a word for poor Galapagos plants—remember the regret Humboldt expressed that you had not published some sketch of them;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> whenever you do I shall be very curious to know, what sort of relation the Flora bears to that of S. America.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am getting on with my second very thin part on “Volcanic Isl<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi>”.— My coral-volume has sold tolerably according to my views, &amp; has received its quant: suff: of praise. I wrote to you after the first day’s display by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charslworth; &amp; the second had the same result—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I never saw any man, to use a theatrical expression, so utterly damned. His whole case broke down, &amp; the Council came off triumphant, being blamed by several (unknown to us) speakers, for having been too kind &amp; considerate to him— The Council did not even acknowledge his latter letters, &amp; of this he made heavy complaint,—so he was requested to read aloud his own letter to the Council in which he calls your informant a liar &amp;c—&amp; Murchison told him with a sweet little smile that that was our reason for not acknowledging his letters— This answer the Soc: approved of by acclamation. The absurdest part, was, that a requisition signed by between 20 &amp; 30 men was brought forward to change a law, &amp; it is required by bye-laws, that to make such change, five of the requisitionist, sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> show they were present: Whether they were or not I do not know, but it was long before even one w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> rise, &amp; three members of the Council were obliged to second the proposal, in order that the discussion might be brought on— So completely cowed &amp; ashamed were M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ch. advocates, 〈I〉 am told (I know not whether truly) that Ch. has given up controversy &amp; science (synonymous in his eyes) &amp; has gone to Edinburgh to study medicine.—</p>
<p>Farewell, I wonder, whether we shall ever see you in this house— I heartily hope we may.—</p>
<p>Pray remember me very kindly to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Henslow &amp; believe me Ever yours | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 Leibig] ‘e’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘i’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.5 I] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘al’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.11 day’s] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.21 required] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘that’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi> : 2.10 ‘quant:’; 2.14 ‘considerate to’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Henslow was then writing a series of newspaper articles on scientific methods of fertilisation. These were collected in Henslow 1843a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Justus von Liebig</ref> was well known for his theories of agricultural chemistry.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Henslow had organised the farmers near Hadleigh to conduct fertiliser experiments (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4193.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jenyns 1862</ref>, pp. 77–82).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-534.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alexander von Humboldt, 18 September 1839</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The work was eventually done by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (J. D. Hooker 1845 and 1846).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Henslow had initially been a supporter of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_890.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Charlesworth</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, [5 and 7 October 1842]</ref>). The meeting described is evidently that of 14 December 1842 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-651.xml" resp="#automat">letter to W. H. Miller, [16 October–27 November 1842]</ref>, n. 4).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>