<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8311">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Paolo Mantegazza<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   4 May 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10157</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8311 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8311.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8311.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 38</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 38</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3154.xml">Mantegazza, Paolo</persName>
                <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                <date when="1872-05-04">4 May 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD has been elected Honorary Member of Società Italiana di Antropologia e di Etnologia.</p>
            <p>Cranial measurements connect man and apes.</p>
            <p>He has shown differences between male and female skulls that bear on sexual selection.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">apes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex differences</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">honorary membership</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Societa Italiana di Antropologia e di Etnologia</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                    <date>4 Mai 1872—</date>
                    <salute>Illustre Monsieur.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai l’honneur de vous annoncer que dans une de ses dernières seances la Société Italienne d’Anthropologie et d’ Ethnologie vous a acclamé à son <hi rend="underline">Membre honoraire</hi>, et que vous en recevrez sous peu de temps le diplome.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>J’ai reçu la dernière édition de votre immortel ouvrage sur <hi rend="underline">l’origine de l’espèce</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Mille et mille fois merci de l’honneur que vous avez voulu me faire. Je le garderai comme un de mes plus chers souvenirs.</p>
<p>Vous recevrez quelques unes de mes brochures anthropologiques: j’appelle votre attention sur les deux cas de dents surnumeraires observés par moi, dont un dans un nègre. (Brochure verte. pag. 23).<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Dans l’étude de mon index <hi rend="underline">cephalospinal</hi> et <hi rend="underline">cephalorbitaire</hi>, c’est à dire sur le rapport du volume de la moelle épinière et des orbites avec la capacité du crâne vous trouverez des singuliers rapprochements entre les singes et l’homme   Je m’occupe maintenant de la mesuration des fosses nasales, qui vient de m’être rendue possible par un ingenieux instrument inventé par M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Broca. En sommant le volume des fosses nasales et celles des orbites je pense êtablir l’index <hi rend="underline">prosopocephalique</hi> c’est à dire le rapport entre les cavités des sens et la cavité du crâne; et je crois que j’aurai un moyen plus scientifique pour établir la yerarchie d’un crâne qu’avec l’angle facial et l’angle sphénoidal.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Pour votre election sexuelle je vous prie de lire mon mémoire sur les <hi rend="underline">Caractères sexuels du crâne humain</hi>, dans le quel je veux demontrer que le developpement des <hi rend="underline">arcades supraorbitaires</hi> est le caractère plus masculin du crâne humain.</p>
<p>Je viens de trouver un crâne de negre <hi rend="underline">dinka</hi> avec un seul os nasal.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Dans deux autres crânes de la même race il y a une grande tendance à la fusion des deux os &amp; dans un seul. On dirait que l’un est avorté. J’ai observé le même fait dans un crâne très simien de la Sardaigne.— Dans trois crânes de la Nouvelle Zelande l’<hi rend="underline">os intermaxillaire</hi> est bien defini, et se separe par une veritable suture incomplete de l’os maxillaire. Je vais publier ces faits, mais j’ai voulu les annoncer au grand pontife de la science nouvelle.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> J’espère que vous pouvez les ajouter aux autres semblables dans une seconde edition de votre dernier ouvrage.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Vos idées marchent en Italie, et bien vite. On ne contraste que votre election sexuelle, pour la quelle je n’ai pas pu me convertir même avec votre dernière lettre.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Aimez moi, comme je vous <hi rend="italic">[</hi>aime<hi rend="italic">]</hi>.—</p>
<p>Votre admirateur et ami | Prof. Paul Mantegazza | President de la Societé italienne d’anthropologie etc.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                    <date>4 May 1872—</date>
                    <salute>Most renowned Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have the honour of informing you that in one of its recent sessions the Italian Society of Anthropology and Ethnology has proclaimed you an <hi rend="underline">Honorary member</hi>, and that you will shortly be receiving its diploma.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have received the latest edition of your immortal work on the <hi rend="underline">origin of species</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> A thousand thanks for the honour you have done me. I shall keep it as one of my dearest souvenirs.</p>
<p>You will be receiving some of my anthropological pamphlets: may I draw your attention to the two cases of supernumerary teeth I have observed, one of which was in a negro. (The green pamphlet. pag. 23).<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In the study on my <hi rend="underline">cephalospinal</hi> and <hi rend="underline">cephalorbital</hi> index, that is to say on the relations between the volume of the spinal cord and orbits and cranial capacity, you will find singular resemblances between monkeys and man   I am now occupying myself with the measurement of the nasal fossae, which has just been made possible for me by an ingenious instrument invented by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Broca. By adding the volume of the nasal fossae to that of the orbits, I hope to establish a <hi rend="underline">prosopocephalic</hi> index, that is to say the relation between the sensory cavities and the cranial cavity; and I think I will thereby have a more scientific means of establishing the hierarchy of a skull than with the facial angle and the sphenoidal angle.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>For your sexual selection, I beg you will read my memoir on the <hi rend="underline">Sexual characteristics of the human skull</hi>, in which I attempt to show that the development of the <hi rend="underline">supraciliary arches</hi> is the most masculine character of the human skull.</p>
<p>I have just found a skull from a <hi rend="underline">Dinka</hi> negro with a single nasal bone.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In two other skulls from the same race there is a great tendency for the two bones to be fused and in one of them one would say that one of the bones is vestigial. I have observed the same fact in a very simian skull from Sardinia.— In three skulls from New Zealand, the <hi rend="underline">intermaxillary bone</hi> is well defined, and separated from the maxillary bone by a genuine incomplete suture. I shall publish these facts, but I wanted to announce them to the great pontiff of the new science.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I hope that you will be able to add them to other similar ones in a second edition of your latest work.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Your ideas are progressing in Italy, and quickly too. Only your sexual selection is being opposed, to which I have not been able to convert even after your last letter.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Love me as I love you.—</p>
<p>Your admirer and friend | Prof. Paul Mantegazza | President of the Italian Society of Anthropology etc.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 181–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For the diploma, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix III.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">There are three essays by Mantegazza, printed continuously and bound in green paper, in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL; their titles are: ‘Dei caratteri sessuali del cranio umano’ (Sexual characteristics of the human skull), ‘Il cranio di una donna microcefala e quello di una donna imbecile’ (The skull of a microcephalous woman and an imbecile woman), and ‘Due casi di denti sopranumerarii nell’uomo’ (Two cases of supernumerary teeth in humans). The pages are not all cut, but there is an annotation by CD on page 16 (the conclusion) of the first article and another on the outside cover. The articles were originally published in <hi rend="italic">Archivio per l’Antropologia e la Etnologia</hi> 2 (1872): 11–34. No other 1872 articles by Mantegazza have been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_643.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paul Broca</ref> invented at least twenty-seven instruments for the study of craniology (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>). In <hi rend="italic">Revue d’anthropologie</hi> 1 (1872): 3–4 and 35 Broca describes and provides an illustration of a sliding calliper that he used for measuring the nose. Mantegazza’s publications on this subject were Mantegazza 1870a, 1871, 1872a, and 1873.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The Dinka are the largest ethnic group in South Sudan (Appiah and Gates 2005).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Mantegazza published his research in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5200.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mantegazza 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Mantegazza refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>: a second edition was published in 1874, but it did not cite Mantegazza’s new work on human skulls.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD’s letter to Mantegazza has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>