<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4252">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   23 July [1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14762</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4252 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4252.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4252.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 95</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 95</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>Edinburgh Botanic Gardens</placeName>
                <date when="1863-07-23">23 July [1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses heterostyly in <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi>.</p>  
<p>Criticises L. C. Treviranus’ statements on <hi rend="italic">Primula longiflora</hi>’s having short-styled form.</p>  
<p>Describes his results with crossing different coloured primroses. Will let CD, when he reads his paper, decide whether his finding white and red varieties perfectly sterile when crossed, yet fertile <hi rend="italic">inter se</hi>, ought to be published.</p>  
<p>Difficulty in getting his orchid paper published in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Hottonia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">primroses</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Primula longiflora</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4802">Treviranus, L. C.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Scott, John 1863a</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Scott, John 1864b</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Botanic Gardens Edinburgh</placeName>
                    <date>July. 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I duly received yours of the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am greatly obliged for your account of the structure of Hottonia.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will be able to had—if I had results—a few experiments on a <hi rend="underline">short-styled</hi> form with <hi rend="underline">own-pollen</hi>; and also with that from a <hi rend="underline">long-styled</hi> form: having been favoured with a few flowers of the latter from a friend.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I can also add from observations on dried specimens of the North American <hi rend="underline">H. inflata</hi>, as a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">non</hi>- <hi rend="underline">dimorphic</hi> species. The style is very short &amp; reaches the anthers: pollen-grains very similar to those of long-styled H. palustris.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I should like much to hear whether the <hi rend="underline">H. sessiliflora</hi> of Java is <hi rend="underline">dimorphic</hi> or not—as it would enable me to include as I believe all the representatives of the genus—but I cannot find a single specimen of it in any of the Herbaria to which I have access. The description of the species unfortunately takes no notice of either stamens or pistil.</p>
<p>I am much astonished with your extracts from Bot. Zeit. respecting the P. <hi rend="underline">longiflora</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/>   I have had numerous specimens and never found an <hi rend="underline">approach</hi> to the <hi rend="underline">short-styled</hi> state: in those cases where styles &amp; stamens differed in length I <hi rend="underline">invariably</hi> found the <hi rend="underline">former</hi> <hi rend="underline">organ</hi> <hi rend="underline">projecting beyond the stamens</hi>: anthers <hi rend="underline">always surrounding the</hi> <hi rend="underline">mouth of tubes</hi>. It is also quite a mistake of Prof. Treviranus to suppose that long-styled P. Auricula is sterile.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> As bearing on this point however I mention in my paper the <hi rend="underline">long-styled</hi> form of P. <hi rend="underline">denticulata</hi>, from which I have never been able to get a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">single</hi> <hi rend="underline">seed</hi> neither with own-pollen nor that of closely allied species.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I had no short-styled form of the species to try it with. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.Nab likewise informs me that though it has now been in cultivation in the Gardens for upwards of 18 years, yet he has never seen it produce a seed.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>—It is singular how Koch &amp; Tausch could have hazarded such a statement respecting universal dimorphism in the species of Primula: for I cannot think if they had carefully examined the other forms could have escaped them.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Singularly enough we have also made directly opposite observations on P. <hi rend="underline">longiflora</hi>!<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I am glad you gave me an authority to support me as to its being a <hi rend="underline">non-dimorphic</hi> species.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Though I of course have the fine suite of specimens of this species in the Edinburgh University Herbarium to refer to in support of my statement.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>I am gradually getting results of my Primula work. Those from my crosses with <hi rend="doubleUnderline">differently coloured</hi> Primroses are most remarkable.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Thus from homomorphic crosses of P. <hi rend="underline">vulgaris</hi> &amp; var. <hi rend="underline">alba</hi> I got an average of about <hi rend="doubleUnderline">five</hi> <hi rend="underline">seeds per capsule</hi>: from the latter fertilised with <hi rend="underline">own-pollen</hi> I had an average of <hi rend="doubleUnderline">eleven</hi>. But the most astonishing results were those from a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Red Primrose</hi> &amp; the common <hi rend="doubleUnderline">yellow</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline">white</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Reciprocal unions</hi> between the former &amp; the two latter have not yielded me a single seed. I also took the precaution to prove that that the plants of the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Red</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleUnderline">White</hi> varieties experimented upon were productive with own-pollen; as I find that many individuals of both varieties will not produce a single seed even after careful fertilisation. The less robust growing plants have alone proved productive with me; more especially in the case of the <hi rend="underline">Red</hi>, with the <hi rend="underline">white</hi> it is somewhat different. Both varieties have been cultivated in the Gardens here for many years yet M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.Nab tells me that he has never known them to produce any seed! In my own mind I certainly have a conviction that I have here an illustration of the attainment of the <hi rend="underline">very zero</hi> of <hi rend="underline">fertility between varieties of a species</hi>; though I fear my experiments will not be sufficiently numerous to carry a like conviction to the minds of all. Indeed I had some little hesitation in bringing them forward in my paper at all; until I had further opportunities of repeating them. After a careful consideration of those I have already made, I think myself justified in stating them at least. Individuals of varieties perfectly sterile when crossed; yet productive at the same time with own-pollen, is certainly curious if it is not in reality due to the cause I suppose. As you have however so kindly offered to examine my paper;<ref target="#foot.f15"/> I will leave it entirely in your hands, and you can form an idea from the nature of the evidence on which it is based, whether or not it would be advisable to record it along with my others.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>I have been most unfortunate with my unions of <hi rend="underline">Cowslips</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Primroses</hi>: my experimental plants were accidentally sent down to our Class-room in illustration of the Order; and best of the capsules were taken off.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I am very sorry for this as I fear I will be quite unable to give anything like a table of these unions.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>My Orchid paper is not published yet: they promised to bring out in the late no. of the Edin. New Phil. Jour. but it was pushed aside for others which they thought were more interesting.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> It has certainly disappointed me very much. I have spoken to the publisher,<ref target="#foot.f20"/> however, and he has promised to throw off a few copies of it in a short time; so I hope to be able to send you them sometime previous to the publication of the next Journal. By the way I have made out a few more cases of Individual Sterility in Orchids: I will state them in my next, in case you may need further illustrations.<ref target="#foot.f21"/></p>
<p>I know I was wrong in suggesting the slightest modification of results in my last.<ref target="#foot.f22"/> Pray excuse me. I merely did it under the impression that otherwise, it might afford an argument for some of your numerous carping critics against the view you take, that for example the differentiation the male &amp; female sexual e〈le〉ments of either form of Primulas have undergone with respect to their homomorphic action was a slowly acquired quality.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> This I thought was opposed by the non-dimorphic cowslip. At least it appeared to me that any inclined to dispute your views might have instanced it as probably illustrative of the other forms having thus likewise suddenly attained their structural &amp; functional peculiarities.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> I however, may be quite wrong: anyhow, I will ever remember, &amp; act in accordance with the judicious counsel you have given me.<ref target="#foot.f25"/></p>
<p>I regret to find by your last that you was afraid for an attack of scarlet-fever in your family.<ref target="#foot.f26"/> I sincerely trust this has been awarded, and that all ere this are again enjoying that most invaluable of gifts.</p>
<p>Excuse my hurried scribble. | Very respectfully yours. | J. Scott</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>4.18 After a … suppose. 4.21] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 I have been … Order; 5.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 My Orchid … yet:] <hi rend="italic">two crosses in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>6.6 By the way … illustrations. 6.8] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin and scored, pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See the second enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref> and n. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">This individual has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Scott reported the results of his experiments on <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi>, including his own and CD’s observations, in Scott 1864a, pp. 78–9. CD referred to Scott’s experimental results in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 51.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had told Scott of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4802.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludolph Christian Treviranus’s</ref> report that, according to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2737.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wilhelm Daniel Joseph Koch</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4665.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ignaz Friedrich Tausch</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Primula longiflora</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. halleri</hi>) was invariably short-styled (see the first enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref> and n. 8.). The reference is to Treviranus 1863a, which was published in the <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung.</hi> Scott’s own observation was that the styles of this species were either slightly longer than the stamens, or of an equal length (Scott 1864a, p. 81).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See the first enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref> and n. 3. The reference is to Treviranus 1863a, p. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Scott 1864a, pp. 90–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3279.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James McNab</ref> was curator of the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See the first enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref> and n. 8. Scott refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koch 1843–4</ref>, 2: 673, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7624.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tausch 1821</ref>, p. 355. Scott disputed their claim in Scott 1864a, p. 81.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See n. 6, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD had previously told Scott that Treviranus claimed <hi rend="italic">Primula longiflora</hi> was a non-dimorphic species (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref> and n. 9). The reference is to Treviranus 1863a, p. 5. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4253.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 [July 1863]</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Scott was foreman of the propagating department at the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4021.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 3 March 1863</ref>. Scott reported on these crosses in Scott 1864a, pp. 97–103.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4206.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 6 June [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4253.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 [July 1863]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">There was a purpose-built classroom at the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh, for the use of the keeper, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hutton Balfour</ref>. Balfour gave classes in botany, apparently both for students of the University of Edinburgh, and for the staff of the botanic garden (see Fletcher and Brown 1970, pp. 141–3, 146; <hi rend="italic">Transactions and proceedings of the Botanical Society [of Edinburgh]</hi> 14 (1863): 160).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">In his paper (Scott 1864a, pp. 103–4), Scott presented results from crossing experiments carried out by CD with the common primrose (<hi rend="italic">Primula vulgaris</hi>) and the cowslip (<hi rend="italic">P. veris</hi>). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4253.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 [July 1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4213.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to CD of 16 June [1863]</ref>, Scott had reported that his paper on the pollination of orchids, read before the Botanical Society of Edinburgh on 14 May 1863, was in press. The quarterly <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</hi> regularly published the proceedings of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh, including abstracts of some papers. An abstract of Scott’s paper appeared in the October 1863 issue of the journal. However, the publication of the full version of the paper in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Botanical Society [of Edinburgh]</hi> apparently pre-dated the abstract (Scott 1863a; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4260.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 1 and 3 August [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">The <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</hi> was published in Edinburgh by Adam and Charles Black.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, [26 July – 2 August 1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Scott’s letter has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">Scott refers to a non-dimorphic cowslip (<hi rend="italic">Primula veris</hi>), which he had discovered among a number of seedling cowslips. He had been surprised to discover that it was remarkably sterile with both dimorphic forms, while being extremely self-fertile (see letters from John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4174.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 May [1863]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[3 June 1863]</ref>, and Scott 1864a, pp. 105–10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 2 July [1863]</ref> and n. 6.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>