<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4939">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From James Shaw   20 November 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10723</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4939 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4939.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4939.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 149</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 149</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4321.xml">Shaw, James</persName>
                <placeName>Tynron Parish School</placeName>
                <date when="1865-11-20">20 Nov 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Praises CD’s theory.</p>
            <p>Comments on criticism of CD’s work by Duke of Argyll.</p>
            <p>Beauty in nature as caused by sexual selection.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
                <term type="tag" ref="#religious_beliefs">Religious Beliefs</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00708_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00708_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="149:1r" xml:id="i708">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00708.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00708_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00708.dzi" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:1v" xml:id="i709">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00709.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00709_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00709.dzi" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:2r" xml:id="i710">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00710.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00710_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00710.dzi" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:2v" xml:id="i711">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00711.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00711_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00711.dzi" width="3279px" height="5448px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Tynron Parish School | Dumfriesshire.</placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 20— 1865.</date>
                    <salute>Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Here in the solitude of a remote glen your noble work has reached me and is another proof to me that the Age of Romance has not perished but that Truth is indeed stranger than Fiction.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> You have given articulation to a thousand things lying dumb within me. When the <hi rend="underline">Vestiges</hi> was attacked by friends and foes I used to skirmish in its defence<ref target="#foot.f2"/> (<hi rend="underline">vide</hi> my letter pub. by Lewis then Ed. of the Leader)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but never at least within the present century did I expect so scientific an exposition of the grandest general facts—of the deepest truth—yet presented to the human mind to contemplate. Never before have I conceived so clearly the wonderful relation of the individual to the august whole. Those dim ages when nature was silently strewing on her barren shores the dust of future continents and making out of her dead organisms quarries from which Ionic &amp; Doric columns should be wrought are no longer in imagination spectral gleams but wear rather all the interest of history. I am a Man, said the Roman, and everything human has an interest for me.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I a humble student of that Nature with which we are all so strangely knit and everything natural has an interest for me. The comparative anatomy of brain or pelvis—a thousand things hard to understand—hard to attract—have now by a light which never before shone on sea or land assumed a meaning and an interest which never attached to them before. Newton’s ocean of wonder on whose shore he gathered shells seems no longer a dark unnavigable sea crested with howling breakers.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Here and there through its awful bosom the strong vision with which you have supplied us enables us to see at least that there are other islands whose conditions are explicable by our own. It was a grand moment in the history of discovery when Lord Rosse was able to stand at one end of his magnificent tube and command the belt of Orion to swim forward millions of leagues nearer him as it were through unfathomable Space.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Grander still was that hour when using the plumb-line of generalization you enabled us to dip back into the far Past and bring it home to our hearths and our hearts. Wisdom says the inspired man dwelt with the Creator ere he laid the foundations of the world. By wisdom, toil, patience, perseverance the race has arrived at a point when a foremost man here and there looking back from the amazing pinnacle, can construct a chart of the lands over which Life has travelled and of the epochs through which it has progressed, and then spreading his wings in flight can conduct us through those unvisited regions until we stand like archangels at the gates of morning and at the Creation of rock of river and of hill, &amp; of the tenants which therein are.</p>
<p>Some strictures were lately passed on your hypothesis by the Duke of Argyll.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I endeavoured to point out where his Lordship was at fault.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Of some of my objections to his criticism he took notice but to other of my objections he was silent. Out of that communication there is only one suggestion which I think is worth transmitting to you, but if the smallest scintillation of mine is acceptable for the light which you have shed on me you are welcome.</p>
<p>His Lordship (<hi rend="underline">vide</hi> Good Words 1865) is puzzled to understand why there is so much beauty in the world—beauty in the shell—beauty in the flower—exquisite beauty, wonderful patterns of colour, in the plumes of humming birds. Then he proceeds to account for it not on your hypothesis but on the hypothesis that beauty affords a direct pleasure to its creator, remarking that your hypothesis is not yet wide enough to treat this subject. Now I have no objection to the Creator being delighted with beauty and making it to please himself, but not being taken in to his confidence at the creation of it, I cannot give an opinion on the subject.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>But to return to observation. Does his Grace deny all sense or love of beauty in the brutes? (To this query he returns no answer) Comte says the religion of brutes is the reverence gratitude and obedience which they display towards their masters.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> If dogs be credited with religion why should birds be denied all aesthetical faculty? Birds like benighted Africans are fond of glittering pieces. Witness how larks in France are caught by twirling for them. The gorgeous Birds of Paradise are extremely attentive to their plumage and exceedingly sensitive concerning its cleaness &amp;c &amp;c   His Grace points to the savage as an example of the width of range of the love of ornament,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> and Carlyle suggests that rather than the desire of comfort the love of ornament was the first step towards clothes.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Strange if a passion diffused throughout all humanity should have no counterpart in other regions of life. Beauty like song is developed in the male chiefly at the breeding season. If the female give preference to the male of gaudiest hue or richest plumage it will be a chance for the preservation of such. The question propounded concerning the beautiful in Nature is I grant wider than this answer—but I think this answer ought not to be forgot in favour of your hypothesis.</p>
<p>I am, | Sir, | Yours most respectfully, | Ja<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Shaw. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>. F.RS.</p>
<p>I had yr address as given in a letter to the Athenaeum but have laid it aside therefore I have taken the liberty of sending this on to your publisher.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> J.S.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Shaw refers to <hi rend="italic">Origin.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">First published anonymously, <hi rend="italic">The vestiges of the natural history of creation</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1348.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Chambers] 1844</ref>) presented a continuous, progressive view of development in accordance with natural laws and divine purpose. The work gave rise to extensive public debate, and successive editions were published in the 1840s and 1850s responding to criticisms. On the controversial reception of <hi rend="italic">Vestiges</hi> and the speculation about its author, see J. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7068.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Secord 2000</ref>. For CD’s assessment of the book, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 3 and 4, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 5, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 2 September [1854]</ref>, and the ‘historical sketch’ added to the third and subsequent editions of <hi rend="italic">Origin.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Henry Lewes</ref> was one of the founders and editors of the <hi rend="italic">Leader</hi>, a radical weekly journal published in London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>; see also J. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7068.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Secord 2000</ref>, pp. 483–4). Shaw’s letter appeared in the 24 September 1853 issue of the journal, in response to a lengthy review of the tenth edition of <hi rend="italic">Vestiges</hi> by Lewes (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4724.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lewes 1853</ref>). Shaw defended the view that ‘the progression (of animal life)’ was ‘the result of <hi rend="italic">an aspiration towards new and superior fields of existence</hi>’ (see R. Wallace ed. 1899, pp. lii–liv).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Shaw refers to a famous line from the play <hi rend="italic">The self-tormentor</hi>, by the Roman dramatist Terence: ‘homo sum: humani nil a me alienum puto’ (77).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Shaw alludes to the remarks of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isaac Newton</ref>, which were published in his memoirs (Brewster ed. 1855, 2: 407): <quote type="quote"> I do not know what I may appear to the world, but to myself I seem to have been only like a boy playing on the sea-shore, and diverting myself in now and then finding a smoother pebble or a prettier shell than ordinary, whilst the great ocean of truth lay undiscovered before me. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3702.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Parsons</ref>, third earl of Rosse, designed and constructed large reflecting telescopes, and made detailed observations of nebulae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his article ‘The reign of law’ in the religious weekly <hi rend="italic">Good Words</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_802.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Douglas Campbell</ref>, eighth duke of Argyll, had criticised CD’s theory of natural selection for failing to explain adequately the beauty and variety in nature (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. D. Campbell 1865</ref>, p. 231): <quote type="quote"> The evidence is indeed abundant, that ornament and variety are provided for in nature for themselves and by themselves, separate from all other use whatever. Any theory on the origin of species which is too narrow to hold this fact, must be taken back for enlargement and repair. </quote> Campbell had made the same criticism in his address to the Royal Society of Edinburgh on 5 December 1864 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1186.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. D. Campbell 1864</ref>). For a discussion of Campbell’s address and CD’s response, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4746.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 16 January 1865</ref> and nn. 6–11, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4752.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 22 January [1865]</ref> and nn. 5–14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">No published reply by Shaw to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. D. Campbell 1865</ref> has been found; however, Campbell is listed as a correspondent of Shaw’s (R. Wallace ed. 1899, p. xxiv).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Shaw refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. D. Campbell 1865</ref>, pp. 227–32; see also n. 7, above. In an undated autobiographical note, Shaw remarked that he had written this letter to CD without having read the discussion of sexual selection in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (R. Wallace ed. 1899, pp. lv–lvi).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In his most extended discussion of the origins of religion, the French philosopher and founder of positivism, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Auguste Comte</ref>, drew an analogy between the love and devotion felt by domestic animals for their human masters, and the worship of gods and angels by humans (Comte 1851–4, 1: 496). Shaw is described as being ‘for a great many years a pronounced Positivist’ (R. Wallace ed. 1899, xxii). On the reception of Comte’s writings on religion in Britain, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8517.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. R. Wright 1986</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Campbell referred to the ‘habits of the rudest savage’, who covered ‘with elaborate carving the handle of his war-club’, as illustrating the universal love of ornament (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. D. Campbell 1865</ref>, p. 230).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In <hi rend="italic">Sartor Resartus</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_832.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Carlyle</ref> wrote: ‘The first purpose of Clothes, as our Professor imagines, was not warmth or decency, but ornament’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1242.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Carlyle] 1838</ref>, p. 37).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Shaw refers to the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> and to CD’s publisher, John Murray.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>