<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10925">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Johannes Schön<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 April 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10641</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10925 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10925.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10925.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 62</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 62</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4197.xml">Schön, Johannes</persName>
                <placeName>Stettin</placeName>
                <date when="1877-04-10">10 Apr 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>In the name of a student science club, asks whether CD’s theory of evolution applies to mental as well as physical characteristics of men and animals. Asks whether animals have free-will like humans. Do animals have a sense that humans lack?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Schon, Johannes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">student science club</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Stettin</placeName>
                    <date>den 10<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi>. April 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Höchst verehrter Herr.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Wenn von einem Naturforscher eine neue Hypothese aufgestellt wird, welche alle bisherigen Ansichten völlig umstösst, so ist es ganz natürlich, dass sich hierbei unter den Gelehrten die mannigfaltigsten Streitfragen über diesen oder jenen Punkt solcher neuen Theorie erheben. Dass aber auch <hi rend="underline">Laien</hi> den lebhaftesten Antheil daran nehmen, dürfte wohl nicht leicht vorkommen und kann nur darin seine Erklaerung finden, dass eine solche neue naturwissenschaftliche Hypothese von so durchgreifender Wirkung ist, dass von ihr nicht nur die gelehrte Welt sondern auch die gewöhnliche Menschenklasse hingerissen und begeistert wird. Und dass Ihre herrliche Theorie über die Entstehung der Organismen solche Wirkung auch im Auslande hervorgebracht hat, das können Sie, hochverehrter Herr, aus diesem Schreiben abnehmen; denn wir, die Unterzeichneten dieses Briefes, sind durchaus keine Männer von Fach sondern Schüler höherer Lehranstalten und bitten deshalb um gütige Nachsicht. Wir bilden nämlich, um Ihnen mit wenigen Worten den Sachverhalt auseinanderzusetzen, einen kleinen wissenschaftlichen Verein, und haben dabei den Zweck, unsere allgemeine Bildung zu erweitern. Es war unvermeidlich, dass wir, beim Studiren der Naturwissenschaften, auch Ihre Theorie kennen lernten, und wir Alle ohne Ausnahme gehören zu den eifrigsten Anhängern derselben. Dennoch aber können wir uns bis heute noch nicht über einige Punkte einigen und sind endlich überein gekommen uns mit unserer Angelegenheit an den Begründer der Theorie, an Sie, zu wenden. Die Punkte aber um deren gütige Auskunft wir bitten sind folgende:</p>
<p>Schon vorher, ehe wir uns mit Ihrer Hypothese bekannt machten, hatten wir uns oft die Frage zu beantworten versucht, wie sich der Mensch <hi rend="underline">geistig</hi> vom Thier unterscheidet, und es hatten sich unter uns zwei ganz verschiedene Ansichten geltend gemacht, nämlich:</p>
<p>Die Einen meinten, der Unterschied zwischen Mensch und Thier sei ein ganz allmählicher, so dass der geistige Uebergang vom höchststehenden Thier zum tiefststehenden Menschen ebenso unmerklich sei, wie derjenige eines geistig minderbefähigten Thieres zu einem geistig begabteren.</p>
<p>Die Anderen dagegen behaupteten, der Mensch und das Thier seien in ihren geistigen Anlagen gar nicht zu vergleichen, denn auch der tiefststehende Mensch überrage weit das höchstehende Thier.</p>
<p>Die Ersteren schrieben ferner dem Thiere vollständig freien Willen zu, während die Anderen wieder sagten, der freie Wille käme nur dem Menschen zu und gerade das sei ein Hauptunterschied zwischen Thier und Mensch.</p>
<p>Nachdem wir nun Ihre Theorie kennen gelernt hatten, wurde diese Frage über den geistigen Unterschied von Neuem aufgeworfen, und die Ersteren suchten ihre Ansicht dadurch zu begründen, dass sie sagten, auch Darwin wäre sicherlich ihrer Meinung; denn auch er liesse den Menschen aus dem Thiere hervorgehen, also wäre auch der <hi rend="underline">Geist</hi> des Menschen nichts als ein etwas vollkomnerer thierischer Geist. Dagegen erwiederten die Anderen: Darwin hätte in seiner Theorie nur eine Erklaerung geben wollen, wie sich der <hi rend="underline">Stoff</hi> allmählich entwickelt habe, wie aus dem formlosen Protoplasma durch langsame Bildung in ganz allmählichen Uebergängen schliesslich die vollendetste Gestalt der Schöpfung, der Mensch, hervorgegangen sei; aber die Entwickelung des <hi rend="underline">Geistes</hi> wäre mit der Darwin’schen Theorie durchaus nicht in Einklang zu bringen. Mit diesen beiden ganz entgegengesetzten Ansichten steht auch die schon erwähnte Meinung über den freien Willen in richtigem Verhältniss. Diejenigen von uns nämlich, welche glauben, Ihre Theorie erkläre nicht nur die Entwickelung des Stoffes, sondern auch des Geistes, schreiben dem Thiere den freien Willen zu, während die Anderen ihm einen solchen abläugnen. Nur der Mensch, so behaupten die Letzteren, hat vollständig freien Willen. Er kann thun und lassen, ganz nach seinem Belieben; das Thier dagegen muss seinem Naturtriebe gehorchen, das heisst mit anderen Worten: Der Mensch will, das Thier muss. Der Zugvogel, zum Beispiel, muss seinem Naturtriebe folgen, wenn der Winter naht, und muss südlicher ziehen. Ueberhaupt fahren die Vertreter derselben Ansicht fort, hat eigentlich nur der Mensch Geist und Vernunft, während die Thiere zum Ersatz dafür Sinne haben, die dem Menschen fehlen. Solche Sinne sind zum Beispiel nach ihrer Meinung der Ortssinn, welcher den Schlittenhund Sibiriens beim furchtbarsten Schneegestöber seinen Weg einhalten lehrt; ferner der Raumsinn, welcher sich bei den Affen und Katzen zeigt, indem sie ihre Sprünge genau zu berechnen wissen; ferner der Zeitsinn bei zur Arbeit verwendeten Hunden, welche die Stunden und sogar die Wochentage genau kennen, wo die Reihe sie trifft.—</p>
<p>Demgegenuber lautet nun die Meinung der Anderen von uns folgendermassen: Den freien Willen hat das Thier ebenso gut, wie der Mensch; der Zugvogel wird durchaus nicht vom Naturtriebe gezwungen, seine Heimath beim Nahen des Winters zu verlassen, sondern ob er nach Süden zieht oder nicht, hängt von seinem freien Willen ab, wie sich dies namentlich darin zeigt, das hie und da wirklich einige Zugvögel sich nicht zum Abreisen, sondern zum Ueberwintern entschliessen, so zum Beispiel der Edelfink. Auch brauchen wir durchaus bei dem Thiere keine Sinne anzunehmen, die dem Menschen fehlen, sondern das Thier verrichtet alles genau nach Ueberlegung und Berechnung wie der Mensch.</p>
<p>Diese Streitpunkte sind es, über welche wir uns, wie gesagt nicht einigen können, und um endlich eine Entscheidung herbeizuführen, haben wir Sie zum Schiedsrichter erwählt in der freudigen Erwartung, dass Sie unsere Bitte nicht abschlagen werden. Wir wünschen also, um es noch einmal kurz zusammenzufassen, über folgendes gütige Auskunft:</p>
<p>1. Ist nach Ihrer Theorie die Entwicklung der Organismen eine nur <hi rend="underline">körperliche</hi> oder geht Hand in Hand damit auch die <hi rend="underline">geistige</hi> Entwicklung?</p>
<p>2. Haben die Thiere freien Willen, oder nicht?</p>
<p>3. Hat das Thier Sinne, die dem Menschen fehlen oder verrichtet auch das Thier seine Handlungen nach Ueberlegung und Berechnung, wie der Mensch?</p>
<p>Endlich halten wir es noch für unsere Pflicht Ihnen das Buch zu nennen, aus dem wir unsere Kenntniss von Ihrer Theorie geschöpft haben, denn wir sind nicht in der Lage gewesen, Ihre eigenen Werke zu studiren, wir kennen aber den Inhalt derselben aus dem Buche: “Jäger, die Darwin’sche Theorie”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In der Hoffnung, dass wir Sie, höchstverehrter Herr, mit unserer Bitte nicht belästigen werden, und dass Sie auf uns als Laien und Schüler billige Rücksicht nehmen werden, unterzeichnen wir mit vorzüglichster Hochachtung:</p>
<p>Der Wissenschaftliche Verein. | gezeichnet: | <hi rend="underline">Johannes Schön</hi> | Schriftführer. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Stettin</hi><hi rend="underline"> grosse Domstrasse 22</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Stettin</placeName>
                    <date>10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. April 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>When a new hypothesis is put forward by a naturalist, one that completely overthrows all former views, it is quite natural that various disputes arise among scholars regarding some aspect or other of such a new theory. However, for <hi rend="underline">laymen</hi> as well to show the most lively interest might not readily happen and can only be explained if such a new scientific theory has so pervasive an impact that not only the world of scholarship but also the ordinary class of people are moved and inspired by it. And that your magnificent theory on the origin of organisms has had such an impact even abroad, you, most esteemed Sir, may infer from this letter; for we, the undersigned, are by no means experts, but pupils of higher educational establishments, and thus we ask for your kind forbearance. We are organising, you see, to explain in a few words, a little scientific society, and its purpose is to broaden our general education. It was unavoidable that when studying the natural sciences, we should also become acquainted with your theory, and we are all without exception among your most enthusiastic followers. Anyway, we are still unable to agree on some points and we have finally resolved to turn to you, the founder of the theory, with our concerns. The points regarding which we kindly ask for information are the following:</p>
<p>Even before we became acquainted with your hypothesis, we had often tried to answer the question, in what way man differs <hi rend="underline">intellectually</hi> from animals, and two entirely different views had emerged, namely:</p>
<p>Some maintained that the difference between man and animal was totally gradual, so that the intellectual transition from the highest animal to the lowest man was just as imperceptible as that from a less mentally capable animal to a more gifted one.</p>
<p>Others maintained on the contrary, that man and animal could not be compared at all in regard to their mental faculties, for even the lowest man far outshone the highest animal.</p>
<p>The former further ascribed complete free will to animals, while the latter again said that free will was possessed only by man and was precisely a principal difference between animal and man.</p>
<p>After we had now got to know your theory, this question concerning the intellectual difference arose again and the first group sought to support their views by saying that even Darwin would be on their side; for he, too, viewed man as emerging from animals; therefore the <hi rend="underline">mind</hi> of man was nothing but a somewhat more complete animal mind. Against this the others responded: Darwin, in his theory, had only wanted to give an explanation of how <hi rend="underline">matter</hi> had gradually developed, how, from formless protoplasm through a slow process in quite gradual transitions, the most perfect form of creation, namely man, had emerged; the development of <hi rend="underline">mind</hi>, however, could not be reconciled with Darwin’s theory. These two quite opposing views are also linked to the opinion on free will, which we have already mentioned. Those of us who believe that your theory explains not just the development of matter but also of mind, ascribe free will to animals; while the others deny this. Only man, the latter hold, has complete free will. He can do as he pleases; animals, on the other hand, must obey their instincts, that is (in other words): man wants, the animal must. A migratory bird, for example, must follow its natural instinct when winter approaches, and must move south. Anyhow, those adhering to this position continue, only man is really endowed with mind and reason, while animals by way of compensation have senses that man is lacking. Such senses are, for example, in their opinion, the sense of direction, which allows the sled dog of Siberia to stay on the right course through the worst sowstorm. Furthermore, the spatial sense, which manifests itself in monkeys and cats, when they calculate their leaps precisely; further, the sense of time of dogs that are used for labour; they know exactly the hours and even the days of the week when it is their turn.—</p>
<p>Against this, the opinion of the others among us is as follows: the animal has free will just like man; a migratory bird is by no means forced by natural instinct to leave its home when winter approaches, rather whether it moves south or not depends on its free will, as is shown by the fact that here and there a number of migratory birds decide not to move on, but to spend the winter at home, such as, for example, the chaffinch. Also, we certainly do not need to assume that animals have senses man is lacking; rather, an animal carries out all its actions precisely after deliberating and calculating, just like man.</p>
<p>These are the points of contention, which as stated we were unable to resolve, and in order to bring about a final decision, we have chosen you as referee, in the keen expectation that you will not turn down our request. We wish therefore, to briefly summarise again, information on the following:</p>
<p>1. Is development of organisms, according to your theory, merely <hi rend="underline">physical</hi> or does it go hand in hand with the development of <hi rend="underline">mind</hi>?</p>
<p>2. Do animals have free will, or not?</p>
<p>3. Does the animal have senses lacking in man, or does the animal act with deliberation and calculation, like man?</p>
<p>Finally, we consider it our duty to tell you the book from which we have drawn our information on your theory, for we were not in a position to study your own work, but know its substance from the book: “Jäger, die Darwin’sche Theorie”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In the hope not to have bothered you, most esteemed Sir, with our request, and that you will kindly bear in mind that we are mere lay persons and pupils, we sign most respectfully:</p>
<p>The Scientific Society. | signed: | <hi rend="underline">Johannes Schön</hi> | secretary. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Stettin</hi><hi rend="underline"> grosse Domstrasse 22</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Jäger</ref> had attempted to reconcile Darwinian theory and Christianity in his book <hi rend="italic">Die Darwin’sche Theorie und ihre Stellung zu Moral und Religion</hi> (The Darwinian theory and its relation to ethics and religion; Jäger 1869). CD received two copies of the book, one of which was given to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>; CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6885.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Gustav Jäger, 9 September 1869</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7111.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Gustav Jäger, 17 February 1870</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>