<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9885">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Lawson Tait   12 March [1875]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10881</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9885 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9885.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9885.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4653.xml">Tait, R. L.</persName>
                <placeName>Birmingham</placeName>
                <date when="1875-03-12">12 Mar [1875]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Purpose of bushy tails; their usefulness to their owners as a means of keeping warm.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">7, Great Charles St. | Birmingham.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Mar 12</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have had previous occasion to correspond with you on subjects bearing on evolution, and there is one more little matter on which I should like your opinion.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As one of your disciples it has been my object to try the doctrine of evolution by survival of fitness at every possible point and amongst other things I have speculated on the origin of tails</p>
<p>For every tail I got a satisfactory reason, save for the bushy tail of such animals as the civet cat,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> some dogs, wolf &amp;c. That variety long puzzled me until the accidental observation of a favourite white cat, who is perfectly deaf, solved the riddle to me On him I can perform experiments by reason of his deafness, without arousing his suspicion and I find that he uses his tail as a respirator to keep up his temperature. I catch him asleep before a German stove, lying at full length on his side with tail &amp; limbs stretched out to enjoy the full heat. Then I intercept the heat by a screen &amp; without waking he gradually coils himself up so as to cover as much surface as possible to save loss of heat. Then when I drive a current of cold air on him from a pair of bellows he twines his tail round him &amp; buries his nose completely in the fur between it &amp; the thigh, thereby establishing a natural respirator which must conserve his temperature to a very marked extent</p>
<p>Birds do the same thing when they bury their noses in their wings. I cannot find a bushy tailed animal which cannot curl itself up. If I could my theory would be spoilt</p>
<p>I mentioned this to my friend Prof Haughton<ref target="#foot.f4"/> of Dublin a few days ago when on a visit to him, and on a very cold morning we started round the Zoological Gardens to examine for the point. We found the civet cat &amp; others coiled up &amp; their noses covered with the fur. I do not know whether the observation is an original one or not, but it is at any rate interesting   I purpose communicating a short note on it to the Birmingham Natural History Society and previous to that I should like to know your opinion of my theory.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Yours faithfully | Lawson Tait</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘30£’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by Tait’s reference to his communication to the Birmingham Natural History Society (see n. 5, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The only earlier extant correspondence with Tait is the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7993.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, 8 October 1871</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19); it concerns the supra-condyloid foramen of the humerus.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The civet cat is <hi rend="italic">Civettictis civetta</hi>, the African civet; it is not a cat, but a member of the family Viverridae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2165.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Haughton</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Tait lectured on the subject of animals’ tails at the Birmingham Natural History Society on 5 April 1875; a summary of his remarks, including part of CD’s response to this letter, appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Birmingham Daily Post</hi>, 8 April 1875, p. 6, and later in <hi rend="italic">Hardwicke’s Science-Gossip</hi>, June 1875 (Tait 1875a). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9885F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, [13–15 March 1875]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>