<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6690">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Richard Spruce   [before 1 April 1869]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10784</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6690 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6690.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6690.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 241</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 241</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4507.xml">Spruce, Richard</persName>
                <placeName>Welburn, Castle Howard</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1869-03-31">[before 1 Apr 1869]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends CD a paper ["Ant-agency in plant structure", published in Spruce <hi rend="italic">Notes of a botanist on the Amazon and Andes</hi>, ed. A. R. Wallace (1908)] on plant structures he believes are the work of insects; asks him to forward it to the Linnean Society [read 15 Apr 1869].</p>  
<p>Writes of his support for the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, before which he had been much concerned by the delimitation of so-called species.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ants</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Notes of a botanist on the Amazon and Andes</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4935">Wallace, A. R.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Spruce, Richard 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">definitions (will revert to tyd)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Linnean Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Welburn | Castle-Howard | York.</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">8 lines missing</hi>〉 plain of 〈    〉— I never again saw a plant of that fam〈ily〉 〈Had〉 I been able to travel I should have gone again in quest of them, not only to try to obtain the information you wanted, but to follow up some observations of my own touching the origin of curious bags on the leaves of some of the species inhabited by ants.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>A few years ago I drew up a memoir on certain modifications of the organs of plants which I consider entirely the work of insects, altho’ some of them take rank as specific and even generic characters. I have kept the Mst. by me hoping at least to go again to Kew and reexamine my specimens of those curious structures, but as the state of my health renders that an impossibility I have written out the memoir afresh, and send it to you by this day’s post, requesting to be kind enough to look through it carefully and then hand it over to the Linnean Society to be read at one of their meetings.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I shall be thankful for a line to say how far you consider my inferences justified by the facts.</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">8 lines excised</hi>〉</p>
<p>It is a great defect of my relation that it contains no definite account of the ants infesting the plants, &amp; I have no materials for supplying it. I have somewhere a small packet of ants that dropped out of my specimens of Amaioua saccifera,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> but I cannot just now lay my hand on it.</p>
<p>I have often wished to write to thank you for your admirable writings on philosophic biology, most of which I have read since I returned home invalided 4 years ago. The ‘Origin of Species’, especially, filled up a void of which I had long been sensible in my own speculations. When a very young botanist I came to some of the same conclusions as yourself, but very empirically, &amp; not by any process of laborious and accurate observation such as you have gone through. When I read Linnæus’s definition of a species in the ‘Philosophia Botanica’, based on the supposed fact that no hybrid between <hi rend="underline">true</hi> species could be fertile,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I said to myself “We ought surely to <hi rend="underline">experiment</hi> unceasingly on the interbreeding of so-called species, for we may go on <hi rend="underline">describing</hi> animals &amp; plants to the end of all time and we shall never attain to the correct delimitation of a single species”. Afterwards, when I tried to deduce some “law of species” from the writings of eminent botanists, I could find only this, running through the descriptions of every author: “<hi rend="underline">My</hi> species are <hi rend="underline">good</hi> species—those of other authors probably not”—the same as in any other orthodoxy &amp; heterodoxy. I could then only resolve to examine everything for myself—to take names and descriptions as (at best) attempts to fix transitory aspects of things—and to try to trace what variation of form &amp; structure was tending to. Your book makes it most clear that <hi rend="underline">variation in plants and animals is not oscillation round fixed centres but progress in directions determined by surrounding influences</hi>.</p>
<p>But I am taking up too much of your precious time, so, wishing you still a long lease of life and energy to continue your most valuable labours, I subscribe myself | Yours very faithfully | Rich. Spruce. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6691.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Richard Spruce, 1 April 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Spruce probably refers to the former family Melastomeae in the order Melastomaceae (now the family Melastomataceae in the order Myrtales). CD had sent Spruce queries about Melastomataceae at the end of 1863, when Spruce was ill and coming to the end of his stay in South America (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4378.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 2 January 1864</ref> and nn. 12 and 13); CD’s letter to Spruce has not been found. CD was interested in a possible new form of dimorphism in the Melastomaceae (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3404.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 22 January [1862]</ref> and n. 13).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Spruce’s paper was read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 15 April 1869, but was not published in the society’s proceedings. The paper is printed in full in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7395.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spruce 1908</ref>, 2: 384–412, together with an account by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref> of events associated with its reading. Spruce also refers to the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Amaioua saccifera</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Duroia saccifera</hi>, a member of the family Rubiaceae. It has ‘ant-houses’ on its leaves (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8405.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Willis 1973</ref>). A specimen of the wood of <hi rend="italic">A. saccifera</hi> is in the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4507.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Spruce</ref> Collection, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Spruce refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2942.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl von Linné</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnaeus 1751</ref>: see especially sections 132 and 259. CD wrote on hybrid fertility in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 246–50; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 310–26, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix VI.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>