<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4974">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Jeffries Wyman   11 January 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11142</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4974 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4974.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4974.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 221.4: 257r</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 191</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 191</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5268.xml">Wyman, Jeffries</persName>
                <placeName>Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>
                <date when="1866-01-11">11 Jan 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has made observations on bees’ cells. Their dimensions are not constant, nor do single bees make single cells; each one is a result of co-operation.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bees</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nesting and other home-making or web-making behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cambridge [Massachusetts]</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1866</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Having lately given some attention to the study of the cells of the bee I have been struck with the fact that the deviations from the form alledged to have been measured by Maraldi &amp; which was calculated by Koenig, are much greater than is mentioned in any of the descriptions I have seen.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The conclusion to which I have been led, is, that whatever the <hi rend="underline">typical</hi> form of the cell be, it is rarely, if ever, realised.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As you have given your own careful attention to this subject, I feel that I run the risk of writing what may be already better known to you than to myself.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Then it occurs to me that cumulative evidence is worth something. At all events I will state what I have to say briefly.</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> After repeated measurments of hundreds of worker cells I find, as Reaumer did in the drone cells, that the diameters are very frequently variable, so that nine cells measured in the direction of one diameter will sometimes fill a space, which it will require ten to fill if measured in the direction of another.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. The terminal rhombs are the most variable parts of the cell. I have shown this very satisfactorily by means of plaster casts, &amp; even by the coccoons from old brood cells which give a very good model of the base— Sometimes the rhombs are all of different sizes, &amp; at others one is nearly eliminated, the other two making nearly the whole of the partition between two adjoining cells. 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. The introduction of the fourth side to the base does not always, or even generally depend upon the transition from worker to drone cells, as stated by Huber,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but either upon an incorrect allinement of the cells on opposite sides of the comb, or upon an increase of the size of the cells on one side not corresponding with that on the other. 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the most remarkable deviation which I have noticed is a sort of rotation as it were of the cells, so that those of the two sides, differed in position about 30<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>Fig 1 being the normal position, 2 &amp; 3 are the abnormal ones— in 2 the angle of one cell corresponds with the centre of the other, but instead of pointing to one of the angles of the other cell it points to one of the sides. In 3 the cells were fitted together by their whole bases, &amp;, projected on to the same plane, are concentric. In both of these cases the rhombic faces became impracticable, &amp; the bees compromised on a <hi rend="underline">flat</hi> bottom to the cell— I found this arrangement in a large part of a worker brood-comb, &amp; in the whole of a piece of drone comb. 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Lastly there is no regular mode of transition from worker to drone cells, but this may be effected in several ways, viz by means of irregular polygonal cells, by a gradual change of size, so that no line of separation is noticeable between the two kinds; &amp; by the close approximation of worker &amp; drone cells making an abrupt change; but as the worker cells are one fifth smaller than the drone cells, &amp; therefore fail to fill up the space, a new row is intercalated for this purpose.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>These intercalated rows however do come at regular intervals, &amp; the emergency is often met by thickened walls.</p>
<p>I have studied the cells with reference to the hexagonal shape, &amp; it seems to me that the view taken by Mr Waterhouse &amp; yourself is the most tenable one.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Fearing that you may not have seen the work, I take the liberty of calling your attention to the so called “fossil tadpole nests”, in Prof Hitchcocks report on the Ichnology of Massachusetts. Have you not there exactly the phenomenon in question? A lot of tadpoles get together each wiggling about on a centre, as is is necessary in a crowd, each excavates a place in the mud, but their respective cavities soon come in collision &amp; a flat wall between them results, &amp; in many cases a hexagonal cell almost as true as that of the bee—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>One thing seems entirely clear, that the hexagonal cell results from the cooperation of several bees &amp; is never made by a single bee, &amp; if he have no antagonist in the construction of a wall it is curvilinear.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> In some of my wasps nests from S America it appears that even in working with paste board, the outer walls of the new cells are always curved <hi rend="underline">at first</hi>, but when other cells are made outside of them they are flattened so as to conform to those that have preceded them.</p>
<p>Before I close allow me to mention the observations of Mr Putnam on the cells of our humble bees—which he has shown are at first a mass of pollen &amp; honey, on which an egg is placed, &amp; into which the larva eats as soon as hatched.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> The cavity thus formed is the beginning of the cell.— This is increased by additions of pollen, which is gradually consumed; eventually wax is applied to the exterior in a very thin layer.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I requested Mr Putnam to send you a copy of his paper, which perhaps you will have received before this reaches you.</p>
<p>I fear I have trespassed upon your time, but hope you will excuse me on the score of good intention</p>
<p>With great respect | Truly yours | J. Wyman <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin, Esq. | Downe Bromley Kent.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.4 The conclusion … realised. 1.6] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.3 attention … Massachusetts. 3.5] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 One … single bee, 4.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Before … bees— 5.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">On cover</hi>: ‘Size [<hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘Thickness’] of Cells &amp; irregularities—good—Wyman’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Giacomo Filippo Maraldi’s</ref> geometrical measurements of hive-bee (honey-bee) cells (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5209.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maraldi 1712</ref>, pp. 304–9) and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6079.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Samuel Koenig’s</ref> calculations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4422.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koenig 1739</ref>) were cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Réaumur 1734–42</ref>, 5: 382, 388–9. The base of each cell, a hexagonal prism, is composed of three parallelograms (rhombs), for which Koenig calculated the internal angles required to achieve the most efficient relationship between volume and the amount of wax required to build the cell. As Koenig’s theoretical figures corresponded closely with Maraldi’s empirical measurements (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Réaumur 1734–42</ref>, 5: 388–90), the notion arose that the dimensions of hive-bee cells were more or less standard.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Wyman’s conclusion is cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 271–2: ‘I hear from Prof. Wyman, who has made numerous careful measurements, that the accuracy of the workmanship of the bee has been greatly exaggerated; so much so, that, as he adds, whatever the typical form of the cell may be, it is rarely, if ever, realised.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Differences in the shapes of the cells made by various kinds of bees presented a potential problem for natural selection (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 224). The issue continued to interest CD after the publication of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2564.xml" resp="#automat">letter to W. H. Miller 1 December [1860]</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4376.xml" resp="#automat">letter to A. R. Wallace, 1 January 1864</ref> and n. 2). CD’s notes on bees’ cells are in DAR 48B. For a detailed examination of CD’s effort to demonstrate that the complex geometry of the cell could be achieved through the gradual evolution of complex instinct, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6416.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Prete 1990</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Brood combs include cells of different sizes. The smallest and most abundant cells of hive-bee combs are occupied by the larvae of workers, while the larvae of drones occupy larger cells (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7409.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stanek 1969</ref>, p. 177, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7084.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Seeley 1995</ref>, pp. 177–8). In his measurements of hive-bee cells, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3900.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">René Antoine Ferchault de Réaumur</ref> recorded greater variability among the diameters of drone cells than among those of worker cells (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Réaumur 1734–42</ref>, 5: 397–400).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2422.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">François Huber</ref> contended that the transition from worker cells to drone cells required that the pyramidal base of each cell be made up of four rhombs rather than three, as found typically in the worker cell (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Huber 1814</ref>, 2: 222–4). In his annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Huber 1814</ref> in the Darwin Library–CUL, CD scored parts of this passage (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 412). Further detail on structural aspects of the transition from worker to drone cells is given in the appendix to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Huber 1814</ref>, written by his son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2424.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jean Pierre Huber</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 2: 231–51).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In contrast to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2422.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">François Huber</ref>, who held that the bee cell was the product of the bee’s ability to construct geometrical forms, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4972.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Robert Waterhouse</ref> considered that the hexagonal cell of the hive-bee, and the rhombs of its base, originated in the form of a simple cylinder with a curved base. In his theoretical model, a number of pliable wax cylinders when packed tightly together under even pressure became hexagonal (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8184.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Waterhouse] 1835</ref>, pp. 153–5). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 225, CD wrote: ‘I was led to investigate this subject by Mr. Waterhouse, who has shown that the form of the cell stands in close relation to the presence of adjoining cells; and the following view may, perhaps, be considered only as a modification of his theory.’ CD went on to propose an underlying instinct by which bees build cell walls according to a scheme of intersecting circles, adding that the hive-bee’s hexagonal cells resulted from the natural selection of successive slight modifications in instinct that conferred increasing economy in the use of wax (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 235). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. R. Waterhouse, 13 February 1858</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2344.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 17 [October 1858]</ref> and nn. 3 and 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2307.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Hitchcock</ref> established the science of ichnology (<hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society</hi> 9 (1864): 445). Hitchcock observed both mud and fossils containing cavities that were hexagonal in form like bee cells; he concluded that in both cases the cavities had been formed by tadpoles (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3693.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hitchcock 1858</ref>, pp. 121–3 and plates 21 and 50). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Cresy, 10 September 1865</ref> and n. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In preparing the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> during the spring of 1866 (see ‘Journal’, Appendix II), CD deleted a sentence in which he had cautiously entertained the possibility that hive-bees construct each cell as ‘an isolated hexagon’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 233, and Peckham ed. 1959, p. 410).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederic Ward Putnam</ref> and Putnam 1863a, an annotated copy of which is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD’s annotations on Putnam’s paper included the scoring of passages on the formation by adult humble-bees (<hi rend="italic">Bombus</hi>) of a thin wax wall around the pupa, and Putnam’s rejection of the view that eggs were laid in pre-formed cells (Putnam 1863a, pp. 101–4).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>