<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-36">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Sarah Harriet Owen   31 [December 1827]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5169</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-36 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-36.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-36.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Incomplete</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 58</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2059.xml">Owen, S. H. M.</persName>
                <placeName>[Brighton]</placeName>
                <date when="1827-12-31">31 [Dec 1827]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>They have been having a very gay time. Tells of "Redcoats &amp; Shootables" and several mutual friends.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="social" ref="#">"Redcoats &amp; Shootables"</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>6. Marine Square. [Brighton]</placeName>
                    <date>Monday 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was very glad to receive your letter, though it gave an additional pang to my guilty conscience for not having sooner fulfilled my promise of writing to you, but I hope you do not think that <hi rend="underline">forgetfulness</hi> has been the cause of my silence. I have said to myself every day for the last fortnight, “I <hi rend="underline">will</hi> write to Charles Darwin.” &amp; every day some awfully sudden event has prevented my doing so, but as to my forgetting <hi rend="underline">you</hi>, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles <hi rend="underline">that</hi> is quite out of the question—</p>
<p>I am afraid I have nothing very interesting to tell you, though I have been very gay since came here, &amp; like Brighton <hi rend="underline">very</hi> much, we are out almost every night, which <hi rend="underline">I</hi> think very wonderful, considering we knew so few people here when we first came. Last week we were at <hi rend="underline">three</hi> Balls, besides Parties, &amp; are engaged to four or five more, you make such particular enquries after <hi rend="underline">Red coats &amp; shootables<ref target="#foot.f1"/> that I cannot resist telling you (like M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Mathew) that they are most of them “remarkably frightful,” &amp; the </hi>scarlet shootables<hi rend="underline"> &amp; Scorpions<ref target="#foot.f2"/> are also </hi>remarkably useless<hi rend="underline"> as very few of them go out &amp; dance. I had the supreme bliss of </hi>chauncing<hi rend="underline"> to meet my very favourite shootable yesterday, viz M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. </hi>Charles Jones<hi rend="underline">, we met out walking &amp; were equally surprised to see each other, he fancied I was at Eaton<ref target="#foot.f3"/> , &amp; I thought him safe in London, he turned back &amp; walked with me for an hour by </hi>Shrewsbury Clocks<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; of course was very agreeable &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c <hi rend="underline">as usual</hi> I am afraid he is only here for a day or two, he called on us yesterday but we were out, &amp; did not see him— I have only had one <hi rend="underline">ramrodding</hi> excrescence<ref target="#foot.f5"/> since I came here, &amp; that was with the Foxhounds, &amp; excellent sport we had, I wish we could have the Spaniard here, instead of at the <hi rend="underline">Forest</hi>, where he is now quite useless, there are very good horses to be hired here, &amp; we intend to have another gallop soon—</p>
<p>Brighton is so <hi rend="underline">horridly</hi> windy that there is very little pleasure in walking here, &amp; besides we are in sad want of a <hi rend="underline">walking</hi> Chaperon, &amp; I <hi rend="underline">often</hi> wish you were here to take pity on two <hi rend="underline">desolate</hi> <hi rend="underline">Flams</hi>. Caddy<ref target="#foot.f6"/> wrote me word you were to go to the Forest the first hard frost, but I have not yet heard your name amongst the fashionable arrivals, remember you will owe two or three long visits by the time we return, I do not exactly know when that will be, I should think not before the beginning of February, I hope you will not be departed to your “<hi rend="underline">brilliant establishment</hi>” at Cambridge—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> We dined yesterday at Sir George Anson’s, &amp; had a very pleasant evening, Francis Anson is very goodnatured &amp; agreeable &amp; a great favourite with us all, he <hi rend="underline">chaunces</hi> to drop in every Morning to see what we are about, &amp; enquire if he can be useful in any way, I do not know what we should do without him. Then there is Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Fremantle who is very goodnatured &amp; civil, but I do not like him half so well as Francis— As for 〈    〉<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>〈    〉 Darwin Hall &amp; believe me, my dear Charles. | ever Yours sincerely | S. H Owen</p>
<p>The <hi rend="underline">quantity</hi> of this will I hope atone for the <hi rend="underline">quality</hi>, if you ever have patience to read it all—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Presumably officers and other targets for unmarried young ladies. As later letters make clear, ‘shootable’ is also used by the Owen girls generally for ‘suitable’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In Lister’s popular novel <hi rend="italic">Granby</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4831.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lister 1826</ref>) the term ‘scorpions’ is used for ‘That detrimental class … younger brothers’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Eaton Mascott, near Shrewsbury, home of the Williams family. Sarah Owen married <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Hosier Williams</ref> in 1831.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘by Shrewsbury clock’, a colloquial phrase lessening or even cancelling the period of time (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Partridge 1973</ref>, p. 840). Shakespeare used the term in <hi rend="italic">Henry IV</hi> Part I, 5. 4. 147 (Arden edition) in Falstaff’s fabricated account of his fighting with Percy for ‘a long hour by Shrewsbury clock’ at the battle of Shrewsbury.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Excursion or outing. Other examples of the Owen–Darwin private language that occur in the correspondence are: broadcloth = man; black broadcloth = clergyman; budget = letter; clandecently = clandestinely; foiblesse = weakness, foible; halter = altar; hare = suitor; insinivating = insinuating; insinivation = invitation; leetle = little; muslin = woman; mystery = rumour, gossip; punchon = penchant; statue = statute (of lunacy).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Probably a nickname for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3613.xml">Caroline Owen</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had been admitted pensioner to Christ’s College, 15 October 1827 but did not come into residence at Cambridge until January 1828 (<hi rend="italic">Biographical Register of Christ’s College</hi>, vol. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">At least one page is missing. The final lines are written vertically across the first page.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>