<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4578">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   29 July [1864]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14791</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4578 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4578.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4578.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="12">12</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 112</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 112</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>Denholm</placeName>
                <date when="1864-07-29">29 July [1864]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Asks for additional financial aid for trip to India.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, miscellaneous</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">India</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">voyage</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Denholm</placeName>
                    <date>29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. July.</date>
                    <salute>Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I duly received your letter of the 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am now almost afraid that for all the time I have had to prepare for my voyage, I might yet hear from the agent ere I was quite ready to leave.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will now state to you how this has occurred. I have been of late led to hope that a friend of mine here would advance a sum of money on my behalf, and accordingly was trusting in such, feeling ashamed to draw more deeply on your generous offers for my immediate wants.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I stated to him plainly my circumstances &amp; hopes of success in India, when I would repay him all that he might advance—asking him to assist me: but I have been disappointed, as he told me from certain alterations which he was about to make, he really could not at the present time spare me any money.</p>
<p>I have thus deferred mentioning to you any want of money, until I have given myself I fear little to time to again receive aid from you ere hearing from the agent as to sailing. I assure you I feel deeply in so heavily taxing your generosity—even though you have so repeatedly pressed me to let you know as to my pecuniary wants.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> These indeed would have been materially lessened had I not been so long out of a situation. I sincerely hope, therefore, that you will on this account excuse me in asking you for additional assistance to clear expenses here—and further believe that I am not unnecessarily drawing on your liberality.</p>
<p>I would therefore be greatly obliged by your transmitting to me a cheque for the amount which you think I might require on arriving in Calcutta, and also if you would include a little for sundry items &amp; expenses here.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> You would thus enable me to meet all which I may incur in this country, &amp; I fear not from the recomendations which you have induced D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker to give me that I will soon find something to do in India.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Permit me again to assure you that I feel very sorry that I should have occasion to ask you for further pecuniary assistance here: and I will only add that whatever you are pleased to grant me now, as well as that which you have already laid out on my account will be fully &amp; pleasently repaid so soon as I am fairly settled &amp; succeeding in India.</p>
<p>With this hope, I would thus respectfully solicit your aid, and beg you to excuse my not stating any sum, And now with best thanks for your kindness to me | I have the honour to remain | Sir | Your obed<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. &amp; obliged Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. | John Scott</p>
<p>P.S. I suppose a few standard works on Nat. Hist. will be all the books that I need take with me.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4582.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 2 August 1864</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter to Scott has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Following <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker’s</ref> advice, Scott was preparing to embark for India to seek employment (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4501.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 19 May 1864</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4505F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 21 May [1864]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4513.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 28 May [1864]</ref>). The shipping agent was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4670.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Taylor</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4584.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [29 July 1864]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had given Scott £25 for his voyage (see second letter from John Scott, 10 June [1864]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">After Scott left his position at the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh, in March, CD offered to assist him financially (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4458F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 9 April 1864</ref>; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 16 May [1864]</ref> and n. 11, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4505F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 21 May [1864]</ref> and n. 5). In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter to J. D. Hooker of 22 [May 1864]</ref>, CD wrote that he would pay for Scott’s voyage and initial expenses on arrival in Calcutta, if necessary.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD sent a cheque for £10 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4582.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 2 August 1864</ref> and nn. 1 and 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Between April and June 1864, CD had corresponded at length with Hooker regarding Scott’s prospects. After some hesistation, Hooker made enquiries about a post for Scott in India, and furnished Scott with letters of introduction to Thomas Anderson and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2004.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Grote</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [4 June 1864]</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>