<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6055">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Roland Trimen   26 March 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16160</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6055 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6055.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6055.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp † encl 1p (sketch)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 81: 76, DAR 85: B61–2, DAR 84.1: 134–5</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>85: B61–2,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>84.1: 134–5,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>81: 76</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4806.xml">Trimen, Roland</persName>
                <placeName>London, Guildford St, 71</placeName>
                <date when="1868-03-26">26 Mar 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Coloration in moths.</p> 
<p>Quotes Achille Guénée on relative proportion of sexes in <hi rend="italic">Phalaenites</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">moths</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Phalaenites</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Guenee, Achille</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>71, Guildford Street,</placeName>
                    <date>26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. March, 1868.</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have traced (from the plate in Guenée’s “Phalénites”) the enclosed outline of the Moth that I had in my mind as possessing so beautiful an under-surface. You will gather an idea of its colouring from what I have written on and about the tracing.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The grand ocellus on the forewing is a marvellous feature, when one reflects that there is no trace whatever of it on the upper side! Unfortunately, the insect is a ♀; or what a case it would have been had the ♂ only possessed so magnificent an ornament. (Query:— May not female animals sometimes be provided with special ornaments to attract the males, and may not sexual selection operate in their case as well as in that of males?) This is what Guenée says about <hi rend="underline">Gastrophora</hi>: vol. IX, p. 187— “J’établis ce genre sur une magnifique espèce australienne, dont je ne possède malheureusement qu’un seul sexe. Il est probable que le mâle fournit des caractères encore plus tranchés”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> He places the genus in the family <hi rend="underline">Œnochromidæ</hi> of the “Phalénites” (= our <hi rend="underline">Geometræ</hi>).<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The two following <hi rend="underline">Geometræ</hi> (also figured by Guenée) have the under surface more conspicuously coloured than the upper, viz: <hi rend="underline">Hypographa Phlegetonaria</hi> Guén. (Tasmania), belonging to the same Family as the beautiful <hi rend="underline">Gastrophora</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and <hi rend="underline">Hyperythra limbolaria</hi>, Guén. (Bengal), belonging to the Family <hi rend="underline">Ennomidæ</hi> (the “Thorn” Moths of English collectors).<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In the first of these, the dull-grey with darker striæ of the upper side is varied beneath with white lines and cloudings which bring the dark streaks out into strong relief: the sexes are quite similar. The second, <hi rend="underline">Hyperythra limbolaria</hi>, is of the usual orange-yellow of the “Thorns” on the superior surface, but the outer margin of both wings on the underside has a broad irregular bordering of deep-red. (Fortunately enough, this species affords a capital instance of the female being apparently much more abundant than the male, Guenée observing (IX, p. 101) “Elle parait très-commune aux Indes et j’en ai vu une grande quantité, <hi rend="underline">mais jamais un seul mâle</hi>”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Indeed he says of the whole genus, in noting some diversities of structure between the sexes, p. 100 “Ces différences sont d’autant plus essentielles à noter, que l’on trouve dans les envois <hi rend="underline">quatre ou cinq femelles</hi> <hi rend="underline">au moins</hi> contre un seul mâle”.)<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Among English <hi rend="underline">Geometræ</hi>, several species of <hi rend="underline">Ennomos</hi> (such as <hi rend="underline">E. illunaria</hi>) and <hi rend="underline">Fidonia piniaria</hi> occur to me as having the undersurface more variegated than the upper.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> <hi rend="underline">Fidonia piniaria</hi> is much given to holding the wings quite erect over its back, retaining them in that position for a considerable time. I have just referred to Guenée’s notes on the genus <hi rend="underline">Fidonia</hi>, &amp; find him observing this habit of <hi rend="underline">F. piniaria</hi>. He says: “Le papillon porte, au repos, les ailes relevées comme les Diurnes”.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I have noticed many Geometræ who carry the wings in the same manner just after settling, but they soon let them sink to a level with the body. At the Cape,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> a near ally of <hi rend="underline">Fidonia piniaria</hi>, apparently undescribed, holds its wings erect almost as long as the English species is in the habit of doing. Both sexes do this, but I am not sure whether the ♀s retain the position as long as the ♂s.</p>
<p>Turning to the <hi rend="underline">Noctuæ</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I find that Guenée figures the undersides of three species presenting a more conspicuous appearance than the upper. These are <hi rend="underline">Lygniodes hypoleuca</hi>, Guén. (Bengal), <hi rend="underline">Hypopyra unistrigata</hi>, Guén. (Bengal), and <hi rend="underline">Entomogramma pardus</hi> (Senegal)<ref target="#foot.f12"/> The first (♂) is glossy brownish-black above, but <hi rend="underline">white</hi>, with two brownish bands beneath: in the ♀ the contrast of the two surfaces is much less striking, the upper side being duller &amp; browner &amp; the under of an impure whitish. The second is dull ochrey-grey, with darker &amp; lighter streaks above; while the underside is bright <hi rend="underline">orange-red</hi>, with black stripes. The third (which I have taken commonly at Natal)<ref target="#foot.f13"/> is pale, dull greyish-ochreous above, with a darker border; but beneath is <hi rend="underline">ochre-yellow</hi> with numerous black-spots. All three are quadrifid Noctuæ,<ref target="#foot.f14"/> the first belonging to the family <hi rend="underline">Ophideridæ</hi>, &amp; the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. &amp; 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. to the <hi rend="underline">Hypopyridæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> <hi rend="underline">Entomogramma pardus</hi> is a day-flying moth, and I have noticed that both it and another much larger species of the same family (with a bright <hi rend="underline">red-lead</hi> underside Hypopyra Capensis, Herr.– Schäff.) have a habit, when settled on the ground or herbage, of now and then suddenly lifting the wings slightly, so as to afford one a glimpse of the bright colouring of the abdomen and underside. <hi rend="underline">These</hi> Quadrifid <hi rend="underline">Noctuæ</hi> (though by no means all of the section) seem to approach the <hi rend="underline">Geometræ</hi> in having the posterior wings almost wholly exposed when at rest and marked with a continuation of the lines and colouring of the anterior wings on both surfaces.</p>
<p>I have only one example of each sex of <hi rend="underline">Erebia</hi> (<hi rend="underline">Oreina</hi>) <hi rend="underline">Ligea</hi>, but I find that the ♂ does want the whitish pupil of the ocelli on the upper surface, but underneath (though the ocelli are smaller than in the ♀) the pupils are distinct. The same thing is observable in the allied <hi rend="underline">Erebia Euryale</hi> (also European).<ref target="#foot.f16"/> In the genus <hi rend="underline">Satyrus</hi> it seems often the case that the ocelli of the ♂ are less distinct than those of the ♀; I find this observable in <hi rend="underline">S. Hermione</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Alcyone</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Briseis</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Arethusa</hi> (all European).<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>As regards the <hi rend="underline">Hesperiidæ</hi> that settle with all the wings expanded, usually on the underside of leaves, the only species with which I am acquainted (in nature) that have anything remarkable about their <hi rend="underline">under</hi>-surface are the Natalian <hi rend="underline">Nisoniades Ophione</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Caprona Canopus</hi> both of which have the hindwings white.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> It may be advantageous to conceal the conspicuous whiteness, though this could as well be effected by settling on the upperside of leaves; but by choosing the underside of a leaf it would seem that these active insects evade actual pursuers or watchful foes very effectually. Under the shade of foliage, too, their fully-expanded wings, usually of sombre colours, would less readily attract the notice of enemies on the ground.</p>
<p>I hope that these notes may prove of use, imperfect as they are. I shall bear the subject in mind, and acquaint you with anything that I chance upon in connection with it.</p>
<p>Very truly yours, | Roland Trimen</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
              <figure rend="blockCentred width50">
                  <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6055.png"/>
              </figure>
              
              
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I have … quite similar. 2.7] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>2.7 The second, … deep-red. 2.9] ‘♀’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 Among … both surfaces. 4.19] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 As regards … with it. 7.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Number of sexes’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; <hi rend="italic">possible gamma, ink, circled blue crayon</hi>QQQQ</note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2012.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Achille Guenée</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 10: pl. 21, fig. 4, which shows both sides of the wings of the moth, <hi rend="italic">Gastrophora henricaria.</hi> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 397, CD cited Trimen for informing him about moths referred to in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>. Trimen had probably visited CD on 25 March 1868 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Roland Trimen, [21 March 1868]</ref>) and may have discussed the moth wings then.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">‘I base this genus on a magnificent Australian species, of which, unfortunately, I only possess a single sex. It is probable that the male offers characters that are still more distinctive’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: 187). In his addenda to the volume, Guenée added that he later received a male specimen, but its ocellus, as well as its general colour, was less distinctive than that of the female (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 10: 540).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Geometrae was the name of a group of moth families roughly equivalent to the present superfamily Geometroidea (butterfly moths). <hi rend="italic">Gastrophora</hi> is now in the family Geometridae, subfamily Oenochrominae. For more on the group ‘Phalénites’, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: v–viii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: 190 and 10: pl. 14, fig. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: 101 and 10: pl 3, figs. 3 and 4. <hi rend="italic">Hyperythra limbolaria</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">H. lutea</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fletcher 1979</ref>, p. 105). It is now in the family Geometridae, subfamily Ennominae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">‘It appeared to be very common in the Indies and I saw a great number, <hi rend="italic">but never a single male</hi>’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: 101).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">‘These differences are all the more essential to note, as <hi rend="italic">at least four or five females</hi> to every male are found in these regions’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: 100).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Trimen probably meant <hi rend="italic">Selenia illunaria</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 9: 152), now <hi rend="italic">S. dentaria</hi>, the early thorn moth (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fletcher 1979</ref>, p. 188). <hi rend="italic">Fidonia piniaria</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 10: 156–7) is now <hi rend="italic">Bupalus piniaria</hi>, the bordered white or pine looper.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">‘The moth, when resting, holds its wings up as butterflies do’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1857</ref>, 10: 152).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Trimen refers to Cape of Good Hope.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Noctuae was the name of a group of moth families roughly equivalent to the present superfamily Noctuoidea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">For <hi rend="italic">Lygniodes hypoleuca</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1852</ref>, 7: 125, pl. 16 fig. 5; for <hi rend="italic">Hypopyra unistrigata</hi>, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 7: 201, pl. 21 fig. 1; for <hi rend="italic">Entomogramma pardus</hi>, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 7: 205, pl. 21 fig. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Natal, now Kwazulu/Natal, a province of South Africa.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">In the classificatory system used in <hi rend="italic">Noctuélites</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Guenée 1852</ref>), the ‘division’ Noctuélites was divided into two ‘phalanges’, the Trifidae and the Quadrifidae. For more on Guenée’s system, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4388.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kitching 1984</ref>, pp. 159–65.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">All three species are now in the family Noctuidae (owlet moths).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><hi rend="italic">Erebia ligea</hi> is the Arran brown butterfly (<hi rend="italic">Oreina ligea</hi> is a junior synonym); <hi rend="italic">E. euryale</hi> is the large ringlet. See CD’s annotations to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5785.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Roland Trimen, 13 January 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><hi rend="italic">Satyrus hermione</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Hipparchia fagi</hi>; <hi rend="italic">S. alcyone</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Hipparchia alcyone</hi>; <hi rend="italic">S. briseis</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Chazara briseis</hi>; <hi rend="italic">S. arethusa</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Arethusana arethusa</hi> (personal communication, Niklas Wahlberg).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Hesperiidae is the family of skippers. Trimen published the name <hi rend="italic">Nisoniades ophion</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7821.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Trimen 1862–6</ref>, pp. 313–14; he later described the species as <hi rend="italic">Pterygospidea flesus</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7828.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Trimen 1887–9</ref>, 3: 363). It is now <hi rend="italic">Tagiades flesus</hi>, the clouded flat. <hi rend="italic">Caprona canopus</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Netrobalane canopus</hi>, the buff-tipped skipper.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>