<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6142">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Gerolamo Boccardo<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   23 April 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6931</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6142 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6142.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6142.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160: 233</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 233</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_505.xml">Boccardo, Gerolamo</persName>
                <placeName>R. Istituto Tecnico di Genova</placeName>
                <date when="1868-04-23">23 Apr 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for gift of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>.</p>  
<p>GB sent copies of his <hi rend="italic">Fisica del globo</hi> [1868] to Lyell and the presidents of British scientific societies but has received no acknowledgment; asks CD to check that they received the work. Could CD arrange for a notice of the book to appear in England?</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fisica del globo</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3051">Lyell, Charles</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">presidents of British scientific societies</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Boccardo, Gerolamo 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-09-15" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes">For vol. 30 supplement</change>
        <change when="2020-09-15" status="alteredPostPublication" type="letter">New transcription</change>
        <change when="2020-09-15" status="sup-footnoted">Footnoted for vol. 30 supp <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2021-11-01" status="sup-reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-08" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00971_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00971_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
        <surface n="233:1r" xml:id="i971">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00971.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00971_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00971.dzi" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="233:1v" xml:id="i972">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00972.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00972_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00972.dzi" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="233:2r" xml:id="i973">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00973.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00973_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00973.dzi" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="233:2v" xml:id="i974">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00974.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00974_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00974.dzi" width="3628px" height="5997px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">R. Istituto Tecnico | Industriale Professionale | e di Marina Mercantile | Della Provincia di Genova</hi> Genova</placeName>
                    <date>23 Aprile | 1868.</date>
                    <salute>Mio Caro Signore</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
                    <p>Permetta che io Le scriva questa volta nella mia propria lingua, nella quale potrò, più chiaramente che nel bellissimo idioma di V. S., esprimerle alcuni pensieri che vorrei in modo particolare raccomandare alla sua attenzione.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>La ringrazio prima di tutto della gentilissima sua lettera dei 13. corrente.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Io conserverò quell’autografo tra i documenti a me più cari e preziosi.</p>
                    <p>Le sono pure gratissimo del dono dell’ ultima e magnifica sua opera “Plants and Animals under Domestication”, che io mi avevo però già provveduta a Londra il giorno stesso ch’era stata pubblicata.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Profittando ora della squisita bontà che Ella si degna dimostrarmi, mi faccio ardito a pregarla di due segnalati favori, i quali spero la cortesia sua vorrà accordarmi.</p>
                    <p>Io mandai in dono il mio libro “Fisica del Globo” all’illustre Sig. Baronetto Carlo Lyell, al Presidente della Royal Society, al Presidente della Royal Geographical Society, al Presidente della Anthropological Society.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Non avendo io ricevuto da alcuno di quei Signori cenno alcuno di risposta, temo che i volumi non sieno loro pervenuti. Io La pregherei adunque, quando ciò non dovesse costarle soverchio incomodo, di volere avvertire i Signori summentovati, coi quali ha certamente personali rapporti, che io ho spedito loro la mia opera, la quale se non è ginuta nelle loro mani, deve sicuramente trovarsi agli uffici postali, ove li prego quindi di volerne fare ricerca.</p>
                    <p>La secunda preghiera che ho io in animo di farle, mi sta ancora più a cuore della precedente. Nel mio volume io ho procurato con tutta diligenza di fare tesoro dei grandi lavori scientifici Inglesi; ed Ella stessa si è compiaciuta di farmene un gentile elogio nella sua lettera. Ora io bramerei che la dotta Inghilterra sapesse che in Italia si sa apprezzare degnamente il merito dei meravigliosi ingegni di quella fortunata Nazione. Potrebbe Ella adunque procurare che qualche Giornale Scientifico e qualche Accademia facessero conoscere al pubblico Inglese il mio lavoro? Sarebbe questo per fermo il titolo maggiore della mia riconoscenza verso la S. V., alla quale debbo già tanto siccome ad uno de’ maestri più venerati.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>La diffusione delle dottrine Darwiniane in Italia incontra ostacoli d’una natura affatto particolare, e che sarebbe molto difficile il comprendere da chi vive e lavora in un paese da secoli avvezzo alla libertà del pensiero. Io ho però cosi profonda fede nella causa della Verità, che punto non dubito che molti anni non trascorreranno che anche nella mia patria essa dovrà ottenere pieno e sicuro trionfo.</p>
                    <p>Perdoni, Illustre Signore, se ho preso tanta sicurtà di V. S., da farle le accennate mie due preghiere, e se oso ancora sperare che Ella vorrà onorarmi di una sua risposta intorno alle medesime.</p>
                    <p>Viva sano, e mi creda | Suo Devotiss<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Serv’re | Gerolamo Boccardo</p>
                    <p>P.S. La prego di accettare il tenue omaggio di un mio recentissimo Discorso Accademico, ch’Ella riceverà per posta con la presente.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div> 
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">R. Istituto Tecnico | Industriale Professionale | e di Marina Mercantile | Della Provincia di Genova</hi> Genoa</placeName>
                    <date>23 | April 1868.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Allow me to write this time in my own tongue, in which I will be able to express more clearly than in your beautiful language some thoughts of mine to which I would especially draw your attention.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>First of all I thank you for your very kind letter of the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will keep that autograph amongst those documents dearest and most precious to me.</p>
<p>I am also extremely grateful for the gift of your latest and magnificent work “Plants and Animals under domestication”, of which I had, however, already acquired a copy from London the very day of its publication.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Taking advantage of the great kindness you have done me, I make so bold as to beg two particular favours from you which I hope you will be kind enough to grant me.</p>
<p>I sent as a gift my book “Fisica del Globo” to the illustrious Sir Charles Lyell, Bart., to the President of the Royal Society, to the President of the Royal Geographical Society, and to the President of the Anthropological Society.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Not having received any sign of a reply from any of these gentlemen, I fear that the volumes did not reach them. I would therefore beg you, if this does not cause you too much inconvenience, to inform the above-mentioned gentlemen, with whom you are certainly acquainted, that if the work that I sent them express has not arrived in their hands, it will surely be found at the post office, where they are therefore requested to make enquiries.</p>
<p>The second request that I wish to make to you is even more important for me than the first. In my book I have taken care with every diligence to set store by the great English scientific works; and you were kind enough to compliment me on that in your letter. Now, I would wish learned England to know that in Italy we know how to appreciate the true value of the merits of the wonderful intellects of that fortunate Nation. Could you therefore see that either some Scientific Journal or some Academy introduce my work to the British public? If you would do this to help me, I would owe a greater title for my gratitude due to You, than the great debt I already owe to one of my most venerated masters.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>The spread of Darwinian doctrines in Italy meets with obstacles of a quite distinctive kind, very difficult to understand for someone living and working in a country for centuries accustomed to freedom of thought. However, I have such profound faith in the cause of the Truth, that I do not doubt that not many years hence it will achieve a complete and lasting triumph in my country also.</p>
<p>Please forgive me, illustrious Sir, if I took the liberty to ask for these two favours, and dare to hope that you will be kind enough to again honour me with a reply concerning the same.</p>
<p>Take care of your health, and believe me, Sir, your most obedient servant | Gerolamo Boccardo</p>
<p>P.S. Please accept the meagre gift of a very recent Academic Discourse of mine which you will receive with this letter.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I. It was originally published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 16, and is republished here with an improved transcription.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see Transcript. It was originally published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 16, and is republished here with an improved transcription.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">No earlier letter from Boccardo has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s letter to Boccardo of 13 April 1868 has not been found, but see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 13 April [1868]</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Boccardo refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>, which was published on 30 January 1868 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml">Freeman 1977</ref>). CD had instructed his publisher, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">John Murray</ref>, to send a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> to Boccardo (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6114.xml">letter to John Murray, 13 April [1868]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Royal Society of London and the Royal Geographical Society have copies of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_760.xml">Boccardo 1868a</ref>. The Anthropology Library at the British Museum (the collection of the Anthropological Society) does not have a copy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">No reply to this letter has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">No discourse by Boccardo has been found in the Darwin Archive. Boccardo may have sent <hi rend="italic">La connessione delle scienze</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_761.xml">Boccardo 1868b</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>