<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1910">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   25 June [1856]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">132</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1910 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1910.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1910.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">5pp &amp; ADraft 8pp † (by CD)</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 114: 165a, DAR 146: 194</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 74</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 6: 153</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.132)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>132</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>50: D6–D11</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1856-06-25">25 June [1856]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Criticises at length the concept of submerged continents attaching islands to the mainland in the recent period. Notes drastic alteration of geography required, the dissimilar species on opposite shores of continents, and differences between volcanic islands and mountains of mainland areas. Admits sea-bed subsidence, but not enough to engulf continents. Denies that theory can explain island flora and fauna.</p>
            <p>Considers Edward Forbes’s idea a check on study of dissemination of species.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">continents, submerged</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">mountains</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">recent</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1680">Forbes, Edward</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dispersion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">volcanoes and earthquakes</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>June 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I will have the following tremendous letter copied to make the reading easier, &amp; as I want to keep a copy.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>As you say you would like to hear my reasons for being most unwilling to believe in the continental extensions of late authors, I gladly write them; as, without I am convinced of my error, I shall have to give them condensed in my Essay, when I discuss single and multiple creation.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I shall therefore be particularly glad to have your general opinion on them. I may <hi rend="underline">quite likely</hi> have persuaded myself in my wrath that there is more in them than there is.— If there was much more reason to admit a continental extension in any one or two instances (as in Madeira) then in other cases, I should feel no difficulty whatever. But if on account of European plants and littoral sea-shells, it is thought necessary to join Madeira to mainland, Hooker is quite right to join New Holland to New Zealand, and Aukland Isl<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> (and Raoul Is<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to N.E) and these to S. America and the Falklands, and these to Tristan d’Acunha, and these to Kerguelen Land;—thus making, either strictly at the same time, or at different periods, but all within the life of recent beings an almost circumpolar belt of land.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> So again Galapagos and Juan Fernandez must be joined to America; and if we trust to littoral sea-shells, the Galapagos must have been joined to Pacific isl<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. (2400 miles distant, as well as to America; and as Woodward seems to think all the islands in the Pacific into a magnificent continent:<ref target="#foot.f5"/> also the islands in the Southern Indian Ocean into another continent with Madagascar and Africa and perhaps India. In the N. Atlantic, Europe will stretch half way across the ocean to the Azores, and further North, right across. In short we must suppose probably, half the present ocean was land within the period of living organisms.— The globe within this period must have had a quite different aspect. Now the only way to test this, that I can see, is to consider whether the continents have undergone within this same period such wonderful permutations. In all N. and S. and central America, we have both recent and miocene (or eocene) shells, quite distinct on the opposite sides, and hence I cannot doubt that <hi rend="underline">fundamentally</hi> America has held its place since at least the miocene period. In Africa almost all the living shells are distinct on the opposite sides of the intertropical regions, short as the distance is compared to the range of marine mollusca in uninterrupted seas; hence I infer that Africa has existed since our present species were created. Even the isthmus of Suez, and the Aralo-Caspian basin have had a great antiquity. So I imagine from the Tertiary deposits, has India. In Australia the great Fauna of extinct Marsupials, shows that before the present mammals appeared, Australia was a separate continent. I do not for one second doubt that very large portions of all these continents have undergone <hi rend="underline">great</hi> changes of level within this period, but yet I conclude that fundamentally they stood as barriers in the sea, where they now stand; and therefore I should require the weightiest evidence to make me believe in such immense changes within the period of living organisms in our oceans; where, moreover from the great depths, the changes must have been vaster in a vertical sense.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Secondly</hi>. Submerge our present continents, leaving a few mountain peaks as islands, and what will the character of the islands be.— Consider that the Pyrenees, Sierra Nevada, Apennines, Alps, Carpathians are non-volcanic Etna and Caucausus, volcanic.— In Asia, Altai and Himmalaya, I believe non-volcanic.— In N. Africa the non-volcanic as I imagine alps of Abyssinia and of the Atlas: in S. Africa the Snow Mountains.— In Australia the non-volcanic Alps. In N. America, the White Mountains, Alleghanies, and Rocky Mountains, some of the latter alone I believe volcanic. In S. America to the East, the non-volcanic Silla of Caraccas and Itacolumi of Brazil, further South the S. Ventana; and in the Cordilleras, many volcanic but not all.— Now compare these peaks with the oceanic islands; as far as known all are volcanic, except S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Pauls (a strange bedevilled rock) and the Seychelles, if this latter can be called oceanic in the line of Madagascar; the Falklands only 500 miles off are only a shallow bank; New Caledonia, hardly oceanic, is another exception.— This argument has to me great weight. Compare on a Geographical<ref target="#foot.f6"/> map, islands which, we have <hi rend="underline">several</hi> reasons to suppose were connected with mainland, as Sardinia and how different it appears. Believing, as I am inclined, that continents as continents, and oceans as oceans, are of immense antiquity, I should say that if the existing oceanic islands have any relation of any kind to continents, they are forming continents; and that by the time they could form a continent the volcanos would be denuded to their cores, leaving peaks of syenite diorite or porphyry. But have we nowhere any last wreck of a continent in the midst of the ocean? S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Pauls rock and such are old battered volcanic islands, as S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Helena may be; but I think we can see some reason why we should have less evidence of sinking than of rising continents (if my view in my Coral volume has any truth in it, viz: that volcanic outbursts accompany rising areas) for during subsidence there will be no compensating agent at work,—in rising areas there will be the <hi rend="underline">additional</hi> element of out-poured volcanic matter.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Thirdly</hi>. Considering the depth of ocean, I was, before I got your letter, inclined vehemently to dispute the vast amount of subsidence, but I must strike my colours,— with respect to coral-reefs I carefully guarded against its being supposed that a continent was indicated by the groups of atolls.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> It is difficult to guess, as it seems to me, the amount of subsidence indicated by coral-reefs; but in such large areas, as the Low Arch: the Marshall Arch. and Laccadive group, it would, judging from the heights of existing oceanic archipelagoes, be odd if some peaks of from 8000 to 10,000 had not been buried.— Even after your letter a suspicion crossed me whether it would be fair to argue from subsidences in middle of greatest oceans to continents; but refreshing my memory by talking with Ramsay in regard to probable thickness in one vertical line of the Silurian and carboniferous formations,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> it seems there must have been <hi rend="underline">at least</hi> 10,000 feet of subsidence during these formations in Europe and N. America, and therefore during the continuance of nearly the same set of organic beings. But even 12,000 feet would not be enough for the Azores or for Hooker’s continent. I believe Hooker does not infer a continuous continent, but approximate groups of islands, with, if we may judge from existing continents, not <hi rend="underline">profoundly</hi> deep sea between them: but the argument from the volcanic nature of nearly every existing oceanic island tell against such supposed groups of islands,—for I presume he does not suppose a mere chain of volcanic islands belting the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Fourthly</hi>.— The supposed continental extensions do not seem to me <hi rend="underline">perfectly</hi> to account for all the phenomena of distribution on islands:—as the absence of mammals and Batrachians; the absence of certain great groups of insects on Madeira, and of Acaciæ and Banksias &amp;c in New Zealand:—the paucity of plants in some cases &amp;c.— Not that those who believe in various accidental means of dispersal can explain most of these cases; but they may at least say that these facts seem hardly compatable with former continuous land.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Finally</hi>, for these several reasons, and especially considering it certain (in which you will agree) that we are extremely ignorant of means of dispersal, I cannot avoid thinking that Forbe’s Atlantis was an ill-service to Science, as checking a close study of means of dissemination. I shall be really grateful to hear as briefly as you like, whether these arguments have <hi rend="underline">any</hi> weight with you, putting yourself in the position of an honest judge. I told Hooker I was going to write to you on this subject; and I should like him to read this; but whether he or you will think it worth time and postage remains to be proved.—</p>
<p>Yours most truly. | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.2 25] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘24’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.3 Essay] ‘E’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘e’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.5 my wrath 2.6] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.8 European] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.11 Raoul Is<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.11 America] <hi rend="italic">before del comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.12 Acunha] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘Acunda’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.12 making,] <hi rend="italic">comma added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.14 circumpolar] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap above del</hi> ‘contin’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">2.15 and if we … America; 2.16] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">2.19 perhaps] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">2.23 organisms] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">2.25 and central] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">2.26 miocene] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">2.26 eocene] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">2.27 that] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">2.27 <hi rend="italic">fundamentally</hi>] <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>‘n’ <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">2.27 America] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">2.27 miocene] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">2.28 shells] <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">2.30 in uninterrupted seas] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">2.30 since] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘since’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">2.31 the isthmus] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">2.31 the Aralo-] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25">2.32 basin] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n26">2.32 deposits,] <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n27">2.33 Fauna] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n28">2.33 Marsupials] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n29">2.36 level] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n30">2.39 organisms] <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n31">2.39 our oceans] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘one ocean’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n32">2.39 , moreover] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n33">2.40 vaster] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘faster’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n34">3.1 as] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘and’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n35">3.2 Consider that the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n36">3.3 Nevada,] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n37">3.3 are] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n38">3.4 Asia,] <hi rend="italic">comma added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n39">3.5 alps of Abyssinia] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n40">3.5 of the 3.6] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n41">3.8 alone] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n42">3.9 Silla of Caraccas] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n43">3.9 Itacolumi] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n44">3.9 S. Ventana] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n45">3.10 in] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n46">3.10 these] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘them’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n47">3.10 peaks] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n48">3.12 rock] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n49">3.13 bank;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon altered from full stop</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n50">3.13 New Caledonia, … exception. 3.14] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n51">3.17 as continents,] ‘s,’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n52">3.18 oceans,] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n53">3.19 continents,] <hi rend="italic">comma over colon</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n54">3.19 forming continents;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n55">3.20 volcanos] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n56">3.21 cores] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n57">3.21 syenite diorite] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n58">3.21 porphyry] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n59">3.25 my Coral volume] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n60">3.25 volcanic] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n61">3.25 outbursts] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n62">3.27 -poured] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n63">4.4 atolls] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n64">4.5 coral] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n65">4.6 Low Arch] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n66">4.6 Arch.] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n67">4.6 Laccadive] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n68">4.7 heights] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n69">4.11 the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n70">4.11 Silurian] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n71">4.12 carboniferous formations,] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n72">4.13 these formations] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘their for-mation’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n73">4.15 Hooker’s] <hi rend="italic">apostrophe inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n74">4.17 with,] <hi rend="italic">comma added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n75">4.17 not] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n76">4.18 nearly every] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘necessary’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n77">4.19 island] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘islands’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n78">5.3 Batrachians] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n79">5.4 Acaciæ] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n80">5.4 Banksias &amp;c] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n81">5.4 paucity] <hi rend="italic">inserted in gap</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n82">5.7 former] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘some’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n83">6.3 Atlantis] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘c’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n84">6.3 as checking] ‘as’ <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n85">6.8 proved.] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘found.’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 17 June 1856</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The remainder of the letter, except for CD’s signature, is in the hand of the copyist. CD corrected the copy and filled in many gaps left by the copyist, as well as making some additions. Only these alterations have been noted in the Manuscript alterations and comments section. CD’s draft is preserved in DAR 50 (ser. 4): 6–11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Although CD evidently intended to discuss this topic and mentioned it in the introductory paragraphs of the chapter on geographical distribution in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref> (p. 534), he did not do so until he included it in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 352–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3764.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Hooker 1853–5</ref>, 1: xxi–xxvii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5239.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Pickworth Woodward</ref> expressed this view in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Woodward 1851–6</ref>, 3: 406.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his draft (DAR 50 (ser. 4): 8), CD had written ‘geological’, but he omitted to correct the copyist’s ‘Geographical’ in the copy sent to Lyell.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>, pp. 142–8. CD had previously discussed this issue with Lyell (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-605.xml" resp="#automat">letter to Charles Lyell, [September – December 1842]</ref>). He also commented on the subsidence required by his coral reef theory in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Maclaren, [15 November – December 1842]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay’s</ref> researches in Wales had led both Lyell and CD to discuss with him the probable depth of deposits before erosion had taken place (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, [2 September 1849]</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1004.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[3 October 1846]</ref>, and to A. C. Ramsay, 10 October [1846]). CD may have met Ramsay on 18 June 1856 at a special general meeting held at the Geological Society to elect a new president following the death of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4311.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Sharpe</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>