<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6241">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. B. Innes   13 June 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1664</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6241 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6241.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6241.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Stecher (1961): 218</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 167: 16</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>167: 16</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2502.xml">Innes, J. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Milton Brodie</placeName>
                <date when="1868-06-13">13 June 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Writes about difficulties in which S. J. O. Horsman, curate at Down, has involved himself and others. Horsman has said he would resign. JBI offers to give up his interests in the living at Down.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">curate of Down</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2399">Horsman, S. J. H.</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#darwin_and_church">Darwin And The Church</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Milton Brodie | Forres</placeName>
                    <date>13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. June 1868</date>
                    <salute>Dear Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You can imagine, better than I can explain, how much I am grieved at the difficulties Horsman has got himself and others into.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It is not often the case that I take a strong dislike to a man at first sight, as I did to him, and it was with no small reluctance that I gave way to the universal judgment in his favour last August, and allowed him to stay.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> At that time he had not been licensed, and I could have got rid of him at once; but it was necessary he should be licensed if he remained, and he was so. After that I have no power over him, but by the process of reporting any failure of duty to the Archbishop,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> and requesting him to withdraw the licence.</p>
<p>The last I heard from him was from 1 Elm Court Temple, to say he was on his way to Downe; would write himself to the Archbishop and resign; (I had told him I should report him to his Grace) and requesting me to pay a quarter’s stipend due 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June to his bankers 75 Cornhill.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I understand he has not gone to Downe, and I have not paid. I understand he has not paid the Sunday School teachers since Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. last. If he has received subscriptions for the Sunday School I should of course deduct the amount due; also balance, if any, due on acc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> of the boys school;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and, if I legally could the sum due to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Humphries 32 Sackville St. for providing for services during his absence at Torquay.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The School money I should be confident about as cash received; I am not sure if M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Humphries’ is more than a private debt.</p>
<p>Can some of your family: Miss Darwin, whom I consider my Minister of Education, (non political) or M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Darwin ascertain the state of matters financial in Schools.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Then as to the future; for present emergency I have written to the Churchwardens and to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Humphries, who appears to have sent clergy men generally satisfactory, to send some one to fill the gap. I tried to get M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jones,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> who is a most able man, to take Sunday and weekly duty also for a time, but he is otherwise engaged; still I hope there may be no immediate difficulty, and permanent arrangements must be made as soon as possible. Hastened by this embarrassment, I am offering to part with all my interest in the living. It would probably have been better if I had done so long ago, but I have always had a hope that I might obtain a house for the parish, and perhaps, as I have so many kind friends about, return and end my days there.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>But the hope has vanished, and I am too old to begin to build a house in a field and plant trees I can never see grow. I hope the Parish will be better with a younger man—</p>
<p>I mentioned to you and to Sir John my probable intention of disposing of my patronage; and I have instructed my agent to offer it to Sir John &amp; you before any one else, in case you should have any friend you may wish to put in.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>With kind regards to your party Believe me | Faithfully Yours | J Brodie Innes</p>
<p>I fear the fierce blackbird of 1866 has fallen a victim to her courage as I have not seen her since. By this time she should have had grandchildren who would have made considerable progress towards being eagles. Bill and claws at any rate should have been developed<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘Organ | Sir John Lubbock | (Interest) | Bryson | <hi rend="italic">[3 or 4 words illeg]</hi>’<ref target="#foot.f12"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Innes, who was vicar of Down, refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2399.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel James O’Hara Horsman</ref>, his curate, who had been absent from his post for some time and was planning to resign it after allegations of financial irregularity (see letter from S. J. O’H. Horsman, 2 June [1868]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 1 September [1867]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15), Innes had written, ‘I hope Horsman will stay quietly, at least for the year he has promised: and that you will continue to like him—’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The archbishop of Canterbury, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Thomas Longley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See also letter from S. J. O’H. Horsman, 2 June [1868]. Seventy-five Cornhill, London, was the address of the Metropolitan Bank.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">That is, the National School for boys (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6375.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office directory of the six home counties</hi></ref> 1866).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Thirty-two Sackville Street, London, was the address of the clerical agent William Humphries. Humphries has not been further identified. The <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, July 1824, p. 10, noted the creation of the new employment of clerical agent as an intermediary in the sale of benefices.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Innes refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Mr Jones has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Innes continued as vicar of Down until 1869 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1451.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Clergy list</hi></ref>). On Innes’s career, and his difficulties in finding a suitable house in Down for himself or his replacement, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5565.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moore 1985</ref>, pp. 468–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Innes refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref>. Innes had bought the advowson of Down (that is, the right to appoint the clergyman) in about 1860 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5565.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moore 1985</ref>, p. 469).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">No letter has been found from Innes referring to a blackbird.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD’s annotations are notes for his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6242.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Innes of 15 June [1868]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>