<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3757F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From T. F. Jamieson to Charles Lyell   17 October 1862</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21001</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3757F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3757F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3757F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 10: 475–6. </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The University of Edinburgh Centre for Research Collections (Gen. 112/2859–60)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_124.xml">Edinburgh</repository>
                    <idno>Gen. 112/2859–60</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2540.xml">Jamieson, T. F.</persName>
                <placeName>Ellon, Aberdeenshire</placeName>
                <date when="1862-10-17">17 Oct 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>TFJ returns CD’s "too flattering" letter concerning Glen Roy [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">3761</hi>]. Further discussion of [A. C.] Ramsay’s, [J. D.] Hooker’s, and CL’s arguments about the formation of glacial lakes.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">3761</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Glen Roy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Ellon Aberdeen<hi rend="superscript">sh</hi>.</placeName>
                    <date>17 Oct 62</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir Charles,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I return you M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin’s too flattering letter and am glad to find that he thinks his difficulties about Glen Roy sufficiently answered.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>With regard to the lakes I think Ramsay’s idea is good altho he may push it too far.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It seems to me intelligible only on the supposition that whenever you have a glacially formed lake in a rock basin there must have been a spot of soft or more easily eroded rock otherwise how would the scooping commence.— D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker says that glaciers sometimes <hi rend="underline">raise</hi> their beds by accumulating debris underneath.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Your explanation of the larger lakes not being filled up owing to the occupation of the hollow by the ice seems to me imperfect in as much as it does not account for the original formation of the hollow—.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Your case of Zurich is very interesting.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I think Ramsay should have shown that glaciers have the immense scooping power which he requires— as that is begging a good deal of the question.</p>
<p>I should like to know also how he explains the absence of lakes in the Himmalaya seeing how large the glaciers were there.</p>
<p>Your suggestion of a subsidence occurring in part of the course of a long valley ought I think to account for some lakes. and I think lines of fracture would account for others— Ramsay’s arguments against these latter seem to me not conclusive. for altho the original yawning chasm may have been removed by denudation yet the deepseated fractures would have a tendency to gape again during fresh movements of disturbance—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>However I am very much inclined to think that a great many lakes have been formed in the way Ramsay suggests— It is difficult otherwise to account for their immense number in those northern countries which have been so much ice worn.</p>
<p>I am glad to see that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin thinks D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tyndall’s explanation of the glacial period insufficient—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> for I cannot see how it will answer for all that he supposes. Really will no astronomer come to the rescue and give us a lift with this great ice affair.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I am | My Dear Sir Charles | Your very obed. serv | Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. F. Jamieson.</p>
<p>P.S. I hope M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. King will publish his lists of Clyde &amp;c shells—giving those of each locality separate with the comparative prevalence of each species—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I have often urged M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Smith of Jordanhill to make out accurate <hi rend="underline">local</hi> lists but in vain.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>T. F. J.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had asked Lyell to forward to Jamieson his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3761.xml">letter of 14 October [1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay’s</ref> controversial theory, detailed in Ramsay 1862, that many European and American rock-basins, now containing lakes, owed their origin to glacial erosion (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3761.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 14 October [1862]</ref> and nn. 8 and 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">J. D. Hooker 1854b, 2: 121 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lyell’s letter has not been found; however, Lyell was the leading critic of Ramsay’s theory (see Davies 1969, pp. 305–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In Ramsay 1862, pp. 192–3, Ramsay argued that the absence of freshwater strata in the Alps intermediate in age between the close of the Miocene and the start of the Pleistocene glacial epoch, constituted further evidence that the Alpine lakes did not exist before the glacial epoch. Lyell had apparently told Jamieson of evidence he had collected showing that there were strata of the sort referred to by Ramsay on the shores of the lake at Zürich; Lyell cited this case as evidence against Ramsay’s theory in C. Lyell 1863a, pp. 314–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his paper, Ramsay had argued against the possibility of the great Alpine lakes being the result of structural features associated with synclines, or local subsidence, or fissures along fault lines (Ramsay 1862, pp. 188–90).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3761.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 14 October [1862]</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">This is apparently a reference to CD’s comment that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Tyndall</ref>, who was primarily a physicist, was going beyond his expertise in writing about glacial phenomena (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3761.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 14 October [1862]</ref> and n. 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The reference is probably to the geologist, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2699.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel William King</ref>, a friend of Lyell’s, who had helped him with a number of geological investigations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). Lyell had apparently sent Jamieson one of his letters from King at the end of September, in which King described a shelly deposit that had a bearing on Jamieson’s views concerning the raised beaches of Scotland and the lower level of the Scottish landmass in the recent geological past (see the letter from Jamieson to Lyell of 29 September 1862, which is in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1454.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edinburgh University</ref> Library, Gen. 112: 2853–4). No publication by King on this subject has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The Scottish geologist and antiquary, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4418.xml">James Smith of Jordanhill</ref>, had published extensively on the raised beaches of the west coast of Scotland, and especially those in the Clyde basin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>, <hi rend="italic">RSCSP</hi>). However, his catalogues of shells, published in J. Smith 1839b, pp. 89–97, were not arranged by location.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>