<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8053">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. W. Spengel   4 November 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10778</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8053 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8053.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8053.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 236</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 236</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4497.xml">Spengel, J. W.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1871-11-04">4 Nov 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends CD additions to his bibliographical list [missing].</p>
            <p>Reports observations indicating that chimpanzees show compassion.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">chimpanzees</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin, | Dorotheenstrasse 18.</placeName>
                    <date>November 4. 1871</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I beg to acknoledge receipt of your esteamed favor of August 28. and am very sorry to learn of it your indisposition and sincerely hope, you are now quite restored.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Meantimes I had the pleasure to receive from you the book by Mr Wright on Mr. Mivart’s “Genesis of Species” and present to you my best thanks for this new prove of your benevolence.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Today I am glad to send you some new additions to my list,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> most of which I took from a work by Prof. Seidlitz at Dorpat “Die Darwin’sche Theorie”, which contains a list of books and papers published on your theory. At the end of this book there is a “Tabellarische Uebersicht der Descendenztheorie”, which seems to me very good.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Specimens of it were distributed at the “Versammlung deutscher Naturforscher” at Rostock to the members of the zoological and botanical sections.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I do not know whether it is of interest to you to hear particulars about observations made on the chimpansee by the keeper and other persons in our Zoological garden at Hamburg.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> We keep two of these anthropomorphs, one of which is suffering by phthisis pulmonum<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and is lying in a melancholy state in the straw of his cage. One day the ill one got a bread, which soon the other healthy and well disposed animal took from the hands of its companion and ran away with it to the other side of the cage. The ill animal wept bitterly and blew its face with its hands, till the other came back and was breaking the bread into two halfs and returned one. When the ill monkey is coughing, the other one puts its hands on its shoulders and regards it with sympathizing looks.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Any further bibliographical news will follow as soon as I shall have collected them. Believe me, Dear Sir, | your very obedient servant | J W Spengel. | stud. med.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter to Spengel has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had arranged for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5254.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Chauncey Wright’s</ref> review of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Genesis of species</hi> (Mivart 1871a) to be published as a pamphlet (Wright 1871b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Spengel had sent CD a bibliography of works on Darwinian theory published mainly in German (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7382.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spengel 1871</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7751.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. W. Spengel, 10 May 1871</ref> and nn. 1 and 2). A copy dated 24 August 1871 with numerous additions in the author’s hand is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4282.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georg von Seidlitz’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Die Darwin’sche Theorie</hi> was a collection of lectures given at the University of Dorpat, It contained appendices on the literature of descent theory since 1859, and a table illustrating descent theories from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref> to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref> roughly in the form of a taxonomic tree (Seidlitz 1871). CD’s annotated copy of the book is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 753).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Versammlung deutscher Naturforscher</hi>: meeting of German naturalists. Spengel refers to the forty-fourth meeting of the association of German naturalists and doctors (Gesellschaft Deutscher Naturforscher und Aertze) held in Rostock in September 1871.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">On the Hamburg Zoological Garden, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6591.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reichenbach 1996</ref>. The keeper has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Phthisis pulmonum or pulmonalis: pulmonary tuberculosis.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD discussed forms of sociability and moral sensibility in the non-human primates in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 75–9.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>