<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6779">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Crichton-Browne   8 June 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17885</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6779 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6779.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6779.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 143: 328</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>143: 328</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1869-06-08">8 June 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_677.xml">Crichton-Browne, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for information about expression.</p>
            <p>Comments on JC-B’s photographs of insane people.</p> 
<p>Sends copy of Duchenne [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">6755</hi>].</p>  
<p>Asks for further information about platysma, his <hi rend="italic">bête noire</hi> for a year or two.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">insane</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1404">Duchenne, G. B. A.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down,</placeName>
                    <date>June 8, 1869</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am grateful for the extremely kind manner in which you offer me further assistance, and for the very valuable aid already given.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> And this is all the more kind, as I am well aware how much your time must be occupied with your arduous duties. The information about the hair standing on end is now quite ample.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am also glad to hear that you have seen the “grief muscles” in action, for these cannot often be observed.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But I may add that I have just had a letter from Egypt from a trustworthy observer that he has seen this expression in a negro.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I shall be particularly anxious to hear at some future time about the platysma which has been my <hi rend="underline">bête noire</hi> for a year or two.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It is indeed wonderful what aid you have already given me, and I think will give me. I may remark with respect to what you say about the neck of one of your patients (though to you the remark will probably be superfluous) that there is a muscle, the name of which I have just now forgotten, running from near the clavicle to the corners of the mouth; I see this muscle in strong action, producing prominent diverging lines on the neck of one of my sons, when he draws strongly backwards the corners of his mouth in producing certain notes on the flute.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I am very much obliged for your present of the photographs of the cretin; they are dreadful to look at.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Can the throwing back of the head be an extreme exaggeration of the attitude assumed during laughter? I have noticed the head thrown a little backwards when a person out of complaisance pretends to laugh and be amused. Sometime ago I went into several shops in London to try to buy photographs of the insane, but failed;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> so you may believe with how much interest I have carefully looked at your excellent ones, and made some notes. I do not, however, think that your kind offer of copies would be of any special use to me. They shall be returned together with Duchenne by rail; and are sent off to-day.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I have arranged the plates of D. with the text, as I think this is the most convenient plan; but you can take them out and arrange them as you like. If you have the inclination and time, I should be delighted if you would write any remarks on the plates or separately,—such as whether you thought any decidedly good or bad etc. Some French authors sneer at Duchenne, but I am inclined to think highly of this work, and Huxley tells me that he has made out much about the muscles of the hand by the aid of galvanism.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I shall not want the book returned for a couple of months and I enclose the best address for its return. On the 10th I and my family start for North Wales to stay there for about 7 weeks, as my health which is always very poor has lately been worse. My address there is C. Darwin, Caerdeon, Barmouth, N. Wales.</p>
<p>Pray believe me, my dear Sir with cordial thanks | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">June 8th, 1869</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6752.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Maudsley, 20 May 1869</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 1 June 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See n. 1, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 1 June 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The observer was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1960.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jane Loring Gray</ref> (see letter from Asa and J. L. Gray, 8 and 9 May 1869).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 1 June 1869</ref>. CD had been asking his correspondents to observe the action of the platysma myoides muscle since at least 1868 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16). He discussed the action and significance of this muscle in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 298–303.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">It is not known which of CD’s sons is referred to.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 1 June 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD was in London from 16 to 24 February 1868 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD had offered to send Crichton-Browne his copy of the ‘Atlas’ of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duchenne 1862</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6755.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to James Crichton-Browne, 22 May 1869</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 1 June 1869</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">No letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> on this subject has been found. Huxley lectured on the teleology and morphology of the hand at Glasgow in 1876, and on the hand at the Working Men’s College in 1878 (L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 456, 489–90).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>