<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5059">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Rudolf Suchsland   16 April 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10806</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5059 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5059.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5059.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 273</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 273</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4611.xml">Suchsland, G. R. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Swansea</placeName>
                <date when="1866-04-16">16 Apr 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Reports that his father has given up the idea of publishing a new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> but points out that H. B. Geinitz of Dresden has, to date, only written against CD’s theory.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4610">Suchsland, F. E.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Suchsland, G. R. E.’s father</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>25. Belle Vue Street. | Swansea.</placeName>
                    <date>16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April 1866.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Yesterday I received a letter from my father, who desires me to thank you for your very interesting communications &amp; to inform you, that under the existing circumstances, he has given up the idea of publishing a new translation of the “Origin of Species”.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Nevertheless he wishes to call your attention to the fact, that Prof. Geinitz of Dresden has until now only written against your theory.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You will find this corroborated by a letter from Dr. Rolle addressed to you, which I take the liberty to enclose.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Dr. Rolle was therefore greatly astonished to hear that Prof. Geinitz was going to superintend the publication of the new edition.</p>
<p>My father begs further to communicate to you the following literary notices, which may perhaps interest you.</p>
<p>Prof. Dr. Oscar Schmidt &amp; Prof. Franz Unger (the celebrated Botanist) have published: “The age of mankind &amp; the Paradise” two lectures, in which Darwin’s theory is highly commended. Prof Schmidt acknowledges openly, that having formerly been an adversary of this theory, he has now become a most decided follower of the same.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Prof. Ernst Hallier of Jena has published: “Darwin’s theory &amp; the Specification,” a little book full of self-praise, in which the author speaks against Bronn’s translation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Count Mariani of Florence has written a most interesting book called: “Confessions of a Metaphysician”. The first volume contains the Ontology particularly directed against Hegel; the second volume, Kosmology pays special attention to Darwin’s theory.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Hoping that I have not tired you, I remain, dear Sir, | yours | most respectfully | R. Suchsland. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Cha<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Darwin Esq. | Down.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letters have not been found. On <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4610.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Emil Suchsland’s</ref> interest in publishing a new German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Rudolf Suchsland, 2 April 1866</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, the publisher of the first and second German editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1860 and 1863), had suggested that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hans Bruno Geinitz</ref> would undertake the translation of a third German edition. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5038.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 23 March 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Friedrich Rolle, 12 April 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The reference is to Schmidt and Unger 1866, two lectures given at the University of Graz. There is a copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Unger’s lecture, ‘Steiermark zur Zeit der Braunkohlenbildung’ (Styria during the time of brown coal formation), contained a brief remark that CD’s theory was compatible with the creation of humans by ‘organic means’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 44–5). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oskar Schmidt’s</ref> lecture, ‘Das Alter der Menscheit: nach den neueren geologischen Forschungen und Darwin’s Hypothese’ (The age of mankind as determined by new geological researches and Darwin’s hypothesis), contained an afterword in which Schmidt discussed recent research by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, Carl Gegenbaur, and others that was supportive of CD’s theory. Schmidt added that he had been especially convinced by Gegenbaur’s work (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 31–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Hallier’s review, ‘Darwin’s Lehre und die Specification’, claimed that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn’s</ref> translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1863) contained many scientific errors, and gave rise to misunderstandings and ‘teleological readings’ not present in the original (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hallier 1865</ref>, pp. 61–2). There is a copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to <hi rend="italic">Confessioni di un Metafisico</hi> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Terenzio Mamiani della Rovere</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5180.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mamiani della Rovere 1865</ref>), and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</ref>. For more on Mamiani della Rovere, see Corsi and Weindling 1985, p. 720.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>