<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5011F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. J. F. Bunbury to Charles Lyell   20 February 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21278</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5011F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5011F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5011F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">F. J. Bunbury ed. 1891–3, <hi rend="italic">Later life</hi> 1: 144–7 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">F. J. Bunbury ed. 1891–3, Later life 1: 144–7</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName>Bunbury, C. F. J.</persName>
                <date when="1866-02-20">20 Feb 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses CD’s and J. D. Hooker’s letters to Lyell concerning Louis Agassiz’s theory of the glaciation of the Amazon basin in Brazil.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Barton</placeName>
                    <date>February 20th, 1866.</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Lyell,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Very many thanks for sending me Hooker’s and Darwin’s letters, which I have read with great interest.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I agree in almost everything that Hooker says, as far as I can make him out, but his letter is <hi rend="underline">very</hi> hard to read. I differ from Darwin as to the plants which he quotes, as instances of the occurrence of temperate forms on the Organ mountains; he seems to consider as a “temperate” genus every genus which is found <hi rend="underline">at all</hi> in temperate climates, and here I think him mistaken.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I think I mentioned in my former letter, that, besides the strictly tropical forms on those peaks, there are species of genera which are very widely spread, and not specially either tropical or the reverse.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Such a genus is Hypericum, one of those which Darwin enumerates; it is found in almost all parts of the world, <hi rend="underline">except</hi> very cold countries. Clematis (which he does not mention) is another instance of the same kind. Drosera and Habernaria (as Hooker points out) have certainly their maximum within the tropics.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> If there are Vacciniums on the Organ mountains, they are of the sub-genus (Gaylussacia of Humboldt), which belongs specially to South America, and of which there is a species even on the coast of Brazil, in the island of St. Catherine.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>If the Brazilian mountains were once a branch of the Andes (which I infer is Darwin’s notion) I should have expected a greater number of the peculiar characteristic forms of the Upper Andes to be found on the mountains of Minus, &amp;c., such as those “Rhododendrons of the Andes” (Befarius), of which Humboldt talks so much.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> There are some such: Gaultherias, Gaylussacias, Escallonias, &amp;c., but not so many as one would expect. The strongest case, perhaps, in favour of Darwin’s view and against mine, is the genus Drimys (the Winter Bark). Whether the American forms of Drimys be all varieties of one species, or a group of closely allied species, they certainly afford a most striking instance of a group of very near relations ranging along the Andes, from Cape Horn all through South America into Mexico, and re-appearing conspicuously on the table land of Brazil.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I do not know whether they are found anywhere <hi rend="underline">between</hi> Minas and the Andes. It is certainly quite allowable for Darwin to say, that they must have migrated to the Brazilian uplands when these were more closely connected with the Andes than they now are. Fuchsia comes nearly into the same category with Drimys, except that there is a greater variety of forms, and some of them more decidedly distinct. I doubt whether either Fuchsia or Drimys is found very high up on the Andes.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I acknowledge that, in my former letter, I did not sufficiently consider the possibility of the Organ mountains and those of Minas having been formerly much higher than now, and of their upper regions having been “<hi rend="underline">glaciated</hi>” while in that position. But after all, as Hooker says, the information in Madame Agassiz’s letter is almost too vague to afford any safe ground for fighting upon. I think the meaning <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be, that the “glacial” marks were observed <hi rend="underline">down to</hi> (not <hi rend="underline">up</hi> to) 3000 feet. This is a most material point.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I do not agree with Darwin, that the nature of the vegetation of New Zealand, gives us reason to believe that tropical families of plants could bear a cold climate. However luxuriant the vegetation of New Zealand, it does not, I think, include any really tropical types.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I am not sure, however, about Chiloe and Valdivia.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>I am very glad to hear that Darwin’s health is better.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Believe me ever your very affectionate Friend | Charles J. F. Bunbury</p>
<p>You may perhaps perceive that a certain degree of change has come over me while I have been writing this letter. I feel that I was perhaps too absolute in my first incredulity as to the possibility of glaciers on the Brazilian mountains: though I still think it quite incredible <hi rend="underline">if they had only their present elevation</hi>; and I have recollected (as I noticed above) some instances of Brazilian plants which might with some plausibility be supposed to have migrated from the Andes.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The reference is to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#automat">letter from CD to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref>, possibly also to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5007.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 15 February [1866]</ref> and, probably, to the letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> to Lyell that was mentioned in CD’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5007.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 15 February [1866]</ref>. The letter from Hooker has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For the ‘temperate’ genera mentioned by CD as occurring on the Serra dos Orgãos, Rio de Janeiro state, Brazil, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and nn. 7 and 8. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5007.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 15 February [1866]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For Bunbury’s earlier remarks on the plant species of the Serra dos Orgãos occurring elsewhere in Brazil, see the <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from C. J. F. Bunbury to Charles Lyell, 3 February 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had described <hi rend="italic">Hypericum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Habenaria</hi> as ‘temperate’ genera (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 8. <hi rend="italic">Gaylussacia</hi> is closely allied to <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lindley 1853</ref>, pp. 757–8). A single species was described in Humboldt <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1815–25, 3: 215–6. CD made a note of Bunbury’s objection that <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium</hi> plants on the Organ mountains in Brazil were not temperate species, but members of the tropical subgenus <hi rend="italic">Gaylussacia</hi> (DAR 50: E47). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 22 February [1866]</ref>, n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is apparently to the mountains of Minas Gerais, a state in eastern Brazil, to the north of Rio de Janeiro and to the east of the Andes (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>). Five species of <hi rend="italic">Befaria</hi> from the Andes are described with additional observations in Humboldt and Bonpland 1808–13, 2: 118–26. The genus is now named <hi rend="italic">Bejaria</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4982.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Luteyn 2002</ref>, p. 18).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Detailed information on the wide distribution, through South America and Mexico, of <hi rend="italic">Drimys winteri</hi>, Winter’s bark, had earlier been communicated to CD (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-723.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [12 December 1843 – 11 January 1844]</ref>). CD had observed <hi rend="italic">D. winteri</hi> growing south of latitude 55<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, that is, south of the Beagle Channel in Tierra del Fuego (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, p. 272).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Descriptions of Andean and other South American species of <hi rend="italic">Fuchsia</hi>, with information on their distribution and subspecific variation, are given in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5721.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Munz 1943</ref>. CD included a report of <hi rend="italic">Fuchsia</hi> thriving near the snowline in Tierra del Fuego in his <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, pp. 271–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD had questioned the same passage in the letter from Elizabeth Cabot Cary Agassiz, and recognised its bearing on the evidence for the former elevation or subsidence of the Amazon basin (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD had argued that types of vegetation observed close to glaciers near the New Zealand coast suggested that, under similar conditions, tropical plants could have survived a former period of global cooling (see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 25).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Chiloé and Valdivia are on the coast of southern Chile at latitude 42<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> and 40<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, respectively; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 25. CD had written of the luxuriant vegetation of Chiloé, noting that peaches could be grown ‘with care’ there, while at the more northerly Valdivia they fruited abundantly (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, pp. 268 and 271).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">In his journal entry for 20 February 1866, written after receiving from Lyell letters by Hooker and CD, Bunbury recorded his initial disagreement with some of CD’s botanical inferences, and with CD’s support for Agassiz’s claim that glaciation might have affected the Serra dos Orgãos. However, Bunbury acknowledged that CD also suggested that the South American mountains had formerly been higher (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref>). In support of CD’s argument that former glaciation might be indicated by the distribution of temperate species in the mountains of eastern and western South America (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref>), Bunbury’s journal entry acknowledged that temperate species of <hi rend="italic">Gaultheria</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gaylussacia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fuchsia</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Drimys</hi>, in particular, might have spread from the Andes to the Brazilian mountains. See F. J. Bunbury ed. 1891–3, <hi rend="italic">Later life</hi> 1: 143–4.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>