<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3642">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Alexander Wooler   5 July 1862</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11121</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3642 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3642.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3642.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">13pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 157</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 157</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5241.xml">Wooler, W. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Darlington</placeName>
                <date when="1862-07-05">5 July 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Believes, contrary to CD, that when anthers arise from petals the development of the pollen is affected by the amputation of the petal.</p>
            <p>Believes interbreeding can be used to combine desirable characters, but that, carried beyond narrow limits, it leads to deterioration of the breed.</p>
            <p>Has been experimenting on crossing polyanthus.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">polyanthus</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">degeneration</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">in-breeding</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Halliwell | Heighington | Darlington</placeName>
                    <date>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. July 62</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In reading your very interesting work on “Fertilization of orchids you will I am sure excuse me in offering an opinion contra to that which you express in reference to the oppening of flowers—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> From some experiment I made some years ago my impression is that when the anthers arise from the petals that the amputation of part of the petals effects the development of the pollen and as we well know that fertilization is followed by decay of the flower I fancy there is considerable connection between the flower &amp; the production of the pollen &amp; seed   I state this with defference as it needs much &amp; careful attention &amp;c before an opinion is stated; for we know how much we have all had to unlearn from mear fances having been stated so positively that they for a while have stoped further observations—being taken as authoritive—</p>
<p>If I am right then there would be an analogy between the vegetable &amp; animal kingdom—</p>
<p>Nature taking so much &amp; beautifll provision for the fertilization of the orchids yet seems to work vastly to no purpose when she produces so many 1000s of seeds but yet these form so extremely few plants—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This may indicate that like many other objects of nature they are in the slow progress of passing away— My notion of inter breeding is as M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jonas Webb with his sheep<ref target="#foot.f3"/> &amp; Booths &amp;c &amp;c, with the short horns<ref target="#foot.f4"/> that within certain limits when there are certain strengths of constitution &amp;c &amp;c without any defect of healthy action that inter breeding combines the strength &amp; other desired properties in the offspring but I quite think that it is a very small limit that this inter breeding can be carried without increasing some tendancy to deteriotion—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>My orange hose in hose polyanthus plant<hi rend="underline">s</hi> planted together have produced flowering seedlings this year as good hose in hose as the parent plant but of a lighter yellow colour— also the pollens fertilizing common polyanthus have produced some few good hose-in-hose the seedling varying in colour from yellow to that of the seed bearing plant— also the orange hose in hose fertilized by a large course &amp; dark polyanthus (for the purpose of marking its effect upon the progeny) has resulted in some seedlings without any appearance of hose in hose but some hose in hose one of which the calyx is as perfectly changed as the mother plant but the colour &amp; form of the flower almost precisely like the plant used as the father.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I have also some seedlings from a cowslip which I fertilized with pollen from the polyanthus &amp; altho some of the seedlings come cowslip some have come coloured but only a little enlarged in size of flower—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I had not however planted them out of the seed place &amp; therefore they not only flowered poorly but many did not do so at all</p>
<p>I met a man who has asses &amp; mules to carry coals from Potto in Yorkshire up the Cleveland Hills &amp; think he might have some knowledge of these dorsal marks with the bars across the legs of horses<ref target="#foot.f8"/>   I learnt from him that he knew a bay pony which often breeding a mule bred ponies &amp; these latter had the line along the back and the bars across the legs— I have sent a few observations to the field on this subject<ref target="#foot.f9"/> &amp; the fact appears to me to present that the variation of species may be produced by this influence—left of the male of a different species upon the female— I have many young Ducks pure Aylesbury ducks &amp; muscovy drakes but next year I intend breeding first from the aylesbury ducks &amp; muscovy drake &amp; then breeding from the same ducks with an aylsbury drake, to see if the other progeny of these ducks the products of eggs obtained after the intercourse with the muscovy vary from the pure aylesbury—and to what extent this influence may have upon the descent of these ducks</p>
<p>The recent work upon the horse by the Editor of the field<ref target="#foot.f10"/> points out that the Americal trotting breed is a pure bred English racer only the taste &amp; 〈the〉 adaptation of the Country made trotting races preferable to the galloping ones of this country &amp; therefore selection to breed for trotting was followed &amp; has produced so much a superior trotting breed<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Norfolk was well known for a certain breed of trotters &amp; this arose from that County being a great breeder of poultry for the London market which 〈it〉 was desirable to deliver fresh &amp; thus the practice of sending it up in vans 〈&amp;c〉 drawn by trotting horses begetting a want for trotters and they were thus produced</p>
<p>—The Editor of the field also in his work upon the dog gives product of the dogs bred between the Grey Hound &amp; bull dog with the descendants<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I shall I hope give more minute particulars of the results of my polyanthus in the Journal of Horticulture shortly.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I am strongly inclined to concur with you in your paper upon the fertilization of the poly〈anthus〉<ref target="#foot.f14"/> and did intend to have 〈carried〉 out some experiments this ye〈ar〉 for altho I am in wonderfully productive cowslip locality yet it is a little too high for my other objects &amp; I am looking out for an estate to build upon for myself—&amp; I am afraid I could not carefully pursue such experiments<ref target="#foot.f15"/>   In my cowslip seedlings some have come quite as cowslips altho the plant was grown in the garden &amp; may have been impregnated from pollen from the fields— This plant is strongly endowed with an idiosyncrasy which may 〈make〉 it not such a ready seeder if shaded by net— I would prefer that a plant should be obtained with a large ball just coming into flower from the Lowlands taken to a warm muck in the hills &amp; then made the object of the experiments as the cowslip grows better upon our hills but are much later in flowering &amp; so would be free from any interference from other plants growing perhaps within a radius of miles &amp; in early spring bees &amp;c are not likely to come from the warm shelter of the low lying lands to the cold &amp; windy hills—</p>
<p>I fear I tire you so beg to remain Yours truly | W Woo〈ler〉 <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">C Darwin Esq | am FRS</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘Fert &amp; seeding of Orchids | Cross fert | Petals | Pony | Aylesbury Ducks | Polyanthus [<hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ’Polyanthus‘] experiments | I have reported many   I think I sent you a copy— Beaton did not <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> my paper’<ref target="#foot.f16"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD discussed the ‘uses of the petals and sepals’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 339–43; the exact reference has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD described the vast superabundance of seed in orchid species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 344–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4990.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jonas Webb</ref> of Babraham, Cambridgeshire, was a renowned breeder of pedigree livestock. The celebrated Babraham flock of short-woolled sheep had been maintained by selective interbreeding between five families within the flock (<hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 6 July 1861, pp. 631–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_541.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Booth</ref> and his sons John and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Booth</ref> of Killerby and later Warlaby, Yorkshire were the originators of the ‘Booth’ strain of shorthorn cattle, first bred in 1790 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">One of CD’s objectives in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> had been to demonstrate that cross-fertilisation was the ‘main object’ of the contrivances by which orchids were pollinated (p. 1). He concluded the book by stating: <quote type="quote"> Nature thus tells us, in the most emphatic manner, that she abhors perpetual self-fertilisation.... For may we not infer as probable, in accordance with the belief of the vast majority of the breeders of our domestic productions, that marriage between near relations is likewise in some way injurious,—that some unknown great good is derived from the union of individuals which have been kept distinct for many generations? </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD’s earlier correspondence with Wooler about polyanthuses has not been found; however, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, p. 79 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 47). CD cited Wooler’s observations in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 365: <quote type="quote"> In the hose and hose primulæ, the calyx becomes brightly coloured and enlarged so as to resemble a corolla; and Mr. W. Wooler informs me that this peculiarity is transmitted; for he crossed a common polyanthus with one having a coloured calyx, and some of the seedlings inherited the coloured calyx during at least six generations. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Having carried out a number of crosses between polyanthuses and common cowslips (<hi rend="italic">Primula veris</hi>), CD had concluded that the former were a cultivated variety of the latter (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 23 March [1861]</ref>, this volume, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alphonse de Candolle, 17 June [1862]</ref>, n. 2, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>, p. 187 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 121).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD was seeking information on colour variation and ‘striping’ in horses for inclusion in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, letter to the <hi rend="italic">Field</hi>, [before 27 April 1861], and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 9 May [1861]</ref>. The subject is discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 55–63.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The journal, the full name of which was <hi rend="italic">The Field, the Farm, the Garden. The Country Gentleman’s Newspaper</hi>, does not appear to have published Wooler’s observations on striping in ponies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4945.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Henry Walsh</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Lupton and Walsh 1861, p. 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walsh 1859</ref>, pp. 177–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Wooler had published a notice on polyanthus in the <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener and Country Gentleman</hi> in 1860 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8489.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wooler 1860</ref>); the journal was renamed the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi> in 1861, but Wooler appears to have published nothing further on the subject.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Wooler refers to CD’s paper, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>. Wooler’s name is included on CD’s presentation list for the work (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Wooler lived at Halliwell House, Heighington, County Durham; by May 1863 he had moved to Sadberge Hall, near Darlington (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4141.xml" resp="#automat">letter from W. A. Wooler, 5 May 1863</ref>; see also <hi rend="italic">North Eastern Daily Gazette</hi>, 5 May 1891).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_345.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Donald Beaton’s</ref> name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>; no letter from Beaton on this subject has been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>