<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7268">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   6 July 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5291</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7268 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7268.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7268.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 54</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 54</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1870-07-06">6 July 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses applicability of evolutionary theory to the question of human origins.</p> 
<p>Describes revisions in 2d edition of <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi>.</p> 
            <p>His research on calcareous sponges.</p> 
<p>Mentions evolutionary content in Gegenbaur’s <hi rend="italic">Vergleichende Anatomie</hi> [2d ed. (1870)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sponges, calcareous</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Naturliche Schopfungsgeschichte</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Vergleichende Anatomie</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gegenbaur, Carl 1870</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1870</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>6 Juli 70</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Es freut micht sehr, aus Ihrem gütigen Schreiben zu sehen, dass Sie mit Ihrer Gesundheit jetzt mehr zufrieden sind und dass Sie das Manuscript Ihrer wichtigen, von allen Seiten mit Ungeduld erwarteten Buchs über den Menschen glücklich beendigt haben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich bin sehr gespannt auf dasselbe und freue mich im Voraus der reichen Belehrung, welche ich dadurch erhalten werde. In unsern deutschen Zeitschriften streiten sich schon jetzt zwei feindliche Parteien darüber, ob Sie die volle und consequente Anwendung der Descendenz Theorie auf den Menschen durchfüren werden oder nicht.</p>
<p>Herr Quatrefages<ref target="#foot.f3"/> in Paris und die andern naiven Knaben, welche kühn behauptet hatten, dass die “Darwinsche Theorie” den Menschen gar nicht berühre, werden schlecht überrascht sein, wenn sie finden, dass Charles Darwin selbst die animale Descendenz der Menschen als natürlichste und wichtigste Consequenz seiner Lehre anerkennt.</p>
<p>—Es wird mich sehr freuen, wenn Sie mit der neuen Auflage der “Natürlichen Schöpfungsgeschichte” zufrieden sind. Ich habe den ganzen Winter auf ihre Verbesserung verwendet. Im IV. Vortrag wird Sie der neue Passus über <hi rend="underline">Treviranno</hi> vielleicht interessieren.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Viele Mühe habe ich mir gegeben, die genealogische Classification wesentlich zu verbessern und ich glaube dass die Stammbäume der einzelnen Thier Classen wesentlich vervollkommnet sind. Ganz befriedigend können sie freilich niemals werden.</p>
<p>—Gegenwärtig bin ich ausschliesslich mit der Monographie der <hi rend="underline">Kalkschwämme</hi> beschäftigt, welche sehr viel Mühe und Zeit kostet.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Die kleine Thier-Gruppe ist aber sehr interessant wegen ihrer unendlicher Form-Wandelungen und der endlosen vermittelnden Übergangs-Bildungen zwischen den verschiedensten Formen. Man kann entweder 4 oder 20 oder 200 “Canal Species” von Grantien annehmen, oder auch alle Calcispongien nur als eine einzige Species betrachten.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Um die feinere Anatomie und Ontogenie der Kalkschwämme zu vollenden, werde ich im August–October an das Mittelmeer gehen, entweder nach Triest oder nach Genua. Es wird aber wohl noch ein paar Jahre dauern, bis mein Buch über die Grantien ganz fertig ist.</p>
<p>—Die “Natürl. Schöpfungsgeschichte” wird jetzt in das Russische &amp; Italianische übersetzt. Wie mir Mr. <hi rend="underline">Ray Lankester</hi> mittheilte, wird sie vielleicht auch in das Englische übersetzt.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Da ich die englische Literatur so sehr schätze, würde mich diese Ehre ganz besonders freuen.</p>
<p>—Nächsten Winter werde ich wieder einen neuen Cyclus von Vorlesungen über den “Darwinismus” halten.—</p>
<p>Über Gegenbaurs Durchführung der Descendenz Theorie in der “Vergleichenden Anatomie” werden Sie sich gewiss gefreut haben.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Meine Collegen Gegenbaur und Preyer<ref target="#foot.f9"/> senden Ihnen die respectvollsten Grüsse und ich bleibe, wie immer, mit der vorzüglichsten Verehrung, und mit den besten Wünschen für Ihr Wohlbefinden</p>
<p>Ihr getreuer | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>6 July 70</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed, dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very glad to see from your kind letter that you are now more satisfied with your health and that you have fortunately completed the manuscript of your important book on man, so eagerly awaited on all sides.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am terribly excited about it, and am looking forward already to the rich instruction that I shall derive from it. In our German newspapers two opposed camps are already quarrelling about the question whether you will carry out a full and consistent application of the theory of descent to man.</p>
<p>Mr Quatrefages<ref target="#foot.f3"/> in Paris, and the other naive fellows who have so boldly claimed that “Darwinian theory” does not apply to man, will get a nasty surprise when they find out that Charles Darwin himself acknowledges man’s descent from animals as the most natural and important consequence of his theory.</p>
<p>—I would be delighted if you are pleased with the new edition of “Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte”. I have devoted the whole winter to its improvement. In lecture IV a new passage on <hi rend="underline">Treviranus</hi> will perhaps be of interest.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have taken great pains to substantially improve the genealogical classification, and I believe that the genealogical trees of the various classes of animals are now essentially complete. Of course, they can never be wholly satisfactory.</p>
<p>—I am at the moment occupied exclusively with the monograph on <hi rend="underline">calcareous sponges</hi>, which takes a lot of effort and time.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The small animal group is, however, very interesting due to its infinite changes of form and the innumerable transitional stages among the most varied forms. One can accept 4 or 20 or 200 “canal species” of Grantia, or consider all Calcispongiae as just one single species.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In order to complete the sections on the precise anatomy and ontogeny of the calcareous sponges, I shall visit the Mediterranean between August and October, either Trieste or Genoa. Still, it will very likely take a couple of years before my book on Grantia is quite ready.</p>
<p>—The “Natürl. Schöpfungsgeschichte” is now going to be translated into Russian and Italian, and Mr. <hi rend="underline">Ray Lankester</hi> has told me that it may be translated into English.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Since I treasure English literature so very much, I would be especially pleased by this honour.</p>
<p>—Next winter I will again give a new cycle of lectures on “Darwinism”.—</p>
<p>I’m sure you were very pleased about Gegenbaur’s exposition of the theory of descent in his “Vergleichenden Anatomie”.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> My colleagues Gegenbaur and Preyer<ref target="#foot.f9"/> send their most respectful greetings and I remain, as ever, with the profoundest reverence and best wishes for your health,</p>
<p>Faithfully yours | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The reference is to <hi rend="italic">Descent.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Armand de Quatrefages.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In the second edition of <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Natural history of creation; Haeckel 1870a, pp. 83–6), Haeckel maintained that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4802.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludolph Christian Treviranus</ref> had presented a monistic interpretation of the unity of nature and argued for the genealogical connectedness of all organisms. For more on Haeckel’s monistic philosophy see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3284.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1899</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel refers to <hi rend="italic">Die Kalkschwämme: eine Monographie</hi> (Calcareous sponges: a monograph; Haeckel 1872).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Grantia</hi>, a genus of Calcispongiae (now the class Calcarea), is characterised by both radial and incurrent canals (a syconoid canal system; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bergquist 1978</ref>, p. 151), which allow the circulation of water throughout the organism.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester’s</ref> translation of Haeckel’s book, based on the German edition, appeared in 1876 (Haeckel 1876).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Haeckel refers to Carl Gegenbaur and <hi rend="italic">Grundzüge der vergleichenden Anatomie</hi> (Elements of comparative anatomy; Gegenbaur 1870). CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">William Thierry Preyer.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>