<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-534">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alexander von Humboldt<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   18 September 1839</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5151</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-534 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-534.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-534.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French) †</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 204: 181 (extracts)</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Barrett &amp; Corcos (1972): 162</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 218</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 204: 180</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 180</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2443.xml">Humboldt, F. W. H. A. von</persName>
                <placeName>Sans Souci, Potsdam</placeName>
                <date when="1839-09-18">18 Sept 1839</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Praises CD’s <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> and comments on some of CD’s observations and conclusions. Considers volcanic activity and its effect on past climate and changes in climate over time. Discusses glacial phenomena. Believes the climate of the coast of Peru is modified by cold sea-currents.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Journal of researches</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive self-criticism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">volcanoes and earthquakes</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>à Sans souci pres Potsdam</placeName>
                    <date>ce 18 Sept | 1839</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Si j’ai tardé si longtems, Monsieur, à Vous offrir l’expression de ma vive et affectueuse reconnoissance, c’est que je ne possede Votre excellent et admirable ouvrage que depuis 15 jours et que je ne voulois pas répondre à Votre lettre, arrivee deux mois plûtôt, sans pouvoir Vous dire tout ce que j’avois puisé d’instruction et de jouissance dans ce que Vous appelez si modestement le „Journal d’un Naturaliste“. Mes éternelles absences et les courses que je viens de faire avec le Roi, m’ont, sans doute empêché de recevoir plutot ce qui m’a fait un plaisir si vif, inspiré un interet si durable.</p>
<p>Vous me dites dans Votre aimable lettre que, tres jeune, ma maniere d’étudier et de peindre la nature sous la zone torride avoit pu contribuer à exciter en Vous l’ardeur et le désir des voyages lointains. D’après l’importance de Vos travaux, Monsieur, ce seroit là le plus grand succes que mes faibles travaux auroient pu obtenir. Les ouvrages ne sont bons, qu’autant qu’ils en font naitre de meilleurs. D’ailleurs, Monsieur, avec le beau nom que Vous portez, que d’inspirations, Vous pouvez puiser dans ces souvenirs de gloire scientifique et litteraire qui font le plus beau patrimoine d’une famille. Mon écrit antediluvien „sur l’irritation de la fibre nerveuse“<ref target="#foot.f2"/> proclame souvent avec quelle chaleur je tirois au poetique auteur de la <hi rend="underline">Zoonomie</hi> ; à celui qui a prouvé qu’un sentiment profond de la nature, une imagination non rêveuse, mais puissante et productive, agrandit, dans les hommes supérieurs, la Sphere des conceptions.</p>
<p>Je regrette doublement, Monsieur, que ma position et des devoirs pas toujours litteraires, me privent du bonheur d’assister a Votre célebre <hi rend="underline">reunion</hi> et de dire de bouche a Monsieur Charles Darwin, ce que j’enonce ici bien imparfaitement et dans des formes qui ne sont pas celles de son pays. Arrivé a la fin de ma carriere, jouissant sans regret avec toute la pureté de l’amour des sciences, des progres de l’intelligence et de la liberté de la gloire des tems modernes, j’exerce sur mes contemporains, non pas cette severité austere et peu bienveillante que mes propres travaux ont eprouve pendant longtems, mais ce jugement libre de prejugés nationaux qui fait sa part a la fois de la force du talent, de la solidité et de l’etendue des connaissances, de l’heureuse disposition litteraire, pour peindre ce que l’on sent et veut faire eprouver au lecteur. Sous tous les rapports, Monsieur, Vous êtes placé bien haut dans mon esprit: Vous réunissez les qualités que j’indique, Vous avez une belle carriere a parcourrir. Votre travail est remarquable par le nombre d’observations nouvelles et ingenieuses sur la distribution geographique des organisations, la physionomie des plantes, la constitution geologique du sol, les anciennes oscillations, l’influence de ce singulier climat littoral qui réunit des Cycadées, des colibris et des perroquets aux formes de Lapponie, sur cette vegetation toujours verte et humide des <hi rend="underline">paramos</hi> <ref target="#foot.f3"/> placée au niveau des mers, sur les ossemens du monde primitif, la possibilite de nourrir de grands pachydermes dans l’absence de tout luxe de vegetation, sur l’ancienne cohabitation d’animaux separés aujourd’hui par d’énormes distances, sur l’origine des Iles à coraux et la merveilleuse uniformité de leurs constructions progressives, sur les phénomenes que presentent les glaciers qui descendent vers le littoral, sur la terre congelée couverte de vegetaux, sur la cause de l’absence des forets, sur l’action des tremblements de terre et leurs rapports avec l’air ambiant …</p>
<p>Vous voyez, Monsieur, que j’aime a recapituler dans ma memoire les points principaux sur lesquels Vous avez agrandi et rectifié mes vues. Vous Vous souvenez des „Observations faites dans un voyage autour du monde“ que Forster pere a publiés d’abord apres son retour avec l’immortel Cook,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> ouvrage de <hi rend="underline">Physique generale </hi> dont on a eu le mauvais esprit de ne pas sentir alors tout le mérite. Quel progrès dans les sciences et dans celui qui en est, comme Vous, l’eloquent interprete, si l’on compare Votre „Journal“ au livre de Reinhold Forster riche en 1776, si pauvre aujourd’hui, J’ai l’habitude de me marquer les passages qui offrent le charme d’une heureuse inspiration, je les relis souvent lorsque, lassé par la triste monotonie de la vie Sociale, je tente à me refugier dans mes souvenirs de l’Orénoque, de la pente des Cordilleres de la sauvage fécondité du sol de la zone torride. Vous avez été heureusement inspiré en tracant ces belles pages <hi rend="underline">394,</hi> 540, 545, 546, <hi rend="underline">548,</hi> 590, 591, <hi rend="underline">605</hi>…</p>
<p>La fin de Votre Journal (p. 608) est l’expression de ce calme moral qui dans une ame pure et bienveillante, laisse le contact avec les classes inférieures de la societé, Il y a p 28 un trait de moeurs saisi avec une delicatesse de sentiment que j’ai du signaler. Vos reflexions sur la possibilité de l’existence, des grands Pachydermes sous un climat (lat 45–55°) non continental, mais insulaire semblable à celui de l’Amerique australe sont excellentes.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> <anchor xml:id="ann.a1" type="annotationStart"/>Elles ont pour moi d’autant plus de poids que j’ai vécu si longtems dans ces regions alpines (Paramos 1800–2200 toises de hauteur) où la th. est continuellement entre +4° et 12° Reaum.) Des formes semblables aux Palmiers, Fougeres arborescentes et Cycadées, peuvent sans doute végeter dans ces climats plus froids que temperes, J’ai moi même fait connoitre toute une tribu de <hi rend="underline">Palmiers alpins</hi> <anchor xml:id="ann.a2" type="annotationEnd"/> Le bois de palmier petrifié est beaucoup plus rare que le disent nos livres de Geognosie. C’est presque toujours du bois de Coniferes qu’on a pris pour des Palmiers. En general cependant les empreintes de la Vegetation primitive laissent quelques objections là ou nous les voyons avancer vers le pole nord. Les <hi rend="underline">Musacées</hi> et les <hi rend="underline">Graminées</hi> en <hi rend="underline">Corrientes</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/> exigent plus de chaleur que Vous pouvez leur offrir dans nos tristes climats. La chute des feuilles (organes appendiculaires) n’est indifferente qu’aux plantes dicotyledonées. Les Monocotyledonées ne peuvent pas vivre par l’axe seul. J’ai cru longtems que la vegetation primitive a eu une autre source de chaleur que celle dont jouit la vegetation actuelle. J’ai pensé que notre terre, comme toute planete, n’a recçu son climat (sa temperature) pendant longtems, non autant par sa position relative à un astre central (le Soleil), mais par son interieur. Sous toutes les latitudes la croute d’une planete s’est fendillée. La Volcanicité n’est que la reaction qu’exerce la partie fluide de l’Interieur vers la surface oxidée, endurcie, pendant le calorique par rayonnement. D’apres ces idées (et la conglobation de la matiere diffuse en planetes, aerolithes … est la cause de la chaleur centrale) le climat des tropiques a pu naître, pour quelque tems, sous toutes les zones et avec ce climat chaud un grand luxe de vegetation. Ces crevasses ouvertes ont pu contribuer, pendant longtems, à temperer l’habitation boreale des Pachydermes. Quelle chaleur ne regnoit pas en 1803, depuis 50 ans sur une lieue carrée autour des Hornitos<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Vous avez fait mention d’un phénomene tres semblable dans Votre interessante description des Galapagos p 455.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> du Volcan de Jorullo,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> là où par de petites mais nombreuses ouvertures, comme dans tous les Volcans actifs l’interieur du globe communiquoit avec l’atmosphere ambiante. A mesure que dans le monde antediluvien ces communications ont cessées et que les crevasses on été remplies par l’injection de matieres minerales (filons) ou par le soulevement lineaires des chaines de montagnes, les climats ont commencé, sous differentes latitudes, à ne devenir dependants que du seul rapport de position vis a vis le corps central calorifiant, qui est le Soleil du systeme planetaire. Une tranchée de 1800–3000 pies de profondeur creusée de Hambourg aux Alpes donneroit encore de nos jours à une grande partie de l’Allemagne un climat d’oliviers et de grenadiers. Cet état de chose dureroit aussi longtems que la faille et ses bords se seroient mis (par effort du rayonnement) en equilibre avec les couches superficielles voisines, car Fourier a prouvé théoriquement<ref target="#foot.f10"/> et mes observations dans l’interieur de mines creusses à Micuipampa (Mines de Gualgayoc) a plus de 2000 toises de hauteur le confirment, que les couches terrestres sont isothermes pres de la croute extérieure du globe malgrè les sinuosites de vallées et de montagnes.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Il me paroit impossible d’admettre et la chaleur centrale (resultat de la formation des planetes de la condensation d’une matiere nebuleuse) et les reactions (dynamiques) de l’interieur d’une planete contre sa croute, sans admettre aussi, dans le monde primitif, des modifications temporaires de climats, dependants de l’etat crevassé de leur surface.—</p>
<p>Aux considerations très curieuses que Vous avez présentés, Monsieur, dans Votre excellent ouvrage sur le melange de formes qui paraissent tropicales et polaires dans l’Amerique australe, <anchor xml:id="ann.a3" type="annotationStart"/>je puis ajouter le fait que dans la partie sudest de l’Altai on peut tuer, par les 50° de lat. à une distance de 30 lieues, le tigre royal identique avec celui dans l’ile de Ceylan, des rennes et des élans. Cet mélange primitif des formes diminue avec le tems: plus de lions en Macedoine, plus d’elephans au nord du Sahara dans l’Atlas; le tigre royal devient plus rare en Sibérie; les perroquets d’apres l’observation de M. Ehrenberg se sont retirés vers le sud en Nubie depuis le tems des Romains.<anchor xml:id="ann.a4" type="annotationEnd"/> <ref target="#foot.f12"/> C’est un phenomene bien digne d’attention. Intimement lié avec M. Agassiz je partage peu ses effrayantes theories des glaces qui periodiquement detruisent l’organisation. Il me reste aussi bien des doutes sur le transport des blocs de nos plaines baltiques sur de radeaux de glace! Il faut distinguer entre de petits! phenomenes locaux, des debacles et affaissemens de montagnes granitiques voisines, des moraines poussées par les glaciers, quelques blocs que les glaciers peuvent porter de côtes a côtes ces „streams of stones (p 254) si remarquables aussi en Asie (Taganay) dans l’Oural meridional et ces depots de blocs disposés sur de vastes surfaces et s’arrêtant loin des chaines des montagnes auxquelles on auroit voulu les attribuer. <anchor xml:id="ann.a5" type="annotationStart"/>Je conviens avec Vous que le manque des blocs dans les plaines tropicales (Llanos de Caracas, Amazone, Sahara) est remarquable, mais le nord de l’Asie est depourvu de blocs aussi. Les sillons et roches <hi rend="underline">rayées </hi> de Scandinavie se dirigent uniformement jusqu’aux côtes les plus boreales de la Norwege:<anchor xml:id="ann.a6" type="annotationEnd"/> La cause de ce phenomene si important et si nouvellement observé, sembleroit donc placée dans les mers polaires! Que de choses nous ignorons encore! Les observations sont trop incomplètes. <anchor xml:id="ann.a7" type="annotationStart"/>Combien je regrette que M. Henslow n’ait pu terminer et ne fusse que pour la determination des familles ou la proximite de quelques genres connus, l’examen de Votre curieuse collection des plants (p 460, 537, 541) La vegetation offre le caractere fondamental d’un pays<anchor xml:id="ann.a8" type="annotationEnd"/> En le traçant, même a grands traits, on donne une image qui se fixe, c’est presque de la stereotypie; les animaux offrent des caracteres mobiles. J’ai a Vous demander mille excuses, Monsieur, de la longueur de cette lettre et de l’illisibilite de mon ecriture hieroglyphique. J’ai rapporté des forets de l’Orénoque sans doute pour avoir couché plusieurs mois sur un sol de feuilles mortes et constamment humides, une grande faiblesse dans le bras droit. J’aurois voulu Vous parler encore de ce courant d’eau froide qui longe les côtes du Perou et dont je me suis tant occupé, croyant qu’il modifie beaucoup le climat du littoral (Mer a la surface, Callao novembre 60°, 2 F. quand, hors du courant d’eau froide qui devie vers l’ouest au Cap Pariña on trouve 82–85 F.). Vous aurez vu la carte du mouvement des eaux du Capitaine Duperrey qui croit qu’un fleuve d’eau froide vient du Sudouest et frappe contre les côtes du Chili lat 35° et 40° Sud, se dirigeant à la fois vers les Chonos au Sud et au nord, le long du Perou. Je voudrois bien savoir si cet appercu est conforme a Votre experience, et à celle du digne Cap. Fitzroy. Peutetre que le passage où dans le Voy. du Beagle il est question de ce courant, m’a echappé.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Toujours le froid de la mer entre les Galapagos (p 454.) est bien remarquable, cet archipel etant placé deja au nord de la ligne, où près Cap Pariña, (pres de la grande convexité de l’Amerique meridionale) le courant froid devie vers l’ouest! Entre des iles rocheuses comme sur les acores (<hi rend="underline">edges</hi>) des bancs se sont quelquefois des filets d’eau froide qui viennent de la profondeur de l’Ocean. Ce sont des courans montans ↑ comme les courans d’air descendans ↓ que l’on sent au pié des Cordilleres. Veuillez bien lire avec indulgence des lignes écrites avec tant d’abandon et agreer l’hommage de ma haute et affectueuse estime. | Alexandre Humboldt</p>
<p>J’espère pouvoir Vous offrir bientot une nouvelle edition de mes Fragmens asiatiques. C’est plutot un tout autre ouvrage refondue sous le titre d’ „<hi rend="underline">Asie centrale</hi> ou Recherches sur les Chaines de montagnes et la Climatologie comparée“.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Mon histoire de la Géographie du 15<hi rend="superscript">me</hi> siècle (<hi rend="underline">Examen critique</hi>) sera terminé avec le 5<hi rend="superscript">me</hi> Volume.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> J’ai meme, malgré mon age, le courage imprudent de travailler a une Physique du Monde, espece de Geographie physique (physische Weltbeschreibung) qui doit renfermer le Kosmos depuis les nebuleuses jusqu’à l’hysope.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Comme je veux que cela soit dans le genre de mes Ansichten der Natur,<ref target="#foot.f17"/> je l’ecris en allemand et j’aurai le chagrin de n’etre pas lu par Vous.</p>
<p>Je Vous supplie de presenter a Monsieur le Capitaine FitzRoy l’expression de ma vive reconnoissance pour les fruits de sa noble et courageuse expedition.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note target="#ann.a1" targetEnd="#ann.a2"><hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 5.18 axe] <hi rend="italic">underl</hi> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi> </note>
                <note target="#ann.a3" targetEnd="#ann.a4"><hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a5" targetEnd="#ann.a6"><hi rend="italic">scored</hi> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a7" targetEnd="#ann.a8"><hi rend="italic">scored</hi> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>at Sans souci, near Potsdam</placeName>
                    <date>18 September 1839</date>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>If I have delayed so long, Sir, in expressing to you my deep and affectionate gratitude, it is because I have had your excellent and admirable book in my possession for only a fortnight, and I did not want to answer your letter which arrived two months earlier without being able to tell you all I have learned and enjoyed in what you so modestly call ‘The Journal of a Naturalist’. My ever-recurring absences and the business I had with the King have no doubt prevented me from receiving sooner that which I enjoyed so much and which has evoked my lasting interest.</p>
<p>You told me in your kind letter that, when you were young, the manner in which I studied and depicted nature in the torrid zones contributed toward exciting in you the ardour and desire to travel in distant lands. Considering theimportance of your work, Sir, this may be the greatest success that my humble work could bring. Works are of value only if they give rise to better ones. Moreover, Sir, with the illustrious name you bear, what inspiration you can draw from the reminder of scientific and literary achievements that make up a family’s finest patrimony. My antediluvian piece ‘on the excitation of nervous fiber’<ref target="#foot.f2"/> frequently attests with what ardour I drew on the poetic author of <hi rend="underline">Zoonomia</hi>, who proved that profound affinity with nature and an imagination that was not dreamy but powerful and productive, enlarge in superior men the realm of understanding.</p>
<p>I doubly regret, Sir, that my position and duties, which are not always literary, prevent me from attending your important meeting and from expressing to Mr Charles Darwin in person what I state here so imperfectly and in a language not his own. Being at the end of my career, enjoying without regrets, with all the purity of the love of science, the progress of intelligence and of liberty, the glory of the modern age, I do not judge my contemporaries with that austere and ill-willed severity my own works suffered for so long, but with a judgment free of national prejudices, which takes into account strength of talent, solid and wide knowledge, and a felicitous literary disposition to describe what one feels and wishes to convey to the reader. On all these counts, Sir, you rank high in my estimation. You combine all the qualities I have indicated. You have an excellent future ahead of you. Your work is remarkable for the number of new and ingenious observations on the geographical distribution of organisms, the physiognomy of plants, the geological structure of the earth’s crust, the ancient oscillations, the influence of that unusual littoral climate which unites Cycads, hummingbirds, and parrots with forms found in Lapland, on the perpetually green and damp vegetation of <hi rend="underline">paramos</hi><ref target="#foot.f3"/> at sea level, on primeval bones, the possibility of feeding the great pachyderms in the absence of luxuriant vegetation, the ancient cohabitation of animals which are now separated by enormous distances, on the origin of coral islands and the marvellous uniformity of their progressive construction, on the phenomena of glaciers descending to the sea, on the frozen earth covered with plants, on the reason for the absence of forests, on the action of earthquakes and their effects on the surrounding air …</p>
<p>You see, Sir, that I like going over the principal points on which you have enlarged and corrected my views. You will remember ‘Observations made on a voyage around the world’ which the elder Forster published soon after his return with the immortal Cook,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> a book on <hi rend="underline">Physique générale</hi> which, because of poverty of spirit, was not then appreciated. What progress indeed has been made in science and in those who like you are its eloquent interpreters, when we compare your ‘Journal’ with Reinhold Forster’s book, so rich in 1776, so poor today. It is my custom to mark passages that offer the charm of a happy inspiration; I reread them often when, tired of the sad monotony of social life, I attempt to take refuge in my memories of the Orinoco, of the slopes of the Cordilleras, of the wild fecund earth of the torrid zone. You have been happily inspired in writing those beautiful pages <hi rend="underline">394</hi>, 540, 545, 546, <hi rend="underline">548</hi>, 590, 591, <hi rend="underline">605</hi>.</p>
<p>The end of your Journal (p. 608) expresses that moral calm which, in a pure and kind soul, is left by contact with the lower classes of society. On p 28 some unusual customs are painted with a delicacy of feeling that I must single out. Your thoughts on the possibility of the existence of large Pachyderms in a climate (lat. 45--55<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>) that is not continental but insular, similar to that of South America, are excellent.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> They carry the more weight with me because I lived so long in those alpine regions (Paramos 1800--2000 <hi rend="underline">toises</hi> elevation) where the temperature is continually between 4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> and 12<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Réaum. Forms similar to the Palms, Tree Ferns, and Cycads can undoubtedly vegetate in these climates which are colder than temperate. I have myself described a tribe of alpine Palms. Petrified palm wood is far rarer than our books of Geognosy say they are. It is almost always the wood of Conifers which is confused with palm wood. In general, however, we are apt to be skeptical when we find fossils of primitive vegetation close to the North Pole. <hi rend="underline">Musaceae</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Gramineae</hi> in <hi rend="underline">Corrientes</hi> <ref target="#foot.f6"/> require more warmth than our sad climates offer. The fall of leaves (appendicular organs) is inconsequential only to dicotyledons. Monocotyledons cannot survive with only an axis. I have long believed that primitive vegetation had an additional source of heat beyond that available to present-day vegetation. I have believed that our earth, like every planet, has received much of its climate (its temperature) for a long time not so much from its position relative to a central star (the sun), but from within. At every latitude there is a fissuring of the crust of a planet. Volcanicity is nothing but the reaction produced by the fluid part of the Interior, near the oxidized, hardened surface losing heat through radiation. According to these ideas (and the conglobation of diffuse matter into planets, meteorites … is the cause of the central heat) the tropical climate could exist for some time in every zone, and in this hot climate a luxuriant vegetation could develop. These open fissures could have contributed for a long time toward tempering the northern habitation of the Pachyderms. How hot it was in 1803 and for the past 50 years in a square league around the Hornitos<ref target="#foot.f7"/> You mention a very similar phenomenon in your interesting description of the Galapagos, p. 455.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> of the Jorullo<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Volcano, where through small but numerous openings, as in all active Volcanoes, the interior of the globe came in contact with the surrounding atmosphere. With time, in the antediluvian world, the contacts ceased and the crevices filled with mineral matter (veins), or by the linear elevation of mountain ranges; the climates at different latitudes began to depend only on their position with respect to the central heating body, that is the sun of our planetary system. An 1800--3000 foot deep trench dug from Hamburg to the Alps would once again today give most of Germany a climate suitable for olive and pomegranate trees. This state of affairs would continue as long as the fault and its edges (due to the strength of its radiation) remained in equilibrium with the superficial neighbouring layers, for Fourier has proven theoretically<ref target="#foot.f10"/> and my observations in the interior of mines dug at an altitude of more than 2000 <hi rend="underline">toises</hi> at Micuipampa (Gualgayoc mines) confirm, that theterrestrial layers are isothermal near the exterior crust of the earth in spite ofthe windings of valleys and mountains<ref target="#foot.f11"/> It seems to me impossible to admit both central heat (resulting from the formation of planets, and the condensation of nebular matter) and the (dynamic) reactions of the interior of the planet against its crust, without also admitting that in the primitive world temporary modifications of climate depended on the prevalence of crevices on the surface.</p>
<p>Regarding the very curious considerations that you have presented, Sir, in your excellent work on the mixture of forms which seem tropical and polar in South America, I can add the fact that in the southeast part of Altai one can kill at a 50<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> lat. within a distance of 30 leagues, the royal tiger, identical to the one found in Ceylon, reindeer and elk. This primitive mixture of forms is diminishing with time: no more lions in Macedonia, no more elephants north of the Sahara in the Atlas mountains. The royal tiger become more and more rare in Siberia. Parrots according to Mr Ehrenberg have moved south in Nubia since Roman times.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> It is a phenomenon well worth attention. Much as I agree with Mr Agassiz I do not share his frightening theories of ice that periodically destroys organised beings. I also doubt the idea that the blocks of our Baltic plains were carried on ice rafts! We have to distinguish among small! local phenomena, debacles, the subsidence of neighbouring granite mountains, moraines pushed by glaciers, a few blocks that glaciers can carry from side to side, those ‘streams of stone’ (p. 254), so remarkable in Asia (Taganay) in the southern Urals and those deposits of blocks spread over vast surfaces and terminating far from the mountains ranges to which one had wanted to attribute their origin. I agree with you that the lack of blocks in the tropical plains (Llanos de Caracas, Amazon, Sahara) is remarkable, but northern Asia is also without blocks. The furrows and grooved rocks of Scandinavia are uniformly directed to the most northern coasts of Norway. The cause of this phenomenon, so important and so recently observed, seems to be in the polar seas! Of how many things are we still ignorant! Observations are so incomplete. How much I regret that Mr Henslow could not finish examining your interesting collection (pp. 460, 537, 541) if only to determine the families or the proximity of some known genera The vegetation exhibits the fundamental character of a country. By tracing even the main features, one gives an image which will remain in one’s mind, something like a stereotype; animals offer mobile characters. I have to ask you, Sir, to excuse the length of this letter and the illegibility of my hieroglyphic handwriting. I brought back from the Orinoco forests a weakness in my right arm, doubtless from having slept many months on ground covered with dead and damp leaves. I would have liked to speak with you more about the cold water current that hugs the coast of Peru and which has so much occupied me, because I believe it greatly modifies the coastal climate (Sea surface, Callao November 60.2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> F., outside the cold current which veers westward at Cape Pariņa one finds 82–85<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> F.). You will have seen the ocean current chart of Captain Duperrey who believes that a stream of cold water flows from the southwest and strikes the coast of Chili at lat 35<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> and 40<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> South, going towards both the south and north of Chonos, along the Peruvian coast. I would like very much to know whether this view agrees with your experience and that of the worthy Cap. FitzRoy. Perhaps I missed the passage in the Voy. of the Beagle where this current is mentioned.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> In any case the cold sea between the Galapagos Islands (p. 454) is indeed remarkable, since the Archipelago lies to the north of the line where near Cape Pariņa (close to the great convex part of South America) the cold current changes its course towards the west. Between rocky islands, as on the edges of sand banks, one sometimes find rivulets of cold water coming from the ocean depth. These are ascending {up arrow} currents, like the descending {down arrow} currents of air that one feels at the foot of the Cordilleras. Please read with indulgence these lines written with so much abandon, and believe in my great and affectionate esteem. | Alexander Humboldt</p>
<p>I hope to be able to offer you very soon a new edition of my Fragmens asiatiques. It is rather an entirely different book revised under the title of “<hi rend="underline">Central Asia</hi> or researches on the mountain chains and comparative climatology”.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> My history of 15th century Geography (<hi rend="underline">Examen critique</hi>) will be finished with the 5th volume.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> I have even, in spite of my age, the imprudent courage to work at a Physical Geography of the World (physische Weltbeschreibung) which will treat of the Cosmos from the nebulae down to the hyssop.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> As I want this book to be in the same genre as my Ansichten der Natur,<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I am writing it in German and I shall have the disappointment of knowing that it will not be read by you.</p>
<p>Please give Captain FitzRoy my keen appreciation for the fruits of his noble and courageous expedition.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, Appendix I for a translation of this letter. The transcription and translation of Humboldt’s original letter, though different in some details, have benefited greatly from the version published by P. H. Barrett and A. F. Corcos (1972).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1"> </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3925.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1797</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The usual meaning is a high bleak plain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2618.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forster 1778</ref>. There is a copy in Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches,</hi> particularly pp. 293–8, in which the remains of Siberian animals, including pachyderms, are explained by the hypothesis that northern Europe and Siberia formerly bordered on a sea, which gave the region a more equable, insular climate, similar to that of the southern hemisphere.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Province of Argentina.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">‘Little ovens’, mounds of cinders and ashes around fumaroles.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The sentence beginning, ‘Vous avez’, was written in the margin, and the place for its insertion marked by an asterisk.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Jorullo volcano is located near Toluca, Mexico.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2636.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fourier 1819</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3927.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1808</ref>, 1: 324, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3939.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1849–58</ref>, 5: 41–2, describe the differences in external and internal air temperature of the mines above Micuipampa.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2271.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ehrenberg 1827</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD does not refer to it. FitzRoy makes only a passing reference to it in discussing the temperature of the sea at the Galápagos (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> 2: 505).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3934.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1843</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1836–9</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1845–62</ref>. Hysope (hyssop): an allusion to 1 Kings 4:33: ‘the hyssop that springeth from the wall’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3927.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humboldt 1808</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>