<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1136">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Henri Milne-Edwards   18 November [1847]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">66</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1136 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1136.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1136.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.66)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>66</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1847-11-18">18 Nov [1847]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3335.xml">Milne-Edwards, Henri</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Offers HM-E some specimens of <hi rend="italic">Lernaea</hi>, a crustacean parasite on <hi rend="italic">Balanus elongatus</hi>.</p>  
<p>Mentions opinion of Harry Goodsir about a form CD believes to be the larva of <hi rend="italic">Lernaea</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Balanus elongatus</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">crustacean</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Lernaea</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1915">Goodsir, H. D. S.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">larvae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I take the liberty of writing to you,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> for the <hi rend="underline">chance</hi> of some specimens which I possess, interesting you. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Goodsir<ref target="#foot.f2"/> has figured in Eding. New Phil. Journal, July 1843, (Vol. 35, p. 88) what he considers,, certainly quite erroneously, the male of the Balanus:<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have found 5 individuals of this Lernæa like strange creature within the sack, (or so called mantle) of the Balanus elongatus of the British seas.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Goodsir, also, figures, what he considers a new genus of isopodous Crust, as parasitic on his <hi rend="underline">male</hi> Balanus. I have found the same, but I believe it is the larva-form of the Lernæa: I have this imagined larva in every stage of development &amp; well preserved &amp; thousands of individuals of them. In fact the Lernæa is a great sack full of these little crustaceans larvæ, which in their early state exist as curious kidney-shaped, papillose bodies. Lastly within the same Balanus, in which 3 of the Lernæa were included, I found a little perfect or mature crustacean animal, something like the larvæ, this I suspect <hi rend="underline">may</hi> be the male of the Lernæa. If, then, my conjectures are correct (&amp; I beg to observe that I have only cursorily looked at these specimens) I have the male, female &amp; the larvæ in different states, of this singular Lernæa like animal, which is parasitic on Balanus.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I do not know whether you are now attending to Crustacea or would think these specimens worth your acceptance.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If you will look at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Goodsirs drawings you will be able to judge: they seem to me very curious.— Should you like these specimens, I could send them through M. Bailliere, the Bookseller.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Should you think them worth having, it would give me great pleasure to send them to you, to whose publications, I have long owed much pleasure &amp; instruction.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I trust anyhow that you will excuse my having troubled you with this letter &amp; I beg to remain with much respect &amp; admiration | Yours faithfully | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Not knowing your address I have directed this to the Academy of Sciences<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 creature] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘w’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.8 stage] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘fo’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.11 curious] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.12 or mature] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.5 having] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘sending’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.6 whose] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘whom’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had met Milne-Edwards at the British Association meeting in Oxford in June 1847 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henri Milne-Edwards, 1 September [1848]</ref>) and both <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> described events at which he was present (see K. M. Lyell ed. 1881, 2: 130 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. S. Owen 1894</ref>, 1: 299).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Henry D. S. (Harry) Goodsir, conservator of the Museum of the Royal College of Surgeons, Edinburgh.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2912.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Goodsir 1843</ref>, in which Goodsir described what he believed to be the male of a <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi>. Although cirripedes were generally thought to be hermaphrodites, Goodsir believed that if they were crustaceans, as <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4721.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Vaughan Thompson’s</ref> work indicated (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thompson 1830</ref>), they should, like the Crustacea, have separate sexes. Furthermore, he reasoned that the males would resemble the small, larva-like male of the Lernaea (see n. 4, below), to which group he believed the Cirripedia were most closely allied. Accordingly, when he discovered a small Lernaea-like organism parasitic within the sack of sessile cirripedes, he believed he had discovered the male of the species. In addition, Goodsir described what he took to be an isopod crustacean parasitic on the ‘male’ <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lernaea, like the Cirripedia, was a much discussed group at this time. In his series ‘Illustrations in British Zoology’ published in <hi rend="italic">Magazine of Natural History</hi> 8 (1835): 565, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Johnston</ref> wrote of this family: <quote> Of all the curious creatures which the naturalist meets with in his researches, there are none more paradoxical than the Lernææ; none which are more at variance with our notions of animal conformation, and which exhibit less of that decent proportion between a body and its members which constitutes what we choose to call symmetry or beauty.</quote> The identification of their larvae in the 1820s showed them to be Crustacea, but their place within the class remained for many years a point of debate. The male Lernaea was first described in the 1830s, presenting a stark contrast to other members of the Crustacea by being much smaller in size than the female, larva-like in appearance, and semi-permanently attached to the female. CD’s parasite was not actually Lernaea, a parasitic copepod, but an isopod now classified as <hi rend="italic">Hemioniscus balani.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">From his own observations of these organisms, CD believed that Goodsir’s ‘male’ was, in fact, a crustacean related to Lernaea and that the parasites he found on it were actually the larval stage of this crustacean. If his specimens indeed included males of this species, they would be of great interest to naturalists studying Crustacea, who frequently found it difficult to locate all these forms together.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Milne-Edwards apparently was not interested in these specimens (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henri Milne-Edwards, 1 September [1848]</ref>). CD later offered them to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana</ref>, who was at work on a monograph of the Crustacea collected by the United States Exploring Expedition (Dana 1852–3) (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1305.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Dana, 24 February [1850]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Jean Baptiste Baillière et ses fils, booksellers, had offices in both London and Paris.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Milne-Edwards was also the author of an important essay on classification (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5458.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Milne-Edwards 1844</ref>) and other works published in the <hi rend="italic">Annales des Sciences Naturelles</hi>, which CD read in December 1846 (DAR 119; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Milne-Edwards had been elected to the zoology section of the Académie des Sciences in 1838.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>