<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6474">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   25 November [1868]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5288</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6474 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6474.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6474.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) damaged</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 51</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 51</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1868-11-25">25 Nov [1868]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on experience of being a father.</p> 
<p>Discusses possible English edition of <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie</hi>. Mentions necessary revisions.</p>  
<p>Thanks CD for comment on <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses problem of assigning specific times to origin of classes.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Generelle Morphologie</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Naturliche Schopfungsgeschichte</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1866</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>25 Nov.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ich danke Ihnen herzlich für Ihren freundlichen Brief, und für die Glückwünsche zur Geburt meines ersten Jungen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Der kleine “<hi rend="underline">Walter Karl</hi>” gedeiht gut, setzt täglich eine Menge neuer Zellen an, und macht uns überhaupt schon viel Freude. Es gehört doch zum vollen und ganzen Manne, dass er auch eigene Kinder hat; und wenn auch der väterlicher Liebes-Instinkt nicht so stark ist, als der mütterliche, so nimmt er doch einen grossen Theil des Gemüthslebens in Anspruch. Auserdem ist es jedenfalls sehr interessant, auch die postembryonale “Ontogenie” der Menschen zu verfolgen, und zu sehen, wie die menschlichen “Instinkte” sich so nach und nach stufenweise entwickeln.</p>
<p>Es macht mir sehr viel Freude, dass meine “Morphologie” jetzt durch die Ray-Society in das Englische übersetzt wird, und das Sie Interesse daran nehmen. Ich habe an Huxley bereits geschrieben, dass ich Alles thun will, um das Buch möglichst zu verbessern, und dem englischen wissenschaftlichen Publicum geniessbar zu machen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ich will namentlich:</p>
<p>1.   Das Volum auf die Hälfte condensiren.</p>
<p>2.   Alle persönliche Polemik fortlassen.</p>
<p>3.   Alle Ketzereien (Heterodoxien), alle schlechten Witze und Anspielungen, und überhaupt Alles nicht streng zur Sache gehörige fortlassen.</p>
<p>So, hoffe ich, wird das Buch ein ganz anderes und wesentlich verbessertes Ansehen bekommen. Auch werde ich die griechischen Fremdwörter möglichst vereinfachen und die überflüssigen fortlassen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Das Ihnen meine Schöpfungsgeschichte im Ganzen gefällt, freut mich sehr;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Ihre Zustimmung ist immer der schönste Lohn für meine Arbeiten! Auch hier in Deutschland findet das Buch viel Beifall, viel mehr als die Morphologie.</p>
<p>Was Sie über die zu grosse Bestimmtheit in Betreff der Zeitangaben über die Entwickelung der Klassen etc. sagen, ist sehr richtig. Auch ich halte den palaeontologischen Schöpfungsbericht für höchst unvollständig. Allein, unter der aussdrücklichen Voraussetzung, das alle solche Angaben nur relativ und provisorisch sind, scheint es mir doch gut, dieselben in geschichtlichen Zusammenhang zu bringen, damit das Publicum wenigstens eine ungefähre Idee von der zeitlichen und fortschreitenden Aufeinanderfolge der Gruppen bekömmt. Freilich kann das Alles in 10 Jahren schon ganz anders aussehen! Dasselbe gilt auch von den Stammbäumen, welche nur erste provisorische Versuche sein sollen!<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>In der Hoffnung, dass Sie mit Ihrer Gesundheit zufrieden sind, und mit den ergebensten Grüssen | Ihr treuer | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>25 Nov.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed, dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I thank you cordially for your kind letter and for the congratulations on the birth of my first son.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The little “<hi rend="underline">Walter Karl</hi>” is thriving, he adds a load of new cells every day, and generally provides us with much joy. To be a full and complete man one really must have one’s own children; and while the paternal love instinct is not as strong as the maternal, it still occupies a large part of emotional life. At any rate it is very interesting to follow also the post-embryonic “ontogeny” of the human and to see how human “instincts” develop step by step.</p>
<p>I am very happy that my “Morphology” will now be translated into English by the Ray Society and that you are taking an interest in it. I have already written to Huxley that I will do everything possible to improve the book and make it readable for an English scientific audience.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In particular I will:</p>
<p>1.   Cut the size of the volume by half.</p>
<p>2  . Leave out all personal polemics.</p>
<p>3.   Leave out all heresies (heterodoxies), all bad jokes and insinuations, and in general everything that isn’t strictly to the point.</p>
<p>Thus, I hope, the book will acquire a totally different and really improved reputation. I will also simplify as far as possible the Greek words and eliminate the superfluous ones.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I am very happy that you like my history of creation.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Your approval is always the best reward for my endeavours! Here in Germany the book is also receiving much praise, much more so than the morphology.</p>
<p>What you say about the too great certainty in connection with the dates of the development of the classes etc. is very true. I also consider the palaeontological account of creation highly incomplete. Yet, given the express assumption that all such accounts are only relative and provisional, it does seem good to me to bring them into an historical context, in order that the audience at least gets a approximate idea of the temporal and progressive succession of the groups. Certainly, in 10 years it may all look very different! The same goes for the genealogies, which should only be considered a first provisional attempt!<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>In the hope that you are content with the state of your health and with the most humble greetings | your devoted | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see part II: 859–60.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 19 November 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 19 November 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref> and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 19 November 1868</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel’s use of Greek neologisms in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref> had caused CD to comment in a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5315.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Huxley of 22 December [1866]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14): <quote type="quote"> The number of new words, to a man like myself weak in his Greek, is something dreadful. He seems to have a passion for defining, I daresay very well, &amp; for coining new words. </quote> Among the more lasting neologisms are ‘ontogeny’ (Ontogenie), ‘phylogeny’ (Phylogenie), and ‘ecology’ (Œcologie; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>, 1: 53, 57, and 2: 286).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel refers to Haeckel 1868c (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 19 November 1868</ref> and n. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 19 November 1868</ref> and n. 7.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>