<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11593F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [before 7 July 1878]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21529</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11593F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11593F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11593F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 57</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 57</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1878-07-06">[before 7 July 1878]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>He has been talking to Julius von Sachs about sleeping plants that move with and without growth.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription"> 
                     
                    <p>I have been talking to Sachs about sleeping plants that move with &amp; without growth &amp; it appears he fully agrees that the cause of the movement is the same in both. He has expressed this in the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> edition of his book which you have—it is at p 852.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> He says he doesn’t agree with Pfeffer about these things—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> He thinks that the cause lies in the protoplasm which causes variations in the turgescence, &amp; that the growth along the convex side is only in consequence of the increased turgescence which precedes it. I am glad to find he doesn’t think very much of Pfeffer, that is he says he is very learned &amp; does very good work, but he doesn’t think clearly. Sachs seemed to think any work in cutting sections asleep &amp; awake would be useless, as there was no doubt about it that whether there was a joint or / not the cause was the same in principle—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I send the extract from Cieselski—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Many thanks for the splendid twisters, the beast of a Sipho wont act with hot &amp; cold water   I must try the tamus— I find <hi rend="underline">Convulvulus arvensis</hi> is most splendidly twisted.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have talked to Sachs about the oats, &amp; he thinks the best way will be to cut the tips off &amp; extract them in alcohol.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> My elasticity of wet &amp; dry wood experiments seem likely to fail, but it is worth going on at.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I can always do some microscoping if it fails quite   The Sunday Society want me to lecture, are they supposed to be done for a charity? if so I feel as if I ought to do it, but if they pay I wont, would you tell me, or send a post card addressed to me to Uncle Ras for him to write on it “paid” or “not paid”<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Yr affec | FD</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.2 it appears … things— 1.4] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.6 the growth … precedes it. 1.7] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.11 Many thanks … paid” 1.20] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, 7 [July 1878]</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The fourth edition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Botanik</hi> (Textbook of botany; Sachs 1868) was published in late 1874 (Sachs 1874). CD cited it in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 2 n., but there is no longer a copy of this edition in the Darwin Library–CUL. CD also cited the English translation (Sachs 1875), which had been made from the third German edition (Sachs 1873), with some additional material from Sachs 1874 added in notes (see Sachs 1875, Translator’s preface). Sachs claimed that the cause of change in turgescence during plant growth was the same as that which caused movement in a mature plant, the only difference being that growth-related changes resulted in a permanent change in cell volume, while those related to movement in a mature plant did not (Sachs 1874, p. 852).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3766.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wilhelm Pfeffer</ref>, a former student of Sachs, had argued that increased turgescence during growth was triggered internally (or was autonomous) while that related to movement resulted from external triggers (or was induced). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10809.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pfeffer 1877</ref>, pp. 205–7. It is unclear whether the ‘cause’ refers to the cause of the turgor or whether the cause was the turgor, which was related to both growth and movement.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had suggested that Francis compare the size of cells in the pulvinus of a leaf when awake or asleep to determine whether there was a loss in cell turgor on one side of the organ (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11577.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, 29 [June 1878]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Francis probably sent a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8188.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Theophil Ciesielski’s</ref> doctoral dissertation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1871</ref>); it was also published in <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Biologie der Pflanzen</hi> without the introductory historical review of the literature (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10454.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1872</ref>). CD’s heavily annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1871</ref> is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. CD wanted to account for the conflicting experimental results of Ciesielski and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref> (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-12131F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [22 June 1878]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Francis had received small lengths of stems from CD, including those of <hi rend="italic">Aristolochia sipho</hi> (Dutchman’s pipe) and <hi rend="italic">Tamus communis</hi> (black bryony). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11577.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, 29 [June 1878]</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Convolvulus arvensis</hi> (‘Convulvulus’ is a misspelling) is field bindweed.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD asked Francis to try to determine whether chlorophyll was present in cotyledons of oats (<hi rend="italic">Avena sativa</hi>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11570.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 26 June [1878]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Francis was attempting to determine whether the strength and elasticity of woody stems changed as they dried out (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-12131F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [22 June 1878]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The Sunday Lecture Society, founded in 1869 as a successor to the Sunday Evenings for the People, held talks on science, literature, and the arts at St George’s Hall, Langham Place, Regent Street, London; CD was a supporter of the society (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8636.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Barton 2014</ref>, p. 204). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Erasmus Alvey Darwin</ref> was probably also a supporter, as he had supported the more controversial Sunday Evenings for the People in 1866 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 191–2).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>