<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6502">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. B. Innes   14 December 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8792</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6502 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6502.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6502.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp encl</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Stecher (1961): 227</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 167: 23, 23a</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>167: 23</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2502.xml">Innes, J. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Milton Brodie</placeName>
                <date when="1868-12-14">14 Dec 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Hopes Miss [Sarah Elizabeth] Wedgwood will sell part of her land for a parsonage at Down. Recounts his futile efforts to obtain land in the past.</p>
            <p>Encloses news item about the supposed hybrid [of cow and deer].</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cow</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">deer</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_5039">Wedgwood, S. E. (b)</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Down</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">parsonage</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#darwin_and_church">Darwin And The Church</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Milton Brodie | Forres | N.B.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Dear Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In my letter of Saturday I omitted to express my hope that Miss Wedgwood will continue her offer of selling some of the land of Tromer for a site for a parsonage.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I do not know that any other is available. I am doing all in my power, both through an agent and privately to find an eligible Clergyman who will undertake to build, who may be presented to Downe, but as I observed before he cannot build in the air. Every attempt I have made in former years has been met with a refusal. The late Sir John<ref target="#foot.f2"/> said his land was tied up. Old Phillips<ref target="#foot.f3"/> was always saying he wanted to see a Parsonage, but when I said then sell me your field and I will build, he could not part with his paternal acres— Phillips Orange Court<ref target="#foot.f4"/> would not sell a bit adjoining the glebe which would have made it available. Smith could have helped me best but refused under the advice of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Abraham, who is now I dare say one of the loudest complainers—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I wrote again to Smith when old Phillips died, thinking I might prevail on him, and got back just such an answer in matter as I should have expected, not quite so as to grammar and spelling but this was accounted for by its being in a female hand.</p>
<p>So at present the only hope seems to be that Miss Wedgwood will let us have land and that some arrangement may be made to divert the footpath a little.</p>
<p>I should not be the least surprised if those who express their wish for a resident clergyman’s family should offer most strenuous opposition to lengthening by a few yards a path which they may tread once a year. I am now in communication with several Clergymen with this view, and I hope I may say that, as far as the owner is concerned, some land can be had which may be made suitable. Probably but for the vacancy in the Archbishopric I should have settled it before now by resigning, and letting the new man build or not as he pleased or could, to get rid of the sad responsibility. Waiting to consult the new Archbishop has caused a little delay, and in the mean time I try this other and better scheme.</p>
<p>I was very sorry to lose good D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Longley.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I had met him several times, and thought of him as I believe every one who knew him did. His help and advice was most valuable—</p>
<p>I do not forget that you have taken, and are taking, a great deal of trouble as a labour of love, having no responsibility but the desire to do good, and help an old friend out of a most distressing dilemma—</p>
<p>Believe me Dear Darwin | Yours Faithfully | J Brodie Innes <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>report of Forres shew— | Elgin Courant | Dec 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1868<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Among the extra stock the most attractive object was a cross, supposed to be between a deer and a common cow, shown by Mr M’Donald, Blervie, two years of age, and reared at Aitnoch, Ardclach. It is a female animal, dun in colour, without any horns, with thin legs. It is about the size of a full-grown stag, resembles very much the appearance of a hind, and, as might be expected, formed an object of great admiration—quite a novelty among cattle and sheep.</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6501.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. B. Innes, 12 December 1868</ref>. Sarah Elizabeth Wedgwood had purchased Tromer Lodge in Down village (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5792.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. B. Innes, 20 January [1868]</ref> and n. 6; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2337.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Emma Darwin</hi> (1904)</ref> 2: 218–19).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">John William Lubbock.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Waker Phillips</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">John Phillips.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Innes refers to John Smith and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6755.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Abraham Smith</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. B. Innes, 1 December 1868</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The archbishop of Canterbury, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Thomas Longley</ref>, died on 27 October 1868; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4651.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Archibald Campbell Tait</ref> became the new archbishop in February 1869 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Innes’s note was written next to the newspaper article, which was stuck to the top of the first page of the letter. See letters from J. B. Innes, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6493.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">7 December 1868</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6501.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">12 December 1868</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6497.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. B. Innes, 10 December [1868]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>