<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9651">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Thomas Meehan   22 September 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10052</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9651 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9651.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9651.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 110</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 110</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3286.xml">Meehan, Thomas</persName>
                <placeName>Gardeners’ Monthly , Germantown, Pa.</placeName>
                <date when="1874-09-22">22 Sept 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends CD his photo</p> 
<p>and a copy of his address at Hartford ["Change by gradual modification not the universal law", <hi rend="italic">Proc. Am. Assoc. Adv. Sci.</hi> (1874) pt 2: 7–12]. Does not believe his observations are unfavourable to natural selection but feels there are other factors involved in the origin of form.</p> 
            <p>Discusses further his work on colour and sex in plants; the linking of high colour and maleness.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Proc. Am. Assoc. Adv. Sci.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Hartford</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Meehan, Thomas 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">intermediate forms, gradation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>
                        <seg><hi rend="print">Office of the | Gardener’s Monthly, | $2.00 a year. Thomas Meehan, Editor.</hi></seg>
                        <seg><hi rend="print">Chas. H. Marot, Publisher.</hi> | Germantown Phil<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>.</seg>
                    </placeName>
                    <date>Sep 22 <hi rend="print">187</hi>4</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Cha<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></seg>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You wrote to me last year acknowledging the photo—of my friend Prof. Cope, and stating that my own sent to you through Mr. Rosengarten had failed to come to hand.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I had no more at that time, and only now have had a chance to have a few more taken.</p>
<p>Knowing it would interest you, I mailed a few weeks ago a copy of my address at Hartford, and also a brief newspaper report of the discussions thereon.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I think, as you will see I believe, that my good friend Prof. Gray did not apprehend the full nature of my facts, as I saw him enter the hall, when the paper had been half read through.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I think his remarks have however tended to misdirect the public press. The <hi rend="underline">Popular</hi> <hi rend="underline">Science Monthly</hi>, for instance, remarks, “on the contrary, all except the Author regarded the facts as favoring M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwins Theory of Natural Selection”.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I am sure there was nothing in my paper, nor in any subsequent remarks of mine, which warranted the “exception”. My point was that there are <hi rend="underline">other</hi> factors in the origination of form, <hi rend="underline">besides</hi>—not opposed to—Natural Selection, both acting perhaps in conjunction therewith.</p>
<p>I am still gathering facts in relation to the connection between color and sex in plants;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but my numerous occupations prevent me from working them up as rapidly as I would like. One of the prettiest facts is in <hi rend="underline">Daucus Carota</hi>. In this part of the world the umbel often has male flowers sparingly. Usually one in the center. That is the gynoecium is arrested at an early stage of its growth, and the stamens become remarkably perfectly formed. These male flowers are always highly colored.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Still in these, as in most other studies of natural phenomena, come in contradictions which make me hesitate about any positive conclusion. Thus the pistils of <hi rend="underline">Corylus Americana</hi> and I suppose others, are deeply rose tinted,—while the male catkins (all catkins?) are in a sense colorless.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I am continually impressed with the apparent fact that the world knows comparatively nothing of plants as <hi rend="underline">living beings</hi>. Most is dry Herbarium knowledge. And we are far behind you in Europe. Still we have a few ardent workers, among whom the best is possibly D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Engelmann, and I wish he would publish more. I have just a brief note from him in Colorado, where he is rusticating this Autumn, in which he tells me he has discovered remarkable behaviour in the stamens and pistils of the Gentians of that Section—the large flowered ones acting differently to the small (including <hi rend="underline">Swertias</hi>) and which has a great and interesting bearing on cross and Insect fertilization.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Forgive this gossip. “Pen in hand” is a great temptation.</p>
<p>Very truly your | Thomas Meehan</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <hi rend="italic">Corrrespondence</hi> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Thomas Meehan, 19 March [1873]</ref>. Meehan refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1066.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Drinker Cope</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6654.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph George Rosengarten</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Meehan refers to his address ‘Change by gradual modification not the universal law’ delivered to the American Association for the Advancement of Science at Hartford, Conn., on 13 August 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5358.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Meehan 1874</ref>). CD’s annotated copies of a newspaper reprint of the address and a newspaper extract reporting on the general discussion following the address are in DAR 45: 183–4. The newspapers from which the extracts were taken have not been identified. The discussion was not published in the <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the discussion following Meehan’s address, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> had argued that Meehan’s examples could be accounted for as monstrosities and the fact that the same characteristics could be produced from seed over successive generations proved nothing since some monstrosities, such as additional fingers or toes in humans, were heritable.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The anonymous note ‘New species by sudden variations’ appeared in <hi rend="italic">Popular Science Monthly</hi>, October 1874, pp. 764–5. The passage referred to by Meehan reads: ‘even Mr. Meehan himself, regarded the argument as a contribution to the theory of evolution, while all but the author were of the opinion that it was quite consistent with the principle of natural selection, and, indeed, had already been taken into the account by Mr. Darwin.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Meehan associated bright colour and variegation with what he termed the ‘male principle’. He discussed his theory and observations on this point in his letter of 3 March 1873 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21). For more on his views about colour in relation to sex, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Meehan 1869</ref> and 1870.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Daucus carota</hi> (wild carrot) has inflorescences composed of a primary umbel and secondary, tertiary, and sometimes quaternary umbels, each with several individual flowers, both hermaphrodite and male. The primary umbel has mostly hermaphrodite flowers with male flowers usually found near the centre of the umbel; the other umbels have mostly male flowers. Most flowers are white, but the central flower of the primary umbel is often a deep red or purple and is hermaphrodite. The flowers are protandrous, that is, the male parts mature before the female (Lamborn and Ollerton 2000, p. 446). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 8, CD noted that he obtained a seed from artificially fertilising the central purple flower.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Corylus americana</hi> (the American hazelnut) has separate male and female flowers with both types present on the same tree.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1510.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Engelmann</ref> had described several species of gentian of the Rocky Mountain region (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. Engelmann 1863</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Swertia</hi> (felwort) is a genus in the family Gentianaceae. Many species formerly identified within this genus are now placed in the related genus <hi rend="italic">Frasera</hi> (elkweed). Meehan probably refers to the section <hi rend="italic">Crossopetalum</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gentianella</hi> of the genus <hi rend="italic">Gentiana</hi> (now the genus <hi rend="italic">Gentianopsis</hi>); Engelmann had described a new species, <hi rend="italic">G. barbellata</hi> (the perennial fringed gentian), in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. Engelmann 1863</ref>, p. 216. Engelmann later noted, having observed living plants, that the versatile anthers changed position as the flower developed; they were pointing inwards, became horizontal and shed pollen when the flower opened, then turned over backwards on the filament with the empty cells directed outward (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. Engelmann 1878</ref>, p. 193 n.).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>