<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6685">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. D. Hooker to Emma Darwin   29 March 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">4635</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6685 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6685.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6685.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 152: 457</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 103: 12–13; Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Directors’ Correspondence 188: 141–2)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>103: 12–13</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <collection>Directors’ Correspondence</collection>
                    <idno>188: 141–2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Kew</placeName>
                <date when="1869-03-29">29 Mar 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Darwin, Emma</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Pleased to come on 17th.</p> 
<p>Is arranging the <hi rend="italic">Aucuba</hi> experiment.</p> 
            <p>Sends some letters for CD’s perusal.</p> 
<p>Asks what CD thinks of Huxley’s address [<hi rend="italic">Q. J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</hi> 25 (1869): xxviii–liii].</p>  
<p>Would be glad to have <hi rend="italic">Drosophyllum</hi> plants.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Aucuba</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Drosophyllum</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Q. J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Huxley, T. H. 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">inviting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Royal Gardens Kew</hi></placeName>
                    <date>March 29 /69.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Mrs Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I shall be delighted to come on the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; I hope by that time to have recovered my heart; which Miss Symonds took away with her on Saturday.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Please tell Mr Darwin that I am arranging for the <hi rend="underline">Aucuba</hi> experiments; with all precautions.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I send a letter of Mr. I. A. Henrys, with message for C.D. &amp; a very interesting one of Sir H. Barklys, marking in both the passages in pencil—as I know he is bored beyond endurance with correspondence.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Frances sends her love   she is very busy, preparing for Russia with me—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>You do not mention Henrietta— we are most anxious to hear how she is.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>If Mr Darwin can write please let him tell me what he thinks of Huxley’s address.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I think it <hi rend="underline">very</hi> clever.</p>
<p>Ever Sincerely Yrs | Jos D Hooker</p>
<p>I should be extremely glad of Drosophyllum plants— We have had seeds &amp; seedlings (raised ourselves) &amp; live plants, which I have had tried in 3 different places &amp; by as many persons, but all died.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="enclosure" subtype="letter">
    <opener>
        <placeName><hi rend="print">Redit, Mauritius</hi></placeName>
        <date>13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feby 1869</date>
        <salute>My dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker,</salute>
    </opener>
    <div type="transcription">
        <p>I am in your debt for two letters dated 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. The former enclosed one from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Baker<ref target="#foot.f8"/> about ferns, which I defer answering till next Mail, by which time I hope to hear again from him about our Bourbon &amp; Madagascan discoveries.</p>
            <p>He rather puzzles us, by finally referring Lady Barkly's Hymenophyllum H. emersum to H. tenellum (as representative of Jacquin's old Adiantum tenellum,) for this latter was identified by your Father in the Sp. Filicum with the H. ricciæfolium which figures in Bojer's Hortus Mauritianus, and is described as like H. Polyanthos a Fern for which M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Baker gives Mauritius credit in the Synopsis.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
        <p>Query does the Kew Herbarium contain specimens of both H. tenellum &amp; H. polyanthos from this Island?</p>
        <p>What complicates the matter is that Bojer gives H. tenellum (of Don) as a synonym of our widely different H. gracile.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
        <p>I will not take up your time with more ferny talk, but I must mention that our friend M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Higginson, the daughter of the former Governor of that name,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> and who has been the companion of many of our explorations and has added to the List of Mauritius Ferns Goniopteris pectifera, &amp; Pellæa <hi rend="italic">[</hi>annluni<hi rend="italic">]</hi> &amp;c, —goes home by this Mail, &amp; will probably find her way in due course to Kew, very full of the subject. She takes with her Plants of the terrestrial Orchid which D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meller fancied might be ‘Dryopeia cordata’, but which you thought new.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> It has flowered with her, and is clearly not the Plant described in Lindley<ref target="#foot.f13"/> as it has 8 to 10 large greenish flowers on its erect stem.</p>
        <p>I had no opportunity of examining the structure of the Flowers on the Pollen, but if it flowers with me I will do so. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Higginson has a drawing of the Plant in flower, which will probably enable you to judge if it be new. I have not received any letter from Meller since he left this, but I heard that he has written to me by sailing Ship, and I heard from D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> V. Mueller<ref target="#foot.f14"/> by the Mail that he had been at Melbourne &amp; gone on to Sydney.</p>
        <p>Horne<ref target="#foot.f15"/> as you remark is very competent to replace him in the case of the Botanic Gardens, and he is superintending our Sugar Cane Experiments to my entire satisfaction.</p>
        <p>With regard to his explanation of the Islets on the Coasts, rumour says that Horne was not bold enough to land at the chief of them—Isle Ronde, a very dangerous matter from the surf, even in calmer conditions, &amp; that his companion young Duncan alone got on shore.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
        <p>The Island however has been lately visited by another Party in which was included the American Consul Colonel Pike, who like most Yankees knows something of everything, &amp; who has written a very interesting Paper on its Geology, with a description of its Fauna &amp; Flora, which is to be read at the next meeting of our Local Royal Society, &amp; of which I will send you a copy.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
        <p>There can be no doubt that this little rock lying but a few Miles from Mauritius offers some of the strangest problems as to the distribution of Plants and Animals that can be met with. It has not only its peculiar Pandanus—as you say—which by the bye has been christened at Rotterdam P. Vandermeerschii—after one of our Surveyors here who has sent many Plants to Holland,— but it has its peculiar Palm the Jubæa spectabilis of Duncans catalogue a name I presume derived from Kew.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
        <p>Another a Latania glaucophylla is found on others of these Islands &amp; I believe in Bourbon, whilst it has also Areca alba in common with Mauritius.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
        <p>As regards its Zoology— Colonel Pike proved that the tradition of its having Snakes (which are unknown here as in most volcanic Islands) is true, by bringing back one in Spirits of the genus <hi rend="italic">[</hi>Heteræum<hi rend="italic">]</hi> about 2 foot long and 2 inches round, &amp; he also captured several large lizards quite unknown here.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
        <p>Having at a little distance the appearance of other great Island Cones about a Mile in diameter at the base &amp; 1000 feet in height to the apex, it has generally been deemed from the days of Bory<ref target="#foot.f21"/> &amp; downwards a Volcano, but Colonel Pike describes it as consisting of beds of friable Sandstone upheaved at angles of inclination more and more acute all round the axis of the Cone from the base to the summit.</p>
        <p>He certainly has given me specimens of red Sandstone.</p>
        <p>Is it not allowable to suppose that Round Island therefore is the remnant of a much more ancient Island or Continent which once existed where Mauritius is now situated and of which traces are to be found in the Casts of the stems of Submarine forests found by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ayres in Gabriel Island &amp; by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles in the Islands off Grand Port.<ref target="#foot.f22"/> If so how many hints in the chain of animal &amp; vegetable existence may not have perished in the Volcanic eruptions which produced the Mascarene groups!  I have just had an opportunity of reading D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wrights letter to the Principal of his University about the Seychelles, &amp; must own I am a good deal disappointed.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> He was I see to publish the first part of his Flora of the groups in November, &amp; I must order it to be sent to me.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> I presume he is competent for the task, but I hope he will be fair to those who have gone before him. I see he makes great capital out of his discovery of Nepenthes Wardii; but surely its existence was well known to your father &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Newton certainly took it to Kew in flower before D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wright set foot at Mahé.<ref target="#foot.f25"/>Thanks for your hint about the Tropical African Flora. I have applied to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Layard for copies.<ref target="#foot.f26"/> Many thanks also for completing Lady Barkly's set of the Synopsis Filicum which she will highly value.<ref target="#foot.f27"/> I hope you will be able to make your expedition to Russia and return in renovated health to your post.<ref target="#foot.f28"/></p>
        <p>Very truly Yours | Henry Barkly
        </p>
    </div>
</div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Hooker refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2355.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hyacinth Symonds</ref>, whom Hooker had met earlier in the year (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [25 January 1869]</ref>). According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242), Hooker visited on 25 April 1869, but no visit is recorded for 17 April.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6666.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 17 March [1869]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Hooker refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_115.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isaac Anderson</ref>-Henry and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_282.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Barkly</ref>. The letter from Anderson-Henry has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frances Harriet Hooker</ref> was preparing for Hooker’s trip to Russia for the International Horticultural Exhibition at St Petersburg (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6655.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 11 March 1869</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref> had been ill for a couple of weeks (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6647.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 8 March [1869]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Hooker refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley’s</ref> presidential address to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref> on 19 February 1869 (T. H. Huxley 1869c).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had received plants of <hi rend="italic">Drosophyllum lusitanicum</hi> from Portugal (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6666.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 17 March [1869]</ref> and nn. 5 and 6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_249.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Gilbert Baker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Hymenophyllum emersum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">H. ricciaefolium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Adiantum tenellum</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">H. tenellum.</hi> <hi rend="italic">H. polyanthos</hi> is the smooth filmy fern. Barkly also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6918.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wenzel Bojer</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bojer 1837</ref>, p. 411, to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Jackson Hooker</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3825.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. J. Hooker 1846–64</ref>, 1: 107–8, and to W. J. Hooker and Baker 1868, p. 60.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bojer 1837</ref>, p. 411. <hi rend="italic">Hymenophyllum gracile</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">H. inaequale.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Barkly refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Higginson</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5910.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Macaulay Higginson</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The names <hi rend="italic">Goniopteris pectifera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pellaea annuli</hi> were evidently not published. <hi rend="italic">Goniopteris</hi> is a genus in the family Thelypteridaceae, marsh ferns; <hi rend="italic">Pellaea</hi> is the genus of cliff-brake in the family Pteridaceae, maidenhair ferns. The orchid described by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles James Meller</ref> as <hi rend="italic">Dryopeia cordata</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Disperis cordata</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dryopria discolor</hi> is a synonym).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Barkly refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4762.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lindley 1830–40</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3441.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferdinand von Mueller</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5947.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Horne</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Barkly refers to Round Island and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5569.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. W. Duncan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Nicolas Pike’s paper ‘Geology, fauna and flora of Round Island, Mauritius’ appeared in <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Society of Arts and Sciences of Mauritius</hi> n.s. 4 (1870): 11–22.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Barkly refers to the screwpine species, <hi rend="italic">Pandanus vandermeeschii</hi>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8645.xml">Jacob van der Meersch</ref> was a Dutch governor of Mauritius. <hi rend="italic">Jubaea spectabilis</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">J. chilensis</hi>, the Chilean wine palm. Barkly also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5570.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Duncan’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of plants in the Royal Botanic Garden, Mauritius</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2196.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duncan 1863</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_364.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Barkly 1870</ref>, pp. 94–5 for his discussion of the misuse of the name <hi rend="italic">J. spectabilis</hi> for a species of Round Island palm).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><hi rend="italic">Latania glaucophylla</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">L. loddigesii</hi>, the blue latan palm. <hi rend="italic">Areca alba</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Dictosperma album</hi>, the hurricane palm.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Barkly may intend <hi rend="italic">Herpetodryas</hi>, a snake genus he mentioned in his paper, ‘Notes on the flora and fauna of Round Island’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_364.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Barkly 1870</ref>, p. 98). The two snakes found on Round Island are <hi rend="italic">Casarea dussumieri</hi>, the Round Island keel-scaled boa, and <hi rend="italic">Bolyeria multocarinata</hi>, the Round Island burrowing boa; they are now in their own family, Bolyeriidae (Mauritius snakes). Round Island has some endemic gecko and skink species, the largest of which are <hi rend="italic">Phelsuma guentheri</hi>, Gunther’s gecko, and <hi rend="italic">Leiolopisma telfairii</hi>, Telfair’s skink.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_550.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jean Baptiste Georges Marie Bory de Saint-Vincent</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">For some observations by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5672.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Burnard Ayres</ref> on the geology of Gabriel Island, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_265.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ayres 1860</ref>. Mr Charles has not been identified. Grand Port is an area in the south-east part of the island of Mauritius near the city of Mahebourg.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">Barkly refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5255.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Perceval Wright</ref>, who was professor of botany at Trinity College, Dublin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">Wright’s paper, ‘Contributions towards a knowledge of the flora of the Seychelles’ was read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4105.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Irish Academy</ref> in December 1868 (Wright 1868).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25"><hi rend="italic">Nepenthes wardii</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">N. pervillei</hi>, the name it was originally given in 1852 (see <hi rend="italic">Museum Botanicum Lugduno</hi> 2 (1852): 10). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3518.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Newton</ref> was colonial secretary of Mauritius. Mahé is the largest island of the Seychelles.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">The first volume of <hi rend="italic">Flora of tropical Africa</hi> had been published in 1868 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oliver 1868–77</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edgar Leopold Layard</ref> was the curator of the South African Museum.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">Barkly refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5968.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anne Maria Barkly</ref> and to <hi rend="italic">Synopsis filicum</hi> (W. J. Hooker and Baker 1868) which updated the earlier five volume work, <hi rend="italic">Species filicum</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3825.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. J. Hooker 1846–64</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28">Hooker visited Russia in May 1869 to attend the International Horticultural Exhibition at St. Petersburg (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6655.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 11 March 1869</ref> and n. 4).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>