<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8213F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. G. Nathorst   [after August 1872]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21262</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8213F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8213F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8213F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">CUL, DAR Pamphlet Collection G779</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>Pam G779</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_6423.xml">Nathorst, A. G.</persName>
                <date notBefore="1872-09-02" notAfter="1882-12-31">[after Aug 1872]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the research for his paper on Arctic plant beds in the freshwater aquifers of Scania (Nathorst 1872).</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>This paper is only my narrative to the Royal Academy of Stockholm of my researches in Skåne 1871 without any conclusions drawn from them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have had no time neither to this nor to determine all the species I have found in Sweden. I believe that their number will be about 30 and I also have some seeds and mosses. These later I believe will also give a number of about 30 species. Most of them are living now in whole Scandinavia as well as on Spitsbergen, but some are arctic species, for example Hypnum ochraceum.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> For my researches in Denmark Germany and Switzerland as well as in England I will as soon as possible give an account in an English journal.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I think that Professor Steenstrup soon will—if he not already has—publish our researches in Denmark.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I cannot <hi rend="underline">publish</hi> anything of my researches in Europe this summer before I have given my narrative to the Royal Academy of Stockholm, but I will here mention that I in the peatmasses of Mecklenburg found Betula nana in the lowest strata. In Bavaria I also found it in a peatmass 8 feet deep and on this peatmass it once had grown.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I found it namely in a stratum that with exception of some single leaves of Betula alba<ref target="#foot.f7"/> contained only the leaves of this plant. And I also found the boughs of it in great multitude with the leaves at their sides. What is the most interesting is that one could follow this stratum as far as one wished. It had evidently once grown in great multitude on this peatmass without leaving place for a single Salix.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The other leaves I found here were of Andromeda polifolia, Oxycoccus palustris and Myrtillus ugilinosa.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> It was on the lowland in Bavaria southerst from Munich.—</p>
<p>On the lowland of Switzerland I found the arctic (alpine) plants under circumstances not different from them in Sweden or Denmark. It was between Zurich and Lac Constance under a peatmass. The peat itself contained upperit leaves and fruit of Quercus, and underit Pinus silvestris.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> In the clay I found upperit Betula alba with some single leaves of Betula nana. Lower this was more common with a great number of Salices and Dryas, and on the greatest depth I also found Salix reticulata and S. polaris (according to the determination of Heer, but I think it worth of further examination).<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Also a single leaf of Azalea and Polygonum viviparum,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> with some dubious fragments. I ought perhaps to remark that the little hills around the peatmass in Switzerland, where once Dryas etc had grown were now planted with grasses.—</p>
<p>At Bovey Tracey in Devonshire I found Betula nana very common on a new locality, which also contained leaves of Betula alba, three different Salices Calluna, Potamageton, seeds.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Most interesting was that I here also found three flowers of Arctostaphylos Uva Ursi—<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the reference to Nathorst’s research in Mecklenburg, which was carried out in the summer of 1872 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5792.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathorst 1873</ref>, p. 227).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Nathorst’s paper on Arctic plant beds in the freshwater aquifers of Scania appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Öfversigt af Kongl. Vetenskaps-Akademiens Förhandlingar</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathorst 1872</ref>). It was communicated to the Swedish <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Academy</ref> on 14 February 1872.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Hypnum ochraceum</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Hygrohyphum ochraceum</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Nathorst’s paper on post-glacial Arctic plants appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Botany</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5792.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathorst 1873</ref>). His findings were based on research carried out between 1870 and the summer of 1872.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4541.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Japetus Steenstrup</ref> did not publish on Danish Arctic plant beds, but Nathorst discussed their findings in a later article (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5793.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathorst 1892</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Nathorst discovered leaves of <hi rend="italic">Betula nana</hi> (dwarf birch) near Oertzenhof in Mecklenburg and at Kolbermoor in southern Bavaria (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5793.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathorst 1892</ref>, p. 274).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Betula alba</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">B. pubescens</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">pubescens</hi>) is the white birch.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Salix</hi> is the genus of willows.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Andromeda polifolia</hi> is bog-rosemary; <hi rend="italic">Oxycoccus palustris</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium oxycoccos</hi>) is the small cranberry; <hi rend="italic">Myrtillus uliginosa</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium uliginosum</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">uliginosum</hi>) is the bog bilberry.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Quercus</hi> is the genus of oaks; <hi rend="italic">Pinus sylvestris</hi> is the Scots pine (‘silvestris’ was a misspelling). Nathorst evidently refers to the uppermost (‘upperit’) and undermost (‘underit’) layers of peat.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Dryas</hi> is a genus of dwarf herbaceous plants of the rose family. <hi rend="italic">Salix reticulata</hi> is the net-leaved willow; <hi rend="italic">S. polaris</hi> is the polar willow. Nathorst refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2199.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oswald Heer</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Polygonum viviparum</hi> is alpine bistort.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> is a monospecific genus of heather. <hi rend="italic">Potamogeton</hi> is the genus of pondweed.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><hi rend="italic">Arctostaphylos uva-ursi</hi> is bearberry.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>