<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2048F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Bernard Peirce Brent   7 February [1857]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21238</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2048F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2048F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2048F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Richard Brent (private collection)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_574.xml">Brent, Richard (private collection)</repository>
                        <collection/>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <date when="1857-02-07">7 Feb [1857]</date>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_608.xml">Brent, B. P.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sympathises with Brent’s legal difficulties. Declines offer of a cock silk fowl, but accepts offer of a German old fashioned pouter pigeon.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Feb. 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am extremely sorry not to hear better news of your affairs— Your case is a <hi rend="underline">most</hi> cruel one: it seems extra hard that you sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. not have even your ancient Family relics.— I most sincerely hope that your London Lawyers may see daylight without ruinous expence.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Very many thanks for the offer of the Cock, but as I have a Hen, &amp; as the Bird is not quite full-grown, I think it is not worth sending. If ever you have occasion to write, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. like to hear whether these silk Fowls can fly as well as other Fowls.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Do not trouble yourself at present to send the C. Gardeners.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I certainly sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be <hi rend="underline">extremely</hi> glad of a German old fashioned Pouter: by a strange coincidence I was writing to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Tegetmeier this morning, &amp; had asked him to apply to Carstang for one; but I have struck out the passage.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> If you will be so kind as to enquire, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be very much obliged, &amp; Hammond could send the Bird by enclosed address; sending the Bird alive in a Basket between 12 &amp; 1 on Thursday to the Nags Head. He c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. send account to me direct.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I suppose it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be best to specify that I would give only a few shillings for it. Will Hammond tell you truly whether it is a really a common German or Dutch Pouter?—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I am ashamed to ask you in the midst of all your troubles to attend to these trifles; &amp; I am sure that it is uncommonly kind of you to think at all about me &amp; my work under your circumstances. It is more, I fear, than I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. do if placed as you are.</p>
<p>I am beginning to write my Book on Variation; but it will take me some two years to complete.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Let me repeat again my wishes for your success, &amp; believe me | My dear Sir | Yours sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.1 as the Bird] ‘as’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.1 be <hi rend="italic">extremely</hi>] ‘be’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.3 I have] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">4.4 Bird by] ‘Bird’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.5 on Thursday] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.8 really] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 6 February [1857]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6); see n. 5, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Files concerning Brent’s lawsuit in Chancery are available at the National Archives (TNA: C 15/359/B255, cause no. 1857 B255 (Brent v Boyton) and TNA: C 15/360/B287, cause no. 1857 B287 (Brent v Briggs)). See also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4607.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. P. Brent, 2 September 1864</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Brent provided information to CD on poultry, and had also given him specimens (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1815.xml" resp="#automat">letter to W. D. Fox, 3 January [1856]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1844.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 20 March [1856]</ref>). See <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 270 for CD’s interest in the flight of silk fowls.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Brent was a regular contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For CD’s request to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Bernhard Tegetmeier</ref> for German pouter pigeons, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 6 February [1857]</ref>; the passage of the letter that CD struck out is in Manuscript alterations and comments. CD also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5339.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Castang</ref>, a game dealer, who is listed in CD’s Address book (Down House MS) under ‘Pigeons’, at Ship Tavern Passage, Leadenhall Market, an area of London associated with meat and poultry markets; see also <hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi> 1861.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Hammond is listed under ‘Pigeons’ as ‘dealer’ in CD’s Address book (Down House MS), at 37 Kent Street, Borough; however, Hammond is not listed in the <hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi> and has not been further identified. The address that CD enclosed was probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4447.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Snow</ref>, Nag’s Head Inn, 102 Borough High Street, Southwark. Snow was the Down carrier who made weekly trips to and from the Nag’s Head public house, in south London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2662.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Freeman 1978</ref>). No mention of the purchase of a pouter pigeon about this time has been found in CD’s Account books (Down House MS).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had previously ordered some German pouter pigeons but was not satisfied that they had been purely bred (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 11 February [1857]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD had begun writing his species book, or what he sometimes called his ‘Book on Variation’, in 1856, but he interrupted his work in 1858 to write an abstract of it, <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vols. 6 and 7, Appendix II). The first two chapters of the species book became <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>, and the remaining chapters were published posthumously as <hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi>, p. 1).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>