<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6051">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. D. Walsh   25 March 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16046</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6051 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6051.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6051.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp † encl 4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 82: A90–1; A117–18, DAR 85: B65</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>82: A90–1, A117–8</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>85: B65</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4944.xml">Walsh, B. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Rock Island, Ill.</placeName>
                <date when="1868-03-25">25 Mar 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sexual preference in insects;</p>
            <p>structures for seizing females;</p>
            <p>coloration.</p>
            <p>Doubts whether CD can make much of a case from insects in support of sexual selection.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex differences</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">The Practical Entomologist, | Editor’s Office, | Rock Island, Ill.,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>March 25 <hi rend="print">186</hi>8</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas— Darwin Esq.</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I should have answered your letters of Feb. 14 &amp; 17 sooner,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> but for bad health &amp; being busy seeing my “Report” through the Press. I expect my copies of it tomorrow or next day, when I shall do myself the pleasure of sending you one.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>After rummaging through my Journals &amp; my entire Collection of Insects, I find but very little indeed that will answer your purpose. Such as it is, however, I enclose it. I always distrust my memory in such matters.</p>
<p>I do not believe that with Insects there is anything deserving the name of “attachment” or “love”. The ♂ seeks the ♀ for copulation, &amp; so soon as that process is accomplished, the partnership is dissolved. Even with some of the social Hymenoptera, (the Honey-bees) the ♂♂ are killed off as soon as their services can be dispensed with; &amp; with the rest of them they die off. The only exception that I have heard of—&amp; I must say that I am rather skeptical about it—is in the genus <hi rend="underline">Tomicus</hi> (<hi rend="underline">Scolytidæ</hi> in Coleoptera), where European authors say that the sexes unite in boring galleries under the bark, which are afterwards stocked with eggs by the females.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I do not doubt the fact of the males boring these galleries, but I believe that they do it simply for food. Our Apple-twig Borer (<hi rend="underline">Bostrichus bicaudatus</hi>, Say)</p> 
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width50">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6051_1.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
<p rend="left">bores the pith of apple-twigs <hi rend="underline">exclusively</hi> for food, no eggs being laid therein by ♀; &amp; ♂♀ occur promiscuously, a single individual in a single boring, which is always commenced just above a bud.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I doubt if there be any use for “the strange horns in ♂ Lamellicorns”, any more than for the tuft on the breast of ♂ Turkey, which you have referred to.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In the <hi rend="underline">Æschna</hi> family, there are earlets (“oreillettes”) one on each side of the basal abdomenal ♂ joint</p> 
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width10">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6051_2.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
<p rend="left">(especially in the genus <hi rend="underline">Gomphus</hi>,) which seem to be equally destitute of use.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> At least I can conceive no possible use for them. <hi rend="underline">Gomphus</hi> is characterized by the eyes being almost as wide apart as in <hi rend="underline">Agrion</hi>, &amp; by the coloration being always black &amp; yellow. <hi rend="underline">G. vulgatissimus</hi> is an English species. In this group the tip of abdomen is clavate. The sexual distinctions in this genus are by no means conspicuous.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have enumerated such as occur in the species which have been described by me. The ♂♂ are by no means more brilliantly colored than ♀ ♀.</p>
<p>Westwood (<hi rend="underline">Introd</hi>. II, p. 206) notices the fact of the male <hi rend="underline">Ammophila</hi> (<hi rend="underline">Sphegidæ</hi>, Hymenoptera) “being exceedingly ardent during their amours, seizing their partners round the neck with their sickle-shaped jaws”. I have noticed the same thing myself a hundred times. He also notices (p. 205) that the jaws ♀ are used in burrowing.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> This is a case of the jaws being used for two distinct purposes; &amp; in this genus jaws ♂♀ are alike or very nearly so.</p>
<p>I must confess I was surprised, on looking through my collection, to find so few <hi rend="underline">conspicuous</hi> colorational distinctions in the sexes. Of course there are plenty of such distinctions which are of an <hi rend="underline">inconspicuous</hi> character; but these you did not want.</p>
<p>On the whole, I doubt whether you can make out much in support of “Sexual Selection” from what we see with our eyes of Insects. I have little doubt that the principle is found or rather exists there; but it will perhaps always be hidden from us by the wide difference in our organs of perception. We may reason by analogy from the eye of a bird or even of a fish to that of a man; but we can scarcely do so from what is conventionally called the eye of an Insect to our own eyes.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Yours ever very truly, | Benj. D. Walsh</p>
<p>P.S. The questions about “Expression” are altogether out of my line. We have no Red Indians here.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>When not otherwise specified in the enclosed paper, the sexes are equal in numbers, so far as I know.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Order Neuroptera—Agrionidæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>1. <hi rend="underline">Calopteryx maculata</hi> has black wings ♂ ♀, ♂ deep opaque black, ♀ semitransparent smoky black. The ♀ (but not ♂) has a very conspicuous white “pterostigma” (as it is called) at the tip of each wing<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
              <figure rend="blockCentred width25">
                  <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6051_3.jpg"/>
              </figure> 
<p>2. In the very extensive N.A. genus <hi rend="underline">Hetærina</hi>, ♂ (not ♀) has a beautiful carmine-red (or in some species brown) spot at the base of the wing. I enclose a ♂ specimen of <hi rend="underline">H. tricolor</hi> Burm. (=<hi rend="underline">rupamnensis</hi> Walsh), that you may see it for yourself. The males much the more numerous.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Neuroptera—Æschnidæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>1. In <hi rend="underline">Æschna clepsydra</hi> Say &amp; <hi rend="underline">A. constricta</hi> Say (two very closely allied species) the ground-color of ♂ abdomen is sky-blue, that of ♀ abdomen is pale grass-green.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> The difference is obvious, when they are on the wing.</p>
<p>2. In <hi rend="underline">Anax junius</hi> <ref target="#foot.f16"/> ♂ the ground color of the basal parts of the abdomen is a most vivid ultramarine blue, in ♀ grass-green; in ♂ ♀ towards the tip of abdomen the ground-color becomes a dull pale lilac or purple. When on the wing, the coloring ♂ is very conspicuous.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Neuroptera—Libellulidæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>1. In <hi rend="underline">Plathemis 3-maculata</hi> Degeer<ref target="#foot.f18"/> the dark spots on the wings ♂ ♀ (both front &amp; hind wings) differ, as per margin, the rest of wing being hyaline. There is never any the least hyaline spot at the tip of ♀ wing.</p> 
              <figure rend="blockCentred width33">
                  <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6051_4.jpg"/>
              </figure>                
<p>2. Both in the above species, in <hi rend="underline">Libellula luctuosa</hi> Burm., in <hi rend="underline">Mesothemis simplicicollis</hi> Say, &amp; in <hi rend="underline">Mes. longipennis</hi> Burm. the body of the <hi rend="underline">mature</hi> ♂ becomes overspread with an external secretion of a milky-blue color on different parts of it, so as to be very conspicuous, especially in <hi rend="underline">Pl. 3-maculata</hi>. Technically, this is known as “pruinescence!” &amp; occurs also in some <hi rend="underline">Agrion</hi> ♂ when mature.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> The immature ♂ differs in coloration in no respect from ♀ in all these insects.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Neuroptera—Psocidæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>About the enormous preponderance of ♀ ♀ in certain European <hi rend="underline">Psocas</hi>, see Hagen in <hi rend="underline">Proc. Ent. Soc. Phil.,</hi> Oct. 1863, p. 168. (My Paper.)<ref target="#foot.f21"/></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Neuroptera—Sialidæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f22"/></p>
<p>In reference to the prehensile jaws of the <hi rend="underline">Lucanidæ</hi>, which by the way I do not doubt may be used for pugnacious as well as amatory purposes, I have the following remarks in N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 10 Vol. II of the <hi rend="underline">Practical Entomologist</hi>, p. 107<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p> 
              <figure rend="blockCentred width33">
                  <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6051_5.jpg"/>
              </figure> 
<p>“We find another such case in a gigantic Fly with 4 gray wings, common near large rivers, (<hi rend="underline">Corydalis cornutus</hi>, Linn.),<ref target="#foot.f24"/> where the jaws of the male are lengthened into the shape of the finger of a grain-cradle, evidently to enable him to embrace the soft body of the female; for, as jaws to bite or gnaw with, they are absolutely useless. In this instance, although the jaws, both of the perfect female fly &amp; of the larva are armed with strong horny teeth, yet the jaws of the perfect male fly are quite smooth. The reason is evident. If they were armed with sharp prongs &amp; teeth, they would penetrate the soft body of the female fly, &amp; thus defeat the purpose for which nature constructed them. The Horn-bugs, on the contrary, are, as is well known, enveloped in a strong coat of mail; &amp; here we find the prehensile jaws of the male armed with sharp prongs &amp; teeth, &amp; curved in such a manner as to give the best possible grip on the slippery shelly body of the female”.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Orthoptera—Phasmidæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f25"/></p>
<p>The only conspicuous colorational distinction that I notice in this Order is <hi rend="underline">Spectrum (diapheromera) femoratum</hi> Say;<ref target="#foot.f26"/> where ♂ is of a polished, shining brownish-yellow color, &amp; ♀ of a dull, opaque, cinerous-brown color, when mature, but when immature ♂ ♀ are green.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Coleoptera—Crioceridæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f27"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Orsodacna atra</hi> Ahrens is black, legs &amp; all; <hi rend="underline">O. ruficollis</hi> Newman differs in having a rufous thorax. The former is the ♂, the latter the ♀, of one &amp; the same species, &amp; I have found them repeatedly <hi rend="underline">in coitu</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f28"/></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Coleoptera—Cryptocephalidæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f29"/></p>
<p>In <hi rend="underline">Anomoia laticlavis</hi> Forster, the ♂ has the anterior legs greatly elongated, &amp; the tips of the front tibiæ crooked inwards, doubtless for sexual purposes.<ref target="#foot.f30"/></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Hymenoptera—Cynipidæ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f31"/></p>
<p>Almost Universally, so far as I know, in the <hi rend="underline">gall-making</hi>, species of <hi rend="underline">Cynips</hi> the ♀ ♀ are <hi rend="underline">at least</hi> 4 or 5 times as numerous as ♂ ♂; &amp; in certain species there appear to be no ♂ ♂ at all, at least in ordinary seasons. So in the allied genus <hi rend="underline">Rhodites</hi>, making <hi rend="underline">galls</hi> on the Rose.<ref target="#foot.f32"/> In certain species the ♂ ♂ are very rare indeed. On the other hand, in the <hi rend="underline">inquilinous</hi> Gall-flies, the sexes are about equal.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Hymenoptera—Tenthredinidæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f33"/></p>
<p>Curtis says “It generally happens that the female saw-flies are much less abundant than the other sex, &amp; this is believed to be the case with the Turnip-sawfly (<hi rend="underline">Athalia spinarum</hi>), the males being as 6 to 1 when they have been bred; but it has been exactly the reverse in those I have caught in the fields, for out of 15 specimens there were only 3 males”. (<hi rend="underline">Farm Insects</hi>, pp. 45–6)<ref target="#foot.f34"/> Probably it was a little late in the season; for it is a very general rule with Insects that ♂ comes out 2 or 3 days, or even 2 or 3 weeks, before ♀. Edwards<ref target="#foot.f35"/> finds this to be so with almost all Butterflies; &amp; I have noticed it in many of the orders. For example, June 7 &amp; 8 I bred 86 ♂ of a gall-making Gallfly, <hi rend="underline">Cynips q. operator</hi> O.S.,<ref target="#foot.f36"/> without a single ♀ among them; June 9 85 ♂, &amp; only 4 ♀; June 10, out of 54 counted promiscuously, 52 were ♀. Sometimes (&amp; I think generally with us) in the Sawflies the ♀ ♀ are the most numerous. Of <hi rend="underline">Pristiphora grossulariæ</hi> Walsh (the N.A. gooseberry sawfly) I bred 4 ♂, 49 ♀; &amp; of <hi rend="underline">Cræsus latitarsus</hi> Norton I bred about 4 times as many ♀ as ♂<ref target="#foot.f37"/></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Hymenoptera—Uroceridæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f38"/></p>
<p>In <hi rend="underline">Tremex columba</hi> Linn. the ♀ is much brighter-colored than ♂, having abdomen very variably banded with yellow, while ♂ has brown or piceous abdomen.—<ref target="#foot.f39"/></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Diptera—Cecidomyidæ.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f40"/></p>
<p>In the gall-making <hi rend="underline">Cecidomyia</hi> the ♀ ♀ are about 4 times as numerous as ♂ ♂. The discrepancy is especially remarkable in my <hi rend="underline">Cec. s. batatas</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f41"/> of which I bred hundreds of ♀ to 1 ♂. In the inquilinous <hi rend="underline">Cecidomyia</hi>, there seems to be little difference in numbers.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Lepidoptera—the Butterflies.</hi></p>
<p>Throughout <hi rend="underline">Papilio</hi>, the ♂ ♂ are 4 times (about) as numerous as ♀ ♀. In many species the ♀ is hard to get. This is what Edwards says; &amp; he has large experience, receiving many collections from all quarters, &amp; collecting himself extensively. In <hi rend="underline">Papilio Turnus</hi> the ♂ ♂ are certainly <hi rend="underline">at least</hi> 4 times as numerous as ♀ ♀; we have only 4 species of the genus here.<ref target="#foot.f42"/></p>
<p>In <hi rend="underline">Pieris protodice</hi> the ♂ ♂ are remarkably less marked with black than ♀ ♀; so that, when I began collecting, I took them for distinct species.<ref target="#foot.f43"/> So far as I recollect, the same law prevails with your English species. In <hi rend="underline">Parnassius smintheus</hi> (the only species of the genus I have) the same thing holds good.<ref target="#foot.f44"/> Almost any one at first sight would take the ♀ for a different species.— In <hi rend="underline">Hipparchia nephele</hi> (color brown) the ♂ is always several shades darker than ♀, so that I at first thought them distinct species.—<ref target="#foot.f45"/> In <hi rend="underline">Nathalis iole</hi>, ♀ has a good deal more black than ♂ on upper face of hind wing, &amp; in ♂, there is a singular oval white spot (B) enclosed in the black band on the upper face of the hind wing, so as to be generally concealed by the overlap of the front wing, which is not found in ♀.<ref target="#foot.f46"/> On the other hand, in <hi rend="underline">Colias philodice</hi>, <hi rend="underline">C. eurytheme</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline">C. cæsonia</hi>, ♂ has more black in both wings above than ♀; &amp; I believe it is the same in your European species, <hi rend="underline">Edusa</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">hyale</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f47"/> In <hi rend="underline">Danais archippus</hi> ♂ has a singular black spot (A) by the side of one of the veins of the hind wing, which is not found in ♀.<ref target="#foot.f48"/></p> 
              <figure rend="blockCentred width33">
                  <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6051_6.jpg"/>
              </figure> 
<p>In <hi rend="underline">Thecla falacer</hi>? Bdv. &amp; Lec. the ♂ has an oval spot of a paler brown color &amp; shining, on the middle of the subcosta above, which is absent in ♀.— In <hi rend="underline">Thecla poeas?</hi> Hübn., one sex (I think ♀) is mostly bright blue above, the other brown.—<ref target="#foot.f49"/> In <hi rend="underline">Polyommatus neglectus</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">P. pseudargiolus</hi>, ♂ wings are blue immaculate above, ♀ broadly edged with black except behind.<ref target="#foot.f50"/> In <hi rend="underline">P. comyntas</hi> Godt., <hi rend="underline">P. lygdamas</hi> Doubl., <hi rend="underline">P. heteronea</hi> Bdv., &amp; <hi rend="underline">P. acmon</hi> Doubl., ♂ wings are blue above, ♀ brown (more or less tinged with blue) or reddish brown.—<ref target="#foot.f51"/> <hi rend="underline">Argynnis Diana</hi>, you know all about the coloration; as to the numbers of the sexes, I think that Edwards found them about equal.<ref target="#foot.f52"/> At all events, he told me nothing to the contrary.</p>
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Lepidoptera–the Moths</hi>.</p>
<p>In <hi rend="underline">Cossus robiniæ</hi> <ref target="#foot.f53"/> the top half of the hind wing is orange not uniform dull gray as in ♀.— In <hi rend="underline">Ægeria exitiosa</hi> <ref target="#foot.f54"/> Say. ♀ there is a broad orange band on middle of the steel-blue abdomen not found in ♂; but ♂ front wing is mostly hyaline &amp; that of ♀ steel-blue opaque.— In <hi rend="underline">Saturnia io</hi> ground-color of ♂ wings is bright ochre-yellow, instead of reddish brown as in ♀.—<ref target="#foot.f55"/> In <hi rend="underline">Acontia</hi> (2 species) a genus of Tineidæ,<ref target="#foot.f56"/> ♀ has a good deal more black than ♂.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I should … bud. 3.00] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 I doubt … ♀♀. 4.10] ‘Neuroptera’ <hi rend="italic">added blue crayon</hi>; <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi>; ‘not used’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.3 there are … &amp; yellow. 4.00] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Westwood … nearly so. 5.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi>; ‘Hymenoptera’ <hi rend="italic">added blue ink</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 On the whole, … here. 9.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>10.1 When … I know. 10.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure:</hi></note>
                <note>1.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Order</hi> … Paper.) 11.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>1.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Agrionidæ</hi>] ‘&amp; no of sexes’ <hi rend="italic">added after blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 <hi rend="italic">Hetærina</hi>] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.3 The … numerous. 3.4] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">underl and circled red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.2 sky-blue] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.2 pale grass-green] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 most … blue, 6.2] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.2 grass-green] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Neuroptera—Libellulidæ</hi>] ‘Colours’ <hi rend="italic">added and circled blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>9.3 milky-blue … parts] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>9.3 so as … conspicuous 9.4] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>11.1 About … Paper.)] 11.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>12.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Neuroptera—Sialidæ</hi> … green. 16.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>17.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Coleoptera—Crioceridæ</hi>] ‘Colour’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>19.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Coleoptera—Cryptocephalidæ</hi>] ‘Colour’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>20.1 In <hi rend="italic">Anomoia</hi> … purposes. 20.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>21.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Hymenoptera—Cynipidæ</hi>] ‘Colour’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>22.1 Almost … equal. 22.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>22.1 Almost … ♀ as ♂ 24.13] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>25.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Hymenoptera—Uroceridæ</hi>] ‘<hi rend="doubleUnderline">Hymenoptera</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>26.1 In … abdomen.— 26.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>27.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Diptera—Cecidomyidæ</hi>] ‘Colour’ <hi rend="italic">added and circled blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>28.1 In … numbers. 28.4] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>30.1 Throughout … here. 30.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>31.1 In <hi rend="italic">Pieris protodice</hi> … than ♂. 34.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of enclosure</hi>: ‘When not specified sexes equal.—’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Letters to B. D. Walsh, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5876.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">14 February 1868</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5883.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">17 February [1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Walsh refers to his <hi rend="italic">First annual report on the noxious insects of Illinois</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8157.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">B. D. Walsh 1868</ref>). CD’s lightly annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection, CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Walsh refers to the bark beetles (genus <hi rend="italic">Tomicus</hi>, subfamily Scolytinae). For more on mating systems in <hi rend="italic">Tomicus</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4386.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kirkendall 1983</ref>, pp. 302, 306.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Bostrichus bicaudatus</hi>, the apple-twig borer, is now <hi rend="italic">Amphicerus bicaudatus</hi> (family Bostrichidae).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 293, CD mentioned the presence of a tuft of hair on the breast of male turkeys.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The genus name <hi rend="italic">Aeschna</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Aeshna</hi> (family Aeshnidae, darners) while <hi rend="italic">Gomphus</hi> is a genus in the family Gomphidae, clubtails; both belong to the suborder Anisoptera, dragonflies. The earlets that Walsh refers to are now known as auricles, found on either side of the second abdominal segment in males of some families of Anisoptera. It is now thought that the purpose of the auricles is to guide the female’s abdomen into the optimal position for copulation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Silsby 2001</ref>, p. 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Agrion</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Calopteryx</hi>, a genus of demoiselle damselfly (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5548.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Montgomery 1954</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Gomphus vulgatissimus</hi>, the club-tailed dragonfly, occurs locally in southern England and Wales (see S. Brooks ed. 1997, p. 118). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 362, CD cited Walsh for information on colour differences between the sexes in dragonflies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The quotation is from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Obadiah Westwood’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the modern classification of insects</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8305.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Westwood 1839–40</ref>, 2: 206). The passage is scored in CD’s copy; similarly CD underlined the passage about jaws being used for burrowing (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8305.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Westwood 1839–40</ref>, 2: 205). <hi rend="italic">Ammophila</hi> is a genus of sand wasp of the family Sphegidae (now Sphecidae). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 342 and n. 5, CD quoted the passage from Westwood and cited Walsh for calling it to his attention.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Walsh is probably alluding to the compound insect eye, which is composed of anything from a few to several thousand facets.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD had evidently enclosed a copy of his queries about expression in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5876.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Walsh of 14 February 1868</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix V).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Agrionidae is a synonym of Calopterygidae, the family of broad-winged damselflies. The family now belongs to the order Odonata (dragonflies and damselflies), suborder Zygoptera. The order Neuroptera is now restricted to lacewings and their kin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Calopteryx maculata</hi> is the ebony jewelwing damselfly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><hi rend="italic">Hetaerina</hi> is the genus of rubyspot damselflies. <hi rend="italic">Hetaerina tricolor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">H. rupamnensis</hi> (as described in B. D. Walsh 1863a, pp. 230–3) are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">H. titia</hi>, the smoky rubyspot damselfly (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2728.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Garrison 1990</ref>, p. 227). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 362, CD mentioned the carmine spot in <hi rend="italic">Hetaerina</hi> males.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Aeschnidae is a synonym of the family name Aeshnidae (see n. 6, above).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><hi rend="italic">Aeschna clepsydra</hi>, the mottled darner, is now <hi rend="italic">Aeshna clepsydra.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Aeshna constricta</hi> is the lance-tipped darner.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><hi rend="italic">Anax junius</hi> is the green darner.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">The dragonfly family Libellulidae (common skimmers), is now in the order Odonata, suborder Anisoptera.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><hi rend="italic">Plathemis trimaculata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Libellula lydia</hi>, the common whitetail dragonfly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><hi rend="italic">Libellula luctuosa</hi> is the widow skimmer dragonfly; <hi rend="italic">Mesothemis simplicicollis</hi>, the eastern pondhawk dragonfly (now <hi rend="italic">Erythemis simplicicollis</hi>); <hi rend="italic">M. longipennis</hi>, the blue dasher dragonfly (now <hi rend="italic">Pachydiplax longipennis</hi>). On <hi rend="italic">Agrion</hi>, see n. 7, above. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 363, CD mentions the differences in appearance caused by pruinescence but does not use the technical term, which is first recorded in print in 1890 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">The family Psocidae is now in the order Psocoptera, bark lice.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">Walsh refers to the paper, ‘Observations on certain N.A. Neuroptera, by H. Hagen’ (B. D. Walsh 1863a). The paper consists of Walsh’s translation of observations by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann August Hagen</ref>, along with some new species descriptions by Walsh himself. CD scored the passage on the preponderance of females in his copy of the article (Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">The family Sialidae (alderflies) is now in the order Megaloptera (alderflies, dobsonflies, fishflies).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">The passage quoted is from the ‘Answers to correspondents’ section of <hi rend="italic">Practical Entomologist</hi> 2 (1867): 107; Walsh, the magazine’s editor, wrote all the replies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24"><hi rend="italic">Corydalus cornutus</hi> is the dobsonfly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">The family Phasmidae (now Phasmatidae, walking sticks) is now in the order Phasmida. The order Orthoptera is now restricted to crickets, grasshoppers, katydids, and locusts.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26"><hi rend="italic">Spectrum femoratum</hi>, the walking stick, is now <hi rend="italic">Diapheromera femorata</hi>, the northern walking stick. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 361, CD quoted Walsh’s description of the colour differences in the sexes of <hi rend="italic">S. femoratum.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">The family Crioceridae is now the subfamily Criocerinae of the family Chrysomelidae, leaf beetles, in the order Coleoptera.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28"><hi rend="italic">Orsodacna atra</hi> and <hi rend="italic">O. ruficollis</hi> are now both <hi rend="italic">Orsodacne atra</hi> (subfamily Orsodacninae, family Chrysomelidae). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 368 n. 58, CD cited Walsh on colour differences in the sexes of <hi rend="italic">O. atra.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f29">The family <hi rend="italic">Cryptocephalidae</hi> is now the subfamily <hi rend="italic">Cryptocephalinae</hi> in the family Chrysomelidae, leaf beetles, in the order Coleoptera.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f30">Walsh evidently refers to <hi rend="italic">Anomoea laticlavia</hi>, the clay-coloured leaf beetle. It is now placed in the subfamily Clytrinae, family Chrysomelidae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f31">Cynipidae is the family of gall wasps.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f32"><hi rend="italic">Rhodites</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Diplolepis</hi>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 314, CD cited Walsh on the proportion of sexes in Cynipidae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f33">Tenthredinidae is the family of saw-flies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f34">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Curtis</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1699.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Curtis 1860</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 314, CD cited the information from Curtis. <hi rend="italic">Athalia spinarum</hi>, the turnip saw-fly, is now <hi rend="italic">A. rosae.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f35"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Edwards</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f36"><hi rend="italic">Cynips quercus operator</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Callirhytis operator</hi>, the pip gall wasp.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f37"><hi rend="italic">Pristiphora grossulariae</hi> (described as a new species by Walsh in <hi rend="italic">Practical Entomologist</hi> 1 (1866): 123–4) is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. appendiculata</hi>, the tenthredid wasp. <hi rend="italic">Croesus latitarsus</hi> is the dusky birch saw-fly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f38">The family Uroceridae, horntail wasps, is now Siricidae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f39"><hi rend="italic">Tremex columba</hi> is the pigeon tremex. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 365, CD refers to the species as <hi rend="italic">T. columbae</hi> (family Siricidae) and cites Walsh on colour differences in the sexes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f40">The family Cecidomyidae is now Cecidomyiidae, gall midges.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f41">Walsh refers to <hi rend="italic">Cecidomyia salicisbatatas</hi>, the willow potatogall midge, now <hi rend="italic">Rabdophaga salicisbatatas.</hi> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 314, CD cites Walsh on the proportion of sexes in gall-making Cecidomyiidae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f42"><hi rend="italic">Papilio turnus</hi>, the tiger swallowtail, is now <hi rend="italic">P. glaucus</hi>; in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 309–10, CD cited Edwards on the proportion of the sexes in <hi rend="italic">Papilio</hi> and mentioned Walsh’s observations on the numbers in <hi rend="italic">P. turnus.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f43"><hi rend="italic">Pieris protodice</hi>, the checkered white butterfly, is now <hi rend="italic">Pontia protodice.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f44"><hi rend="italic">Parnassius smintheus</hi> is the Rocky Mountain parnassian.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f45"><hi rend="italic">Hipparchia nephele</hi>, the clouded wood nymph, is now a subspecies of <hi rend="italic">Cercyonis pegala</hi>, the common wood nymph. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 387, CD noted that English meadow-browns (‘Hipparchiæ’; on the use of ‘Hipparchia’ as a general term for satyrid species, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2339.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emmet 1991</ref>, p. 30) had similarly coloured sexes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f46"><hi rend="italic">Nathalis iole</hi> is the dainty sulphur butterfly.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f47"><hi rend="italic">Colias philodice</hi> is the clouded sulphur; <hi rend="italic">C. eurytheme</hi>, the orange sulphur; <hi rend="italic">C. caesonia</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">C. cesonia</hi>), the southern dogface; <hi rend="italic">C. edusa</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">C. croceus</hi>), the clouded yellow; and <hi rend="italic">C. hyale</hi>, the pale clouded yellow.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f48"><hi rend="italic">Danais archippus</hi>, the monarch butterfly, is now <hi rend="italic">Danaus plexippus.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f49"><hi rend="italic">Thecla falacer</hi> is now a subspecies of <hi rend="italic">Satyrium calanus</hi>, the banded hairstreak. <hi rend="italic">Thecla poeas</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Calycopis cecrops</hi>, the red-banded hairstreak.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f50">The name <hi rend="italic">Polyommatus neglectus</hi> was not at the time published (the recently published name, <hi rend="italic">P. neglectus</hi> (Stradomsky and Arzanov 1999), refers to a different butterfly), but Walsh probably refers to the species <hi rend="italic">Lycaena neglecta</hi>, now <hi rend="italic">Celastrina neglecta</hi>, the summer azure. The unpublished name <hi rend="italic">Polyommatus pseudargiolus</hi> was probably used by Walsh to refer to <hi rend="italic">Argus pseudargiolus</hi>, now <hi rend="italic">Celastrina ladon</hi>, the spring azure.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f51"><hi rend="italic">Polyommatus comyntas</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Elkalyce comyntas</hi>, the eastern tailed-blue. The butterfly Walsh refers to as <hi rend="italic">P. lygdamas</hi> was <hi rend="italic">Lycaena lygdamus</hi> (see Doubleday and Westwood 1846–52, 2: 491), now <hi rend="italic">Glaucopsyche lygdamus</hi>, the silver blue. <hi rend="italic">Polyommatus heteronea</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5603.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Morris 1862</ref>, p. 89) is now <hi rend="italic">Lycaena heteronea</hi>, the blue copper. The butterfly Walsh refers to as <hi rend="italic">P. acmon</hi> was <hi rend="italic">Lycaena acmon</hi> (see Doubleday and Westwood 1846–52, 2: 494), now <hi rend="italic">Plebejus acmon</hi>, the acmon blue.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f52"><hi rend="italic">Argynnis diana</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Speyeria diana</hi>, the Diana fritillary, is highly sexually dimorphic. Edwards described the female of the species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2265.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. H. Edwards 1864</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f53"><hi rend="italic">Cossus robiniae</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Prionoxystus robiniae</hi>, the carpenterworm moth.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f54"><hi rend="italic">Aegeria exitiosa</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Synanthedon exitiosa</hi>, the peachtree borer.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f55"><hi rend="italic">Saturnia io</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Automeris io</hi>, the io moth. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 398, CD mentioned the colour differences in <hi rend="italic">Saturnia io</hi>, but did not cite Walsh for the information.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f56">The genus <hi rend="italic">Acontia</hi> in fact belonged to the family Acontidae (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7404.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stainton 1856–9</ref>, 1: 295–7). It now belongs to the subfamily Acontiinae, family Noctuidae (noctuid, dagger, and owlet moths).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>