<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5256">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   26 October 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10652</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5256 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5256.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5256.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 73</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 73</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</persName>
                <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                <date when="1866-10-26">26 Oct 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Plans to have J. V. Carus handle translation of new edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. Describes Carus’ views on the edition.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_849">Carus, J. V.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                    <date>den 26 October 1866.</date>
                    <salute>Verehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Seit ich das letztemal an Sie geschrieben habe, ist eine geraume Zeit vergangen, während welcher Sie so gütig waren mir nach und nach die Bogen der neuen Auflage Ihres Origin zu senden.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Sie wissen dass die traurige Zeit des deutschen Krieges nicht geeignet war zu literarischen Unternehmungen;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> dem ungeachtet habe ich die neue Auflage nicht ausser Acht gelassen, sondern mich, nachdem Herr Prof. Geinitz und Herr Prof Leonhard der Aufgabe nicht sich zu unterziehen meinten, auf Empfehlung des Ersteren an Herrn Prof. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Victor Carus in Leipzig gewendet.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Ich habe die grosse Befriedigung Ihnen anzeigen zu können daß derselbe aufs Bereitwilligste meinen Antrag angenomen hat und sich wegen der Sache sich mit Ihnen in brieflichen Verkehr setzen wird;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> einstweilen sandte ich ihm das Exemplar Ihres Werkes welches ich von Ihnen erhalten habe, dazu 1 Ex der deutschen Ausgabe.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Nach allem was mir Herr Carus schreibt ist er ganz der rechte Mann für das Buch; er behält sich ganze Freiheit vor von den Anmerkungen des Herrn Bronn wegzulassen was er selbst nicht wissenschaftlich vertreten könne;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Hr Carus ist ein erklärter Anhänger Ihrer Theorie und will seinerseits solche durch allgemein physikälisch-physiologische Gründe zu stützen und zu bekräftigen versuchen. H<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carus wird sich selbst brieflich an Sie wenden; ich dachte aber Ihnen diese Mittheilung gleich machen zu müssen, damit Sie wissen wie es damit steht.</p>
<p>Indem ich Ihnen nochmals meinen Dank sage für all die Freundlichkeit der ich mich von Ihnen zu erfreuen hatte bin ich mit größter Hochachtung und Verehrung | Ihr ergebenster | E Schweizerbart</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.5 Herrn … Leipzig] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Note on Hybrid Chapter’<ref target="#foot.f8"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                    <date>26 October 1866</date>
                    <salute>Most respected Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Since I last wrote to you, a long time has passed, during which you kindly sent me the proofs of the new edition of your Origin.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>You know that the sad time of the German war was not appropriate for literary undertakings;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> this notwithstanding, I have not left the new edition unattended, but, after Prof. Geinitz and Prof. Leonhard said they would not undertake the task, on the recommendation of the former I have approached Prof. Victor Carus in Leipzig.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I take great pleasure in reporting to you that he has accepted my proposal most readily, and will be writing to you in this regard;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> meanwhile I have sent him the copy of your work that I received from you, along with one copy of the German edition.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> From all Mr Carus has written to me, he is exactly the right man for the book; he requests complete freedom to delete from Mr Bronn’s annotations anything that he cannot himself support from a scientific standpoint.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Mr Carus is an acknowledged proponent of your theory and will try on his part to support and strengthen it through general physical-physiological grounds. Mr Carus will write to you himself about this; I thought however I had better give you this information at once, so that you would know how things stand.</p>
<p>Thanking you once again for all the kindness I have enjoyed from you, I am with great esteem and admiration | Yours truly | E. Schweizerbart</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.14, Appendix I. It was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, the head of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>, who used the signature E. Schweizerbart in business communications.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 362–3. It was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, the head of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>, who used the signature E. Schweizerbart in business communications.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5085.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 10 May 1866</ref>. Page proofs of the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> were available by mid-July 1866 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5155.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 15 July [1866]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to the Austro-Prussian War. Stuttgart, where the Schweizerbart firm was located, was the capital of Württemberg, one of the German states that sided with Austria (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5085.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 10 May 1866</ref> and n. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Schweizerbart had orginally approached <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2893.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav von Leonhard</ref> to supervise the third German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, but he declined, recommending <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hans Bruno Geinitz</ref> as his replacement. Geinitz also declined but suggested that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Victor Carus</ref> would be well qualified for the job (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5085.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 10 May 1866</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5269.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. V. Carus, 7 November 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Schweizerbart refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref> and Bronn trans. 1863.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">For more on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn’s</ref> annotations to the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5269.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. V. Carus, 7 November 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD’s annotation refers to a note added to the chapter on hybridism in the second German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1863, p. 274 n.; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5273.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. V. Carus, 10 November 1866</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>