<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8935">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From George Cupples   4 June 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16592</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8935 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8935.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8935.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 299</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 299</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1163.xml">Cupples, George</persName>
                <placeName>Guard Bridge</placeName>
                <date when="1873-06-04">4 June 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>J. V. Carus’ lecture.</p>
            <p>Edinburgh intellectual climate.</p>
            <p>Ralph Waldo Emerson’s visit to Edinburgh.</p> 
<p>J. H. Stirling did not write anonymous review of <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi>. Suggests T. Spencer Baynes of St Andrews. [? T. S. Baynes, "Darwin on expression", 137 (1873): 492–528.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Edinburgh Review</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_849">Carus, J. V.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1504">Emerson, R. W.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4568">Stirling, J. H.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Edinburgh</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>The Cottage, | Guard Bridge, Fifeshire | N.B.</placeName>
                    <date>June 4/73.</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Mr Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>We have just now got home from Edinburgh, where I looked out the number of the Edinburgh Review containing the article you referred to—but had not time to read it.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Nobody seemed to have given it any attention—as it was understood to be pretty much a repetition of what had been said before, with the addition of some fresh vinegar and pepper. As to the authorship, I asked two or three friends, without saying why I wanted to know. I am glad to be able to say that my friend Dr Stirling knew nothing about it—had not even heard of it till I spoke of the article, which he read afterwards and appeared neither to like the tone nor set value on the argument.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>His notion was, that the writer is most likely Professor Spencer Baynes of St Andrew’s—near here, and an acquaintance of my own (a devout Hamiltonian and adherent of the Scotch school in metaphysics.)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Such papers are not likely to find favour about Edinburgh, however—where the University in general, as elsewhere, seems to lean the other way. The old psychologists (Platonics apart, e.g. the Grecian Stuart Blackie)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> become Berkeleian, and so swallow things quietly—whilst Theology endeavours grimly to accept the Inevitable.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Dr John Brown had dipped into the review in question, but seemed not to have found it interesting enough to do more.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The intellectual atmosphere of Edinburgh is liberal. Emerson from America was there lately—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I don’t know whether he has met you, but from what I know of him (Transcendentalist as he is) I should say he would have delighted in doing so, more even than in saying the same thing over again with Carlyle at Chelsea, or vainly “interviewing” Tennyson.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I can fancy the ingenuous pleasure which Emerson would have had—the pure idealist that he is, most Greek of modern thinkers—in coming together for a little while with the Realist of Realists, and putting questions there as to Nature’s self. I can imagine how he would go away home, feeling satisfied that he had seen what Americans must feel to be the most representatively English thing in England yet. If you and he did <hi rend="underline">not</hi> meet, it only brings the more forcibly on me a sense of that old contrariety in Fate,—which denies—or perhaps only postpones—the best conceivable sort of meetings and understandings between men.— <hi rend="underline">Thought</hi> and Fact—ideal and real—can they meet? Do they <hi rend="underline">need</hi> to meet! Are they not the two poles, reciprocally playing in each, and through all—wherefore then the bitterness of reviewers, the rage of sects, the apparent anger at truth having its way? The calm manner of English scientific men is certainly a strong presumption in their favour at present, and I don’t see why Hegelians<ref target="#foot.f9"/> should wax hot on the other hand if they are right.</p>
<p>Pray pardon this summer vein of writing, which may, I hope, be allowed to pass as such.</p>
<p>I saw a dog-show in Edinburgh, where the first-prize dog (which carries all before him throughout England at the great shows) was “Morni”, grand-uncle to your “Bran.” He was twice brought up to our lodgings in town—and I took some good drawings of him. A splendid specimen he is. His attendant (a quondam taxidermist, a naturalist in his way, once in the employment of the late Lord Derby) proved the most extraordinary enthusiast I ever met with.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I had a letter from him afterwards, about that dog, which would really have amused you. I would not for worlds have missed it.</p>
<p>I ascertain that Iceland dogs (a small Esquimaux) have all six claws or toes on the hind-feet—like Pyreneans (which resemble a <hi rend="underline">large</hi> Esquimaux.) I suppose shepherd colleys have <hi rend="underline">five</hi> claws—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Ordinary well-bred dogs having <hi rend="underline">four</hi>.</p>
<p>My paper failing, I close, and with kindest regards from Mrs Cupples<ref target="#foot.f12"/> to Mrs Darwin and yourself, remain, dear Mr Darwin, yours ever truly, George Cupples</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had asked about the authorship of the unfavourable review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> that had appeared in the April 1873 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_465.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Baynes 1873]</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8886.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to George Cupples, 28 April [1873]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had suggested that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4568.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Hutchison Stirling</ref> might be the author of the review in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8886.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Cupples of 28 April [1873]</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8891.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Cupples, 1 May 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The review was in fact by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_338.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Spencer Baynes</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Wellesley index</hi></ref>). He was professor of logic, metaphysics, and English literature at the University of St Andrews, and had studied under <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hamilton</ref> at the University of Edinburgh (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_467.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Stuart Blackie</ref> was professor of Greek at Edinburgh (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Cupples alludes to the Irish philosopher <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6535.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Berkeley</ref> and his influential writings on idealism and the psychology of perception (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>). For contemporary accounts of Scottish metaphysics and idealism, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. F. Ferrier 1875</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7121.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Seth Pringle-Pattison 1885</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The Edinburgh physician and writer John Brown published widely in Scottish periodicals such as the <hi rend="italic">North British Review</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1504.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ralph Waldo Emerson</ref> visited England and Scotland in the spring of 1873; he was in Edinburgh for one day, 8 May 1873, to visit Stirling (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4101.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ireland 1882</ref>, p. 21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Emerson had visited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_832.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Carlyle</ref> on trips to England in 1833 and 1847 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4101.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ireland 1882</ref>, pp. 53–4, 60). Cupples also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4696.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Tennyson</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Cupples refers to followers of the idealist philosophy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8891.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Cupples, 1 May 1873</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Cupples had given CD an Irish deerhound puppy named Bran in 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18). Morni was a champion deerhound whose owner, G. W. Hickman, was a breeder and authority on deerhounds (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1737.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dalziel 1889</ref>, 1: 48–9, 74). The late <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4523.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley</ref>, fourteenth earl of Derby, had kept at Knowsley Hall near Liverpool a large menagerie, which had been established by his father, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4525.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Smith Stanley</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The Pyrenean mountain dog has double spurs or dew-claws on the hind feet; the Icelandic sheepdog often has two dew-claws, and the shepherd or Border collie generally has one dew-claw.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Ann Jane Cupples.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>