<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13270">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Leopold Würtenberger<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   3 August 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11140</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13270 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13270.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13270.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 188</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 188</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4911.xml">Würtenberger, Leopold</persName>
                <placeName>Konstanz</placeName>
                <date when="1881-08-03">3 Aug 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Repeats request for loan in order to spend probationary training period in chemical factory.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, miscellaneous</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3503">Wurtenberger, Leopold</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">chemical factory</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">probationary training period</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-06" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-06" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-30" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00942_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00942_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="188:1r" xml:id="i942">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00942.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00942_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00942.dzi" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="188:1v" xml:id="i943">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00943.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00943_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00943.dzi" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="188:2r" xml:id="i944">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00944.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00944_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00944.dzi" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="188:2v" xml:id="i945">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00945.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00945_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00945.dzi" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="188:3r" xml:id="i946">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00946.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00946_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00946.dzi" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="188:3v" xml:id="i947">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00947.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00947_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00181-000-00947.dzi" width="3933px" height="6356px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Konstanz (Wessenbergstr. 27) Gr. Baden</placeName>
                    <date>den 3. Aug. 1881.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>In Ihrem geehrten Schreiben vom 29. Juli theilen Sie mir mit, dass Sie meinem Ansuchen nicht entsprechen können.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich erlaube mir, nochmals auf den Gegenstand zurückzukommen, indem, wie es scheint, ein Missverständniss mit unterlaufen ist. Ich beabsichtigte nämlich die bezeichnete Summe nur als <hi rend="underline">Darlehen</hi> zu erlangen, und kann mit gutem Gewissen die ganz bestimmte Versicherung geben, dass ich in den Stand gesetzt würde, diese Summe nach einiger Zeit zurückzuzahlen, wenn ich in eine Stellung bei einer chemischen Fabrik komme. Es ist dies nicht blos eine unbegründete Einbildung, ich spreche aus Erfahrung. Ich hatte nämlich früher eine Stelle als technischer Chemiker bei der badischen Münzstätte. Hiebei hatte ich mein gutes Auskommen und, wenn ich geblieben wäre, hätte ich jetzt einen Gehalt, der mich in den Stand setzte, ein Schönes als Ersparniss zurückzulegen. Aber leider hieng ich damals zu sehr am Idealen und die reelle Praxis missfiel mir, so dass ich nicht ruhte, bis ich aus meiner Stellung heraus war. Da ich von jeher mit Vorliebe rein wissenschaftliche Dinge verfolgte, glaubte ich mein Lebensglück zu finden, wenn ich in den Stand gesetzt würde, mich ganz den Wissenschaften widmen zu können; und eine entsprechende Stellung zu finden, schien mir leicht; aber in letzter Hinsicht wurde ich nur zu schwer enttäuscht. Ich weiss jetzt, dass sich nur derjenige auf das wissenschaftliche Gebiet verlocken lassen sollte, der die Mittel dazu hat, um längere Zeit unabhängig leben und es in Gemüthsruhe abwarten zu können, bis ihn der Zufall einer entsprechenden Stellung zuführt. Mich haben meine wissenschaftlichen Bestrebungen jetzt bereits in eine gänzlich hoffnungslose Lage gebracht; gerne würde ich jetzt wieder umkehren, aber im Münzfache jetzt augenblicklich wieder Stellung zu erlangen, geht nicht so ohne weiteres und in andern Zweigen der chemichen Technologie fehlt mir die pracktische Erfahrung. Es werden jeweils für verschiedene Brauchen, namentlich für die Farben-Technik Chemiker gesucht, aber immer nur Leute, welche bereits <hi rend="underline">prakticirt haben</hi>; aus diesem Grunde waren meine Bewerbungen bei einer Anzahl Stellen in letzter Zeit immer erfolglos. Da ich aber in der allgemeinen und analytischen Chemie die erforderlichen Kenntnisse besitze, so wäre es mir ein Leichtes, mich in einer gewissen Zeit in eine technologische Specialität, z. B. Anilinfabrikation, hineinzuarbeiten, und dann wäre mir eine gut bezahlte Stelle sicher; aber, um zu diesem Zwecke in einer Fabrik zu volontiren, dazu fehlen mir eben die Mittel, und da ich keine Verwandten oder Freunde besitze, die im Stande wären, mir die erforderliche Summe zu leihen, so erlaubte ich mir, mich in dieser Angelegenheit an Sie zu wenden.</p>
<p>Hochgeehrtester Herr! ich erlaube mir nochmals, die ergebenste Bitte zu wiederholen, mir die bezeichnete Summe (70–80 £) für einige Jahre gütigst <hi rend="underline">leihen</hi> zu wollen. Ich werde sicher, wenn ich wieder eine Stellung habe, schon in der ersten Zeit es durch Sparsamkeit dazu bringen, diese Schuld nach und nach abtragen zu können. Wenn Sie durch diese Gefälligkeit einem Unglücklichen, der durch ein herbes Schicksal in die bitterste Noth und der Verzweiflung nahe gebracht wurde, wieder aufhelfen wollten, so wäre Ihnen derselbe zeitlebens zu unaussprechlicher Dankbarkeit verpflichtet.</p>
<p>Mit der Hoffnung, dass Sie meine Bitte gefl. berücksichtigen und meine Dringlichkeit nicht übel nehmen möchten verbleibe ich | mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung | Ihr ergebenster | L. Würtenberger</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Constance (Wessenbergstr. 27) Duchy of Baden</placeName>
                    <date>3 Aug. 1881.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>In your kind letter of 29 July you let me know that you are unable to comply with my request.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I venture to bring up the matter again as it looks as though there was a misunderstanding. For I meant to get the sum in question as a <hi rend="underline">loan</hi> only, and I can in good conscience absolutely guarantee that I would be able to repay this sum after a while if I got a position at a chemical factory. This is not merely unfounded wishful thinking, but I speak from experience. You see, I used to be employed as a technical assistant at the Baden mint. On this occasion, I made a good living and had I stayed I would now have a salary that would enable me to lay aside a tidy sum as a nest egg. Alas, in those days I clung too much to ideals and real experience displeased me, so that I did not rest until I was rid of my job. Having always been partial to the pursuit of purely scientific matters, I believed my future happiness depended on being put in the position to wholly dedicate myself to the sciences; and to find such a post to me seemed simple; however, regarding the latter I was only too bitterly disappointed. I know now that only those should allow themselves to be lured into the realm of science who have the financial means to live independently for quite some time and who can leisurely wait until chance brings a suitable position their way. My scientific aspirations have now already put me into a completely hopeless situation; gladly would I now go back but it is not all that simple at the moment to get another job in the minting business and in other branches of chemical technology I lack practical experience. In the various branches, particularly in the technology of dyes, chemists are wanted, but invariably people who already have <hi rend="underline">practical experience</hi>; for this reason my recent applications for a number of positions were always unsuccessful. However, since I have the required knowledge in general and analytical chemistry, it would be no problem for me to familiarise myself within a certain period of time with a technological specialty, e.g. the making of aniline, and then a well-paid position would be a certainty; however, I lack the means to train in a factory at my own expense for this purpose, and as I have no relatives or friends who would be able to lend me the required sum, I ventured to turn to you with this matter.</p>
<p>Most esteemed Sir! once more I venture to repeat the most humble request to kindly <hi rend="underline">lend</hi> me the sum in question (70–80 £) for a few years. When I am employed again, I certainly will even early on succeed in being able through thriftiness little by little to settle my debt. If by granting this favour you were to lend a hand to an unhappy person, whom a hard lot brought into bitter need and close to despair, he would be obliged to you in inexpressible gratitude all his life.</p>
<p>In the hope that you will consider my request and that you may not be offended by my urgency I remain | with the greatest Respect | Yours most devoted | L. Würtenberger</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>  
        
          
        
          
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter has not been found; see, however, the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13253.xml">letter from Leopold Würtenberger, 26 July 1881</ref>.</note>
            
        </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>