<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11236">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. G. Joyce   15 November 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19306</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11236 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11236.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11236.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">AmemS</note>
            <note type="physdesc">AmemS 8pp, sketches †, encl 3pp, sketches</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 64.2: 63–6; DAR 65: 104, 106, 108</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>64.2: 63–6; 65: 104, 106, 108</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2617.xml">Joyce, J. G.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1877-11-15">15 Nov 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Memorandum on Silchester. Report by IGJ of investigations carried out at Silchester with Frank and Horace [Darwin] on earthworm activity at the site of a Roman villa. Sections of vertical cuttings at Silchester, traced from the journal of the excavations of the Roman house, and notes on the same.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">earthworm</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1222">Darwin, Francis</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1226">Darwin, Horace</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Roman villa</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Silchester</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">worms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-29" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2016-08-18" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-18" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-18" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name>. Corrections entered by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name>.</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00065-000-00217_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="9714px" height="7338px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00065-000-00217_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="9714px" height="7338px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="104 foldout" xml:id="i217">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00065-000-00217.jpg" width="9714px" height="7338px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00065-000-00217_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="9714px" height="7338px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00065-000-00217.dzi" width="9714px" height="7338px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>15 Nov 77</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Memorandum on Silchester:— copied from the Journal of Excav<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> 15 Nov 77</p>
<p>On Tuesday Nov 13. 1877 Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. F. &amp; H. Darwin<ref target="#foot.f2"/> went to Silchester with me when we were enabled to carry out in the course of three hours a very careful examination of several exposed vertical cuttings, from the herbage, directly down to the floors of R. Construction.</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Investigation.— House excavated in the Meadow, contiguous to the Spring. Two objects were in view. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. inspection of floors sunk toward the centre &amp; away from the walls. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. The texture of the mould overlying walls &amp; floors.</p>
<p>General Aspect: This excavation presents at this date the following:— viz. a quadrangle in the centre, round 3 sides of which runs a corridor or ambulatory with tesselation left in patches upon its floors.— The ambulatory is on the N. the E. &amp; the S.— none on the W. Upon the N. ambulatory there abuts a range of Rooms, five (or more strictly, six,) in number, with floors of tesseræ remaining in four. Examination was first directed to ascertain what amount of sinking or “sagging” had taken place where the tesselation was sufficiently complete to give data.</p>
                    <p>The S. ambulatory has remaining a piece of tesselation of large &amp; coarse cubes (2) of tile, chipped to 1<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> or 1<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inch each,)— A line was strained across tightly from the level of the herbage on the N. to that on the S. opposite, (slope of field surface 3.<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>40<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. from N to S.)— Depth of floor here below field surface—at the centre of the corridor 2<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>.10″. at the wall 2<hi rend="superscript">′</hi>.2″<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula>—which gives the maximum depth of sinking or sagging of this floor 7<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inches.— The height of the summit of what remains of the walls— 2′, 1<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula>″ below the field surface at this part, w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>. leaves only <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inch of wall above floor.</p>
<p>The N. Ambulatory was next examined.</p>
                    <p>The floor of the N. Ambulatory is disintegrated, it contains some rough tesselation but not enough to be any guide as to the amount of sinking.— Wall separating this ambulatory from the quadrangle 3<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>.5<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>. under field surface line. This wall, very slightly higher than the ancient floor was. The Rooms were examined next. The floor of a narrow rectangular room about the centre of the range was selected because in the most complete condition. The tesselation covers the greater part of the floor, but is absent at the S. end. Here is a strongly marked depression toward the middle— so much so as to make it almost look as though a hypocaust were below the floor, but there is no ground to think this.— Observing the tesselation, it is fairly perfect in the centre but appears to cease just before it arrives at the walls on both sides. It almost has the look of having been removed for a breadth of 5 to 6 inches. It does not seem that this was the case,— there would have been no conceivable reason for taking away the tesseræ from there, those in the centre being both easier to get, &amp; more obvious to see, if any person wished to take them, but it does seem on the other hand as if the whole body of tesseræ slid inward a little toward the depression in the centre—without breaking up.— (we omitted to take the exact depth of this hollow) The summit of the wall along the north side is 2′ 7″<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> below the field surface, &amp; between the summit of the wall &amp; the floor is a depth varying from 1′.6″—to 1 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. We examined the mould overlying this. The section was an excellent one, &amp; showed exactly what was there. From the top of the wall to the herbage was 31<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inches.</p>
                    <p>This 31<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inches was made up of two distinct beds, the lower was 24″<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> deep. It is dark brown mould, very thickly interspersed with small sized pebbles of waterworn gravel, &amp; with bits of Roman tiles, mere fragments, apparently worn by the friction of water, or weathered, till the sharp edges of their fractures are gone. There was a much larger intermixture of pebbles &amp; bits of tile in this mould than we expected. Above this 24<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula>″ bed, is the surface mould in w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>. the grass grows. This is homogeneous, free from pebbles, rich &amp; dense of a dark brown colour, entirely without any fragments of broken tile— &amp; about 7 inches deep.</p>
<p>The traces of worm casts were not so marked or so frequent here as we expected to have found them.</p>
                    <p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. Investigation— In large excavation on the line of the Great N. Road, in the centre of the town—known as Block II.</p>
<p>General aspect.— a large Quadrangle—Ambulatories on the N. &amp; S. both perfectly paved with tesselation in a perfect state, many rooms upon the outer side of these ambulatories, &amp; along the west side also.— E side, no rooms open. Field surface found by a line strained tight above the centre of the S. ambulatory, from the herbage level at the W end to the herbage level at the E End.</p>
<p>Floor of South Ambulatory, tesselation quite perfect, 11<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inches at East end, below the field, &amp; 2<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>. 4<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> <hi rend="superscript">in</hi>. at the west end, the field here sloping rather rapidly from W. to E. In this ambulatory there is very slight “sagging”— Examining the floor for worm casts, we found in a low part where water had remained &amp; left a deposit of mud (very slight), very distinct worm casts, where the worms must have come up between the tesseræ. Observing that here &amp; there a tessera was loose, &amp; a little higher in level, we removed these loose ones to look below, &amp; found in each instance that a worm pipe existed underneath, where the loose tessera had been dislodged, &amp; not unfrequently two pipes. This tesselation is formed not of tile work, but of hard sandstone, cubes ab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1 inch—chipped to shape with a tool.</p>
                    <p>We next investigated by measurement the exact sinking toward a centre in a Room where the floor is quite perfect   The Room we measured is that immediately next to the Red Wooden Hut,— &amp; is at the Western End of the last named ambulatory—on the right as one advances up the corridor from E to W.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Section from N. to S</p>
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width75">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_1.jpg"/>
                    </figure>  
                    <p>The maximum here is 5″<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula>, but it is obvious that the whole floor has sunk every where, more or less.</p>
<p>On this floor whilst we were examining it we found a worm which had just come up between two tesseræ, nearly 7 inches long.— Memorandum entered here “worms seem to lift some of the tesseræ completely out of their places.”— Yet there were very few worm casts visible on the face of the pavement.</p>
<p>Round the walls, in various places the tesseræ have parted from the wall—looking as if removed—in other places they remain in situ close up to the line of the wall of the room.</p>
<p>We examined next the corner Room of the same house “Block II” at the S.E Angle.</p>
<p>This Room in the corner was enlarged. There was an insertion of a large hypocaust into the original ground plan. The hypocaust and the room containing the furnace were next to this corner chamber, the original room was enclosed within the original walls o . o . o . o, but the part of the room at R. R. was removed to give more space for inserting the hypocaust. In order to compensate the chamber, its area was extended beyond the house wall on the S. and an addition A. A. A. was made, encreasing the size on that side but altering the shape.</p> 
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width65">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_2.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
<p>In carrying out this change they did not remove away the portion of original wall at the centre of the altered apartment but left it under the floor buried. The floor has subsided considerably on each side, &amp; leaves now a hump or ridge to indicate where the buried wall is. There is no visible trace of a wall but the certainty of its presence was demonstrated by digging— it was found readily below the hump at 5<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>. 4<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>. distance from the actual S. wall of the room.</p>
<p>3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. investigation.— Object,— 1. to trace whether worms are to be found quite underneath the R. walls.— and 2. whether may be traced as forcing their way right up through the centre of such walls.</p>
<p>For this, we investigated the walls now in process of present exposure, at the excavation which is in progress. General aspect.— A large quadrangle of extraordinary magntitude &amp; probably the quadrangle of some public place. Round it ambulatories—with suites of rooms, &amp; hypocausts upon the western range.— Masonry very solid—walls perfectly sound &amp; strong—depth of the foundations below floor levels, 4 feet of substantial flint &amp; mortar, 1<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>. 6<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>. thick throughout.</p>
<p>Taking the fractured extremity of a principal wall on the N.— &amp; near the N.W. angle of the building, a sinking was made deep enough to get below the lowest course of flints.— A spadefull of earth being thrown up from exactly underneath the wall itself several worms of very large dimensions appeared. Two in particular, 8 inches long, &amp; <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inch (or more) in diameter.</p>
<p>With a view to trace the presence of worms in the wall itself, if there, the lower flints were now removed, and the interior of the wall searched. It was soft &amp; crumbly &amp; appeared very moist. There was no doubt as to traces of worms being in the rotten mortar which was found in the middle of the wall. The mortar was not white, nor light coloured—it was quite dark, &amp; largely mixed with mould. This was not its original condition, &amp; the mould permeating it must be due to the action of worms which carry mould with them into the very heart of the wall, when they pass between the flints.</p>
<p>But this investigation was at a fractured part, &amp; the structure might be looser there in consequence. Therefore the investigation was repeated in two other parts of the same building, &amp; in the instance of walls absolutely sound &amp; good.</p>
<p>In the case of a wall upon the East side, now at this date in process of being exposed to view, a piece of wall was purposely opened for the first time to carry out this investigation. Worm casts &amp; worm pipes were certainly found here in a fresh wall never exposed before. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Horace Darwin removed a flint of some size, &amp; finding worm pipes he pursued these—one large pipe in particular, quite down into the very substance of this wall.</p>
<p>But being desirous of trying if possible more completely, I called D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. F. Darwin’s attention to certain chambers in this building at its S. W. Corner, where the walls have been laid entirely bare below the floor levels, the whole floor &amp; its sustratum being dug completely out, in order to exhibit the astonishing depth of the foundations. The walls go down quite 4 feet below the floors. The mortar here is perfectly hard, &amp; looks quite fresh; With great effort a large flint was forced out of its place at a height of 12 to 14 inches from the bottom. It resisted strongly, seeming quite embedded in mortar as hard as cement, but once wrenched away, there appeared traces of worms work behind it in the inside of the wall within. There was, even here, dark mould mixed in the mortar of the middle part, &amp; this mortar itself in places, instead of being hard &amp; close as one w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. expect, was friable &amp; could be picked away by the finger.</p>
<p>The last experiment gave me more surprize, &amp; brought more conviction, than any before it. I should have said, and did say, that it was perfectly impossible such a wall could be penetrated by, or could contain, any earth worms.</p>
<p>J. G. Joyce. | 15 Nov 1877.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>Sections of vertical cuttings at Silchester; traced from the Journal of Excavations<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width85">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_3.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                    <p><ref target="#foot.f5"/><ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                      
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width55">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_4.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
               
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width45">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_5.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                   
                   <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width85">
                       <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_6.jpg"/>
                   </figure> 
                   
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width55">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_7.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width85">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11236_8.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                    
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="annotations">
    <note>3.1 Meadow,] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon, after</hi> ‘grass’ <hi rend="italic">interl blue crayon, underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>3.1 the Spring.] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>5.1 The S. ambulatory] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>5.3 3.′40°.] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>5.5 2<hi rend="superscript">ft</hi>. 10″.] <hi rend="italic">underl red and blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>7.1 The floor] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘2/’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>7.9 Observing the] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>7.9 is fairly … arrives 7.10] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon; cross in left margin red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>7.11 breadth … inches.] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon; cross in left margin red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>7.13 easier … up.— 7.16] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon; two crosses in left margin red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>7.16 (we … take the] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>8.1 This … weathered 8.4] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>8.1 the lower] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘3/’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>9.1 The traces … them.] 9.2] ‘HD’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note>10.1 in … town 10.2] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>11.1 General … E End. 10.5] ‘When was this was excavated or cleared’ <hi rend="italic">left margin pencil</hi></note>
    <note>12.2 the west … E. 12.3] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>12.3 W. to E.] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>12.4 found] ‘10’ <hi rend="italic">left margin pencil</hi></note>
    <note>12.4 left] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘4’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>12.5 the worms … tool. 12.10] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>13.1 We next] <hi rend="italic">two crosses in left margin red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>13.1 We next … W. 13.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
    <note>13.3 Red Wooden Hut,] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note><hi rend="italic">Fig. </hi> Section … S] ‘Walls generally 18 inches’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘Section E’ <hi rend="italic">pencil, boxed pencil</hi>; ‘see Horace No 11.’<ref target="#foot.f7"/>  <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘Draw on scale—taking <hi rend="italic">[</hi>alternate measure<hi rend="italic">]</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 13 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.] ‘3<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>8</mn></mfrac></math></formula>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 14 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.] ‘3<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note>15.1 On … found] <hi rend="italic">del pencil</hi></note>
    <note>15.1 On … room. 16.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
    <note>16.1 Round … room. 16.2] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>16.1 have parted] <hi rend="italic">two crosses in left margin red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>17.1 “Block II”] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘5’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>19.2 The floor … wall is. 19.4] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>19.4 its presence 19.5] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘6’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>21.1 present … progress. 21.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
    <note>21.5 depth of the] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>21.5 below floor levels] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>21.6 1 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. 6<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>.] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>22.2 sinking … diameter. 22.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>22.5 diameter.] ‘Horace is sure did not come from beneath the walls’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note>23.1 itself,] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘(7’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>23.3 worms being … consequence. 24.2] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
    <note>23.5 it was … mould.] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>23.5 This was … flints. 23.7] ‘<hi rend="italic">[</hi>fibre<hi rend="italic">]</hi> w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> also be dissolved out | See Horace remarks (21)’<ref target="#foot.f8"/>  <hi rend="italic">left margin pencil</hi></note>
    <note>23.6 worms … flints. 23.7] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>24.1 But … good. 24.3] ‘perhaps cavities left in walls.’ <hi rend="italic">left margin blue ink</hi></note>
    <note>25.3 Worm … before. 25.4] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.1 But] <hi rend="italic">below</hi> ‘8/’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.1 But … floors. 26.5] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.1 But … bottom. 26.7] ‘Account for sinking of floor in comparison with Abinger’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note>26.3 floor &amp; … go down 26.5] <hi rend="italic">heavily scored pencil</hi></note>
    <note>26.4 exhibit … foundations.] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.5 walls … floors.] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
    <note>26.5 quite 4 feet] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.8 traces … part, 26.10] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.10 &amp; this … finger. 26.11] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
    <note>26.11 was friable … 1877. 28.1] ‘It is somewhere said that fragment of tile &amp;c have a worn aspect | disintegration with removal of disintegrated matter as I supposed’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure:</hi></note>
    <note>Diagram N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 1.] ‘B’ <hi rend="italic">deleted and circled, blue crayon</hi>; ‘Cut 9’ <hi rend="italic">enclosed in box, blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>Diagram N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 3.] ‘C’ <hi rend="italic">deleted and circled, blue crayon</hi>; ‘Cut 10’ <hi rend="italic">enclosed in box, blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>Diagram N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 6.] ‘B’ <hi rend="italic">deleted and circled, blue crayon</hi>; ‘Cut 11’ <hi rend="italic">enclosed in box, blue crayon</hi></note>
    <note>made bottom … 8″] <hi rend="italic">above</hi> ‘with frags of tiles’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    <note>Diagram N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 7.] ‘N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 7’ <hi rend="italic">del blue crayon</hi>; ‘A’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon, del blue crayon</hi>; ‘Fig 8.’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon, boxed right, left and below blue crayon</hi>; ‘scale <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> inch to foot’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
    
    
</div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        

        
        

        
        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Joyce excavated the Roman town at Silchester, Hampshire, between 1864 and his death in 1878, recording his work in a three-volume journal that is now in the collections of Reading Museum (http://www.readingmuseum.org.uk/collections/archaeology/silchester/, accessed 10 May 2016). CD cited Joyce in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>, pp. 203–23.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Francis and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The diagram is reproduced at 50 per cent of its original size. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>, p. 212, fig. 13.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For colour images of the sections, see plate section following p. 468. In the transcription, labels that would not fit in their original position have been keyed to the diagrams with numbers in square brackets. The diagrams have been reproduced at between 40 and 50 per cent of the size of the originals, except for No. 5, which is actual size.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Aerarium</hi>: treasury (Latin).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">On the Silchester eagle, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9600.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Toynbee 1963</ref>, plate 61 and p. 150. CD discussed the remains at Silchester in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>, pp. 201–21, and reproduced versions of Joyce’s sections.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Horace and Francis’s notes are in DAR 64.2: 67–72. His no. 11 reads: ‘In this section in our notes we find the depth at 13′ to be 3<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>8</mn></mfrac></math></formula>″ and at 14′, 3<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula>″ instead of 3<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula>″ in both cases. If this were drawn, I think one would be able to see which was the true value by the curve. The whole distance between the walls was 18′–4″’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Note 21 (see n. 7, above) reads: ‘The worm mentioned in (19) was found in the wall just at the end at 2′–5″ below the old floor level and, and 4′–1<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula>″ below ground level.’ A series of numbers added to the text in pencil, and either overwritten in ink or erased and replaced by inked numbers in the margin, is also keyed to these notes and was probably added by Horace or Francis.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>