<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4766">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Maxwell Tylden Masters   7 February 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10075</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4766 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4766.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4766.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp ††</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 71</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 71</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3217.xml">Masters, M. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Peckham</placeName>
                <date when="1865-02-07">7 Feb 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>MTM heard part of the abstract of CD’s paper on climbing plants, read at the Linnean Society on 2 Feb. Offers CD his opinion and information on the subject, which he has studied for many years.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbing plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Linnean Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rye Lane | Peckham.</placeName>
                    <date>Feb. 7./65.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir/</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I had the pleasure of hearing a portion of the summary of your paper on twining plants at the last meeting of the Linn. Society and I hope you will not think me intrusive by writing to you on the matter—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> As unfortunately I only heard part of the abstract read I do not know the extent of ground you travel over and hence perhaps the contents of this note may seem irrelevant, if so excuse me and throw aside this letter—</p>
<p>As an accidental occurrence, growth in a spiral direction takes place in two ways either as a twisting of the stem, branch or leaf as the case may be, upon itself in which instances the fibres of the organ are only secondarily and indirectly affected or the fibres of the stem etc themselves may be chiefly and primarily implicated— This condition is very often associated with the first but not necessarily so.— Moquin speaks of the first cases as “Enroulements” of the latter not very happily as Torsions.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The latter cases occur very generally in Plants with opposite or verticillate leaves e.g. Galium (for a specimen of w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>. I am indebted to yourself)—Dipsacus—Valerian Equisetum, Labiates &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Comparatively rarely does this spiralism affect plants with alternate leaves— As a consequence of this twisting of the stem it often happens that the leaves &amp; branches instead of retaining their usual opposite, verticillate or decussate condition become placed one over the other along one edge—sometimes though more rarely in two rows— I enclose a drawing from a Dipsacus stem which I showed at the Linnean Society when I first began to study Botany and which puzzled me so much at the time that the description I gave of it though substantially correct I believe is by no means lucid—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Some of these cases of spiral growth—if not all are dependent upon some obstacle to upward growth—resistance to motion—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Again they are very frequently associated with fasciation—</p>
<p>—Another point I noticed in the resumé of your paper was the assumption by a petiole of the characteristics of an axis so far as its wood circle was concerned—under certain conditions—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> from this you drew the inference (quite in accordance with what I have always thought and indeed expressed in print) that there is a closer relationship between leaf &amp; stem axis and appendage than is usually surmised.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> In truth the arrangement of the woody bundles in a leaf stalk depends on or at least is associated with differences in form in the stalk itself thus when the petiole is cylindrical the woody bundles are arranged in a ring</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>instead of in a semi circle as they usually are in the channelled petioles</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>In all peltate leaved plants the petiole is cylindrical and the woody bundles arranged in a ring—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>In one of the recent volumes of the Brit Assoc. Reports there is an abstract of a paper on this subject by myself wherein I endeavour to show that the grooved petiole has reference to the protection of the axillary bud from undue pressure etc etc<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I have some thoughts of putting together my notes on spiralism as a teratological phenomenon so as to form a paper for the Linn. Soc. but I shall wait till I see the results of your labors in extenso—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> meanwhile if by supplying references or in any other way I can be of the least assistance I shall be glad to do so if only to compensate for boring you with what may be irrelevant matters</p>
<p>faithfully y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. | Maxwell. T. Masters</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 Some … motion— 3.2] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 Some … fasciation— 3.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.6 In truth … petioles 4.12] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.9 cylindrical] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘very interesting letter | Spiralism p 4— | Petioles— <hi rend="italic">[</hi>showed<hi rend="italic">]</hi> bundles are cylindrical— but, I think you will find that I have expressed myself with caution’<ref target="#foot.f11"/> <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi>; ‘Put foot-note that I hear from D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Masters that is cylindrical [<hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi>] petiole—because petioles of Solanum apparently cylindrical &amp; lose channelled structures, after clasping—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> | Give the reference to B. Assoc Year &amp; page.’<ref target="#foot.f13"/> <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">An abstract of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> was read at the meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 2 February 1865. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> mentioned a comment Masters made at the meeting in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4765.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 3 February 1865</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moquin-Tandon 1841</ref>, pp. 178–82. CD’s heavily annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moquin-Tandon 1841</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Eléments de tératologie végétale, ou histoire abrégée des anomalies de l’organisation dans les végétaux</hi>) is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 598–601); the only annotation on pages 178–82 is a scoring of the last sentence on page 182. CD’s reading notebooks record that he read <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moquin-Tandon 1841</ref> in 1846 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-973.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">10 April [1846]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-971.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[May 1846]</ref>, and Appendix IV). For CD’s discussion of types of spiral growth in twining plants, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, pp. 5–7, 96–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In 1864, CD sent Masters several specimens of abnormal plants, including one showing an example of torsion in <hi rend="italic">Galium</hi>; in his reply, Masters mentioned a similar torsion in <hi rend="italic">Dipsacus</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4617.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter from M. T. Masters, 19 September 1864)</ref>. Examples of spiral torsion in <hi rend="italic">Galium</hi> and other plants are discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5297.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1869</ref>, pp. 319–26, and an illustration of the <hi rend="italic">Galium</hi> sent by CD is given on page 323. CD mentioned the hook-climber <hi rend="italic">Galium aparine</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, p. 105; see also DAR 157.1: 59. Masters cites CD’s findings on spiral torsion in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5297.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1869</ref>, p. 320 n. There is an annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5297.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1869</ref> in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 571).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Masters may refer to a paper he read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 6 March 1855 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5287.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1855</ref>). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4617.xml" resp="#automat">letter from M. T. Masters, 19 September 1864</ref>. The enclosure has not been found; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5287.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1855</ref> was published without an illustration. However, Masters discussed spiral torsion in <hi rend="italic">Dipsacus</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5297.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1869</ref>, pp. 320–1, with an illustration on page 321.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD included this statement in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, p. 6 n., and prefaced it by observing that it was well known that stems occasionally became spirally twisted in a monstrous manner. The note was inserted into a discussion of the probability that stems twisted themselves to gain rigidity for additional strength and for easier upward growth around rough surfaces. CD added that Master’s statement agreed with and might explain the normal axial twisting of twining plants, but that it did ‘not preclude the twisting being of service to the plant by giving greater rigidity to the stem’. CD may have sent this note and others to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> for inclusion in the manuscript of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> that he had already sent on 18 January 1865 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4748.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 19 January [1865]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, pp. 42–3, CD noted the changes in a <hi rend="italic">Solanum jasminoides</hi> petiole after it had clasped a stick. When examining cellular changes in a transverse slice of the petiole, he found that a ‘semilunar band’ of woody vessels had grown and been converted into a complete ring of hard tissue in the clasping petiole; he included a diagram of this change in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, p. 43 (see also CD’s notes on these observations in DAR 157.1: 101–3). For a comment by Masters on petiole structure, made at the meeting during which the abstract of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> was read, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4765.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 3 February 1865</ref> and n. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">For CD’s notice of the relationship between leaves and the stem axis as indicated by the <hi rend="italic">Solanum</hi> petioles, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, pp. 43, 47, and 113–14. CD had read the paper in which Masters came to a similar conclusion regarding leaves and stems (see Masters 1862a, pp. 211–14, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3459.xml" resp="#automat">letter to M. T. Masters, 26 February [1862]</ref>). CD had considered the relationship between plant parts in 1864, also in relation to his work with climbing plants (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4424.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 11 March [1864]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Daniel Oliver, 12 March 1864</ref> and n. 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD referred to Master’s points on the general structure and shape of petioles, and related these to the changes in the <hi rend="italic">Solanum</hi> petiole, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, pp. 43–4 n. For CD’s addition of this note to the manuscript of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, see n. 5, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Masters 1863b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Only an abstract of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> was read at a meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 2 February 1865; the paper was printed in full in the double issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society of London</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>) for 12 June 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2782.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">General index to the Journal of the Linnean Society</hi></ref>, p. vi). Masters included a section on ‘Spiral torsion’, in which he cited <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, in <hi rend="italic">Vegetable teratology</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5297.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Masters 1869</ref>, pp. 319–26).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Evidently these are notes for CD’s reply; however, the letter to Masters has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See nn. 6–8, above. The leaf-climber <hi rend="italic">Solanum jasminoides</hi> is described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, pp. 41–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD did not cite Masters 1863b in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>