<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1822">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To John Phillips   18 January [1856]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">122</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1822 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1822.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1822.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.122)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>122</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1856-01-18">18 Jan [1856]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3773.xml">Phillips, John</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses chapter [6] on cleavage and foliation in <hi rend="italic">South America</hi>. Notes especially cleavage where two series cross and cleavage as basis of foliation in metamorphosed rock. Notes foliation in rocks that have been liquefied by heat. Mentions case described in his "Geology of the Falkland Islands" [<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 203–12]. Discusses relationship of cleavage to beds. Speculations on association between grauwacke and clay-slates.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">cleavage</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">foliation</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">metamorphosed rock</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">South America</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>—</date>
                    <salute>Dear Phillips</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been looking over my Chapter on Cleavage &amp; Foliation in my Geolog. Observ. on S. America 1846, &amp; with that candour so characteristic of authors I really think it worth your looking over.— Some remarks in first part of Chapt. p. 140, are, perhaps, worth skimming over; but the concluding remarks p. 162 give my results.— I see I give one case p. 147 of cleavage not strictly coincident with mountain range. I may remark that I think you may trust my observations, as I made a vast number <hi rend="underline">always</hi> with compass (corrected for var.) &amp; note-book, as I was at time deeply interested in subject, &amp; astounded at cleavage being quite distinct from stratification. The case p. 144 of the confused cleavage, where two <hi rend="underline">great</hi> series crossed each other; the separate hillocks running in different directions, each with its own folia parallel to its longer axis seems interesting.</p>
<p>The foliation of the Chonos Group p. 157 seems to me a grand case, &amp; here it is <hi rend="underline">not</hi> parallel to line of coast: the apparent crossing (p 159) of a subsequently formed chain is worth notice I think.— In my general conclusions, I allude to well-known fact of cleaved clay-slate when metamorphosed by neighbouring granite, becoming foliated in the planes of cleavage; &amp; I <hi rend="underline">now</hi> suppose that this is the explanation of most of the cases of widely extended foliated rocks having the same strike, described by me, for instance that of the Chonos group; at the same time, I think, it should never be forgotten that rocks which have been liquefied by heat, sometimes have their crystallized materials so arranged, as almost to deserve to be called foliated, of which I saw grand instance in Eastern Cordillera of Chile.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In a brief description of the Falkland Isl<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. in Journal of Geolog. Soc. (read in March 1846) Vol. 2 (?) p. 270,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I give a case of a range of stratified quartz, changing its course, &amp; with it the cleavage of the clay-slate at its base: I remember making numerous careful observations on this head.— At p. 271, I give from Capt. Sulivan<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (a careful observer) a case, which I have never myself seen; of cleavage in a set of folded beds, in some vertical, in others at right angles to each bed.—</p>
<p>I ought to apologise for troubling you with so long a note more especially as I do not know how much you are concerned with the vaguely denominated foliated rocks.—</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>The remark p. 163 of Geolog. Observat. in S. America of difference in Mineralogical composition in the planes of cleavage; I do not remember to have seen noticed: I am sure of its accuracy, &amp; presume it is the first step towards metamorphosism or the segregation of separate minerals in the planes of cleavage.—</p>
<p>One other remark,—for years &amp; years the existence of grauwacke with Clay-Slates in various parts of world has perplexed me; as clay-slates seem to have been formed in deep &amp; tranquil seas— Do you think that the same pressure which causes the cleavage, &amp; some movement along the planes of cleavage, can in <hi rend="underline">part</hi> have actually broken up the rock &amp; mingled different varieties together,, like fragments of ice in a glacier, &amp; like these subsequently recemented together by pressure.— Do just think of this.—</p>
<p>My Geolog. Observ. in S. America must be in Bodleian Library<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>If you care to have copy of my 3 vols. together, I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. with pleasure give you order for one. on Smith &amp; Elder.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 p. 162] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.5 give] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘gives’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.1 &amp; here] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.1 it] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.2 apparent] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.4 becoming] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘become’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.9 sometimes] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.9 crystallized] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.2 270,] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘267,’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.6 vertical] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘at’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">7.2 in various parts of world] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">7.5 together,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">7.6 these] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘them’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">7.6 subsequently] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated on the basis that Phillips was preparing his report on cleavage for the meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science to be held in August 1856 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1856</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Phillips’s intention in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1856</ref> was to distinguish the phenomenon of cleavage in rocks from that of stratification, a distinction that CD had also taken pains to make in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref> (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1053.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, [on or before 20 January 1847]</ref>, n. 2). In his discussion of the relationship between the planes of cleavage and the inclination of strata, Phillips cited CD’s observations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1856</ref>, pp. 375–6), and in commenting on the symmetry between cleavage planes and axes of elevation he quoted from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 162: ‘The cleavage laminæ range over wide areas with remarkable uniformity, being parallel in strike to the <hi rend="italic">main axes</hi> of elevation, and generally to the outlines of the coast’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1856</ref>, p. 375).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">‘On the geology of the Falkland Islands,’<hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of the Geological Society of London. Proceedings of the Geological Society</hi>, pt 1, 2 (1846): 267–74 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 203–12). The page reference is to a passage on quartz.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bartholomew James Sulivan</ref>, lieutenant in the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>, made two surveying voyages to the Falkland Islands, 1837–9 and 1842–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Bodleian is the University Library of Oxford. Phillips was keeper of the Ashmolean Museum at Oxford and reader in geology. He became professor of geology in 1857.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In 1851, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4407.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Smith, Elder &amp; Co</ref>. had published a combined edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref> entitled <hi rend="italic">Geological observations on coral reefs, volcanic islands, and on South America</hi> etc. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2805.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Geology of the ‘Beagle’</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>