<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10473">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Lawson Tait   25 April [1876]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10888</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10473 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10473.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10473.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 33</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 33</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4653.xml">Tait, R. L.</persName>
                <placeName>Birmingham</placeName>
                <date when="1876-04-25">25 Apr [1876]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Apologises for placing CD in the objectionable position of sponsor for a rejected paper. RLT has gone over old ground in ignorance.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">7, Great Charles St. | Birmingham.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Ap 25</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I do not know in what terms to make my apology to you for having placed you in so objectionable a position, as to be sponsor for a rejected paper.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>The lesson to me is a severe one, but one to be profited by &amp; for the future I shall not venture into subjects where even my elementary knowledge seems deficient. The snubbing about the use of the terms seems, from the pencilled remarks of the referee, to be thoroughly deserved, and if you know who he is, I should be obliged if you would let him know this.</p>
<p>I was and am now perfectly unacquainted with the authors whom you mention, and my apology must be that if I have gone over old ground I did it in ignorance &amp; that my work has been found fault with only in its want of novelty seems to be an appreciation of its fidelity. I must say further that I may be excused for my ignorance when the most eminent botanist of the day seems equally unaware of the work of these authors and gives an inaccurate account of structures which I am certain I describe exactly<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I am sorry not to have information on the objections to the physiological part of my paper.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> These I should be quite ready to give issue on by facts &amp; the conclusions from them with the referee, no matter who he may be, and I should be glad to have an opportunity to discuss the subject with him.</p>
<p>Could you tell me where Hashall &amp; Griffith’s work is to be found?<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I cannot even find a reference to their names.</p>
<p>Yours truly, | Lawson Tait</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, 24 April 1876</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had submitted Tait’s paper on <hi rend="italic">Nepenthes</hi> (the genus of tropical pitcher-plants) to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref> and it had been rejected; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, 24 April 1876</ref> and n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">On Tait’s use of terms and the morphological referee’s recommendation of authors that he should have cited, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, 24 April 1876</ref> and n. 2. The ‘most eminent botanist’ is probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, who had not cited these authors (see n. 5, below) in his paper on <hi rend="italic">Nepenthes</hi> (Hooker 1874). However, Hooker had done so in his extensive bibliography in A. P. de Candolle and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1215.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1824–73</ref>, 17: 90–105, of which Tait was unaware.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, 24 April 1876</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2744.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pieter Willem Korthals</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1996.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Griffith</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10470.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Lawson Tait, 24 April 1876</ref> and n. 2. Evidently, Tait had misread ‘Korthals’ as ‘Hashall’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>