<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5608">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Hermann Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   16 August [1867]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13552</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5608 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5608.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5608.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy and printed source, incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">1p inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 146: 429; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9069.xml">Krause 1884</ref>, p. 17</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>146: 429</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Krause 1884, p. 17 (German)</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1867-08-16">16 Aug [1867]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Müller, Hermann</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Made aware by Asa Gray of error with respect to <hi rend="italic">Cypripedium</hi>. Does not doubt it is self-fertilised.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Cypripedium</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1957">Gray, Asa</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative self-criticism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-09-15" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes"/>
        <change when="2020-09-15" status="alteredPostPublication" type="letter"/>
        <change when="2020-09-15" status="offlineForRe-edit">Taken offline for re-edit <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2021-05-04" status="sup-footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-30" status="sup-reviewed">Reviewed for vol. 30 supplement by<name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-08" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-06" status="re-released"/>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00146-000-00880_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="7754px" height="10223px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00146-000-00880_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="7754px" height="10223px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="880" xml:id="i880">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00146-000-00880.jpg" width="7754px" height="10223px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00146-000-00880_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="7754px" height="10223px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00146-000-00880.dzi" width="7754px" height="10223px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Bromley, Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Aug: 16.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ich bin Ihnen für Ihren höchst interessanten Brief sehr verbunden, aber es macht mir Sorge, dass Sie sich so viele Arbeit gemacht haben, mich zu verpflichten. … Sie theilen offenbar Ihres Bruders wundervolle Beobachtungsgabe, sowie seine Fertigkeit, sich englisch auszudrücken und seine Geschicklichkeit im Zeichnen. Ich hoffe, dass Sie Ihre excellente Beschreibung veröffentlichen werden.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I was made aware by Prof. Asa Gray (either in a paper in the Amer. Journal of Science or in a letter) of my error with respect to Cypripedium.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> By an odd chance I put an Andrena into the labellum, and saw what you describe as naturally taking place.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Ich kann nicht umhin, ein wenig an der Vergiftung der Bienen zu zweifeln, da es die Ueberführung des Pollens von Pflanze zu Pflanze durchkreuzen würde Bienen sterben, wenn sie stark angestrengt werden, bald an Erschöpfung. Der grosse Robert Brown behauptet indessin, dass der Nektar der <hi rend="underline">Asclepias</hi> Bienen vergifte, und das unterstützt Ihre Ansicht.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Sie erwähnen nicht der wohlangepassten Einwärtskrümmung des Randes der Lippenöffnung, welche die Insekten verhindert, herauszukriechen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Ihre Beobachtungen an <hi rend="underline">Epipactis</hi> erscheinen mir noch werthvoller. <hi rend="underline">E. viridiflora</hi> scheint in demselben Falle wie <hi rend="underline">Cephalanthera</hi> zu sein, aber man kann von dem Vorhandensein des Nektars daselbst schliessen, dass Insekten gelegentlich Pollen von Pflanze zu Pflanze führen. Könnten Sie nicht mit Anwendung des Pollens einer verschiedenen Pflanze und andererseits ihres eigenen experimentiren, und den Inhalt der Kapseln vergleichen? I do not doubt that this species is generally self-fertilized; and I am aware that I erred in supposing that this happened to so few species.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Neottia nidus avis is often self-fertilized.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Epipactis latifolia I find is always fertilized by wasps (vespa)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> — — — —</p>
<p>Yours very faithfully | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener>
            <placeName>Down, Bromley, Kent</placeName>
            <date>Aug: 16.</date>
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
    <div type="transcription">
        <p>I am very grateful to you for your most interesting letter, but I worry that you have given yourself so much work in order to oblige me. … You obviously share your brother’s wonderful powers of observation, as well as his proficiency in expressing himself in English and his skill in drawing. I hope that you will publish your excellent description.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I was made aware by Prof. Asa Gray (either in a paper in the Amer. Journal of Science or in a letter) of my error with respect to Cypripedium.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> By an odd chance I put an Andrena into the labellum, and saw what you describe as naturally taking place.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I cannot help but doubt a little the poisoning of bees, since bees would die from crossing from flower to flower to transfer pollen, if they were overtaxed to the point of exhaustion. The great Robert Brown maintains, however, that the nectar of <hi rend="underline">Asclepias</hi> poisons bees, and this supports your view.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> You do not mention the well adapted inward curvature of the edge of the opening into the labellum, which prevents insects from entering.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
        <p>Your observations on <hi rend="underline">Epipactis</hi> seem to me even more valuable. <hi rend="underline">E. viridiflora</hi> seems to be a similar case to <hi rend="underline">Cephalanthera</hi>, but it is apparent from the presence of nectar there, that insects occasionally carry pollen from plant to plant. Could you not try an experiment with the application of pollen of a different plant and of its own, and compare the contents of the capsules? I do not doubt that this species is generally self-fertilised; and I am aware that I erred in supposing that this happened to so few species.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Neottia nidus avis is often self-fertilised.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Epipactis latifolia I find is always fertilised by wasps (vespa)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> — — — —</p>
        <p>Yours very faithfully | Charles Darwin</p> 
    </div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The English parts of this letter, from a copy made for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Francis Darwin</ref>, were previously published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15; the German translation of some missing parts were later transcribed from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9069.xml">Krause 1884</ref>. For a translation of the German of the printed source, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">The English parts of this letter, from a copy made for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Francis Darwin</ref>, were previously published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15; the German translation of some missing parts were later transcribed from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9069.xml">Krause 1884</ref>. For a transcription of the German of the printed source, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The year is established by the reference, in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5605.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 15 August [1867]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15), to a letter from Hermann Müller containing observations on the fertilisation of orchids. Hermann began his work on orchids in the summer of 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>, 2: 111). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Müller’s letter has not been found (see n. 1, above). Müller published his observations, with two plates illustrating the reproductive morphology of the orchids mentioned, in ‘Beobachtungen an westfälischen Orchideen’ (Observations on Westphalian orchids; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml">H. Müller 1868</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 274–5, CD had speculated on the means by which flowers of <hi rend="italic">Cypripedium</hi> might be pollinated, concluding that an insect would have to insert its proboscis through one of two small openings above the lateral anthers.  <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray</ref> concluded, from observations of American species of <hi rend="italic">Cypripedium</hi>, that an insect would enter a flower through the large opening on the dorsal surface of the flower, then crawl out through one of the small openings above the anthers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 10–20 June [1862]</ref> and n. 16). Gray later published his observations in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3023.xml">A. Gray 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 230–1, CD described his experiment with a small bee of the genus <hi rend="italic">Adrena</hi> and referred to the observations of Gray and Müller (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4110.xml">letter to Asa Gray, 20 April [1863]</ref>). In the published version of his observations on Westphalian orchids, Müller described the fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Cypripedium calceolus</hi> (lady’s slipper), noting that the bee’s path through the flower necessitated its touching the stigma before the anthers, thus ensuring cross-fertilisation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml">H. Müller 1868</ref>, pp. 1–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml">H. Müller 1868</ref>, pp. 4–5, Müller described his observations and initial conclusion that the odour of the lady’s slipper orchid had killed the honey-bee. He added CD’s observation about the design of the rim of the labellum and concluded that the death of the honey-bees was due to the fact that they could not exit in the same manner as the smaller <hi rend="italic">Adrena</hi> bees, through the narrow posterior openings, and simply died of exhaustion. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_671.xml">Brown</ref> had written a paper, ‘On the organs and mode of fecundation in Orchideæ and Asclepiadeæ’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_982.xml">Brown 1831</ref>), but he did not mention his observation on the nectar of <hi rend="italic">Asclepias</hi> (milkweed).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his published paper, Müller described the inward curvature of the rim of the labellum (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml">H. Müller 1868</ref>, p. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Müller’s observations on <hi rend="italic">Epipactis viridiflora</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">E. purpurata</hi>, violet helleborine) were published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml">H. Müller 1868</ref>, pp. 7–10, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 102–3). Müller observed that the flower lacked a rostellum, which in most orchids separates the anther from the fertile stigma, and so was easily self-pollinated. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 358, CD had concluded that self-fertilisation in orchids was a ‘rare event’, but in the second edition he modified his view, acknowledging that some species were ‘regularly or often self-fertilised’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 290).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 290, CD included <hi rend="italic">Neottia nidus-avis</hi> (bird’s-nest orchid) among those species capable of self-fertilisation, but more often fertilised by insects.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Vespa</hi> is a genus in the family Vespidae (hornets, paper wasps, potter wasps, yellowjackets). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 101–2, CD noted that wasps were the only insects he had seen visiting <hi rend="italic">Epipactis latifolia</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">E. helleborine</hi>, broad-leaved helleborine). Müller cited CD’s letter informing him of this fact in his paper on Westphalian orchids (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5694.xml">H. Müller 1868</ref>, p. 12).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>