<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1679">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   8 May [1855]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">113</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1679 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1679.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1679.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 188</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 153</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 5: 326</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.113)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>113</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1855-05-08">8 May [1855]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Mentions his paper ["Transportal of erratic boulders", <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 218–27]. Discusses ice-borne rock. Reference to unpublished paper on icebergs [?"Power of icebergs to make grooves", <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 252–5]. Remarks on scoring by icebergs. Comments on judgment of theories by Geological Society.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">erratic boulders</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Collected papers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down.</placeName>
                    <date>May 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The notion you refer to was published in Geological Journal Vol IV (1848) p 315,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> with references to all the cases, which I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. collect of Boulders apparently higher than parent-rock.—</p>
<p>The argument of <hi rend="underline">probable</hi> proportion of rock dressed by <hi rend="underline">sea-ice</hi>, compared to <hi rend="underline">land</hi> glaciers, is new to me.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have often thought of the idea of viscosity &amp; enormous momentum of great icebergs &amp; still think that the notion, I pointed out in appendix to Ramsay’s Paper<ref target="#foot.f3"/> is probable &amp; can hardly help being applicable in some cases. I wonder whether the Phil. Journal w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. publish it, if I could get it from Ramsay or Geolog. Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. <ref target="#foot.f4"/> If you chance to meet Ramsay will you ask him whether he has it.— I think it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi> worth while just to call the N. American geologists’<ref target="#foot.f5"/> attention to the idea; but it is not worth any trouble, &amp; I am tremendously busy with all sorts of experiments.— By the way, Hopkins at the Geolog. Soc. <hi rend="underline">seemed</hi> to admit some truth in idea of scoring by (viscid) icebergs.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>If the Geolog. Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. takes so much to judge of truth of notions, as you were telling me in regard to Ramsay’s Permian glaciers,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> it will be as injurious to progress, as French Institute<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Ever your’s | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.7 <hi rend="italic">perhaps</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.8 idea;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon altered from colon</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.10 icebergs—] ‘—’ <hi rend="italic">after omitted point</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">A reference to CD’s paper, ‘Transportal of erratic boulders from a lower to a higher level’ (<hi rend="italic">Collected</hi> <hi rend="italic">papers</hi> 1: 218–19). Lyell was at this time investigating the possibility of a glacial period having occurred before the Pleistocene, as suggested by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay</ref> on the basis of fieldwork in Wales (Ramsay 1852 and 1855). Ramsay had described erratic boulders high up in the Welsh mountains as evidence for some glacial activity prior to the geological actions that left deposits of ‘drift’. CD, on the other hand, believed such boulders were contemporaneous with the drift and had indeed been transported to great heights by the agency of floating ice.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to Ramsay’s statement that ‘the peculiar forms, polish, and markings of many of the stones indicate that these characteristics have been produced by the agency of ice of the nature of glaciers, for mere coast-ice would have picked up and drifted away numerous rounded pebbles from the beach, and not a great majority of angular flattened stones, such as form the breccias wherever they occur.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6515.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1854</ref>, p. 200).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Probably a reference to Ramsay 1852, which was originally read at the Geological Society on 26 March 1851 and then withheld by Ramsay in order to revise his argument after a critical response (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2775.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geikie 1895</ref>, pp. 177–8). As published, the paper had no reference to any appendix by CD but contained matter which may well have once been supplemented by CD’s work on viscous icebergs (eventually published as a separate paper, see n. 5, below). Ramsay had argued that scratch marks on the rocks of Anglesea were due to floating ice, indicating that the land was then partially submerged. The scratches, however, ran counter to the line of the valleys, i.e., they indicated that the icebergs must have travelled transversely <hi rend="italic">across</hi> the valleys rather than along them (Ramsay 1852, p. 374). CD’s work on icebergs treated precisely this question and suggested that icebergs possessed a certain viscosity which made the bottom run closely over the sea bed and enabled currents to push them over irregularities of topography (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 252–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The <hi rend="italic">London, Edinburgh, and Dublin</hi> <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Magazine and Journal of Science</hi>, in which CD’s paper ‘On the power of icebergs to make rectilinear, uniformly-directed grooves across a submarine undulatory surface’ appeared in August 1855 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 252–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4061.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Barton Rogers</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Darwin Rogers</ref>. Lyell had also geologised with the Canadian <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1264.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John William Dawson</ref> on his second visit to America in 1852 (see K. M. Lyell ed. 1881, 2: 178–84).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In an earlier <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1518.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Lyell, 7 June [1853]</ref>, CD reported that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref> had supported the idea of plastic icebergs being driven in straight courses by their momentum.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Ramsay had presented his evidence for the existence of glaciers during the Permian period in a paper read to the Geological Society on 21 February 1855 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6516.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramsay 1855</ref>). Many geologists doubted the possibility of a cool period long before the Pleistocene because it contradicted widespread assumptions about the gradual cooling of the earth. The reception of Ramsay’s paper is described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2775.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geikie 1895</ref>, pp. 228–9: <quote> The subject had been rather laughed at by [Henry] De la Beche, who said, ‘As to the scratching of breccia fragments— “’tis their nature to”—a tumble-down house will give plenty of them; and then as to old localities for the fragments, independently of not having cakes which have been eaten, who the dickens, in such places, can say what rocks are beneath the sprawl of New Reds?’ Lyell, however, took a much more serious view of the matter, and with that eager enthusiasm so characteristic of him, threw himself into it, and endeavoured to master all the evidence.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">L’Institut de France, composed of five academies, one of which was the Académie des Sciences.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>