<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3383">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Thomas Henry Huxley   13 January 1862</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3384</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3383 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3383.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3383.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp damaged †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Huxley (1900) 1: 194</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 10: 15</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166.2: 290</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 290</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Jermyn St</placeName>
                <date when="1862-01-13">13 Jan 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Against all predictions his Edinburgh lecture was well received [<hi rend="italic">Evidence as to man’s place in nature</hi> (1863)].</p> 
            <p>Took his old line about problem of infertility of hybrids as a test of CD’s views.</p> 
<p>Report [from a newspaper] not quite right about what he said, but they have not refuted his statement that some form of progressive development theory is certainly true, nor that man and the apes come from same stock. Owen has gone in for progressive development in second edition of the <hi rend="italic">Palaeontology</hi> [1861].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">apes</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Evidence as to man’s place in nature</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Edinburgh</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Huxley, T. H. 1863a</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jermyn St</placeName>
                    <date>Jan 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1862</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In the first place a new years greeting to you &amp; yours— In the next I inclose this slip—(please return it when you have read it) to shew you what I have been doing in the North—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Everybody prophesied I should be stoned &amp; cast out of the city gate—but on the contrary I met with unmitigated applauses!!</p>
<p>Three cheers for the progress of liberal opinion!!</p>
<p>The Report is as good as any but they have not put quite rightly what I said about your views—respectg which I took my old line about the infertility difficulty—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Furthermore they have not reported my statement that whether you were right or wrong—some form of the progressive development theory is certainly true— Nor have they reported here my distinct statement that I believe Man &amp; the apes to have come from one stock.—</p>
<p>Having got this far I find the Lecture better reported in the “Courant” so I send you that instead<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I mean to publish the lectures in full by &amp; bye (about the time the Orchids comes out)<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I suppose somebody her〈e〉 told you that Owen has gone in for progressive development in the second Edition of the ‘Paleontology’ which can only be described as a rather more scoundrelly book than the first—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>The way I am ignored &amp; you are pooh-poohed is glorious<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Ever | Yours faithfully | T H Huxley</p>
<p>I deserved the greatest credit for 〈not〉 having made an onslaught on 〈Brewster〉 for his foolish impertinence 〈of y〉our views in ‘Good words’—<ref target="#foot.f7"/>but 〈declined〉 to stir Nationality—which you 〈know (in him)〉 is rather more than his Bible<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Huxley delivered two lectures under the title ‘Relation of man to the lower animals’ before the Philosophical Institution of Edinburgh on 4 and 7 January 1862, respectively. For an account of the lectures and their reception, see L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 192–4. The newspaper report of the lectures that Huxley initially intended sending has not been identified, since Huxley subsequently decided to send one from a different newspaper (see n. 3, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his review of <hi rend="italic">Origin,</hi> Huxley stated that a significant if inconclusive test of whether two individuals represented distinct ‘physiological’ species was to attempt to hybridise them, since distinct species would often either be infertile <hi rend="italic">inter se</hi> or produce infertile offspring, whereas varieties of the same species would give rise to fertile progeny (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[T. H. Huxley] 1860</ref>, pp. 552–5). The lack of any positive evidence ‘that any group of animals has, by variation and selective breeding, given rise to another group which was even in the least degree infertile with the first’ was, he argued, the weakest point in CD’s hypothesis of natural selection (<hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> pp. 567–8). Huxley expressed the same view in the published version of his Edinburgh lectures, stating that his acceptance of CD’s theory of natural selection was subject to proof that ‘physiological species may be produced by selective breeding’ (T. H. Huxley 1863a, p. 108).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Huxley refers to the report of his second lecture that appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi>, 11 January 1862 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix V); the enclosed copy has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The substance of Huxley’s Edinburgh lectures was published in T. H. Huxley 1863a, pp. 57–118. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> was published in May 1862 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1977</ref>, p. 112).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the first edition of his <hi rend="italic">Palæontology</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen’s</ref> critique of all existing hypotheses to account for the origin of species was followed by a paragraph outlining principles that, he claimed, ‘tended to impress upon the minds of the closest reasoners in Biology a conviction of a continuously operative secondary creative law’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6099.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">R. Owen 1860a</ref>, p. 407). In the second edition he expanded and emboldened this paragraph, heading it ‘Evidence of origin of species by secondary law’ (R. Owen 1861a, p. xvi) and stating (p. 444): ‘The inductive demonstration of the nature and mode of operation of such secondary continuously operative species-producing force will henceforth be the great aim of the philosophical naturalist’. Owen also changed the heading of another of the concluding sections of the volume from ‘Comparison of uniformitarian and progressional evidences’ to ‘Evidence of progress and advance in organisation’. He added a new paragraph to the section, stating (p. 449): <quote type="quote"> the sum of what is known [from the study of extinct forms] yields the legitimate deduction, that there has been a succession of species illustrating in the main the progressive perfection of the nervous system, and the concomitant predominance of mind over matter. </quote> There is a copy of the first edition of the work (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6099.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">R. Owen 1860a</ref>) in the Darwin Library–CUL, and of the second edition (R. Owen 1861a) in the Darwin Library–Down; both are lightly annotated (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 656).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In the second edition, Owen considerably reduced his already brief account of CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace’s</ref> theory, removing part of it to a footnote earlier in the text (R. Owen 1861a, pp. 442–3, 434–5 n.; compare <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6099.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">R. Owen 1860a</ref>, pp. 405–6). The limited nature of Owen’s response to natural selection in the first edition of his <hi rend="italic">Palæontology</hi> is discusssed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6790.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rupke 1994</ref>, pp. 242–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_893.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Brewster 1862</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The original letter is damaged. The words and letters in angle brackets have been taken from the text printed in L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 194.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>