<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8312">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Hermann Müller   [before 5 May 1872]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13556</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8312 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8312.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8312.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy and (encl) published translation</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">3pp (encl: published trans)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 96</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Krause 1884 (letter in German)</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 146: 433; DAR 194: 1; Krause ed. 1885–6, 2: 84–8</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>146: 433</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>194: 1</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Krause ed. 1885–6 2: 84–8</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1872-05-04">[before 5 May 1872]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Müller, H. L. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on HM’s paper ["Anwendung der Darwin’schen Lehre auf Bienen", <hi rend="italic">Verh. Naturhist. Ver. preuss. Rheinland</hi> 29 (1872): 1–96];</p> 
            <p>sexual selection in bees.</p> 
<p>Encloses account on habits of <hi rend="italic">Bombus</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bees</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Bombus</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Verh. Naturhist. Ver. preuss. Rheinland</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Müller, Hermann 1872</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">habit</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Beckenham, Kent</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have now read with the greatest interest your essay, which contains a vast amount of matter quite new to me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I really have no criticisms or suggestions to offer. The perfection of the gradation in the character of bees, especially in such important parts as the mouth-organs, was altogether unknown to me. You bring out all such facts very clearly by your comparison with the corresponding organs in the allied <hi rend="underline">hymenoptera</hi>. How very curious is the case of bees and wasps having acquired, independently of inheritance from a common source, the habit of building hexagonal cells and of producing sterile workers! But I have been most interested by your discussion on secondary sexual differences: I do not suppose so full an account of such differences in any other group of animals has ever been published.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It delights me to find that we have independently arrived at almost exactly the same conclusion with respect to the more important points deserving investigation, in relation to sexual selection. For instance, the relative number of the two sexes,—the earlier emergence of the males,<ref target="#foot.f4"/>—the laws of inheritance &amp;c. What an admirable illustration you give of the transference of characters, acquired by one sex, namely that of the male of <hi rend="underline">Bombus</hi> possessing the pollen-collecting apparatus.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Many of your facts about the differences between male and female bees are surprisingly parallel with those which occur with birds. The reading your essay has given me great confidence in the efficacy of sexual selection; and I wanted some encouragement as extremely few naturalists in England seem inclined to believe in it. I am, however, glad to find that Prof. Weismann has some faith in this principle.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>The males of <hi rend="underline">Bombus</hi> follow one remarkable habit, which I think it would interest you to investigate this coming summer; and no one could do it better than you. I have therefore enclosed a briefly and roughly drawn up account of this habit.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Should you succeed in making any observations on this subject, and if you would like to use in any way my M.S. you are perfectly welcome. I could, should you hereafter wish to make any use of the facts, give them in rather fuller detail; but I think that I have given enough.</p>
<p>I hope that you may long have health, leisure and inclination to do much more work as excellent as you recent essay.</p>
<p>Believe me, my dear Sir | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f8"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Über die Wege der Hummel-Männchen.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
<p>Am 8. September 1854 sah einer meiner Söhne einige Hummeln in eine Auszackung am Fusse des grossen Eschenbaumes (siehe den Plan)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> eintreten. Da ich ein Hummelnest darin zu finden hoffte, blickte ich hinein, konnte aber keine Höhlung sehen. Während dessen nahm eine andere Hummel ihren Eintritt in die Auszackung, kam fast unmittelbar wieder heraus, stieg am Stamm ungefähr eine Elle empor und flog durch eine Gabelung zwischen zwei grossen Zweigen hindurch. Ich entfernte darauf alle die Gräser und Pflanzen, welche in der Auszackung wuchsen, aber es war daselbst keine Höhle vorhanden. Nach einer oder zwei Minuten kam eine andere Hummel und brummte über dem nun von Pflanzen entblössten Boden, flog aufwärts und passierte gleich der vorigen Hummel durch die Gablung. In der Folge sah ich viele, welche jedesmal nach wenigen Minuten eintrafen, sämtlich in derselben Richtung kamen und sich alle in genau der nämlichen Weise benahmen, mit der Ausnahme, dass einige rings um den Stamm der grossen Esche, statt durch die Gablung flogen. Ich vergewisserte mich später, dass das alles Männchen der Gartenhummel (<hi rend="underline">Bombus hortorum</hi>) waren. An vielen darauffolgenden Tagen beobachtete ich ähnliche Thatsachen. Ich verfolgte die Hummeln von der grossen Esche bis zu einem kahlen Fleck an der Seite eines Grabens, woselbst sie stets brummten, dann weiter zu einem Epheublatt in einigen Ellen Entfernung, woselbst sie wiederum brummten. Ich will daher diese Stellen, woselbst sie für wenige Sekunden anhielten, “Brummplätze” nennen. Von dem Epheublatt stiegen sie in den trockenen Graben, in welchem eine dichte Hecke wuchs, hinab und flogen langsam längs des Grundes zwischen den dicht verwachsenen Dornsträuchen hindurch. Ich konnte sie längs dieses Grabens nur dadurch verfolgen, dass ich mehrere meiner Kinder veranlasste, hineinzukriechen und darin auf ihren Bäuchen zu liegen, aber in dieser Weise verfolgte ich ihre Spur ungefähr 25 Ellen weit. Sie kamen aus der Hecke stets durch dieselbe Öffnung in das offene Feld heraus und hier führten drei (in dem Plane durch punktierte Linien angedeutete) Wege auseinander, die so weit eingetragen sind, wie ich den Hummeln folgte. Sie brummten an vielen und stets an den nämlichen Stellen in der Entfernung weniger Ellen von einander auf allen ihren Wegen. Einer der Brummplätze war ein sehr seltsamer, da die Hummeln auf den Boden einer sehr dichten Hecke bis zur Tiefe einiger Fusse eindrangen, über einem abgestorbenen Blatte brummten und geradenwegs wieder zurückkehrten.</p>
<p>Ich verfolgte sodann die Flugbahn auf eine Entfernung von ungefähr 150 Ellen, bis sie zu dem grossen Eschenbaum kamen; längs dieser Linie brummten die Hummeln an vielen feststehenden Plätzen. An dem weiteren Ende, dicht bei der “gestutzten Eiche” teilte sich der Weg in zwei, wie im Plane angedeutet. An manchen Tagen flogen sämtliche Hummeln in der hier beschriebenen Richtung, an andern Tagen kamen einige in der entgegengesetzten Richtung daher. Nach der grossen, an günstigen Tagen beobachteten Zahl, die sämtlich in derselben Richtung zogen, müssen sie, denke ich, in einem grossen Zirkel fliegen. Sie halten mitunter an und saugen auf ihrer Reise an Blumen. Ich vergewisserte mich, dass sie, im währenden Fluge mit der Schnelligkeit von ungefähr zehn englischen Meilen in der Stunde fliegen, aber sie verlieren viel Zeit an ihren Brummplätzen. Die Wege bleiben für eine beträchtliche Zeit die nämlichen und die Brummplätze sind bis auf einen Zoll genau die gleichen. Um dies zu erweisen, will ich erwähnen, dass ich wiederholt fünf oder sechs meiner Kinder, jedes dicht bei einem Brummplatz aufstellte, und dem am meisten entfernten sagte, dass es, sobald eine Hummel dort brumme, schreien solle: “hier ist eine Biene”, und so auch die andren Kinder nacheinander, und die Worte: “hier ist eine Biene”, wurden von Kind zu Kind, ohne dass jemals eine Unterbrechung eintrat, überliefert, bis die Hummel an dem Brummplatze, woselbst ich stand, ankam.</p>
<p>Nach mehreren Tagen waren die Wege teilweise verändert; die Hummeln begannen nämlich am Fusse eines hohen, dünnen Dornbaums in einer der grossen Esche gegenüberliegenden Hecke zu brummen; sie flogen dann langsam und dicht an dem Stamme des Dornbaumes bis zu einer beträchtlichen Höhe empor, kreuzten über einen grossen Ast der Esche, woselbst sie brummten, und wurden aus dem Gesicht verloren, indem sie höher über den Eschenbaum emporflogen. Ich habe Dutzende von Hummeln an diesem besonderen Dornbaum emporsteigen sehen, sah aber niemals auch nur eine einzige herabkommen. Diese Gewohnheiten sind in verschiedenen Jahren von der Mitte des Juli bis zum Ende des Septembers beobachtet worden. Die Mitte eines warmen Tages ist für die Beobachtung am geeignetsten.</p>
<p>Ich habe nunmehr den seltsamsten Teil der ganzen Affaire hinzuzufügen. In mehreren aufeinanderfolgenden Jahren haben die Männchen nahezu dieselben Wege verfolgt, und haben an einigen, genau die gleichen gebliebenen, Plätzen gebrummt, z. B. in der Auszackung am Fusse der grossen Esche, und sind darauf durch dieselbe Gablung hinweggeflogen. Sie sind auch denselben trockenen Graben entlang gewandert und durch genau dieselbe kleine Öffnung am Ende der Hecke herausgekommen oder eingetreten, obwohl daselbst zahlreiche ähnliche Öffnungen vorhanden waren, welche ebensogut dazu hätten dienen können.</p>
<p>In dem einen Jahre sah ich Dutzende von Hummeln durch diese besondere Öffnung eintreten und den Boden des Grabens entlang bis zu dem grossen Eschenbaum fliegen. In einem zweiten Jahre besuchten die Hummeln hingegen den nämlichen, vorhin erwähnten Dornbaum und flogen daran empor, aber in einem anderen Jahre besuchten sie einen dicht dabei wachsenden Dornbaum. Zuerst war ich durch diese Thatsachen verwirrt und konnte nicht begreifen, wie diese während aufeinanderfolgender Jahre geborenen Hummeln möglicherweise dieselben Gewohnheiten erlernen könnten. Aber sie scheinen es vorzuziehen, längs der Hecken und Wege zu wandern und sie lieben es, am Fusse der Bäume zu brummen, so dass ich annehme, die nämlichen Wege und die gleichen Brummplätze seien in irgend einer Weise anziehend für die Species: worin aber dies Anziehende besteht, davon kann ich mir keinen Begriff machen. An vielen Brummplätzen ist durchaus nichts Bemerkenswertes vorhanden. Nachdem einer derselben häufig besucht worden ist, kann sein Aussehen, ohne dass die Besuche darum unterbrochen würden, gänzlich verändert werden. So bestreute ich den einen Fleck mit weissem Mehl und riss alles Gras und alle Pflanzen am Fusse der Esche aus, ohne irgend welchen Wechsel in den Besuchen herbeizuführen. Thatsächlich liegt keine grössere Schwierigkeit vor, zu verstehen, wie die Hummeln in aufeinanderfolgenden Jahren den nämlichen Wegen folgen und dieselben Brummplätze auswählen, als darin, zu begreifen, wie die Männchen desselben Nestes oder verschiedener Nester in demselben Bezirk, den nämlichen Wegen folgen und an den nämlichen Plätzen brummen, denn ich glaube, dass stets ein Männchen nach dem andern ausschlüpft und ich habe niemals auf ihren Wanderungen zwei in Gesellschaft gesehen. Auch bin ich niemals im stande gewesen, den Zweck dieser Gewohnheit, längs derselben Linie zu wandern und an denselben Plätzen zu brummen, womit sie viel Zeit verschwenden, zu ergründen. Ich habe nach Weibchen ausgeschaut, aber niemals eins auf den Wegen gesehen.</p>
<p>Die Männchen von <hi rend="underline">Bombus pratorum</hi> haben Brummplätze und benehmen sich in mancher Hinsicht den Männchen von <hi rend="underline">Bombus hortorum</hi> ähnlich; aber ihre Art und Weise zu wandern erscheint etwas verschieden. Während ich mich in Devonshire aufhielt, vergewisserte ich mich, dass die Männchen von <hi rend="underline">Bombus lucorum</hi> in gleicher Weise Brummplätze besuchen.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Herr J. Smith<ref target="#foot.f12"/> am Britishen Museum wusste nichts von dieser Gewohnheit, aber er verwies mich auf eine kurze Notiz über den Gegenstand von Col. Newman in den “<hi rend="underline">Transact. Entomol. Soc. of London (New Series Vol. I. part 6, 1851, p. 67)</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Ich habe stets bedauert, dass ich nicht mit Gummi ein Flöckchen Baumwolle oder Daunenfeder auf den Hummeln befestigt habe, weil es dann viel leichter gewesen wäre, ihnen nachzuspüren.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[SKETCH HERE]</p> </figure> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1"><hi rend="italic">Diagram</hi>: 21y] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘21 y’ </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
            <ab><ref target="#foot_trans.f8"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
                      
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="doubleUnderline">On the routes of the males of Bombus.</hi><ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
<p>On 8 September 1854 one of my sons saw a few humble-bees going into a hollow at the foot of a tall ash tree (see the diagram).<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Hoping to find a humble-bee nest inside, I looked in, but could not see any chamber. Meanwhile another humble-bee came out again almost immediately, climbed up the trunk about a yard and flew through a crutch between two tall branches. I removed all the grass and plants growing in the hollow, but there was no nest inside. After a minute or two another humble-bee arrived and buzzed over the ground which was now stripped of plants, flew forward and followed the other humble-bee through the crutch. Afterwards I saw many, which entered every time after a couple of minutes, all of whom came in the same direction and behaved in exactly the same way, except for some that flew around the trunk of the tall ash rather than through the crutch. I later confirmed that they were all males of the garden humble-bee (<hi rend="underline">Bombus hortorum</hi>). On several of the following days I observed similar facts. I followed the humble-bees from the tall ash up to a bare patch on the side of a ditch where they always buzzed, then further on to an ivy leaf about a couple of yards away, where they again buzzed. I will now refer to these places, where they stopped for a few seconds, as “buzzing places”. From the ivy leaf they climbed into the dry ditch, in which a thick hedge grew, and flew through slowly along the ground between the thickly overgrown briars. I could follow them along this ditch only by having several of my children crawl in and lie on their stomachs, but in this way I followed their trail for around 25 yards. They always came out of the hedge through the same opening into the open field and here I recorded three widely followed routes (indicated on the diagram by broken lines) that diverged as I followed the humble-bees. They buzzed a lot and always in those same places a few yards distant from one another on all of their routes. One of the buzzing places was very curious, for the humble-bees penetrated a couple of feet deep into the base of a very thick hedge, buzzed over a decayed leaf and directly turned back again.</p>
<p>I then followed the flight path for a distance of about 150 yards, until it arrived at the tall ash; the humble-bees buzzed at fixed spots along this route. At the farther end, near the “pollard oak” the route divided in two as indicated in the diagram. Some days all the bees flew in the direction just described, other days some came from the opposite direction. Based on the large number observed on favorable days, when all flew in the same direction, they must, I think, fly in a wide circle. They stop at times on their trip to suck at flowers. I confirmed that while in flight they moved at about ten English miles an hour, but they lose a lot of time at their buzzing places. The routes remain the same for a considerable time and the buzzing places are exactly the same to within an inch. In order to test this, I should mention, that I repeatedly stationed five or six of my children, each close to a buzzing place, and told the one farthest away to shout as soon a bee buzzed there: “here is a bee”, and so on with the other children one after another, the words “here is a bee” were passed on from child to child without interruption, until the bees reached the buzzing place where I myself was standing.</p>
<p>After a few days the routes changed slightly; the bees began to buzz at the base of a tall slender thorn tree in a hedge opposite the tall ash; they then flew slowly upwards, close to the trunk of the thorn tree, up to a considerable height, crossed over a large branch of the ash, where they buzzed, and were lost from view as they flew up higher over the ash tree. I saw scores of bees flying up this particular thorn tree, but never saw even one come down again. These circumstances were observed from the middle of July until the end of September for several years. The middle of a warm day is the best time for observation.</p>
<p>I have only to add the strangest part of the whole business. For many successive years the males followed almost the same routes and buzzed at some of the exact same places, e.g. in the hole at the foot of the tall ash, and afterwards always flew away through the same crutch. The also travelled along the same dry ditches and came out or went in through exactly the same small opening at the end of the hedge, although many similar openings were available, which could have served the purpose just as well.</p>
<p>In the first year I saw scores of bees entering this particular opening and flying along the bottom of the ditch to the tall ash. Whereas in the second year the bees visited the the thorn tree mentioned above and flew up from there, but in another year they visited a thorn tree growing nearby. At first I was perplexed by these facts and could not understand how these bees, born in successive years, could apparently learn the same habits. But they seem to prefer to fly along hedges and paths and they love to buzz at the foot of trees, so that I assume the same routes and the same buzzing places are in some way preferred by this species: but I cannot understand in what this attraction consists. In many buzzing places there is nothing particularly noteworthy. When one of these has been frequently visited, its appearance can be completely changed without interrupting the visits. So I sprinkled one spot with white flour and pulled up all the grass and plants at the foot of the ash, without any change at all in the visits being made. Actually nothing is more difficult to understand than how the bees in successive years choose the same routes and the same buzzing places, or than how the males from the same nest or a different nest in the same area follow the same routes and buzz in the same places, for I believe that males always hatch out one after another and I have never seen two travelling together. Also I have never been in a position to discover the purpose of this habit of going along the same route and buzzing in the same places, by which they lose a lot of time. I have looked out for females, but never seen one on the routes.</p>
<p>The males of <hi rend="underline">Bombus pratorum</hi> have buzzing places and behave in many ways like those of <hi rend="underline">Bombus hortorum</hi>; but their manner of travelling appears somewhat different. While I was staying in Devonshire, I confirmed that males of <hi rend="underline">Bombus lucorum</hi> visit buzzing places in the same way.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Mr J. Smith<ref target="#foot.f12"/> at the British Museum knew nothing about this habit, but he referred me to a short notice on the subject by Col. Newman in the “<hi rend="underline">Transact. Entomol. Soc. of London (New Series Vol. I. part 6, 1851, p. 67)</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>I have always been sorry that I did not stick a bit of cotton wool or down on the bees, for it would have been much easier to track them.</p>
              <p><figure><graphic url=""/></figure><ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
                </div>
        
    </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 5 May 1872</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">There is an annotated copy of Müller’s article ‘Anwendung der Darwin’schen Lehre auf Bienen’ (The application of Darwinian theory to bees; H. Müller 1872) in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 292, CD cited H. Müller 1872 for Müller’s conclusion that sexual differences in colour in some bee species were due mostly to sexual selection.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD cited H. Müller 1872 for Müller’s observations on the relative number of male and female bees, and the earlier emergence of the males from their cocoons, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 254.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 228, CD cited H. Müller 1872 for Müller’s observation that males of <hi rend="italic">Bombus</hi> had pollen-collecting apparatus like that of the females, although they did not collect pollen.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had received in February a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Weismann’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Ueber den Einfluss der Isolierung auf die Artbildung</hi> (On the influence of isolation on the formation of species; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1872</ref>); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8228.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to August Weismann, 29 February 1872</ref> and n. 3. For Weismann’s views on how sexual selection influences speciation, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1872</ref>, pp. 72–4. CD cited <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1872</ref> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 312, for his comment that the bright blue upper wing-surfaces of the male of a certain butterfly species, which were hidden when the butterfly was at rest, could not be protective.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The original enclosure has been lost; however, it concerned the paths taken by males of <hi rend="italic">Bombus</hi> (the humble-bee; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 5 May 1872</ref>). A German translation of the enclosure was published in 1886 (Krause ed. 1885–6, vol. 2), from the original, which was then among Müller’s papers (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2660.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1968</ref>, p. 179). An English translation of this German translation is in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2660.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1968</ref>, pp. 181–3. The German version is reproduced here, with a new translation back into English in Appendix I. CD’s original observations of bees following fixed routes, with fixed ‘buzzing places’, year after year, began in 1854. In 1876, Müller wrote to CD that he had not observed the ‘regular traveling in certain pathways’ that CD had reported (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-10631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 4 October 1876</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 10631).</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">For a translation of the enclosure, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix I. See also n. 7, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f8">For a transcription of this enclosure in the German of its printed source, and the letter that the original enclosure (now lost) was enclosed in, see pp. 182–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD’s original title was ‘On the routes of the males of Bombus’ (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 5 May 1872</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Bombus</hi> are humble-bees (bumble-bees).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">A reproduction of CD’s diagram was published with the German translation (Krause ed. 1885–6, vol. 2) and reproduced in English in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2660.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1968</ref>, p. 180. The diagram reproduced here is CD’s own drawing, now in the Darwin Archive–CUL (DAR 194.1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Bombus pratorum</hi> is the early bumblebee; <hi rend="italic">B. lucorum</hi> is the white-tailed bumblebee.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The reference is to Frederick Smith (the ‘J.’ was evidently an error in transcription).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Wenman Newman’s</ref> report on the habits of humble-bees was read at a meeting of the Entomological Society of London, 2 June 1851, and published the same year (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newman 1851</ref>). Newman wrote that each species had ‘its own peculiar mode of going its round, some near the ground, others through hedges, trees, shrubs, &amp;c.’ (p. 88). He noted that males made a round of visits to particular spots during the day (p. 91).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The diagram is reproduced at 50 per cent of its original size. See n. 10, above.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>