<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1016">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Daniel Sharpe   [1 November 1846]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1944</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1016 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1016.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1016.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp &amp; C</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 147: 471</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>De Beer (1958): 104;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 200</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 3: 360</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">The British Library (Add MS 37725: ff. 4–5)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Add MS 37725</collection>
                    <idno>ff. 4–5</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1846-11-01">[1 Nov 1846]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4311.xml">Sharpe, Daniel</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses foliation and cleavage. Comments on dip of cleavage laminae in mountains. Mentions views of Sedgwick and Studer. Suggests reading C. L. von Buch [<hi rend="italic">Travels through Norway and Lapland</hi> (1813)] "as an amusement". Praises views of William Hopkins. Suggests reading paper by H. D. Rogers ["On cleavage of slate-strata", <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh New Philos. J.</hi> 41 (1846): 422–3)]. Comments on the paper.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">cleavage</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">foliation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I have been much interested with your letter &amp; am delighted that you have thought my few remarks, worth attention. My observations on foliation are more deserving confidence than those on cleavage;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> for during my first year in clay-slate countries I was quite unaware of there being any marked difference between cleavage &amp; stratification; I well remember my astonishment at coming to the conclusion that they were totally different actions, &amp; my delight at subsequently reading Sedgwicks views;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> hence at that time I was only just getting out of a mist. With respect to cleavage-laminæ dipping inwards, on mountain-flanks I have certainly often observed it, so often that I thought myself justified in propounding it as usual; I might perhaps have been some degree prejudiced by Von Buch’s remarks,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> for which in those days I had a somewhat greater deference than I now have.— The mount at M. Video (p. 146 of my Book) is certainly an instance of the cleavage laminæ of an hornblendic schist dipping inwards on both sides; for I examined this hill <hi rend="underline">carefully</hi> with compass in hand &amp; note book. I <hi rend="underline">entirely</hi> admit, however, that a conclusion drawn from striking a rough balance in one’s mind, is worth <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>, compared with the evidence drawn from one <hi rend="underline">continuous</hi> line of section. I read Studer’s Papers carefully &amp; drew the conclusion stated, from it;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> but I may very likely be in an error. I only state that I have “<hi rend="underline">frequently</hi>” seen cleavage-laminæ dipping inwards on mountain-sides; that I cannot give up, but I daresay a general extension of the rule, (as might justly be inferred from the manner of my statement) would be quite erroneous.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Von Buch’s statement is in his Travels in Norway; I have unfortunately lost the reference &amp; it is a high crime, I confess, ever to refer to an opinion, without a precise reference. If you never read these Travels, they might be worth skimming, chiefly as an <hi rend="underline">amusement</hi>; &amp; if you like, &amp; will send me a line by the Gen. Post on Monday or Tuesday, I will either send it up with Hopkins on Wednesday, or bring it myself to Geolog. Soc. I am very glad you are going to read Hopkins;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> his views appear to me <hi rend="underline">eminently</hi> worth well comprehending: false views &amp; language appear to me to be almost universally held by geologists on the formation of fissures, dikes &amp; mountain-chains. If you would have the patience, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be glad if you w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. read in my “Volcanic Islands” from page 65, or <hi rend="underline">even 54</hi> to 72, viz on the lamination of volcanic rocks: I may add that I sent the series of specimens there described to Prof. Forbes of Edinburgh, &amp; he thought they bore out my views.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>There is a short extract from Prof. Rogers’ in the last Eding. New Phil. Journ. well worth your attention on the cleavage of the Appalachian Chain,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; which seems far more uniform in direction of dip, than in any case, which I have met with: the Rogers’ doctrine of the ridges being thrown up by great waves I believe is monstrous; but the manner in which the ridges have been thrown over (as if by a lateral force acting on one side on a higher level than on the other) very curious, &amp; he now states that the cleavage is 〈parallel〉<ref target="#foot.f9"/> to the axis-plane of these thrown over ridges.— Your case of the limestone beds to my mind is the greatest difficulty on any mechanical doctrine; though I did not expect ever to find actual displacement, as seems to be proved by your shell-evidence.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I am extremely glad you have taken up this <hi rend="underline">most</hi> interesting subject in such a philosophical spirit; I have no doubt you will do much in it;—Sedgwick let a fine opportunity slip away.— I hope you will get out another section like that in your letter; these are the real things wanted.</p>
<p>Believe me Yours very sincerely | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 quite] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘employed’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.8 on mountain-flanks] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.9 observed it,] ‘it,’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.10 usual] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘common’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.14 with compass in hand &amp; note book] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.20 (as might … statement) 1.21] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.3 precise] ‘r’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.4 Post on] ‘on’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘of’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.5 Monday or] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.7 the axis-plane of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">3.8 ridges] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘planes’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, pp. 162–8. In a paper read to the Geological Society on 2 December 1846, Sharpe referred to CD’s views (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7131.xml">Sharpe 1847</ref>, p. 105). During the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage, and afterwards while he was working on the geology of South America, CD summarized his observations on cleavage and stratification, see DAR 41.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7072.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sedgwick 1835</ref>, especially pp. 469–75.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Buch 1813</ref>. A copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7527.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Studer 1842</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref> (p. 164 n.) CD refers to only this paper by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4602.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bernhard Studer</ref>. The source is erroneously given as volume twenty-three instead of volume thirty-three of the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</hi> (April–October 1842).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD’s discussion of inwardly dipping cleavage planes, in which he cited <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Buch 1813</ref>, p. 169, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7527.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Studer 1842</ref>, is in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 164. CD’s statement there is slightly different: ‘On the flanks of the mountains both in Tierra del Fuego and in other countries, I have observed that the cleavage-planes frequently dip at a high angle inwards’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7131.xml">Sharpe 1847</ref>, p. 100, cites three publications by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref>: <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3844.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hopkins 1836</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3847.xml">1838</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3851.xml">1845–56</ref>. It is probably Hopkins 1838 that is referred to here.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See letters to J. D. Forbes, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-781.xml" resp="#automat">11 October [1844]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-790.xml" resp="#automat">13 [November 1844]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6697.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. D. Rogers 1846</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The word ‘parallel’ has been added in pencil over a repair to the manuscript. It is not in CD’s hand.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7131.xml">Sharpe 1847</ref>, pp. 75–87. CD cited Sharpe on this point in his article on geology (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 237) for the Admiralty <hi rend="italic">Manual of scientific enquiry</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3596.xml">Herschel ed. 1849</ref>): <quote> Fossil shells have been found by Mr. Sharpe in slaty rocks, which have had their shapes greatly altered, and all in the same direction; here then we have a guide to judge of the amount and direction of the mechanical displacement which the surrounding slate-rocks have undergone.</quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>