<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11739">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. J. Sulivan   7 November 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10837</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11739 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11739.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11739.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">AL incomplete?</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="AL">inc?</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 307</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 307</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml">Sulivan, B. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                <date when="1878-11-07">7 Nov 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Explains the occurrence of cattle on the Fuegian islands.</p>
            <p>Discusses intentions with regard to missionary stations and steamers in the area.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cattle</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Fuegian islands</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Tierra del Fuego</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">steamers</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">missionary stations</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>B.</placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 7.78</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am glad to hear so good an account of yourself—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> As to the cattle I believe there is grass land here and there, and especially in Navarin Island.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In some of the coves near E end of Beagle channel good land with some pasture inside has been found. and as guanacoes were always found on that Island I think it would probably feed numbers of cattle. At the Station there is clear feeding land in parts of the small peninsula and at Gable <hi rend="underline">Island</hi>—which on the chart is made a peninsula—there is much clear pasture land where natives alone are taking care of mission cattle which will keep a herd up for supplying native wants when Falkland Island Station is given up. This we hope to before long as there is now a better station for communication and supplies at Sandy Point with frequent steam communication to East and west coast. &amp; we look forward to replacing our Jawl with a large Steam launch or small Steam vessel, with a native crew except master &amp; engineer, which would connect Beagle Channel, through Western passages, with Sandy point. and with stations we hope to have opposite near Useless Bay when that fine tribe are made friendly. all that north &amp; NE coast would be a fine Cattle country—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Gable Island is the peninsula marked in the chart on the North shore at East entrance to Beagle channel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
 
 
 <div type="footnotes">
     <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11736.xml">letter to B. J. Sulivan, 5 November [1878]</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had been surprised at accounts of successful cattle-rearing in Tierra del Fuego (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11734.xml">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 3 November 1878</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11736.xml">letter to B. J. Sulivan, 5 November [1878]</ref>). Navarino Island (Isla Navarino) is a large island south of the Beagle Channel.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f3">Sulivan was a supporter of the Anglican mission station at Ushuaia, Tierra del Fuego, Patagonia (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11734.xml">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 3 November 1878</ref> and n. 1). Gable Island (Isla Gable) is a small island close to the north shore of the Beagle Channel, opposite the east end of Navarino Island. Sandy Point (Punta Arenas) in Patagonia is at the mid-point of the north shore of the Strait of Magellan.</note>
 </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>