<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5077F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. C. Watson to J. D. Hooker   1 January 186[8]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21280</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5077F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5077F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5077F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Directors’ Correspondence 105 f. 222</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <collection>DC</collection>
                    <idno>105 f. 222</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4975.xml">Watson, H. C</persName>
                <date when="1868-01-01">1 Jan 186[8]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>HCW’s criticisms of CD’s theory.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Thames Ditton</placeName>
                    <date>Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 1 6[8]</date>
                    <salute>My dear Hooker</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Thank you for the name of Cyathea affinis, &amp; the determination to have it raised; the spores being of this year give likelihood.</p>
<p>As to Vicia Daunesiana, which is only a sug. name, &amp; not well merited, possibly one of my plants may flower next summer.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> They are weakly, having been almost lost through the sharp frosts of Epsom race-week,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> just previous to which they had been turned into the open ground from a frame.</p>
<p>How provoking to receive the Kerguelen cabbage in its dead state!<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I suppose that plants of cold climes encounter the chance of the sun converting the cases into ovens on shipboard.</p>
<p>Glad to receive your good report of Mr. Darwin’s health. I have read nothing about Darwinism since his 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. edition came out,—but thought of his theory pretty often.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> My conviction is nearly complete, either that there is a something fallacious to be eliminated from it, or else a something important to be added to it. By what process of divergent variation can you conceive your two S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Helena Umbellifers to have come into existence, so similar in characters usually looked to for distinguishing species (foliage etc) and yet so dissimilar in those resorted to for genera?<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If our technical classifications in botany &amp; zoology refuse to harmonize with the Darwinian theory, one or other must be thoroughly unsound. My present notion is, that divergent variation is just one half of the story, and that Darwin has missed the other half, its counterbalance in nature. When anyone equally fit shall have taken like pains to shew &amp; establish the alternate half, the theory will stand firm on two legs, instead of tottering upon one only, unable to go back, or to go forward, without a fatal fall,—a reductio ad absurdum.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>All this you will think very impudent &amp; presumptious in me— But there was a date when <hi rend="underline">you</hi> declared believers in the mutability of species, to be “superficial naturalists”;—on reading which, in Flora Indica, I resolved to remind you of it some future day!<ref target="#foot.f8"/> You don’t think them <hi rend="underline">all</hi> such now!— And so we all live to learn and change.</p>
<p>With very good wishes for the date, Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> first— | Yours sincerely | Hewett C. Watson</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 6 January [1868]</ref>. The letter was forwarded to CD by Hooker, and may have been enclosed in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5789.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [before 6 January 1868?]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Vicia</hi> is a broad-bean genus. Watson’s suggested species name, ‘Daunesiana’, was never published.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Watson refers to the Derby, a horse-race held annually in May or early June on Epsom Downs, Surrey (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6375.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office directory of the six home counties</hi></ref> 1868). In 1867, the event was held on 22 May (<hi rend="italic">Annual Register</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Kerguelen cabbage (<hi rend="italic">Pringlea antiscorbutica</hi>) was found on Kerguelen island in the south Indian Ocean on the voyage of the <hi rend="italic">Erebus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Terror</hi> from 1839 to 1844; it was described by Hooker in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3746.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Hooker 1844–7</ref>, pp. 239–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> was published in 1860.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Hooker had described the two Umbelliferae as <hi rend="italic">Sium helenianum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lichtensteinia burchellii</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3798.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Hooker 1867–91</ref>, 1: 23–5). Hooker noted that the similarity between the species was ‘in many respects striking’, but that <hi rend="italic">L. burchellii</hi> departed from the generic character in the petals (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 25). The two species are now placed in the same genus: <hi rend="italic">S. helenianum</hi> (jellico) and <hi rend="italic">S. burchellii</hi> (dwarf jellico).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Watson had previously argued that indefinite divergence of species without a ‘counter-action in nature’ was inconceivable and absurd (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2636.xml" resp="#automat">letter from H. C. Watson, [3? January 1860]</ref>). For further correspondence between Watson and CD on divergence and convergence of species, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2639.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. C. Watson, [5–11 January 1860]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2793.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. C. Watson, 10 May 1860</ref>; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3041A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. C. Watson to J. D. Hooker, 4 January 1861</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The passage appears in J. D. Hooker and Thomson 1855, p. 20: ‘It cannot be doubted that the general acceptance which the doctrine of the mutability of species has met with amongst superficial naturalists, has originated in a reaction from early impressions of the absolute fixity of characters.’ Watson had declared his belief in the transmutation of species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Watson 1845</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Watson 1847–59</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6471.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 24 November 1868</ref> and n. 2.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>