<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9223">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Fritz Müller   1 January 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1700</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9223 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9223.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9223.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">3pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 457a</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 359</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Loan MS 10 no 36)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Loan MS 10</collection>
                    <idno>36</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1874-01-01">1 Jan 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for two pamphlets.</p> 
<p>Sends Thomas Belt’s [<hi rend="italic">The naturalist in Nicaragua</hi> (1874)], "the best Nat. Hist. book of travels ever published".</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">The naturalist in Nicaragua</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Belt, Thomas 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Jan 1. 1874</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>No doubt I owe to your kindness two pamphlets received a few days ago, which have interested me in an extraordinary degree.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It is quite new to me what you shew about the effects of relationship in hybrids; that is to say, as far as direct proof is concerned. I felt hardly any doubt on the subject, from the fact of hybrids becoming more fertile when grown in numbers in nursery gardens, exactly the reverse of what occurred with Gärtner.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The paper on Termites is even still more interesting, &amp; the analogy with Cleistogene flowers is wonderful.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The manner in which you refer to my chapter on crossing is one of the most elegant compliments which I have ever received.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I have directed to be sent to you Belt’s Nicuaragua, which seems to me the best Nat. Hist. book of travels ever published.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Pray look to what he says about the leaf-carrying ants storing the leaves up in a minced state to generate mycelium, on which he supposes that the larvæ feed.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Now could you open the stomachs of these ants &amp; examine the contents so as to prove or disprove this remarkable hypothesis?</p>
<p>With hearty admiration of all that you publish, I remain | my dear Sir | yours sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Müller had sent copies of his papers ‘Bestaubungsversuche an Abutilon-Arten’ (Pollination experiments on <hi rend="italic">Abutilon</hi> species; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5679.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1871–3</ref>), and the first part of ‘Beiträge zur Kenntniss der Termiten’ (Contributions to the understanding of termites; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1873–5</ref>). CD’s annotated copies are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Müller began experiments to study the fertility of crosses in species of <hi rend="italic">Abutilon</hi> (Indian mallow) in 1869 and reported his initial results to CD in a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6943.xml">letter of 18 October 1869</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5679.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1871–3</ref>, pp. 29–30, Müller criticised <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Friedrich von Gärtner’s</ref> conclusions on the fertility of hybrids, noting that Gärtner had made both theoretical and methodological errors. In his heavily annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2736.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gärtner 1849</ref>, CD had also noted flaws in Gärtner’s experimental design and pointed out theoretical errors in his discussion of hybrid fertility (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 267–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the first part of his study of termites (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1873–5</ref>, pp. 333–9), Müller had described two sexual forms of both male and female termites in a newly discovered species <hi rend="italic">Calotermes canellae</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Glyptotermes canellae</hi>). Winged forms had well-developed genitalia, while soldiers of both sexes had smaller, rudimentary organs. Cleistogamic flowers are modified forms in which the flower never opens and only self-fertilisation is possible. CD discussed cleistogamy in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 310–45.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5679.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1871–3</ref>, p. 450, Müller noted that Gärtner’s observation about fertile hybrids losing their fertility over subsequent generations was cited by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1668.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Marie Jean Pierre Flourens</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2554.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Flourens 1864</ref>, p. 101) as proof of a sharp division between species and varieties. Müller contrasted Flourens’s conclusion with CD’s observation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 295: <quote type="quotation"> Darwin hat bereits mit gewohntem Scharfblick die Vermuthung ausgesprochen, dass diese vielfach beobachtete Abnahme der Fruchtbarkeit Folge sei nicht der Bastardnatur, sondern zu enger Inzucht und freue mich in den hier mitgetheilten Beispielen verminderter Fruchtbarkeit und völliger Unfruchtbarkeit als Folge zu enger Inzucht bei Abutilon-Bastarden einen neuen Beleg für die Richtigkeit der Vermuthung Darwin’s bieten zu können. [With his usual perspicacity, Darwin has already argued that this frequently observed decrease of fertility is the result not of hybridity, but of too close inbreeding, and I am happy to be able to offer a new proof of the correctness of Darwin’s contention in the examples presented here of reduced fertility and complete sterility as the result of too close inbreeding in <hi rend="italic">Abutilon</hi> hybrids.] </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Belt’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">The naturalist in Nicaragua</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_533.xml">Belt 1874</ref>) was published in December 1873 (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ circular</hi>, 18 December 1873, p. 1062).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Belt described chambers in the ant nest filled with a spongy substance, which, he discovered, was composed of a minute white fungus growing on small pieces of leaves. He also observed deserted chambers filled with refuse leaf particles and hypothesised that the ants ate not the leaves, but the fungus (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_533.xml">Belt 1874</ref>, pp. 80–1).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>