<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11953">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. A. Wheler   25 March 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19461</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11953 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11953.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11953.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 210.14: 16</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>210.14: 16</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5088.xml">Wheler, E. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Leamington</placeName>
                <date when="1879-03-25">25 Mar 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Regrets she has none of Dr Erasmus Darwin’s letters. Relates some anecdotes concerning her grandfather.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-28" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-19" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-20" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-07-20" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>3 Bertie Terrace Leamington</placeName>
                    <date>25 M<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>. 1879</date>
                    <salute>My dear Cousin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Francis has sent your letter to me, &amp; I am <hi rend="underline">very</hi> glad you are going to add a preface to my g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father Darwin’s life &amp; undo Miss Seward &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Schimmelpenigs untrue remarks.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> How pleased my dear Mother would have been, had she been living!<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>I have no letters, &amp; fear I can help you but little. Reginald Darwin must have several, &amp; I should think Keir Moilliet Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>. Cheyney court, Bishops Frome. Bromyard, would have many, written to his g<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> grandfather, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Keir, who was one of the Lunar Society.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Also Lord Belper must have some written to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Strutt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>My Mother always spoke of her Father with the utmost reverence &amp; affection, his refined &amp; agreeable manner &amp; his kindness to his children. He had no teeth in his head, &amp; was very fond of milk &amp; any thing made of milk cream cheese &amp; such like, but I am sure my Mother would have been shocked at M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Schimmelpenigs account of his <hi rend="underline">greediness</hi>, &amp; would have contradicted it at once. He stammered very much. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Edgeworth in his life speaks of my grandfather in a very gratifying way, &amp; corroborates much my mother has told us of him.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The letter he was writing when he was taken ill &amp; died, was to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Edgeworth. I can tell you a few anecdotes which may amuse you, tho’ I fear of no other use. </p>
                    <p>My grandfather M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Galton who had the <hi rend="underline">highest</hi> opinion of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin in <hi rend="underline">every</hi> way, requested him to go to Margate to see his eldest Daughter who was ill.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> He went, &amp; on his way slept at Newmarket where the races were going on, the Inn very full &amp; noisy. In the middle of the night he heard his door open softly, &amp; a man entered, came to his bedside &amp; made him a sign to be silent. He then said “D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin I am the Jockey who is to ride the favourite Horse tomorrow, &amp; upon whom large bets are laid, you once saved my wife’s life when very ill with a fever, &amp; I can now shew you my gratitude, make any bets you please against the favourite Horse, for we Jockies have settled he shall not win. My g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father thanked the man &amp; requested him to leave the room. He continued his journey to Margate the next day, &amp; on his return thro’ Newmarket he asked which Horse had won, &amp; was told that, to the surprise of everyone, the Horse that was thought sure to win, &amp; on whom thousands had been bet, had failed just at the last, &amp; come in third or fourth.</p>
                    <p>Another time D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D. was riding on a lonely road to Nottingham to see a Patient late in the Even.<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>. A suspicious looking man rode past him, &amp; then went slowly for D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D to pass him. This happened once or twice. At last D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D said “A fine Even.<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> Sir” or something of that sort. The man made a short reply &amp; rode away. The next day a man was taken up on that very spot for robbing some Traveller. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D. had the curiosity to go to the prison &amp; found it was the very man who had passed him the day before. &amp; on asking why he had not robbed him the man replied “I had intended to do so, but thought it was you, &amp; when you spoke I was sure. you saved my life many years ago, &amp; nothing would induce me to rob you.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>My g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father used to drive in his “Sulky” &amp; an old Horse “Doctor” used to follow behind with a saddle on, without being fastened in any way, &amp; when the road was too bad for the carriage, he got out &amp; rode upon Doctor. This Horse lived to a great age &amp; was buried at the Priory.”</p>
                    <p>When my g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father was a young man he &amp; his three Brothers all went to Cambridge at the same time—a great expense to their Father. These young men lived as carefully as they could, They each attended different Lectures &amp; then repeated them to their Brothers. They also mended their own clothes &amp; my g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father often boasted to my mother that if she cut the heel out of a stocking he could put a new one in without missing a stitch.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>Last year some alterations were made in Breadsall Church &amp; the Darwin coffins were exposed<ref target="#foot.f9"/>   My g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father’s coffin had burst open &amp; his remains were visible &amp; in perfect preservation   He was dressed in a purple velvet dressing gown &amp; his features unchanged.</p>
                    <p>One more anecdote I have heard my Mother tell. When my g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>Father took his son (your Father)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> to settle him at Shrewsbury, when taking leave of him he remembered he had forgotten to give him any money. He gave him £20 which was all he had about him &amp; said, “Let me know when you want more &amp; I will send it to you” your Father got into practice immediately &amp; never wrote to his Father for more money.—</p>
                    <p>M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Schimmelpening was my Aunt. She had the unfortunate habit of distorting what was true &amp; making a false impression on those about her. &amp; this is very evident in what she says of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin. My g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>father &amp; g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>mother M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Galton had the <hi rend="underline">highest</hi> respect &amp; estime for D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin &amp; thought him perfect in every way. The two families were very intimate with each other   Both my g<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>fathers belonged to the Lunar Society.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                    <p>I hope you are well &amp; with kind remembrances to your wife &amp; Daughter<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Believe me | y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. very truly, | Eliz<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Anne Wheler</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 Francis … M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Strutt. 2.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 My grandfather M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Galton] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.2 These young men … stitch. 7.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi>; ‘1878’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11947.xml">letter to Francis Galton, 22 March 1879</ref> and nn. 2 and 5; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4209.xml">Mary Anne Schimmelpenninck</ref> was Wheler’s aunt. Her remarks on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> were made in her autobiography (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10569.xml">Hankin ed. 1858</ref>). CD’s long introduction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> (a translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Krause’s</ref> revised version of his essay, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>) contradicted <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref>’s negative portrayal of Erasmus Darwin in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1796.xml">Violetta Galton</ref> was a daughter of Erasmus Darwin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1236.xml">Reginald Darwin</ref> was a grandson of Erasmus Darwin. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8395.xml">James Keir Moilliet</ref> was a great-grandson of Erasmus Darwin and also of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8440.xml">James Keir</ref>. Darwin and Keir had met as medical students at Edinburgh and became lifelong friends (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref> s.v. Keir, James). They were members of the Lunar Society of Birmingham, a small club of pioneering natural philosophers, doctors, and manufacturers (for more on the Lunar Society, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6963.xml">Schofield 1963</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10674.xml">Uglow 2002</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8396.xml">Edward Strutt</ref>, first Baron Belper, was the son of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8397.xml">William Strutt</ref>, who, with Erasmus Darwin, was a founder member of the Derby Philosophical Society (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref> s.v. Strutt, Jedediah).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For Schimmelpenninck’s remarks about Erasmus’s gluttony, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11947.xml">letter to Francis Galton, 22 March 1879</ref> and n. 5. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8398.xml">Richard Lovell Edgeworth</ref> had mentioned Erasmus Darwin frequently in his memoirs, describing him as intelligent and benevolent (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10685.xml">R. Edgeworth and Edgeworth 1820</ref>, 1: 164).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Wheler’s paternal grandfather was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1801.xml">Samuel Galton</ref>; Galton’s eldest daughter was the future <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4209.xml">Mary Anne Schimmelpenninck</ref>. Margate, a town on the Isle of Thanet in north-east Kent, was a popular seaside resort for convalescents (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8169.xml">Walton 1983</ref>, pp. 11–20).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Both the story of the jockey’s tip and the story of the robber were included in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 63–5. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Erasmus Darwin and his brother <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8437.xml">John Darwin</ref> matriculated at Cambridge in June 1750; their eldest brother, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1235.xml">Robert Waring Darwin</ref> (1724–1816), had matriculated in 1743 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml">King-Hele 1999</ref>, p. 10). CD included the stocking anecdote in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Erasmus Darwin was buried at All Saints’ Church, Breadsall, under the nave floor; alterations to the church were carried out in 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10686.xml">Redman 2005</ref>, p. 369).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin</ref> (1766–1848).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1801.xml">Samuel Galton</ref> and Erasmus Darwin were both members of the Lunar Society (see also n. 3, above); Galton’s wife was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8400.xml">Lucy Galton</ref>. Wheler later recalled the anecdotes in this letter in her manuscript memoir, which she wrote in 1905 at the age of 97 (CUL MS Add.8691, pp. 5, 12–14).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1217.xml">Elizabeth Darwin</ref>.</note>
        </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>