<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7011">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To George Bentham   25 November [1869]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">12038</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7011 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7011.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7011.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 143: 106</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 379; <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 43 (1891): 535 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Bentham Correspondence, Vol. 3, Daintree–Dyer, 1830–1884, GEB/1/3: ff. 678–9)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <collection>Bentham, George letters</collection>
                    <idno>GEB/1/3: ff. 678–9</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1869-11-25">25 Nov [1869]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml">Bentham, George</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD finds GB’s address interesting; assures him that he has never said GB was wrong on any point, but that there were differences between them, which he now thinks are not great.</p> 
<p>Comments on specific parts of the address [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">6793</hi>]: colonisation, variability of large and small genera, descent from a single parent or pair of parents, rapid multiplication and change in species, isolation.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">introduced forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">multiple origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">naturalisation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number of species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down.</hi> | Beckenham | <hi rend="print">Kent. S.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 25</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bentham</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was greatly interested by your address, which I have now read thrice, &amp; which I believe will have much influence on all who read it. But you are mistaken in thinking that I ever said you were wrong on any point. All that I meant was that on certain points, &amp; these very doubtful points, I was inclined and had to differ from you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> And now, on further considering the point, on which even 2 or 3 months ago I felt most inclined to differ, viz on isolation,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I find I differ very little. What I have to say is <hi rend="underline">really</hi> not worth saying, but as I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be very sorry not to do whatever you asked, I will scribble down the slightly dissentient thoughts which have occurred to me. It w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be an endless job to specify the points in which you have interested me; but I may just mention the relation of the extreme W. flora of Europe (some such very vague thoughts have crossed my mind, relating to the Glacial period) with S. Africa<ref target="#foot.f4"/>—&amp; your remarks on the contrast of passive &amp; active distribution.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>p. Lxx. I think the contingency of a rising isl<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>, not as yet fully stocked with plants, ought always to be kept in mind, when speaking of colonisation.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>p. Lxxiv. I have met with nothing which makes me in the least doubt, that large genera present a greater number of vars. relatively to their size, than do small genera.— Hooker was formerly convinced by my data, never as yet published in full, only abstracted in the Origin.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>p. Lxxviii.— I dispute whether a new race or species is necessarily, or even generally, descended from a single or pair of parents: the whole body of individuals, I believe, becomes altered together—like our race-horses, and like all domestic breeds which are changed through “unconscious selection” by man.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>p. d<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. When such great lengths of time are considered, as are necessary to change a specific form, I greatly doubt whether more or less rapid powers of multiplication have more than the most insignificant weight.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> These powers, I think, are chiefly related to greater or less destruction in early life.</p>
<p>p. Lxxix. I still think you rather underrate the importance of isolation. I have come to think it very important from various grounds; the anomalous and quasi-extinct forms on islands &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> With respect to areas with numerous “individually durable” forms, can it be said that they generally present a “broken” surface with “impassible barriers”? This no doubt is true in certain cases, as Teneriffe.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> But does this hold with S.W. Australia and the Cape? I much doubt. I have been accustomed to look at the cause of so many forms, as being partly an arid or dry climate (as De Candolle insists) which indirectly leads to diversified conditions, and, secondly to isolation from the rest of the world during a very long period, so that other more dominant forms have not entered, and there has been ample time for much specification and adaptation of character.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Lxxx.— I suppose you think that the Restiaceae, Proteaceae, etc. etc. once extended over the world, leaving fragments in the South.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>You in several places speak of distribution of plants, as if exclusively governed by soil and climate: I know that you do not mean this, but I regret whenever a chance is omitted of pointing out that the struggle with other plants (and hostile animals) is far more important.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I told you that I had nothing worth saying, but I have given you my <hi rend="underline">thoughts</hi>.</p>
<p>How detestable are the Roman numerals. why should not the President’s addresses, which are often, &amp; I am sure in this case, worth more than all the rest of the Number, be paged with Christian figures?—</p>
<p>My dear Mr. Bentham | Your’s very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 Beckenham] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘<hi rend="italic">Bromley.</hi>’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.3 that] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.5 further] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.8 slightly dissentient] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.10 (some … period) 1.11] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.1 fully] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.4 greater or less] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n8">6.5 This is… But 6.6] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n9">6.6 does] ‘d’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘D’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n10">6.7 partly] <hi rend="italic">over del</hi> ‘partly’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n11">6.7 arid or dry] <hi rend="italic">over del illeg</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7005.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Bentham, 23 November 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For CD’s comments on Bentham 1869b, see the letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6793.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 June [1869]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">13 November [1869]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6793.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 22 June [1869]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See Bentham 1869b, p. lxxxvii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See Bentham 1869b, pp. xcv–xcvi.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 466–7 and 472.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD discussed the greater number of varieties in large genera (genera containing many species) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 55–6. In Bentham 1869b, p. lxxiv, Bentham suggested that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker’s</ref> similar opinion expressed in <hi rend="italic">On the flora of Australia, its origin, affinities, and distribution; being an introductory essay to the flora of Tasmania</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Hooker 1859</ref>) had probably since changed.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 355–6. CD discussed ‘unconscious selection’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 34–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 302–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD discussed the role of isolation, including isolation on islands, in forming new species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 104–7. CD made some additions to this section in the fifth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>; see Peckham ed. 1959, p. 196.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">For contemporary knowledge of the botany of Tenerife, one of the Canary Islands, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1068.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. J. F. Bunbury 1855</ref>; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD refers to south-western Australia and the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alphonse de Candolle</ref> referred to isolation in dry climates several times in <hi rend="italic">Géographie botanique raisonnée</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1195.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. de Candolle 1855</ref>); see, for example, vol. 1, p. 562.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Bentham mentioned these and additional names of southern hemisphere families in Bentham 1869b, p. lxxiii, in reference to possible ancient connections between their representatives in South Africa and Australia. Restiaceae is roughly equivalent to the modern family Restionaceae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD mentions the importance of interaction with other plants and animals in determining the range of a species in, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 175.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>