<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11961">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   30 March 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5454</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11961 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11961.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11961.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B21</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B21</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-03-30">30 Mar 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Wants to finish revision of MS on Erasmus Darwin before Dallas begins translation. Has discussed possible German edition with Carl Alberts.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1179">Dallas, W. S.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-10-16" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-20" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-10" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-24" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-07-24" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00160_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00160_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        <surface n="B:21r" xml:id="i160">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00160.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00160_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00160.dzi" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:21v" xml:id="i161">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00161.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00161_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00161.dzi" width="3770px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10.II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 30.3.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Als Ihr freundliches Schreiben vom 27<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. c. heute in meinen Besitz kam, war ich schon so weit vorgeschritten in einer neuen Bearbeitung des Lebens von Dr. Darwin, dass ich Sie herzlich bitten möchte, mich dieselbe vollenden zu lassen, bevor Herr Dallas die Uebersetzung beginnt, da er sonst doppelte Arbeit haben würde.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich wünsche nur noch einige Punkte in Betreff des literarischen Lebens in Lichfield festzustellen und zu diesem Zwecke die Correspondence von Dr. Johnson nachzusehen, ebenso die Werke von Blackmore und Broocke (On universal Beauty); von denen man gesagt hat, dass sie dem Dr. Darwin als Vorbilder gedient hätten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Alle diese Punkte werden, glaube ich, nicht mit Ihren Feststellungen collidiren, und sollte das irgendwo der Fall sein, so bitte ich Sie, jedenfalls den betreffenden Passus aus meinem Essay herauszustreichen. Ich hoffe Ihnen diese Neubearbeitung in acht oder spätestens vierzehn Tagen senden zu können, so dass Herr Dallas Ihnen die Uebersetzung bequem zu der Zeit wird fertigstellen können, in welcher Sie selbst beginnen zu können glauben.</p>
                    <p>Für Ihr gütiges Anerbieten uns für die deutsche Ausgabe eine Anzahl von Lichtdruck-Portraits ueberlassen zu wollen, sage ich Ihnen vorläufig herzlichsten Dank; ich werde demnächst mit dem Buchhändler Rücksprache nehmen, um zu erfahren, eine wie hohe Auflage derselbe zu veranstalten denkt, aber ich sollte meinen, die Herstellungskosten könnten recht wohl von dem betreffenden Buchhändler getragen werden.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Wahrscheinlich würden Sie wünschen, dass die deutsche Ausgabe bei Herrn E. Koch in Stuttgart erschiene.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Allein ich habe schon im vorigen Monat (Februar) über eine Separat-Ausgabe der Lebens-Beschreibung mit Herr Carl Alberts verhandelt, und es würde vielleicht nicht gut gehen, dies nachträglich zu ändern. Herr Preyer in Jena hatte ursprünglich die Absicht, seine Biographie zu erweitern und sie in demselben Bändchen mit abdrucken zu lassen.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Diese Idee ist aufgegeben worden, seit wir erfahren haben, dass Herr Rade in Münster Vorbereitungen für eine ausführlichere und gründlichere Beschreibung Ihres Lebens macht.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Mit den herzlichsten Wünschen für Ihr Wohlbefinden zeichne 〈ich〉 | Hochverehrter Herr | Ihr | treulich ergebenster | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10.II.</placeName>
                    <date>30.3.79.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>When your kind letter of the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of this month came into my possession today, I had already progressed so far with the new version of the life of Dr Darwin that I want to plead with you to let me complete it before Mr Dallas starts the translation, since he would otherwise have twice the work.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I only wish to establish a number of details in reference to the literary life in Lichfield and with this aim to consult the correspondence of Dr Johnson, as well as the works of Blackmore and Broocke (On universal Beauty); of which it has been said that they served Dr Darwin as models.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>All these points will not, I believe, conflict with your observations, and should this be the case in any instance I beg you to delete the passage in question from my essay. I hope to be able to send you this revised version in eight days or at the latest a fortnight, so that Mr Dallas will easily be able to complete the translation for you by the time that you yourself think you can begin.</p>
                    <p>For your kind offer to let us have a number of autotype-portraits for the German edition I thank you most cordially in advance; I will consult with the publisher soon, to establish what number of copies he is aiming to produce, but I should think that the production costs could very well be borne by the publisher in question.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>You would probably want the German edition to be published by Mr E. Koch in Stuttgart.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> However, last month (February), I already negotiated with Mr Carl Alberts regarding a separate edition of the biography, and it would not easily be feasable to change this later. Originally Mr Preyer in Jena intended to expand his biography and to publish it in the same little volume.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> This idea has been abandoned since we heard that Mr Rade in Münster has been making preparations for a more extensive and more thorough description of your life.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>With the most cordial wishes for your health I remain | Most esteemed Sir | Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11958.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 27 March 1879</ref>. CD had suggested that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> might begin translating Krause’s original text from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref> and add Krause’s new material later.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>’s philosophical poetry was said to have been inspired by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8433.xml">Henry Brooke</ref>’s poem ‘Universal beauty’, which, in turn, was thought to imitate <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8434.xml">Richard Blackmore</ref>’s physico-theological poem ‘Creation’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10751.xml">Hunt <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1806–7</ref>, 1: 215). The reference to Brooke as a model for Erasmus Darwin’s poetry is in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5410.xml"><hi rend="italic">Biographie universelle</hi></ref> 10: 558. Krause also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2589.xml">Samuel Johnson</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11932.xml">letter of 14 March 1879</ref>, CD told Krause that he hoped to have autotype copies made of a portrait of Erasmus Darwin owned by his brother, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Erasmus Alvey Darwin</ref>. Autotype, a kind of carbon printing process for the monochrome facsimile reproduction of images, was patented in 1868 by the Autotype Company of London (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD’s German publisher was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2732.xml">Eduard Koch</ref> was head of the firm.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_61.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Alberts</ref> was the head of Ernst Günther’s Verlag, Leipzig, which published <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>; the German version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> was published by his firm (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3855.xml">William Preyer</ref>, who was professor of physiology at Jena, had contributed a biographical sketch of CD to a special number of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> published in February 1879 in celebration of CD’s 70th birthday (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10691.xml">Preyer 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3907.xml">Emil Rade</ref> had organised the production of an album of photographs of German and Austrian scientists made in honour of CD, which was presented to CD in 1877 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10826.xml">letter from Emil Rade, [before 16] February 1877</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10071.xml">Rade 1877</ref>). Rade never published a biography of CD.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>