<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3714">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. C. Ramsay   5 September [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17946</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3714 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3714.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3714.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 261.9: 7 (EH 88205980)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>261.9: 7 (EH 88205980)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                <date when="1862-09-05">5 Sept [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml">Ramsay, A. C.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On ACR’s paper on glacial origin of lakes. CD thinks it is correct. Suggests further investigation to corroborate it. His only doubt has to do with areas of great activity.</p>
            <p>On ACR’s view of cause of glacial period: CD did battle with Hooker on same point.</p>
            <p>T. F. Jamieson has smashed CD’s Glen Roy marine theory in splendid style.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">glacial</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">glacial period</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">marine</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2357">Hooker, J. D.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2540">Jamieson, T. F.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Glen Roy</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Ramsay, A. C. 1862</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cliff Cottage, Bournemouth</placeName>
                    <date>Sept. 5</date>
                    <salute>Dear Ramsay.—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Absence from home &amp; severe illness in my family have prevented me from sooner answering your note &amp; thanking you for your paper.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It has interested me much, &amp; I am surprised, if you are not, that the Council sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. hesitate about publishing it—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I dispute that the Council have any right to set up their opinion against yours.— I have been the more interested in your paper from years ago marvelling what could be the meaning of so many lakes in Finland, Scandinavia &amp; N. America.— I could form no conjecture.— As far as I can judge your theory <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be right to a large extent, possibly wholly. Would it not be worth while for you to look at maps of rocky mountainous countries within the Tropics. I cannot remember lakes in Brazil. How is it in Ceylon, Sumatra, the Neilgherries? Years ago I worked through all the reported cases of erratic boulders within the Tropics, &amp; all seemed to be mere weathering of granitic rocks in situ, as shown in appendix to 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Edit of my Journal.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Would not something of same kind be worth your consideration? As no doubt you will attend for future to all lakes; it may possibly be worth your notice, that I always heard in T. del Fuego that sealers &amp;c always searched for anchorage at the mouths of the deep fiords which penetrate so deeply the land; &amp; that if they passed the bank at the mouth, no soundings could be obtained. This, I believe, is simply due to detritus there alone being formed &amp; accumulated, from the wear of the <hi rend="underline">exposed</hi> coasts on each side of entrance:<ref target="#foot.f5"/> during upheaval, such vast mounds of detritus might possibly bank up the water &amp; form a lake.—</p>
<p>No doubt the great depth of the Italian Lakes is rather a staggerer; but I think your theory must be true to very great extent &amp; seems to me very ingenious &amp; satisfactory. The only doubt which occurs to me is the a priori probability in a much troubled country, that some areas would be lifted up less than others &amp; depressions thus left. I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have doubted whether such irregular depressions could be detected by the lines of stratification, &amp; perhaps in part be due to faults.— I remember years ago being struck with frequency of large lakes at base of volcanos, which fact, conjoined <hi rend="underline">with frequency in all parts of world</hi> of interstratification of <hi rend="underline">volcanic</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">lacustrine</hi> deposits, led me (together with a few other facts) to believe that <hi rend="underline">very generally</hi> large areas subside at the base or near active volcanos.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Might there not be same tendency near points or ranges, into which much fluid rock has been <hi rend="underline">in</hi>jected, instead of <hi rend="underline">e</hi>jected? Could such depressed areas be detected by stratification? An examination of several mountainous countries within the Tropics would throw much light on this doubt.—</p>
<p>I was pleased to see your concluding sentence on cause of Glacial Period:<ref target="#foot.f7"/> it is an old opinion of mine, over which I have fought battles with Hooker, but never dared with Lyell.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> In M.S. I have even gone into details, in attempting to show that there has been no such vast recent geographical change as could account for such vast climatal change.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> As for Hopkin’s Gulf-stream change; it is, in my opinion, an empty hypothesis—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Excuse this scribbling paper worthy of the scribble written on it.—</p>
<p>Again I thank you for your valuable paper &amp; remain | Dear Ramsay | Yours very sincerely | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Jamieson has smacked my marine view of Glen Roy in splendid &amp; most satisfactory style: he seems a real good observer—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The shelves are a magnificent record of the Glacial period—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.20 possibly] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘easily’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.6 be due] ‘be’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.13 several] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.4 recent] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3701.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. C. Ramsay, 26 August 1862</ref> (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3701.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. C. Ramsay, 26 August 1862</ref>, and Ramsay 1862. CD left Down on 13 August 1862, travelling via Southampton to Bournemouth, before returning home on 30 September 1862. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin</ref> had been suffering from scarlet fever since June 1862; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> developed the disease on 13 August (see ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix II), and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3701.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. C. Ramsay, 26 August 1862</ref>. In his paper (Ramsay 1862), Ramsay argued for the glacial origin of a number of lake-filled European and American rock-basins, and rejected former explanations of them as structural features associated with synclines, as the results of local subsidence, or as fissures along fault lines. The paper was strongly criticised by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1585.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Falconer</ref> and others when it was read on 5 March 1862 before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>, of which Ramsay was president, and the council considered not passing the paper for publication in the society’s journal. Two members of the council, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roderick Impey Murchison</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, subsequently attacked Ramsay’s theory in print. For an account of the controversy, see Davies 1969, pp. 303–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to the Addenda to his <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, pp. 609–29; the discussion of erratic blocks is on pages 612–25.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 24 n., CD described these ‘fiords’ as being much shallower at their mouths than further inland, attributing the phenomenon to the accumulation of sediment formed by the wearing down of the rocks exposed to the open sea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>, p. 96 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Ramsay concluded his paper by rejecting the theory advocated by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> that the elevation and subsidence of landmasses were responsible for large-scale climatic change (Ramsay 1862, p. 204). He stated: <quote type="quote"> I find it difficult to believe that the change of climate that put an end to this [the glacial period] could be brought about by mere changes of physical geography. The change is too large and too universal, having extended alike over the Lowlands of the Northern and the Southern Hemispheres. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD had told <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> of his disbelief in ‘the Lyellian view that [the] Global Epoch is connected with [the] position of continents’, in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2432.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 15 March [1859]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7). CD had opposed Hooker’s hypothesis of former land-bridges as an explanation for the geographical distribution of animals and plants (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 [June 1856]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1910.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">25 June [1856]</ref>). Hooker had linked the elevation of such land-bridges to Lyell’s explanation of the causes of climatic change (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Hooker 1853</ref>, pp. xxiii–xxv, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_991.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Browne 1983</ref>, pp. 133–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD may refer to the manuscript of his projected ‘big book’ on species, written between 1856 and 1858, and published posthumously as <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>. CD discussed the Pleistocene glacial period in his draft chapter on the geographical distribution of animals and plants, written in 1856 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 534–66). It was in discussing the abstract of this chapter, drawn up for publication in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, that CD broached with Hooker his disagreement with Lyell’s view of the causes of the climatic changes of the glacial period (see n. 8, above). In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2440.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Hooker of 30 March [1859]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7), CD explained: <quote type="quote"> I think if I had space &amp; time, I could make pretty good case against any great <hi rend="italic">continental</hi> changes since Glacial epoch, &amp; this has mainly led me to give up the Lyellian doctrine as insufficient to explain all mutations of climate.— </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The Cambridge mathematician, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref>, had argued that the European glacial period may have been caused by the Gulf Stream being diverted from its course (Hopkins 1852a and 1852b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">In 1839, CD had published <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Parallel roads of Glen Roy’</ref>, in which he argued that the series of parallel terraces running along the sides of Glen Roy in Lochaber, Scotland, had been formed by the sea as the landmass of Scotland gradually rose. Rejecting CD’s marine theory, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Francis Jamieson</ref> believed that the so-called ‘roads’ represented the shorelines of a series of former lakes, trapped in the glen by ice-flows during a great ‘Ice-Age’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4144.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jamieson 1863</ref>). Jamieson corresponded with CD on the subject in 1861 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9), and CD had recently been informed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> that Jamieson had confirmed his theory following a second visit to the site (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3691.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 20 August 1862</ref> and n. 1).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>