<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5620A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   [8 October 1867]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20486</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5620A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5620A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5620A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc">inc (German trans)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 132</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Möller, Alfred 1915–21 2: 132</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Itajahy, Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1867-10-08">[8 Oct 1867]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has CD ever considered that the colour of seeds of Amarantaceae would attract the attention of birds?</p> 
<p>Describes case of a climbing <hi rend="italic">Chamissoa</hi> of the local flora.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Amarantaceae</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Chamissoa, climbing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Itajahy</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>.... . Hätten Sie je gedacht, dass die Familie der Amarantaceen<ref target="#foot.f3"/> auch auffällige Samen darbieten möchte, welche die Aufmerksamkeit von Vögeln erregen? Nun, dies ist der Fall bei einer kletternden Chamissoa unserer Flora. Die schwarzen Samen sind beinah vollständig von einem weissen Arillus umgeben und bleiben am Grunde der Kapsel angeheftet, deren obere Hälfte abfällt (“utriculus circumscissus”)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> wie bei Anagallis.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Nach Endlicher’s Beschreibung scheint es, dass in andern Arten jener Gattung der Arillus viel kleiner ist (“arillo brevi albo, umbilicum lateraliter cingente”),<ref target="#foot.f6"/> und so bilden diese Formen ein verbindendes Glied zwischen unserer Art und einer andern Amarantacee (Celosia?), bei der die kleinen, schwarzen und glänzenden Samen überhaupt keinen Arillus haben und, obwohl sie nicht sehr ansehnlich sind, dennoch fest angeheftet auf dem Grunde der Kapsel bleiben, welche nach dem Abfallen ihrer oberen Hälfte einen halbkugeligen Becher bildet. Die Thatsache, dass ansehnliche Samen an den offnen Hüllen festhaften, kommt auch bei Monocotyledonen vor. Ich beobachtete sie bei Hedychium (coronarium?—nicht einheimisch hier)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> und bei einer Marantacee.... .</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Itajahy</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>.... . Would you ever have thought that the Amarantaceae<ref target="#foot.f3"/> family could also present conspicuous seeds that attract the attention of birds? Well, this is the case with a climbing Chamissoa in our flora. The black seeds are almost completely surrounded by a white arillus and remain attached to the base of the capsule, the upper half of which falls off (“utriculus circumscissus”)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> as with Anagallis.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> According to Endlicher’s description it seems that in other species of that genus the arillus is much smaller (“arillo brevi albo, umbilicum lateraliter cingente”),<ref target="#foot.f6"/> and so these forms constitute a connecting link between our species and another Amarantaceae (Celosia?), in which the small, black, and shiny seeds have no arillus at all, and although not very sizeable, remain firmly attached to the base of the capsule, which forms a hemispherical cup when its upper half has fallen off. The fact that large seeds stick to the open hull also occurs in monocotyledons. I observed this in a Hedychium (coronarium?—not indigenous here)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and in a Marantaceae.... .</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, Appendix I. For an account of the reconstruction of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5583A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 17 July 1867</ref>, n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the German of its published source, see p. 392. For an account of the reconstruction of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5583A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 17 July 1867</ref>, n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5605.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">15 August [1867]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">30 January [1868]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref> dated the letter fragment ‘September 1867’ when he published it in German translation (Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 132). CD thanked Müller for information ‘about conspicuous seeds’ in his letter of 30 January [1868], and also mentioned receiving Müller’s answers on expression written on 5 October. It is likely that Müller answered the queries on expression on a separate sheet, dated 5 October 1867, which was included with the letter written on 8 October 1867. Müller had written at the top of CD’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5605.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 15 August [1867]</ref>, ‘Received Octobr. 5.— | Answered Octobr. 8.—’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The modern spelling is ‘Amaranthaceae’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘Arillus’: aril; ‘utriculus circumscissus’: utricle circumscissile (Latin; the characterisation comes from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endlicher 1836–42</ref>, s.v. <hi rend="italic">Chamissoa</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The genus <hi rend="italic">Anagallis</hi> belongs to the family Primulaceae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Arillo brevi albo umbilicum lateraliter cingente: with a short white aril surrounding the hilum laterally (Latin). Müller refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1508.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stephan Ladislaus Endlicher</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endlicher 1836–42</ref> (s.v. <hi rend="italic">Chamissoa</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Hedychium coronarium</hi>, though native to tropical Asia, is widely naturalised in tropical America (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mabberley 1997</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>