<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9358">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alfred Newton   13 March 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10239</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9358 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9358.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9358.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 172: 50</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>172: 50</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3517.xml">Newton, Alfred</persName>
                <placeName>Magdalene College, Cambridge</placeName>
                <date when="1874-03-13">13 Mar 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Wishes CD could publish <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> with footnotes.</p>  
<p>Increases in bird populations: starlings are increasing, but AN cannot give reason; mistletoe-thrush increasing but not ousting song-thrush. Doubts trustworthiness of [George?] Edwards, CD’s authority in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> on this matter [see <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, 6th ed., p. 59].</p> 
            <p>AN opposed to bird protection legislation to prohibit egging. Argues egging does not decrease number of birds.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bird</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">starlings</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">thrush, mistletoe-</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">thrush, song-</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">eggs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">human intervention</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">legislation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Magd. Coll.</placeName>
                    <date>13 March 1874.</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I indeed thank you for your letter, which must have given you much trouble, and for your successful “cerebration” which has answered one of my enquiries—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I immediately referred to your authority which I need scarcely say you quoted correctly— Still I doubt whether that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Edward (whom I know by correspondence &amp; report) is sufficiently trustworthy on this point.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The increase of the Mistletoe-Thrush is undeniable &amp; in my revised edition of ‘Yarrell’ I have collected much evidence on that subject, but that it should oust the Song-Thrush is I think very unlikely. They both, it is true, feed on earth worms to some extent, but so far as I know the Mistletoe-Thrush scarcely ever applies itself to the gathering of big snails (<hi rend="underline">Helix aspera</hi> I think) in thick covert as the Song-Thrush habitually does—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> This M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edwards too in a former part of the same paper has a story about the Snowy Owl <hi rend="underline">breeding</hi> in Aberdeenshire which is full of improbabilities not to say impossibilities—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Yet he was or is a very worthy man, but only liable to run away with an idea—and I have not come across any other evidence as to the decrease of the Song-Thrush &amp; from its migratory nature &amp; its singular power of adapting itself to various habitats I do not expect that the assertion can be maintained—</p>
<p>May I hope that “cerebration” or a lucky chance may find the authority for the belief about the Fulmar?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I wish indeed you could publish an Edition of the ‘Origin’ with footnotes giving your authorities— That would be a book! Could you not employ your new Secretary—to whom as to the rest of your family pray give my kind regards—on such a task, laborious as it would be?<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I am sure you may take the increase of the Starling as a fact<ref target="#foot.f7"/>—and it is one I cannot yet see any way of accounting for that is not equally applicable to many other birds that are not increasing—</p>
<p>There is a point which I should much like to discuss with you but I don’t know when I may ever get the opportunity— perhaps you could tell me where I could find something bearing on the subject—</p>
<p>The fanatical party of those who wish to protect birds by Act of Parliament are always urging that no measures are of any use which do not prohibit the taking of eggs— Now anxious as I am to protect birds &amp; conscious of the necessity of some protection I don’t agree with these people—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Letting alone the impropriety of filling gaols with birds’ nesting boys such a step seems to me to be useless. To me it appears that the destruction of even many eggs can have but little effect on the existence of a species—so long as enough eggs are hatched to supply the vacancies caused by death in the ordinary way— and we may trust the instinct of birds to keep a sufficient number of nests out of harm’s way for that purpose. Supposing the existence of a species of bird to be the object we want to attain I often wonder what is the comparative value to that end of an egg, a nestling, or even a young bird that has flown, and a bird which is about to become a parent &amp; has survived all the dangers of migration (&amp; I believe that as <hi rend="underline">individuals</hi> the majority of birds migrate) or of hard weather—. How would an actuary calculate the relative value of a bird’s life as an instrument in preserving the species in August and in March?</p>
<p>Any hints on this matter would be very gratefully received. I am pretty confident in my own opinion being correct but I find it very hard to persuade others—even when I cite the obvious case of a poultry yard in support of it—</p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very truly | Alfred Newton</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alfred Newton, 12 March [1874]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9354.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Newton of 12 March [1874]</ref>, CD had cited an article by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1464.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Edward</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward 1856</ref>), in which Edward claimed that as mistle-thrushes increased in Scotland, song thrushes declined. There are two letters from Edward, a Scottish shoemaker, dated 1872 and 1879, in the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3517.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Newton</ref> archive, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref> Library (MS Add. 9839/1E).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his revision of the first two volumes of the fourth edition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Yarrell’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">History of British birds</hi>, Newton described how the song thrush, unlike the mistle-thrush, fed on large snails (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8553.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Yarrell 1871–85</ref>, 1: 265).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward 1856</ref>, pp. 5201–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9348.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alfred Newton, 10 March 1874</ref> and n. 4. Newton had queried CD’s claim that the fulmar petrel was believed to be the most numerous bird in the world.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> was to become CD’s secretary; he took up the post in summer 1874 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2337.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Emma Darwin</hi> (1904)</ref>, 2: 269). <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> had been published without references because CD intended that it should serve only as an abstract of his theory of natural selection (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 30 March [1859]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2441.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 31 March [1859]</ref>). However, he never returned to the longer exposition of his theory that he had worked on from 1856 to 1858, and which contained footnotes (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had mentioned the increase of starlings in Kent in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9354.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alfred Newton, 12 March [1874]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Newton had been involved in the 1869 Sea Birds Preservation Act (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>); a Wild Birds Protection Act was passed in 1880. It was not illegal to collect birds’ eggs in Britain until 1954.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>