<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2654">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Baden Powell   18 January [1860]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15647</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2654 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2654.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2654.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="endorsement" subtype="letter">60</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Linnean Society of London (Quentin Keynes collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_238.xml">Linnean Society</repository>
                    <collection>(Quentin Keynes collection)</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-01-18">18 Jan [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3836.xml">Powell, Baden</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD is pleased by BP’s appreciative opinion of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. He never intended to claim that he originated the doctrine that species have not been independently created. The only novelty in his work is the attempt to explain <hi rend="italic">how</hi> species became modified and how the theory of descent explains large classes of facts. If he has taken anything from BP, he has done so unconsciously. Gives names of those he would have mentioned in any account of authors who maintained that species have not been separately created.</p>  
<p>CD greatly admires BP’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of creation</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Philosophy of creation</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Powell, Baden 1855</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much pleased by your approbation of my book, as everyone must admit that you are a master in philosophical logic;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am the more pleased at this, as one eminent scientific man writes to me that I have violated the whole spirit of inductive philosophy.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>My health was so poor, whilst I wrote the Book, that I was unwilling to add in the least to my labour; therefore I attempted no history of the subject; nor do I think that I was bound to do so. I just alluded indeed to the Vestiges &amp; I am now heartily sorry I did so.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> No educated person, not even the most ignorant, could suppose that I meant to arrogate to myself the origination of the doctrine that species had not been independently created. The only novelty in my work is the attempt to explain <hi rend="underline">how</hi> species become modified, &amp; to a certain extent how the theory of descent explains certain large classes of facts; &amp; in these respects I received no assistance from my predecessors. To the best of my belief I have acknowledged with pleasure all the chief facts &amp; generalisations which I have borrowed. If I have taken anything from you, I assure you it has been unconsciously; but I will reread your Essay.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Had I alluded to those authors who have maintained, with more or less ability, that species have not been separately created, I should have felt myself bound to have given some account of all; namely, passing over the ancients, Buffon (?) Lamarck (by the way his erroneous views were curiously anticipated by my Grandfather), Geoffry St. Hilaire &amp; especially his son Isidore; Naudin; Keyserling; an American (name this minute forgotten); the Vestiges of Creation; I believe some Germans. Herbert Spencer; &amp; yourself.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>The task would have been not a little difficult, &amp; belongs rather to the Historian of Science than to me. I ought also to have alluded to chief maintainers of opposite doctrines.— I had intended in my larger book to have attempted some such history; but my own catalogue frightens me. I will, however, consult some scientific friends &amp; be guided by their advice.</p>
<p>Permit me to add that I read your Philosophy of Creation with great interest: it struck me as excellently &amp; vigorously argued &amp; written with a clearness, which I remember excited my warmest admiration.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I most fully agree that your work must have had a great effect with philosophical minds in removing prejudices on the subject; in a higher degree but in nearly the same manner as the Vestiges has had with a less highly endowed class of readers. I have had to make by letter the same acknowledgement to the Author (as I believe) of the Vestiges.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> By the above remarks I do not by any means intend to say that your work has not entirely converted many readers, &amp; induced them to give up the doctrine of creation; in simple truth I do not at all know how the case stands.— I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. not have <hi rend="underline">presumed</hi> to have made these remarks on your work, had not your letter induced me.</p>
<p>Believe me, with sincere respect, My dear Sir | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.17 I believe … Germans.] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.4 scientific] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.3 most fully] <hi rend="italic">above del illeg</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3836.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Baden Powell</ref> was Savilian professor of geometry at Oxford University. He was a frequent contributor to scientific periodicals on mathematical topics, but was most famous for his works on doctrinal and philosophical questions. His letter to CD has not been found, but its substance can be inferred from a favourable notice of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> that Powell inserted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6393.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Powell 1860</ref> at the proof stage. He considered <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> to be a ‘masterly volume’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6393.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Powell 1860</ref>, p. 139). Powell died in June 1860.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to Adam Sedgwick. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2548.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Adam Sedgwick, 24 November 1859</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD refers to <hi rend="italic">Vestiges of the natural history of creation</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1348.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Chambers] 1844</ref>). He mentioned the work briefly in the introduction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 3–4, and had been accused of borrowing from its content (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2633.xml" resp="#automat">letter to T. H. Huxley, 1 January [1860]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Powell had enthusiastically adopted the doctrine of the uniformity of nature in the 1830s and discussed the origin of species in several works, most notably in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Powell 1855</ref>, in which he treated <hi rend="italic">Vestiges </hi>(<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1348.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Chambers] 1844</ref>) sympathetically. He rejected the idea of supernatural intervention and endorsed a history of living beings based on the fulfilment of a divine plan by natural means. See Corsi 1988.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_714.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georges Louis Leclerc</ref>, Comte de Buffon; Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de Lamarck; Étienne and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1840.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire</ref>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3492.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Victor Naudin</ref>; Alexandr Andreevich Keyserling; and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1348.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Chambers] 1844</ref>. CD prepared a ‘historical’ essay for the revised American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, expanded for subsequent editions, in which he mentioned all these authors (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.8, Appendix IV). The American to whom he alludes was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2056.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Steman Haldeman</ref> (see following letter).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6391.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Powell 1855</ref>. CD recorded reading this work in January 1856 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV, 128: 14). His notes on it are in DAR 71: 43–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The author of <hi rend="italic">Vestiges</hi> was believed by many to be <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_875.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Chambers</ref>, but his authorship was not publicly acknowledged until after his death (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1982</ref>, pp. 210–11 n. 28, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7065.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Secord 1989</ref>). CD guessed that Chambers was the author in 1847 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [18 April 1847]</ref>). CD’s letter to Chambers has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>