<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10488F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [1 May 1876]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21496</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10488F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10488F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10488F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 24</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 24</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <date when="1876-05-01">[1 May 1876]</date>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Good news about Frankland. Expecting burnt earth. Almost finished the Foodbodies Paper on Acacia. He and Amy are learning to use the new printing machine.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down</placeName>
                    <salute>Dear Father</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is fine news about Frankland. I will get the earth this afternoon   I expect the unburnt will be the best after all, confound all that brick making.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have nearly done the Food bodies paper as far as Acacia goes.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Amy has made a duplicate dummy printing machine &amp; we have races on them (in which I win). I find one learns very quick where to dab down ones fingers   I am pining for the real machine.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Hen was very well yesterday.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I hope you go on keeping well, &amp; mother too | Yrs affec | FD</p>
<p>Amy sends her love</p>
<p>Amy says it is very unfair my saying I win the races, because I have practiced most</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10485B.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, [30 April 1876]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1739.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Frankland</ref> had offered to analyse two types of soil that CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> were using in experiments on cross- and self-fertilisation; they wanted to compare the height and vigour of several generations of both cross- and self-fertilised plants and needed to eliminate the nutrient content of the soil as a cause of variation. The first sample was soil that had been burnt, treated with sulphuric acid, and then washed; the second was clayey soil dug up from the Sandwalk at Down House. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10399.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. H. Gilbert, 16 February 1876</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10485B.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, [30 April 1876]</ref>. In order to rid the soil of most nutrients, CD had been advised to roast sifted clayey soil until all coaly matter disappeared and the resulting porous and friable matter was a brick-red colour (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10416G.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. H. Gilbert, 9 March 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Francis’s paper ‘On the glandular bodies on <hi rend="italic">Acacia sphærocephala</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cecropia peltata</hi> serving as food for ants’ (F. Darwin 1876d) was read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 1 June 1876. <hi rend="italic">Acacia sphaerocephala</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Vachellia sphaerocephala</hi> (bee wattle or bull’s-horn thorn); <hi rend="italic">Cecropia peltata</hi> is the embauba or trumpet tree.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD paid £21 for a typewriter on 2 May 1876 (CD’s Classed account books (Down House MS)). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Amy Darwin</ref>, Francis’s wife, had presumably made mock keyboards on which to learn the layout of the letters.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Francis probably saw <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Litchfield</ref> when he was in London to purchase the typewriter (<ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Horace Darwin to G. H. Darwin, 1 May 1876</ref> (DAR 258: 860)).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>