<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8685">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Jules Michelet<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   15 November 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10023</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8685 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8685.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8685.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 174</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 174</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3316.xml">Michelet, Jules</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1872-11-15">15 Nov 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Darwin and his followers have connected France and England like the projected tunnel and have demonstrated that the French and English are more free than Germany from scholasticism.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Channel tunnel</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">France</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On dit que l’on va faire un passage sous-marin, que le Détroit sera supprimé, et que les deux paÿs reconnaîtront enfin leur voisinage, et disons mieux, leur unité antique.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Personne plus que vous, et les savans illustres qui vous suivent, n’aura contribué à créer ce passage, à rappeler notre voisinage et notre parenté de race et d’esprit</p>
<p>Cette dernière consiste surtout, selon moi, non seulement dans une observation plus exacte que celle des Allemands, mais dans une simplicité vigoureuse qui affranchit les grands esprits Anglais et Français des scolastiques qui retardent et souvent égarent l’Allemagne en mille choses. <hi rend="underline">Vous et nous, nous allons au but</hi>.</p>
<p>Voilà pourquoi les vôtres et les nôtres ont frayé la voie à l’Europe.</p>
<p>Pour moi, quoique porté par mes études sur des voies differentes, je n’en admire pas moins votre méthode, et suis ravi de découvrir tant de liens entre les sciences de la nature et celles de l’homme</p>
<p>Je vous serre la main avec une admiration bien affecteuse. | J. Michelet <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">15 n. 72</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is said that they are going to make a submarine passage, that the Channel will be eliminated, and that the two countries will at last acknowledge their proximity; let us put it better, their ancient unity.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>No-one will have contributed more to the creation of this passage, and to recalling our proximity and our kinship of race and of mind, than yourself and the famous men of science who follow you.</p>
<p>The latter kinship, in my opinion, principally consists both in a power of observation which is more precise than that of the Germans, and in a vigorous simplicity which liberates the great English and French minds from the scholastics who hold Germany back in a thousand ways, and often lead her astray. <hi rend="underline">You and I get to the point</hi>.</p>
<p>That is why the likes of ourselves have beaten a new path for Europe.</p>
<p>For my part, even though I am led in other directions by my studies, I nonetheless admire your method, and am delighted to discover so many links between the sciences of nature and those of man</p>
<p>I shake your hand with most affectionate admiration. | J. Michelet</p>
<p>15 N. 72</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 505–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The Channel Tunnel Company was formed in January 1872 (<hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 18 January 1872, p. 4). On the failure of this venture, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2973.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gourvish 2006</ref>, pp. 4–7.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>