<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2177F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">From James Buckman   [1 December 1857]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">22122</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2177F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2177F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2177F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
               <note type="description">Incomplete</note> 
               
                <note type="physdesc">inc</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 2 January 1858, p. 11</bibl>
                <bibl type="printedSource">Gardeners’ Chronicle, 2 January 1858, p. 11</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_712.xml">Buckman, James</persName>
                    <date when="1857-12-01">[1 Dec 1857]</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
                <abstract>
                <p>Discusses the relative growth of native and foreign weeds.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-08-05" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2022-10-13" status="OnlineEditionOnly"/>
            <change when="2022-10-20" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
            <change when="2022-12-12" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name xml:id="sai">Shelley Innes</name></change>
            <change when="2022-12-12" status="copyedited">Copyedited <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p rend="centre"/>
                        <p>In reference to the observation at page 762, 1857, “There is too much reason to believe that foreign seed of an indigenous species is often more prolific than that grown at home,” I would here observe that these remarks were meant more particularly to apply to weeds accompanying cultivation, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>, agrarian weeds.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> These long observation and experience have taught me obey the same law as varieties of cultivated plants which become the more prolific and grow better the oftener their change from one soil or situation to another, and I cannot but think that the farmer the better keeps up a vigorous weed growth by those that he sows with seed from various distant places, than from those that he lets seed upon the land. It would be as difficult to trace the origin of many of our agrarian weeds, but I incline to the belief that many of the weed forms are as much the result of cultivation as the crop itself, for like the crop they are nowhere found truly wild, but are introduced with culture wherever that pertains. If this be so, it is as necessary for the wellbeing of the weed that its seed should be changed as it is for the better growth of a crop, the same seed wearing out in one case as in another. The constant introduction of new varieties of crop plants, as well as the perpetual change of seed, are so many changes of circumstances by which they were originally produced—and just so is it with the agrarian weeds by which the crop is accompanied. In reference to this I would quote my experiments with Avena fatua. From this I have procured the cultivated types; the A. fatua may thus be viewed as the initiative of A. sativa, but can we view the A. fatua as the primary plant?<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It is never found except as an agrarian, which I hold as an evidence that it, too, is a derivative. In cultivating all wild plants the first step augments their size on account of the change—seed transported from one district to another continues this change in an augmented form in proportion to the distance, and so all those that are capable of gaining a footing and supporting it do so at an accelerated rate. My own observations in America confirm me in these opinions; there every homestead is full of English weeds, and had I been of Mr. Babington’s opinion,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I must have looked upon many of them as distinct species from those at home, for not only were many of them more prolific, but they wanted that sturdy character which they possess at home, hence Sinapis nigra on the alluvial banks of the Ohio is as much as 6 feet in height.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I find in my notes, written on board an Ohio steamer, “June 23: Stuck fast on a sand-bar for the whole day. Went on an island in the evening; good crop of Wheat and Indian Corn. Plants (wild) where European, twice the size of British specimens. Bromus secalinus abundant in the corn” (and I remember the enormous size and height of this Grass).<ref target="#foot.f6"/>The Chysanthemum leucanthemum, commonly called Daisy in America, is as much as a yard high in the meadows, or rather where it occurs—an apology therefor.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> In fact I quite came to the conclusion that even the plants as well as the men became attenuated in the States, and yet with this it may be a question whether both are not more prolific. I have no means of knowing from observation whether imported seed of an aboriginal species in America prevails over the native, but I noticed that in the States agrarian cultivation was affected by the same weeds, with but few exceptions, as our own, and these certainly appeared to me to lose nothing from growth in a new country, but, on the contrary, were larger and more prolific.</p>
                        <p>As regards the questions about the Sinapis nigra on the farm described, I would beg to state that it was somewhere about seven years since the introduction of this in quantity in some foreign Flax seed.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Previously to this it was an occasional plant on the farm (as on what farm is it absent?), but the Sinapis arvensis was, for years before, the chief pest; this latter has been much got under, not only as a result of better farming, but as I take it fairly driven out of the field before the foreign invader, and in the Flax field, where it was originally sown, it constantly comes up in quantity, while the S. arvensis is here the exception, though time was when it was the law. “Weed introduced from other land” is constantly driving out the natives. Coltsfoot establishes itself perhaps from seeds from a distant farm or dirty road-side; let it alone or cultivate it as farmers do by ploughing and scattering the divided rhizomes over the field, and the result will soon be that it will gain more or less perfect possession. Leave in a poor meadow clusters of Brachypodium pennatum without ameliorating the soil, and it will soon occupy its greater part.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Manure it, and in two years this weed Grass will scarcely be seen. Again, let drainage be defective in part of a meadow for a few years, the whereabouts will be indicated by large bunches of Aira cæspitosa.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Remove the cause, and in less than two years most of this weed will die out and be seen on its heels on the sward. In Wiltshire, to recur to Mustards, the Sinapis arvensis has been driven out in some districts by the Sinapis alba, the latter having got possession of the soil from the cultivation of Mustard for sheep.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Lots of instances of the like may be adduced had I time, and indeed so certain is the law of extermination of one form by the introduction of another that I am not sure that the best way to get rid of some more objectionable weeds would not be the cultivation of those less so. <hi rend="italic">J. B.</hi></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                
                                
                
                
                
                
                
                
            </div>
            
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by CD’s reference to the letter in a note in DAR 46.1: 41–2, headed ‘<hi rend="underline">Letter from Prof. Buckman.</hi> Dec.1.57’. CD sent the letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, where it was published on 2 January 1858, p. 11. It was headed ‘Foreign and native weeds’ and introduced with an editorial insertion: ‘[The following remarks have been forwarded to Mr. Darwin on the subject to which he refers at page 779, 1857, and are now published with his permission.]’.   </note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 7 November 1857, p. 762. The editorial article discussed various methods of weed propagation and noted that while foreign seeds of exotic species seldom made much progress, those of indigenous species were often more prolific.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Avena fatua</hi> is spring wild oat; <hi rend="italic">A. sativa</hi> is common oat.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_214.xml">Charles Cardale Babington</ref>, in the preface to his <hi rend="italic">Manual of British botany</hi>, had noted that plants often considered varieties in England were treated as distinct species in other countries, and discussed the difficulties in determining which could be considered truly distinct (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_278.xml">Babington 1843</ref>, pp. v–vii).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Sinapis nigra</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Brassica nigra</hi>, black mustard. </note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f6">Buckman had visited the United States of America in 1854 as a mineral consultant (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>). <hi rend="italic">Bromus secalinus</hi> is rye brome or cheat, a grassy weed infecting winter rye and winter wheat. Although native to Europe, it became widespread in North America.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Chrysanthemum leucanthemum</hi> (‘Chysanthemum’ is a misspelling) is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Leucanthemum vulgare</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">vulgare</hi>, the common ox-eye daisy. It was introduced to North America from Europe.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f8">Flax is <hi rend="italic">Linum usitatissimum</hi></note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Sinapis arvensis</hi> is charlock mustard. Coltsfoot is <hi rend="italic">Tussilago farfara</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Brachypodium pinnatum</hi> (‘pennatum’ is a misspelling) is heath false brome; it thrives in infertile calcareous soils.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Aira caespitosa</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Deschampsia cespitosa</hi>, tufted hair grass. It prefers poorly drained soils.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Sinapis alba</hi> is white mustard; because it is fast growing, it was grown for autumn grazing for lambs.</note> 
            </div>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>