<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7698">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Crichton-Browne   18 April 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17904</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7698 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7698.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7698.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy encl LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">4pp encl 3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 143: 339; DAR 185: 39</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>143: 339, 185: 39</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1871-04-18">18 Apr 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_677.xml">Crichton-Browne, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on notes by JC-B on relation between blushing and mental disturbance. Asks for further information about blushing. "The single pencil line down this MS is my mark that I have used it once."</p>
            <p>Thanks for "dreadful photo of the imbeciles".</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">imbeciles</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down,</placeName>
                    <date>April 18, 1871.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Your MS. is invaluable. I will correct my little discussion and give some of your evidence on the connection between the circulation of brain and skin.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have quite overlooked any statement to this effect, no doubt from not seeing that it concerned me, although I have read a good deal about the vaso-motor nerve-system. I daresay the relation betwen intense blushing and mental disturbance appears to you obvious; but I believe I have read everything published on the subject of blushing, yet have met with no allusion to this point.</p>
<p>Many thanks for the remarks by your sister in law.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As she speaks about blushing when by herself, should you object to ask her whether she has ever felt a blush when by herself in the dark. I have long thought that Shakspear was in error (though this is high treason) when he makes Juliet say to Romeo “Thou knowest the mask of night is on my face, else would a maiden blush bepaint my cheek”, &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Will you ask her whether she agrees to the following statements;—that no one blushes for a fault committed when quite alone, and if not afterwards discovered or suspected by any one. Thus, I believe that if a truthful man had been led to tell an undetected falsehood, he would bitterly repent of it, but would not blush. I can however well imagine that if the thought suddenly occurred to him “had this or that happened, I should have been detected”, then he would probably have blushed, though at the time in solitude. When a person blushes at the thought of a past fault, is it not always at one committed in the presence of others, or afterwards known or suspected by others? Little breaches of etiquette, which perhaps cause more intense blushing than even grave faults, imply the presence of others. Perhaps your sister-in-law will not object to give you her opinion on these points in confirmation or opposition to your own. Please to glance over your enclosed MS., and return it, as I may wish to reconsult it.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The single pencil line down the MS. is my mark that I have used it once. My query refers to your first case at the bottom of p. 1.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> At first I thought that the unfastening the chemise and examining the chest, actually caused the chest to blush; but on reflection I presume it is more probable that the previous blushing was thus rendered more intense and consequently spread further down the body. Can you enlighten me on this point?<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>You offer to send me fragmentary notes on blushing; if you can get any one to copy them I shall be truly glad to read them, as <hi rend="underline">all</hi> your remarks have been most useful to me. My chapter on blushing, however, is already rather too long, so I should read your observations more for the sake of corrections than for additions.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> When I think of all the trouble that I have caused you, my sole excuse is that I hope I may thus give to the public some scraps of your knowledge. Anything which I may publish from you would not, however, interfere with any more elaborate papers by yourself, should your health and leisure hereafter permit you to publish. You most kindly offer to look over my MS. or proof-sheets on blushing.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> This would be an enormous advantage to me, but my MS. will not, I believe, be ready for rather a long time, as I intend to refresh myself with some botanical work this summer.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> When I am ready I will enquire how your health and leisure are. Many thanks for the dreadful photo of the imbeciles and especially for your very curious paper on psychical intoxication, which I have been particularly glad to read.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Yours very sincerely obliged | Ch. Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f11"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>(Please return this)</p>
<p>As your sister-in-law speaks about blushing when by herself, will you ask her whether she has ever felt a blush when by herself in the dark.</p>
<p>I have long thought that Shakspear was in error when he makes it appear that Juliet did not blush in the dark. Will you ask your sister whether she agrees to the following statements;—that no one blushes for a fault committed when quite alone, &amp; if not afterwards discovered or suspected by any one.</p>
<p>I believe that if a truthful man had been led to tell an undetected falsehood, he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> bitterly repent of it, but w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not blush. I can, however, well imagine that if the thought suddenly occurred to him, “had this or that happened, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have been detected”, or “if this or that person were to know of my fault,” then he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> blush, though at the time in solitude.</p>
<p>When a person blushes at the thought of a past fault, is it not always at one committed in the presence of others, or afterwards known or suspected by others? Little breaches of etiquette, which perhaps cause more intense blushing than even grave faults, imply the presence of others.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1"> <hi rend="italic">Enclosure</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.1 (Please return this).] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand; blue crayon square brackets in MS</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.3 “had … detected”] <hi rend="italic">quotation marks in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">4.4 , or “if … fault,”] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.4 were] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘h’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.4 blush] ‘have blushed’ <hi rend="italic">del in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.2 others,] <hi rend="italic">comma before del question mark in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 16 April 1871</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 323–6; see also letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_677.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Crichton-Browne</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7672.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">9 April [1871]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7678.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">12 April 1871</ref>. Crichton-Browne later published an account of this correspondence, including a complete transcription of this letter (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1638.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crichton-Browne [1930]</ref>, pp. 61–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 16 April 1871</ref>. Crichton-Browne’s sister-in-law has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</hi>, 2.2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD evidently sent back the notes on blushing that he had originally received as an enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7134.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 15 March 1870</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD refers to Crichton-Browne’s account of an asylum patient in whom redness of the face extended downwards when her chest was examined (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7134.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 15 March 1870</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">No reply from Crichton-Browne has been found. However, in his later published account of this correspondence, Crichton-Browne wrote: ‘I explained to Darwin that the case which I described to him, and to which he refers … in which a woman, under medical examination, blushing, at first confined to the face and ears, immediately spread over the neck and breast when the chest was exposed—was illustrative of the rapid extension, under increased emotional perturbation, of the vaso-motor paralysis in which blushing really consists. That essentially human prerogative is not under voluntary control. Blushing can neither be induced nor checked by any effort of the will’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1638.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crichton-Browne [1930]</ref>, p. 65).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">No further such notes from Crichton-Browne have been found. CD published on blushing in chapter 13 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 16 April 1871</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD intended to continue work on the insectivorous plants <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Drosophyllum</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7607.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 21 March [1871]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">On the photograph, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 16 April 1871</ref> and n. 1; CD also refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1633.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crichton-Browne 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The enclosure is in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> hand, with the exception of the words ‘(Please return this)’ and ‘or “if this or that person were to know of my fault,’”; presumably it was copied out so that Crichton-Browne could pass it on to his sister-in-law. The main part of the letter is transcribed from a copy.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>