<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12969">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   2 January 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5480</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12969 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12969.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12969.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German) encl 3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B61; DAR 221.2: 27</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B61,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>221.2: 27</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml" resp="high">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1881-01-02">2 Jan 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Encloses reply to Butler [<hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> 8 (1881): 321–2]. Has also written a reply intended for English reader. Will have it translated for <hi rend="italic">Popular Science Review</hi> if CD thinks suitable.</p> 
            <p>Report of Jäger accident was an error.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> has been purchased by Eduard Koch in Stuttgart and will continue as in the past.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Kosmos</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_774">Butler, Samuel (b)</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2514">Jäger, Gustav</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2732">Koch, Eduard</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Stuttgart</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Krause, E. L. 1881</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-08-28" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2019-10-17" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-12-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00240_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00240_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
        <surface n="B:61r" xml:id="i240">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00240.jpg" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00240_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00240.dzi" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:61v" xml:id="i241">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00241.jpg" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00241_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00241.dzi" width="3691px" height="6277px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 11. 3 Tr.</placeName>
                    <date>den 2.1.1881.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Indem ich Ihnen mit bestem Danke das Eintreffen Ihres freundlichen Schreibens vom 26<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. vorigen Monats bestätige<ref target="#foot.f2"/> und meine herzlichen Wünsche zum Jahreswechsel vorausschicke, muss ich sogleich um Entschuldigung bitten, dass meine Antwort so spät kommt. Durch einen Zufall hat sich nämlich die Fertigstellung des Januar-Heftes vom “Kosmos” um einige Tage verspätet, und da ich Ihnen meine darin abgedruckte Antwort auf Herrn Butlers Anklagen mitzusenden wünschte, so habe ich meine Antwort von einem Tage auf den andern verschoben, weil ich stets glaubte, am nächsten Morgen würden die gewünschten Abzüge eintreffen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Dies ist erst heute geschehen, und ich beeile mich, sie Ihnen mit den erforderlichen Correcturen einzusenden.</p>
                    <p>In dieser Erklärung bin ich nicht näher auf den Vorwurf eingegangen, dass ich seinem Buche die Bemerkung Coleridge’s u. das Citat aus Buffon entnommen habe. Die erstere war mir vor vier Jahren im Athenäum selbst aufgefallen, sie ist in deutschen Zeitschriften discutirt, und unter andern in dem von mir citirten Werke Zöckler’s (Life of Erasmus Darwin p. 151) welches vor dem Erscheinen des Opus 4 fertig vorlag, enthalten. Die Stelle aus Buffon habe ich in der That aus Butler’s Werk entliehen, und habe mich nachher in einer hiesigen Bibliothek überzeugt, dass das Citat im Allgemeinen richtig war.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In dem Original-Manuskript hatte ich hierbei speciel auf Butler’s Buch hingewiesen, und dabei bemerkt, dass Mr. Butler Buffon’s Ansichten meistens missverstanden habe. Diese Theile waren aber von Ihnen nachträglich gestrichen worden.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Um nun auf diesen Punkt noch besonders einzugehen, habe ich eine zweite Erwiederung, für den englischen Leser speciale aufgesetzt, welche, wenn Sie Ihnen passender erscheint, vielleicht von Mr. Dallas freundlichst im nächsten Hefte seiner Popular Science Review aufgenommen werden würde?<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In letzterem Falle würde ich Sie bitten, an dieser Antwort nach Ihrem freundlichen Ermessen ändern und kürzen zu wollen, wie es Ihnen am besten erscheinen würde. Es handelt sich in diesem Falle ja gar nicht um mich, sondern nur darum die beispiellos malitiösen Angriffe gegen Ihre Person zurückzuweisen. Mr. Butler sucht überall im Trüben zu fischen, seine ganzen Angriffe sind meiner Überzeugung nach, wider besseres Wissen, auf Täuschung der Leser berechnet. Bei uns wäre ein so alberner Angriff fast nicht denkbar.</p>
                    <p>Die Mittheilungen, welche ich Ihnen neulich über einen Prof. Jäger zugestossanen Unfall, und über ein Eingehen des Kosmos gemacht habe, sind glücklicherweise beide auf einen Irrthum zurückzuführen. Der ersteren lag eine Verwechselung der Person zu Grunde,—der Unfall hat einen andern Prof. Jaeger in Stuttgart getroffen<ref target="#foot.f7"/>—und was den Kosmos betrifft, so ist derselbe von Herrn Eduard Koch in Stuttgart, dem Verleger Ihrer Werke, gekauft worden und wird von demselben ganz in der bisherigen Form weiter geführt werden. Herr Koch theilt darin nicht die Ansicht seines Vorgängers, welcher allerdings mit der Absicht umging, das Journal in eine Wochenschrift umzuwandeln.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                <p>Um den Abgang dieses Briefes noch mit dem heutigen Eisenbahnzuge zu ermöglichen, schliesse ich diese Zeilen mit der Bitte, dass Sie den traurigen Angriffen Butlers nicht mehr Beachtung schenken möchten, als dieselben verdienen und zeichne, hochverehrter Herr | Ihr | dankbar ergebenster | Ernst Krause</p>
<p>P.S. Ich vermuthe, dass die im Manuscript beigefügte Erwiederung gelungener ausgefallen ist. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
                
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Unconscious memory by Samuel Butler</p>
<p>Opus 5. London David Bogue 1880, 208p in 8</p>
                    <p>In diesem Buche, welches sich im Wesentlichen mit dem Nachweise beschäftigt, dass die von M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler in seinem Opus 3 (Life and Habit)<ref target="#foot.f9"/> ausgesprochenen Ideen lange vorher von deutschen Naturforschern und Philosophen—nur mit grösserer Schärfe und in wissentschaftlicher Fassung—dargelegt worden sind, befinden sich eine Reihe grundloser Verdächtigungen gegen Herrn Charles Darwin und den Unterzeichneten, die hier der Reihe nach wiederligt werden sollen:</p>
                    <p>I) M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler behauptet M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin habe meinen in Feb 1879 veröffentlichten Aufsatz über D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erasmus Darwin nur deshalb in’s Englische übersetzen lassen, um sein (M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler’s) im Mai? 1879 erschienenes Opus 4 (Evolution Old and New) zu diskreditiren. Ich bemerke hierauf, dass Herr Darwin mir mehr als zwei Monate vor dem Erscheinen jenes Buches siene Absicht kundgethan hat, meinen Aufsatz in englischer Sprache herauszugeben, worauf ich um einen Aufschub bat um eine Überarbeitung vorzunehmen<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>II) Die Annahme des Herrn Butler, nach welchen Herr Darwin mich veranlasst haben soll, einige versteckte Angriffe gegen ihn (M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B) in meine Skizze einzuschalten, ist in dem Maasse unbegründet, dan M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin im Gegentheil mich ersucht hat, von dem inzwischen erschienenem Buche des Herrn Butler <hi rend="underline">keinerlei Notiz zu nehmen</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Da es indessen zum Ruhme des D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erasmus Darwin beiträgt, dass seine Ansichten über die Entwickelung der lebenden Welt, noch heute gewissen “Denkern” genügen, so habe ich dies in einem schlusssatze und ohne M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler zu nennen, angedeutet. Ich muss ausdrücklich hervorheben, dass Herr Darwin an meiner Arbeit zwar einige kürzungen vorgenommen, <hi rend="underline">aber keinerlei Zusätze gemacht, oder mir vorgeschlagen hat</hi>.</p>
                    <p>III) Wenn Herr Butler verkündet, meine Revision sei “by the light’ seines Buches geschehen, so ist dies insofern richtig, dass ich dusselbe noch vor Absendung meiner Arbeit gelesen habe und durch ihn auf einer stelle Buffon’s aufmerksam geworden bin. Über D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erasmus Darwins wissentschafliche Ansichten und Schriften habe ich dem genannten Buche nicht die geringste Andentung entnommen, oder entnehmen können, da dasselbe fast nur eine Stelle der Zoonomia ausführlicher diskutirt, die ich bereits vor ihm citirt hatte, während er den Botanic Garden nur in einer wenig wesenlichen stelle, die ‘Phytologia’ und den ‘Temple of Nature’ gar nicht benutzt hat,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> so dass ich von seiner höchst oberflächlichen Arbeit <hi rend="underline">keine Zeile</hi> brauchen konnte. Herrn Butler’s Behauptung, dass ich ihm eine Bemerkung von Coleridge entnommen habe, ist völlig grundlos. Ich kannte diesselbe seit Jahren aus der von mir genauer, als von ihm selbst citirten Quelle, sie ist überdem in dem (S 151) von mir citirten und <hi rend="underline">vor</hi> Butler’s Opus 4 erschienenern Werke Zöckler’s (B<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> II S 256) ebenfalls erwähnt.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Das gesammte “Licht,” welches ich Herrn Butler verdanke beschränkt sich also auf eine Citat aus Buffon!</p>
                    <p>IV) Was nun die Hauptbeschuldigang betrifft, dass die vorgenommene Revision meines Aufsatzes in der Vorrede nicht erwähnt is, so handelt es sich, wie ein Kind einsehen kann, hierbei um keine <hi rend="underline">Absicht</hi>, sondern lediglich nur ein <hi rend="underline">Versehen</hi>. Wenn ein Schriftstetter in einem zurückdatirten Artikel eine später erschienene Schrift angreifen wollte, so wäre dass einfach absurd, und weitenfernt, dass die “Fälschung” Herrn Butler schaden könnte, konnte sie ihm nur angenehm sein, da sie dem anaufmerksamen Leser veraulassen musste, zu glauben, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler sei in dem Schlusssatze for nicht gemeint.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> War er aber gemeint—und für jeden Eingeweiheten erscheint das zweifillos,—so wird jeder Mensch mit gesundem Verstande, die fürchterliche “Fälschung” sofort als einfaches Versehen erkennen <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Berlin 2 Januar 1881</p>
<p rend="left">(signed) Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
                       
                        
            
             
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 11. 3 Tr.</placeName>
                    <date>2.1.1881.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>While first mentioning with my best thanks the arrival of your kind letter of the 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of the previous month<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and wishing you a Happy New Year, I must immediately beg your forgiveness for replying so late. You see by accident the completion of the January issue of “Kosmos” was delayed by a few days, and as I wanted to send you my reply to Mr Butler’s accusations which is published in it, I postponed my reply from one day to the next, always thinking that the desired proof-sheets would arrive the next morning.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> This happened only today, and I hasten to send them to you with the necessary corrections.</p>
                    <p>In this statement I did not in any detail consider the accusation that I had taken Coleridge’s remark &amp; the quotation from Buffon from his book. The former I had noticed myself in the Athenæum four years ago, it has been discussed in German journals, and among others it is contained in Zoeckler’s work, which I cited (Life of Erasmus Darwin, p. 151), and which had been completed before Opus 4 came out. The passage from Buffon I have indeed taken from Butler, and I satisfied myself later in a local library that the quotation was generally correct.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In the original manuscript I referred specifically to Butler’s book in this connection, observing that Mr Butler had mostly misunderstood Buffon’s views. However, these passages were subsequently deleted by you.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>So, in order to address this point in particular, I composed a second reply specifically for English readers which, if you deem it more appropriate, could perhaps most helpfully be included by Mr Dallas in the next issue of his Popular Science Review?<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In the latter case, I would ask you to alter and shorten my reply at your kind discretion, as you deem best. Obviously in this case it is not about me, but only about repudiating the unprecedented malicious attacks against your person. Mr Butler seeks everywhere to fish in troubled waters; in my opinion, all his attacks are, against better knowledge, calculated to deceive the reader. Over here such an absurd attack is almost unthinkable.</p>
                    <p>The news I reported to you recently regarding an accident that had befallen Prof. Jäger, and about Kosmos ceasing publication, fortunately both turned out to be erroneous. Underlying the former was a case of mistaken identity,—the disaster had struck another Prof. Jaeger in Stuttgart<ref target="#foot.f7"/>—and as for Kosmos, it has been bought by Herr Eduard Koch of Stuttgart, the publisher of your works, and will be run by him wholly in its current form. In this, Herr Koch does not share the view of his predecessor, who indeed was contemplating to convert the journal into a weekly.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I close in order to allow this letter to go with today’s train, begging you not to give these sad attacks on Butler’s part more attention than they deserve, and remain, most esteemed Sir | Yours | gratefully devoted | Ernst Krause</p>
<p>P.S. I expect that the reply in the enclosed manuscript turned out more successful.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                    <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
                        
                        <div type="transcription">
                    <p>Unconscious memory by Samuel Butler</p>
                    <p>Opus 5. London David Bogue 1880, 208p in 8</p>
                            <p>In this book, which mainly deals with proof that the ideas expounded by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler in his Opus 3 (Life and Habit)<ref target="#foot.f9"/> have long since been elaborated by German naturalists and philosophers—only with greater precision and more scientific wording, a series of unfounded suspicions are levelled against Mr Charles Darwin and the undersigned, which will be disproved here one after the other:</p>
                            <p>I) M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler maintains that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin arranged the translation into English of my essay on D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erasmus Darwin, published in Feb 1879, solely to discredit his (M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler’s) Opus 4 (Evolution Old and New), which appeared in May? 1879. On this point, I note that Mr Darwin had expressed his intention of publishing my essay in English more than two months before the appearance of this book, whereupon I asked for a delay so that I could undertake revisions.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                            <p>II) Mr Butler’s assumption that Mr Darwin arranged to insert some hidden attacks against him (M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B) in my sketch, is wholly unfounded, since on the contrary, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin asked me <hi rend="underline">to take no notice whatsoever</hi> of Mr Butler’s book, which had appeared in the interim.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Since, however, it contributes to the fame of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erasmus Darwin, that his views on the development of the living world even today satisfy certain “thinkers”, I have hinted at it in a concluding sentence and without naming M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler. I must explicitly stress that Mr Darwin indeed made some cuts to my work, <hi rend="underline">but made no additions at all nor suggested any to me</hi>.</p>
                            <p>III) If Mr Butler declares that my revision was made “by the light’ of his book, this is correct in the sense that I read it before sending off my work, and through him I was made aware of a point of Buffon’s. On D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erasmus Darwin’s scientific views and writing I have not taken the slightest suggestion from the aforesaid book, nor could I, since almost only one point in Zoonomia, which I had already cited before him, is extensively discussed in it, while he has used the Botanic Garden only in one point of little importance, and the ‘Phytologia’ and the ‘Temple of Nature’ not at all,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> so that from his highly superficial work I could use <hi rend="underline">not a line</hi>. Mr Butler’s claim that I have taken a remark about Coleridge from him is completely baseless. I knew this remark years ago from the source that he himself cites (by me cited more accurately); it is also mentioned in the work of Zöckler (vol. 2, p. 256) that I cited on p. 151, and that appeared before Butler’s Opus 4.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
                    <p>The whole “light” that I owe to Mr Butler is thus restricted to one quote from Buffon!</p>
                            <p>IV) Regarding the main accusation, that the aforesaid revision of my essay is not mentioned in the preface, as a child can see, this is not a matter of <hi rend="underline">intent</hi>, but rather only an <hi rend="underline">oversight</hi>. It would be simply absurd if a writer wanted to attack a subsequent text in a backdated article, and far from the “falsification” harming Mr Butler, it could only be agreeable to him, since the inattentive reader would be bound to believe that no reference was intended to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butler in the concluding sentence.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> But if he was referred to—and for everyone in the know that seems without doubt,—then every person with common sense would at once recognise the horrible “falsification” as a simple oversight <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
                    <p rend="left">Berlin 2 January 1881</p>
                    <p rend="left">(signed) Ernst Krause</p>                         
                        </div>                           
            </div>
            
            
               
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12939.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 26 December 1880</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Krause’s review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11180.xml">Butler 1880</ref> was published in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11261.xml">Krause 1881b</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Samuel Butler</ref> had accused Krause and CD of making unacknowledged use of his work (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11180.xml">Butler 1880</ref>, pp. 58–79). CD had informed Krause of Butler’s accusations in his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12939.xml">26 December 1880</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Opus 4 was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml">Butler 1879</ref>. The quotation from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1014.xml">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref> was taken by Krause from the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 27 March 1875, p. 423 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 134). The quotation from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_714.xml">Georges Louis Leclerc, comte de Buffon</ref>, had appeared in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Butler 1879</ref>, p. 120; however, in <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, pp. 147–8, Krause cited the original source (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1052.xml">Buffon<hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> 1749–1804</ref>, 5: 104). Krause also cited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5290.xml">Otto Zöckler</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Beziehungen zwischen Theologie und Naturwissenschaft</hi> (History of the relations between theology and natural science; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11166.xml">Zöckler 1877–9</ref>) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 151 n. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had asked Krause to make substantial cuts to his essay in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12192.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 13 August 1879</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12194.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 16 August 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> was the editor of <hi rend="italic">Popular Science Review</hi>. An English translation of Krause’s reply to Butler was published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 27 January 1881, p. 288.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Krause had informed CD that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml">Gustav Jäger</ref> had fallen under a train (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12889.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 4 December 1880</ref>); the other Professor Jäger has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">On the purchase of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2732.xml">Eduard Koch</ref>, the head of E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12889.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 4 December 1880</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml">Butler 1878</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD had requested permission to publish an English translation of Krause’s essay on Erasmus Darwin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879</ref>) in his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11920.xml">9 March 1879</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27). <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Butler 1879</ref> was published on 3 May 1879; CD had been told about it by Dallas, and had also seen a notice of publication (see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12045.xml">letter from W. S. Dallas, 9 May 1879</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12051.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 13 May 1879</ref> and n. 3). Krause had asked for time to revise and enlarge the essay in his letters of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11925.xml">12 March 1879</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11961.xml">30 March 1879</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.)</hi>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">For Krause’s initial assessment of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Butler 1879</ref>, see his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12092.xml">7 June 1879</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27). CD had written to Krause, ‘I hope that you will not expend much powder &amp; shot on Mr. Butler, for he really is not worthy of it. His work is merely ephemeral’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12096.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 9 June [1879]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1793.xml">E. Darwin 1800</ref>, and  <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1794.xml">E. Darwin 1803</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">For the reference to Coleridge, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11166.xml">Zöckler 1877–9</ref>, 2: 256.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The allusion to Butler appeared in the final sentence of Krause’s essay in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 216: ‘Erasmus Darwin’s system was in itself a most significant first step in the path of knowledge which his grandson has opened up for us, but the wish to revive it at the present day as has actually been seriously attempted shows a weakness of thought and a mental anachronism which no man can envy.’</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>