<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8489">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Anton Dohrn   28 August 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16338</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8489 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8489.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8489.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Groeben (1982): 43</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 210</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 210</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml">Dohrn, F. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Lewisham</placeName>
                <date when="1872-08-28">28 Aug 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Will call on CD next year, when he will have worked out the embryology of <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus</hi>; he believes it is not primitive but a degenerate form of fish. He believes the true ancestors of vertebrates are annelids.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">aboriginal forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">degeneration</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Mountsfield. Lewisham. | Naples Address: Palazzo Torlonia. Mergellina.</placeName>
                    <date>28.8.72.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many and sincere thanks for Your kind letter and the generous present You promise for the Library of the Station.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Messrs. Williams &amp; Norgate are ready to act as my Agents for this Country,<ref target="#foot.f2"/>—so whenever You may be disposed to favour the Zoological Station with Your books, they will forward them to Naples. I have even got free transport for everything through the kindness of Admiral Tchichatchoff, the Director of the Russian Steamship-Line in Odessa.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You see I use every opportunity, which offers itself.</p>
<p>Meanwhile I have been paying a short visit to Scarborough, as there is an opportunity for getting up a Second Zoological Station, Mr. Woodall, a banker, being inclined to lay out some 3 or 4000£. for it, and content himself with a moderate return of the money, leaving the surplus to the Scientific work to be done there.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I hope the scheme may be carried, though I am sure the coals want still a little blowing for fear they might burn away. I don’t know whether Zephyrus or Boreas might be in his place there,—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I shall try my powers at any rate.</p>
<p>I got a letter from Prof. Huxley<ref target="#foot.f6"/> the other day, so full of good spirits and of his usual vigour that I hope, if he only would not work to hard he might restore himself completely.</p>
<p>I thank You very heartily for Your kind invitation, which I will accept as soon, as I have to tell You anything settled about that Problem of homologies and genealogical relations between Annelids Arthropod and Vertebrates, which I, against the views of my Jena masters consider to be very close.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I hope, when returning to Your country next year after having carefully worked out the Embryology of Amphioxus, I may be able to prove, that this animal by no means is a primitive but in the contrary a very <hi rend="underline">degraded</hi> and <hi rend="underline">degenerate</hi> form of fish, and that the true ancestors of Vertebrates are <hi rend="underline">Annelids.</hi> It is a long story to tell, but I believe that after all it is the true story of the past and will upset all the Ascidians, and reduce them to still further degraded forms than Amphioxus.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Their relations to Vertebrates I don’t question at all, but instead of placing them at the root, I put them on one end of the tree, whose branches tend as well upright to the sky, as down to the lowest ranks. And I believe, that is very much the tendency in all the other tribes, or so-called types.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> But I am talking to much.</p>
<p>Once more, my dear Sir, my hearty thanks. Your kindness stirs me always mightily up, and I hope I may succeed in my ends, if I meet similar assistance in other quarters.</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Anton Dohrn</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had promised to send a complete set of his publications to the zoological station at Naples (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Anton Dohrn, 24 August [1872]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5147.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Williams &amp; Norgate</ref> was a London publisher.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Admiral Tchichatchoff: Nikolai Matveevich Chikhachev, managing director of the Russian Steam Navigation and Trading Company.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7046.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Woodall Woodall</ref> was a banker in Scarborough, a seaside town in North Yorkshire. He had been a member of the British Association since 1863 (<hi rend="italic">Report of the 42d meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science</hi> (1872)). An aquarium was opened in Scarborough in 1877 as part of a popular entertainment complex that included a concert hall and reading room (Howard Norfolk, ‘Aquariums and public aquariums in mid-Victorian times’, www.aquarticles.com/articles/literature/Norfolk_Victorian_History.html (accessed 19 October 2011)). On Dohrn’s programme for establishing zoological stations around the world, see Dohrn 1872a and 1872b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Zephyros is the Greek god of the west wind; Boreas of the north wind.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Dohrn had worked at the University of Jena under <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref> and Carl Gegenbaur from 1866 to 1868 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 58–60, 67–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">On Dohrn’s work on <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus</hi>, his efforts to establish the Annelida (segmented worms) rather than the Ascidiacea (sea squirts) as the ancestral group of the vertebrates, and his disagreements with Haeckel and Gegenbaur, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5158.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maienschein 1994</ref>. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7925.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Anton Dohrn, 7 September 1871</ref> and n. 17. The lancelet (formerly <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus lanceolatus</hi>, now <hi rend="italic">Branchiostoma lanceolatum</hi>) was initially classed as a primitive fish (subclass Acranii) but has now been moved to its own class, Cephalochordata. The terms amphioxus and lancelet are commonly used now to refer to all members of the class.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Dohrn’s work on the origin of vertebrates was later published as <hi rend="italic">Der Ursprung der Wirbelthiere und das Princip des Functionswechsels</hi> (The origin of vertebrates and the principle of functional change; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>