<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8907">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Hermann Müller   19 May 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9827</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8907 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8907.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8907.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp †, CD note, sketch †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 76: B181–2, DAR 77: 139</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>76: B181–2a,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>77: 139</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Müller, H. L. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Lippstadt</placeName>
                <date when="1873-05-19">19 May 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Praises <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Reports on Fritz Müller’s observations of cross- and self-fertilisation. HM will cultivate the two forms [i.e., mainly self-fertilised and mainly cross-fertilised] in the way CD has described.</p> 
<p>He continues his observation of wild flowers. Encloses drawing of <hi rend="italic">Viola tricolor</hi> with notes on its self-fertility.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">wild flowers</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lippstadt</placeName>
                    <date>19. 5. 73.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You have very much rejoiced me by sending me your book on Expression.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Reading this book immediately after its appearance I have admired anew your inimitable sagacity and exactness in observing such facts that every one has overlooked as insignificant and which in your hands spread a plenty of light over the most mysterious districts of human understanding. I have been ravished by the evident interpretation you have given of the expression of affects in animals and men, and I have anew been convinced that also psychology will make progress only by leaning on observations of the activity of the soul of animals.— I am very glad to possess this wonderful work from your own hand.</p>
<p>My brother has indeed fertilised in different plants some flowers with strictly their own pollen and other ones by other flowers on the same plant. But in the most cases viz. with Bignonia (Bot. Zeit. 1868. Nr. 39), Tabernaemontana echinata (Bot. Z. 1870. p. 274.), and Abutilon (Jenaische Zeitschrift) he found those plants which are sterile with their own pollen, also sterile with the pollen from distinct flowers on the same plant. Only in Eschscholtzia californica (Bot. Zeit. 1869. Nr. 14) which he found sterile with its own pollen, he was successful in some degree in fertilising it with pollen from a distinct flower on the same plant.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In order to acquaint you as quickly as possible with the details I send you spare copies of my brothers trials, except Bot. Zeit. 1870. p. 274., of which I do not possess any spare copy.</p>
<p>The number of those plants which exist in two forms, (one more remarkable, more richly visited by insects and never fertilising itself, the other one unsightly, rarely visited by insects but constantly fertilising itself) is certainly much greater than it would appear according to my book.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have examined just now the wild Viola tricolor (var. arvensis) and I have found that this plant also constantly fertilises itself (I add a drawing of it)   I suppose that Mr. Bennett in the article May 15, 1873 of the “Nature”, you allude to, has published the same fact, and I would be very glad to become acquainted with this article   I will ask the editor of the Nature for it.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Certainly I shall cultivate several of those plants which exist in the two forms alluded to and I shall try with them in the manner announced by you.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>At present I continue ardently to examine the flowers of our wild plants and to research for their fertilisers. Viola tricolor, Myosurus minimus, Calla palustris and Myosotis versicolor are those,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> the examination of which has given the most interesting results. In Myosurus the enorm growth of the cone of pistils effects no other thing but the regular self fertilisation of the numerous stigmas by the small number of anthers</p>
<p>Calla palustris is fertilised, like Arum maculatum by very small Dipterous insects, but not by one species but by very different ones; also various Coleoptera are attracted by the white spatha but without finding a recompense. This plant is proterogyne like Arum maculatum, but not so completely.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I cultivate now specimens in my room, in order to decide if they are fertile by self-fertilisation</p>
<p>In Myosotis versicolor the flower opens before having got its blue colour and its ful greatness, by this the style overlooks the anthers affixed to the corolla, and if insects visit now the flower they fertilise it by pollen of other flowers. But a few hours after the opening of the flower the corolla grows in such a degree that the anthers surround closely the stigma and powder it with own pollen.</p>
<p>My brother is very well. During the last years he has spent his leisure time in observing the mimicry of butterflies and the natural history of termites. On the latter subject he will publish some essays, the copies of which I will send you as soon as I receive them. Intending to investigate the genealogy of bees more closely than I have done in my “application of the Darwinian theory to bees” I have begged my brother for sending me specimens of Brasilian bees, and gratifying to my wishes he has not only sent me many Brasilian forms of bees but also acquainted me with a plenty of facts respecting the economy of them.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>My dear Sir | yours sincerely | H. Müller</p>
<p><figure rend="blockCentred width90">
    <graphic url="../images/DCP-LETT-8907.svg"/>
</figure></p>
<p>This form of Viola tricolor fertilises itself inevitably, the pollen falling from itself out of the anthers and arriving directly in the opening of the stigma-head, which in flowers perfectly opened is always found fulfilled with pollen grains</p>
<p>The specimens which I have cultivated in my room and guarded during the evolution of the flowers from the visits of insects are quite fertile—will come to maturity in several days.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 You have … hand. 1.9] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.3 Tabernaemontana echinata] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.5 also … plant. 2.6] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 The number … of them. 9.8] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Certainly … by you. 5.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘I thank you for very interesting letter in many ways | <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> | Brother | Difference of other flowers on same plant, &amp; strictly self’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">[</hi>Riley<hi rend="italic">]</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon del blue crayon</hi>; ‘Kerner’<ref target="#foot.f9"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Alongside diagram</hi>: ‘H. Muller’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘There is paper by A. W. Bennett Nature 1873 May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> p. 49. on the Fert of Wild Pansy (V. arvensis) &amp; includes fertilisation by Thrips’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi><ref target="#foot.f10"/></note>
            </div>
            <div type="cdnotes">
            <note> 
<p>p. 134. perfect M. S.</p>
<p>Digitalis ♂ flower crossed by own pollen &amp; by that from other flowers on same plant— in watch glasses no difference in quantity, by eye but by weight self seeds heavier <figure type="inlinediagram">
<p>crossed gr self</p>
<p>7<hi rend="superscript">.</hi>65 : 7<hi rend="superscript">.</hi>7</p></figure></p>
<p>p. 67 perfect M. S.— analyse evidence about seeds of Ipomœa</p>
<p>p 150. Origanum *vulgare— long cultivated [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] rather more seeds produced by plants from same <hi rend="italic">[</hi>stock<hi rend="italic">]</hi> than by self fertilisation</p>
<p>p. 209 Perfect M. S. Dianthus no marked [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] difference in number of seeds produced by crossing flowers on same plant &amp; self fertilisation<ref target="#foot.f11"/> [‘<hi rend="italic">Lobelia fulgens</hi> I believe same fact’ <hi rend="italic">pencil del pencil</hi>; ‘Victoria Lily’ <hi rend="italic">ink del ink</hi>]</p></note>
              </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD probably sent Müller a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> in return for Müller’s gift of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 28 February 1873</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had evidently asked Müller the same set of questions he asked Hildebrand (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8912F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Friedrich Hildebrand, 15 May 1873</ref>) in a now missing letter. Müller refers to <hi rend="italic">Eschscholzia californica</hi> and to the work of his brother, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> (see F. Müller 1868, 1870, 1872–3, and 1869). CD drew on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> work in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>. There are copies of F. Müller 1868 and 1872–3 in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. <hi rend="italic">Tabernaemontana echinata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">T. siphilitica</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Müller mentioned thirteen specific plants or genera exhibiting these two forms in his book on the fertilisation of flowers by means of insects (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>), including some species of <hi rend="italic">Viola</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 146). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 610–12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his article on the fertilisation of the wild pansy (Bennett 1873a), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_389.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred William Bennett</ref> had pointed out the inconclusiveness of Müller’s observations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>, p. 118). Joseph <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2971.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Norman Lockyer</ref> was the editor of <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>; Bennett was the biological subeditor.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD possibly mentioned his manner of cultivation in his missing letter (see n. 2, above), or Müller may refer to the experimental method described by CD in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2497.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilisation of Leschenaultia’</ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [before 13 November 1858]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">These plants are the pansy, mousetail (of the buttercup family), water arum, and forget-me-not, respectively.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The flowers of <hi rend="italic">Arum maculatum</hi>, the wild arum, are encased in a sheath or spatha before their expansion. In proterogynous plants the female reproductive organs (pistils) become fertile before the male ones (stamens). Much of the material Müller worked on after the publication of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref> was added to the English translation of 1883 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5700.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1883</ref>, p. vii), including a description of <hi rend="italic">Calla palustris</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 565).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Müller’s brother, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, lived in the Itajaí valley, Brazil. For Müller’s work on the genealogy of bees, see H. Müller 1872.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">These are evidently notes for CD’s reply, which has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8923.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 27 May 1873</ref>. The reference is probably to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2677.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anton Kerner von Marilaun’s</ref> work on the features of floral morphology that govern plant fertilisation (Kerner von Marilaun 1873).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD evidently sent a copy of Bennett 1873a (see n. 4, above) to Müller; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8923.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 27 May 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The page numbers refer to the manuscript pages of CD’s draft of the first ten chapters of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (DAR 2 and DAR 3).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>