<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3710">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   [3–]4 September [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3617</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3710 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3710.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3710.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp sketch</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 212</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 123</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 10: 389</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (68)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>68</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Bournemouth</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1862-09-03" notAfter="1862-09-04">[3–]4 Sept [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Glad AG will publish some separate notes on orchids ["Fertilization of orchids through the agency of insects", <hi rend="italic">Am. J. Sci.</hi> 2d ser. 34 (1862): 420–9].</p>  
<p>Trimorphism in <hi rend="italic">Lythrum</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Bee behaviour.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bees</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Lythrum</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Am. J. Sci.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1862c</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cliff Cottage. Bournemouth. Hants</placeName>
                    <date>Sept. 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Gray.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have just received your most kind letter of Aug 18 &amp; 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; will amuse myself, now my patients are in bed,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> by beginning a letter to you. My poor Boy (whose waxen face blushed up to the eyes at the thought of writing to a live Professor)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> has this day made a marked step &amp; has taken several walks of a few hundred yards; &amp; my wife is recovering well &amp; her skin well peeling.— We have taken two houses here, so I hope &amp; trust this dredful fever will not spread.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am very glad that at present you intend to publish some separate notes on orchids, which you have so capitally worked out.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> No doubt I am not a fair judge; but I must think that it is worth your while.— I am pleased to hear about Goodyera &amp; about Gymnadia tridentata. Your account makes me think the latter like the Bonatea speciosa &amp; often &amp; often have I speculated what on earth could be meaning of its wonderful horn-like stigmas &amp; projecting anthers.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I suspect its structure may have been arrived at by a process somewhat analogous to that which apparently has produced the wondrous nectary of Angræcum sesquipedale.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> It would appear that self-fertilisation is commoner than I thought: since publishing I have found that Neottia nidus-avis fertilises itself, <hi rend="underline">if insects fail to do the job</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Many thanks for Houstonia seed.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I am glad to hear, but disappointed, about the Specularia pollen-tubes.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I cannot resist sending you a diagram about Lythrum (why should I resist? does not prescription give a right? &amp; have I not for long years written &amp; bothered you about all sorts of things?) Lythrum has 3 kinds of stigmas &amp; 3 kinds of pollen; the stamens of same height on two of the three forms producing the same sort of pollen, &amp; I cannot doubt are fitted to fertilise the stigma of that height. I conclude so from watching the Bees; but hope to prove it by my crosses. So that we have three hermaphrodite forms each depending on half the stamens of either one of the two other forms. This is shown by the lines with the arrows. This strikes me as a very curious case. The three forms coexist in about equal numbers. By the way it seems to me that Lindley in Veg. Kingdom describes the homological structure of flower wrong:<ref target="#foot.f12"/> the so called calyx, with its 12 bundles of spiral vessels, appears to consist of 6 narrow sepals &amp; 6 modified petals, all cohering; &amp; that the coloured petals belong to an inner whorl &amp; are modified stamens. By the way can you tell me of any flowers, with fertile anthers of different colours; I believe that this would be pretty sure guide to dimorphism or trimorphism.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>All my semibotanical work, as you know, has been connected with insects, &amp; now I am almost sure (but I find it a disgusting truth that with me first observations are generally all a blunder) that flowers have led me to a curious little discovery with respect to the best-known insect in the world, the Hive Bee. I saw the other day to my dismay (see Origin) Hive Bees sucking the common red clover, but it was a second crop, which I am <hi rend="underline">told</hi> produces shorter flowers;<ref target="#foot.f14"/> but many of the Bees never attempted this, but always inserted their heads between the flowers &amp; sucked at holes bitten through the corolla.— The same bee always followed the same practice. And apparently those which suck at the mouth of the flower have a longer proboscis than the other bees, which suck through the holes.</p>
<p>Farewell my dear Gray, forgive me scribbling about my own work; for I seldom see a soul to talk with on natural history.</p>
<p>Good night— Ever yours most truly | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Since writing the above by Jove I have found I have as usual at first blundered about the probosces; but if you had seen the Bees, the blunder was almost excusable—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> What an ass I was to scribble all the above.—</p>
<p>Progress of Education.— one of my little Boys Horace<ref target="#foot.f16"/> said to me, “there are a terrible number of adders here; but if everyone killed as many as they could, they would sting less”.— I answered “of course they would be fewer”   Horace “Of course, but I did not mean that; what I meant was, that the more timid adders, which run away &amp; do not sting would be saved, &amp; after a time none of the adders would sting”.—</p>
<p>Natural selection!!</p> 
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width65">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_3710.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
<p><ref target="#foot.f17"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.8 must] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.12 horn-like] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.12 its structure] ‘its’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.13 apparently] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.2 (why … things?) 2.4] <hi rend="italic">square brackets in MS</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.7 it] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.16 or] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.2 (but … blunder) 3.3] <hi rend="italic">square brackets in MS</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">7.1 little] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">7.1 Horace] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 18–19 August 1862</ref>. CD’s date was written in the top left-hand margin of the first page of the letter, and apparently represents the date on which the letter was completed. The relationship of this letter to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, [3 September 1862]</ref> indicates that it must have been started before the letter to Lubbock, on the evening of 3 September 1862, and completed after that letter (see nn. 14 and 15, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter from Asa Gray, 18–19 August 1862</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Emma and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin</ref> were recovering from scarlet fever (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3708.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, 2 September [1862]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Gray had sent a number of North American postage stamps for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin’s</ref> stamp collection (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 21 July 1862</ref>), and in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml">letter to CD of 18–19 August 1862</ref>, Gray suggested that Leonard should write to let him know what stamps he still required. A letter from Leonard was apparently enclosed with this letter (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3736.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 22 September 1862</ref> and n. 3); however, the enclosure has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3708.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, 2 September [1862]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 18–19 August 1862</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 18–19 August 1862</ref>, Gray described the occurrence in <hi rend="italic">Gymnadenia tridentata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Platanthera clavellata</hi>, the small green wood orchid) of ‘an arm of stigma carried up each side of anther, &amp; one between the [anther] cells’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The reference is to the long nectary of <hi rend="italic">Angraecum sesquipedale</hi>; in the specimens examined by CD, the nectary had been ‘eleven and a half inches long’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 197). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 202–3, CD provided the following explanation of the origin of the nectary: <quote type="quote"> As certain moths of Madagascar became larger through natural selection in relation to their general conditions of life, either in the larval or mature state, or as the proboscis alone was lengthened to obtain honey from the Angræcum and other deep tubular flowers, those individual plants of the Angræcum which had the longest nectaries … , and which, consequently, compelled the moths to insert their probosces up to the very base, would be best fertilized. These plants would yield most seed, and the seedlings would generally inherit longer nectaries; and so it would be in successive generations of the plant and moth. </quote> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 330, CD had suggested that the length of the caudicle carrying the pollinia in <hi rend="italic">Bonatea speciosa</hi> had probably been ‘largely increased in length by natural selection’, rather than merely by the abortion of the lower pollen-grains.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, CD had sought to demonstrate that the primary object of the various pollination mechanisms of orchids was to ensure cross-pollination (p. 1), and he noted only one case (<hi rend="italic">Ophrys apifera</hi>) in which there were ‘special contrivances’ for self-pollination (p. 359); however, in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml">letter to CD of 18–19 August 1862</ref>, Gray reported that <hi rend="italic">Gymnadenia tridentata</hi> provided a further example. Suspecting that <hi rend="italic">Neottia nidus-avis</hi> might also be self-pollinating, CD had experimented with the species in May, comparing the seed-pods produced by a plant which had been covered to exclude insects, with those from an uncovered plant (see the notes, dated 17 and 21 May 1862, and 10 August 1862, in DAR 70: 73–4, 81). CD included this species on an undated list of ‘self-fertilisers’ that is now in DAR 70: 167, and also discussed it in his revised account of ‘self-fertilisation’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 290.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3679.xml">letter to CD of 4 August 1862</ref>, Gray had expressed a hope that he would be able to send CD seeds of ‘the little <hi rend="italic">Houstonia</hi>’; the seeds were probably enclosed with Gray’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 18–19 August 1862</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3688.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 18–19 August 1862</ref> and n. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lindley 1853</ref>, pp. 574–5. Although CD’s copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Vegetable kingdom</hi> has not been found, this is the edition of the work listed in CD’s Library catalogue (DAR 240), and frequently referred to in <hi rend="italic">Orchids.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3696.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 22 [August 1862]</ref> and n. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, [3 September 1862]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3673.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, [2–3 September 1862]</ref> and n. 5. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 94–5, CD stated that hive-bees were unable to suck the nectar out of the flowers of the common red clover, which he claimed were ‘visited by humble-bees alone’ (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 73). However, on the basis of information provided by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2115.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Hardy</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2877.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Hardy, 23 July 1860</ref>), CD added the following statement to the third edition (p. 100): ‘I have been informed, that when the red clover has been mown, the flowers of the second crop are somewhat smaller, and that these are abundantly visited by hive-bees.’ In the fourth edition (p. 107), CD expressed some doubt about the accuracy of this statement, noting: <quote type="quote"> That this nectar is much liked by the hive-bee is certain; for I have repeatedly seen, but only in the autumn, many hive-bees sucking the flowers through holes in the base of the tube which had been bitten by humble-bees. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, [3 September 1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">The diagram has been reduced to 50% of its original size.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>