<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2327">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Willem Hendrik de Vriese to J. D. Hooker<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>    21 September 1858</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14664</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2327 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2327.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2327.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 180: 27</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>180: 27</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4909.xml">Vriese, W. H. de</persName>
                <placeName>Cheribon, Java</placeName>
                <date when="1858-09-21">21 Sept 1858</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Answers CD’s query about distribution of European perennials in the highlands of Java.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">perennials</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Europe</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Java highlands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Mon cher ami, Dr. Hooker!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Le jardin de Buitenzorg est situé à 800’ de hauteur. Le jardin de Tjipannas, dans les Preanger Regencies est à 2400’. C’est là que l’on cultive beaucoup de plantes, des climats plus temperés, surtout du Japon, de l’Australie, du Cap, de Californie, p.e. les Chènes du Japon, les Araucarias, les Eucalyptus, le Wellingtonia gigantea, et une foule d’autres plantes les plus remarquables.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Un autre jardin se trouve non loin de Tjipannas, mais à une élévation plus grande, de 4000’. C’est le jardin de Tjibodas. On y cultive les légumes Euro-peennes, les fruits des Drupacées, les fraises, les framboises et le Quinquina. Plus haut encore il y a, dans le même voisinage des cultures d’autres plantes, qui exigent une température encore plus élévée. J’ai visité tout recemment tous ces jardins.</p>
<p>Pour repondre à la question de M. Darwin, sur quelle hauteur végétent les plantes perennantes d’environ la latitude de la Grande Bretagne, je dirai ce que j’en ai vu.</p>
<p>Au montagne du Gédé j’ai pu observer, ce qui suit. Les formes Européennes commencent deja à 8500’. La Cankrienia chrysantha, Valeriana officinalis (?), comme un nombre immense de formes alpines, se trouvent sur le sommet du Gédé à 9300’. Mais la Cankrienia 〈se〉 trouve deja à 8700’. Elles portent 〈des〉 fruits et des graines. Je crois que beau〈coup〉 de formes de nos climats y pou〈r〉raient parfaitement réussir, sans aucune protection. Il va sans dire que le degré d’humidité doit différer pour les formes différentes et dans d’autres stations. Je crois que M. Darwin juge très bien que plusieurs plantes de l’Europe centrale reussiront à 5000’–6000’.</p>
<p>Voila mon cher Hooker la reponse aux questions de M. Darwin. Je suis disposé à lui donner après mon retour en Europe mes notes spéciales sur cet objet.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Je suis obligé <hi rend="underline">malgré moi</hi> d’être court. Ne veuillez pas m’en vouloir. Je suis inspecteur des cultures, adviseur du gouvernement ici et en Europe, je dois soigner mes rapports, mes notes, mes collections. etc etc.</p>
<p>Remerciez mad. votre épouse pour les bons souvenirs qu’elle veut bien me porter, et lui souhaite comme à vous toute la prosperité possible avec vos chers enfants. Je regrette beaucoup la perte de M. Brown.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Je le respectais et je l’aimais beaucoup.</p>
<p>Vous avez sans doute toujours beaucoup d’affaires avec vos publications et avec le jardin. Ne travaillez pas trop!</p>
<p>Votre tout devoué | W. H. de Vriese <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> Sheribon (Java)</p>
<p>21 Sept. 1858<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear friend, Dr. Hooker!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The garden of Buitenzorg is located at a height of 800<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>. The garden of Tji-pannas, in the Preanger Regencies is at 2400<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>. Many plants of more temperate climates are cultivated there, especially those of Japan, Australia, the Cape, and California; for example, oaks from Japan, Araucarias, Eucalyptus, Wellingtonia gigantea, and a host of other most unusual plants.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Another garden not far from Tjipannas but at a higher elevation, 4000<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>, is the garden of Tjibodas. European legumes, fruits belonging to the Drupaceae, strawberries, raspberries and quinquina are grown there. Still higher in the same vicinity other plants requiring an even higher temperature are grown. I have visited all these gardens quite recently.</p>
<p>In answer to Mr. Darwin’s question about the elevation at which perennial plants of the latitude of Great Britain grow, I shall tell you what I have seen of them.</p>
<p>On Gedeh mountain I was able to observe the following. European forms begin to occur at 8500<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>. Cankrienia chrysantha, Valeriana officinalis (?), along with a large number of alpine forms, are found on the summit of Gedeh at 9300<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>. Cankrienia is already found at 8700<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>. They bear fruit and seeds. I believe that many forms from your climate would be able to succeed perfectly without any protection. It goes without saying that the degree of humidity required ought to differ for forms that are different or inhabit other sites. I think that Mr. Darwin is quite correct in his judgment that several plants of central Europe would survive at 5000<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>–6000<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>.</p>
<p>There is my answer to Mr. Darwin’s questions, my dear Hooker. I am willing to give him my notes especially related to this subject when I return to Europe.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I regret that I am obliged to be brief. Please don‘t hold it against me. I am inspector of cultivation, advisor to the government here and in Europe, I must take care of my reports, my notes, my collections, etc etc.</p>
<p>Thank your wife for the good remembrances that she wishes to send me, and wish that she, yourself, and your dear children may all prosper. I greatly regret the loss of Mr. Brown,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I respected and liked him very much.</p>
<p>No doubt you are always busy with your publications and the garden. Don’t work too hard!</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | W. H. de Vriese <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Sheribon (Java) | 21 Sept. 1858<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.7, Appendix I. The letter indicates that Hooker had written to Vriese on CD’s behalf. Vriese’s reply was passed on to CD (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [20 November 1858]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For the transcription of this letter in its original French, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.7, pp. 156–8. The letter indicates that Hooker had written to Vriese on CD’s behalf. Vriese’s reply was passed on to CD (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [20 November 1858]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Vriese was professor of botany and director of the botanic garden in Leiden. In 1857, he travelled to Java and the Malay Archipelago on a government-sponsored mission to promote the culture of useful and economic plants (<hi rend="italic">Hooker’s Journal of</hi> <hi rend="italic">Botany and Kew Garden Miscellany</hi> 9 (1857): 346).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD did not cite any of the specific data given in this letter. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 375, however, he reported that: ‘A list of the genera collected on the loftier peaks of Java raises a picture of a collection made on a hill in Europe!’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Robert Brown, who had visited Vriese in Leiden, had died on 10 June 1858. In the early 1850s, Vriese had worked at Kew during the preparation of his monograph on the Marattiaceae. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vriese 1853</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The manuscript is deteriorating and this portion is now missing. The date has been taken from a transcription made by the editors at an earlier date.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>