<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-151">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fanny Owen    2 [December 1831]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5174</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-151 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-151.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-151.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">DE 〈4〉 18〈3〉1</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 54</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 54</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3619.xml">Owen, F. M. (a)</persName>
                <placeName>Woodhouse</placeName>
                <date when="1831-12-02">2 [Dec 1831]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes the wedding of her sister Sarah and related festivities. She misses CD very much.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3630">Owen, S. H. M.</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">wedding</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Woodhouse</placeName>
                    <date>Friday 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In a letter I had from Catherine yesterday, she told me you were still waiting in suspense at Plymouth, &amp; it was uncertain whether you sailed on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or not— I hope <hi rend="underline">not</hi> that this may reach you in time, for I want to have one bit more chat with you— I thought you were expecting every day to be <hi rend="underline">y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. last</hi> at Plymouth so that if I wrote to you it would be useless or I assure you I should not have been silent all this time— my dear Charles how I do wish you had been <hi rend="underline">with</hi> us on the awful <hi rend="doubleUnderline">22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> </hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am sure you would <hi rend="underline">thoroughly</hi> have enjoyed it all—from beginning to end it certainly (tho’ I say it who should not) did go off most brilliantly— I was the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Undertaker</hi> and managed the whole affair from <hi rend="underline">cutting up</hi> of a <hi rend="underline">Ton</hi> of cake to making <hi rend="underline">gallons</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Rum Punch</hi> for the evening’s festivities— Susan &amp; I of course you know were the Bridesmaids, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charles Jones the <hi rend="underline">Bridesmaid’s Man</hi>, about 10 carriages I think composed the Procession to Felton, the <hi rend="underline">dew Drops</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">fell</hi> about 11 o’clock, and I think really every body behaved with becoming fortitude &amp; resignation—as for poor Mama she was wonderful The <hi rend="underline">Bridegroom</hi> I think was the most <hi rend="underline">flabbergasted</hi> of the whole party, poor thing I was quite sorry for him, he was as <hi rend="underline">white</hi> as a <hi rend="underline">sheet</hi> and as <hi rend="underline">I supported</hi> him to the <hi rend="underline">halter</hi> I really expected he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have fainted, no brandy was at hand tho’ he entreated to have some— his stammering he was dreadfully nervous about but got through it all wonderfully the word <hi rend="underline">ch ch ch ch ch–erish</hi> did stick some time but that was the only one— “As soon as the <hi rend="underline">ceremony</hi> was over the happy Pair <hi rend="underline">stept</hi> into their travelling carriage (<hi rend="underline">green</hi> we are informed) and proceeded with all <hi rend="underline">possible speed</hi> on a <hi rend="underline">romantic</hi> <hi rend="underline">Tour</hi> to the <hi rend="underline">Metropolis</hi>, where it is understood they intend to attend all the Theatres”— you may laugh at this announcement but it is <hi rend="underline">a</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">fact</hi> — did you ever hear of any thing half so unsentimental, the very first night they arrived in Town off they went to Covent Garden, the next to the Adelphi, &amp; so on every night they have been in London— it was so like Sarah—determined to lose no time— but to return to our festivities at home— we had actually 37 people to dinner, two Tables, I President of a side table, and <hi rend="underline">didn’t</hi> I pass the Champagne I never allowed a glass to be empty a moment but before the Cloth was removed all <hi rend="doubleUnderline">my</hi> <hi rend="underline">gentlemen</hi> became so much <hi rend="underline">more</hi> <hi rend="underline">elevated</hi> than those at the other table that I began to be in a fright lest they should expose themselves—but luckily nobody was too much elevated except M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. B. O. who rose to propose the <hi rend="underline">Ealth</hi> <hi rend="underline">of</hi> <hi rend="underline">our Ost</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Ostess</hi> and caused much fun— very numerous were the healths &amp; toasts, drunk with 3 times 3—and several neat &amp; appropriate speeches, also a beautiful song by that <hi rend="underline">wild Genius</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Crofton, composed by himself for the occasion, and it is much admired— I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> send it you but think it not worth a double letter— after dinner, the dining room was cleared &amp; prepared for dancing. A most brilliant Ball we had, kept up with the greatest spirit till 5 oclock on Wednesday morning, all the servants dancing. Papa opened the Ball to the tune of “come haste to the Wedding”, with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Kenyon</hi>, can you fancy them?— country dances were the order of the night, and excellent fun we had the only draw back was an occasional dreadful <hi rend="underline">kick</hi>, from the <hi rend="underline">too well shod Fantastic</hi> toes of some of the Beaux, but this was to be expected— altogether we had excellent fun, &amp; I do <hi rend="doubleUnderline">sincerely</hi> regret my dear Charles, you were not of th〈e〉 Party, you might just as well have been as 〈    〉 at Plymouth— How tiresome it is their keep〈ing〉 you so long in suspense— Pray my dear Charles do write me one last adieu if you have a spare half hour before you sail— I should like very much to send you some account of us now &amp; then during y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. absence if I knew where to direct to you? You cannot imagine how I have <hi rend="underline">missed</hi> you already at the Forest, &amp; how I do long to see you again— may every happiness &amp; pleasure attend you dear Charles, and return to us as soon as <hi rend="underline">you can</hi> I <hi rend="underline">selvishly</hi> say!— I miss poor Sarah very much it seems like a dream I can hardly yet believe she is really gone!— I have no news really to tell you. I wish I had. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Mytton is staying here at present she came for the wedding, having got her divorce business all settled before, and <hi rend="underline">her Squire</hi> being safe at Calais, poor thing she is as happy as possible, &amp; we are delighted to have her to keep up our spirits— I must tell you if you should not have heard of it that Edward Williams with all <hi rend="underline">proper Brother in Law good feelings</hi> presented me the other day with a <hi rend="underline">beautiful Horse</hi> at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gore’s sale— it is nearly thorough Bred, and <hi rend="underline">beautiful</hi>, quite <hi rend="underline">perfect</hi> I think &amp; I am delighted with my present— all the fine things from Howell &amp; James’s would not have pleased me half as much— I have made the Governor give me a new London <hi rend="underline">saddle</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">bridle</hi> for old Goldfinder, so you see I am quite a splendid turn out, on coming to my <hi rend="underline">Title</hi> of Miss <hi rend="underline">Owen</hi> — that name I must keep up with all <hi rend="underline">proper dignity</hi>, &amp; what a steady <hi rend="underline">old sober body</hi> you will find me when you return from your Savage Islands— Miss Fanny Sparling, is going to marry <hi rend="underline">Dry</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Corbett</hi>!!!<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This is said every where as a positive <hi rend="underline">fact</hi> — he has been living at Felton almost lately &amp; we heard she said she did not know what people could find to laugh at in <hi rend="underline">Dry</hi> — it is really <hi rend="underline">too good</hi> —&amp; it is <hi rend="underline">devoutly</hi> to be hoped they will make a <hi rend="underline">match</hi> of it for the <hi rend="underline">diversion</hi> it will afford the Country—which is very flat I think at present—</p>
<p>I hear you like Plymouth very much, I thought it a delightful place when I was there for a few days, there is so much going on—</p>
<p>If you have time write to me my dear Charles— how I do wish you had not this horrible <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Beettle</hi> taste you might have staid “<hi rend="underline">asy</hi>” with us here I cannot bear to part with you for so long—</p>
<p>God bless you my dear Charles excuse my dulness but believe me always | Yours most affec<hi rend="superscript">tly</hi>| Fanny Owen</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The wedding day of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2059.xml">Sarah Owen</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Hosier Williams</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dryden Robert Corbet</ref> of Sundorne Castle, Shropshire.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>