<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2308">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Swale<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   13 July 1858</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14592</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2308 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2308.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2308.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp damaged †, CD note</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Gard. Chron.</hi> (1858): 829</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 134</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 323 (fragile), DAR 205.4: 79</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 323 (fragile),</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>205.4: 79</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4635.xml">Swale, William</persName>
                <placeName>Christchurch</placeName>
                <date when="1858-07-13">13 July 1858</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses the absence of a native bee in New Zealand and the insects which probably performed its fertilising function [see "Agency of bees in fertilization", <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 21]. Describes the success of the naturalised hive-bee and also the rapid spread of introduced members of the Fabaceae.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bee</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">New Zealand</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dispersion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">introduced forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">naturalisation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Christ Church | Province of Canterb〈ury〉 | New Zealand</placeName>
                    <date>July 13, 1858.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>Your interesting communication reached me quite safe after a postal journey of 68 days.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Even in the insect world colonisation has conferred a benifit in this Province<anchor xml:id="ann.a2" type="annotationEnd"/>. From enquiries which I have made from older Colonists than myself I find that there is not an <hi rend="underline">indigenous</hi> Bee. The Bees which are here were introduced from the Province of Wellington in 1852 to this Province; and to Wellington from England in the year 1842. When the first Ships with Emigrants arrived here seven years ago to colonise this Province not a Bee was to be seen, and when the right time arrived for sowing Seeds of the Natural Order Fabaceæ they and other usefull Seeds were sown, and during the Summer those kinds sown such as Peas, Beans, Scarlet Runners, Clovers, and so forth; all prospered and matured their Seeds at the end of the season, and when sown the following season germinated and produced crops again in the usual way: <anchor xml:id="ann.a1" type="annotationStart"/>but very abundantly. So abundantly that the red white and crimson clovers are now every where dispersed over this immense Plain wherever the foot-prints of man and Animals can be tracked. The Native Grasses are fast disappearing to make way for the Clovers, Lucerne and English grasses. The enclosed Bees are a sample of the naturalised Bee of this Province.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> There is not the least doubt left in my mind that the function of fertilisation was performed before the introduction of the Hive Bee by the three distinct varieties of native Wasp which I have seen during the summer months. They are smaller than the English wasp: but can sting severely. The two or three varieties of Grasshopper is also very active as well in hopping from flower to flower; and may be added to this, probably the continued high currents of wind which we experience here from time to time which may assist nature to perform her accustomed frolics to facilitate productiveness and the progress of fertilisation by placing the pollen upon the Stigma. The Grasshopper is equally as industrious as the Bee in puncturing the Keel and splitting it open. I have often been amused during the last summer here with his Antics jumping about releasing the Stamens in the Keel. The Garden varieties 〈of the Lupine seed produced〉<ref target="#foot.f4"/> less abun-〈dantly〉 〈than any others〉 of the Leguminous family. No 〈    〉 and 〈<hi rend="underline">two words missing</hi>〉 exists with the flower of the Lupin as with the Erythri〈na〉 〈    〉 the tightness of the Keel which before success can be had 〈must〉 be artificially opened. I have for amusement during the summer released the Stamens with a pin, and a pod of Seed always rewarded me for my trouble and flowers not served so adjoining have all proved blind.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The Atmosphere here, by its moderate warmth, its humidity, and constant current, is peculiarly favourable to the Vegetative powers as we daily witness in the luxurious growth of plants, so from the same causes it suits the Hive Bee. Children grow well and strong, with fresh and rosy faces and I am satisfied that in this respect this Province is superior to Great Britain. The Bees here are able to feed themselves all the year round.</p>
                    <p><figure><graphic url=""/>
                        <p>Staple articles of culture by the farmer here. English names of Leguminous plants, growing in the Province of Canterbury, New Zealand.</p>
                        <p>Common Garden Pea.</p>
                        <p>" Field "</p>
                        <p>Sweet "</p>
                        <p>Tangier "</p>
                        <p>Everlasting "</p>
                        <p>Common Broad Bean</p>
                        <p>" Kidney "</p>
                        <p>" Horse "</p>
                        <p>Scarlet Runners</p>
                        <p>Crimson Clover</p>
                        <p>White "</p>
                        <p>Red "</p>
                        <p>Vetches</p>
                        <p>Lentils</p>
                        <p>Lucerne</p>
                        <p>Saintfoin</p>
                        <p>Trefoil</p>
                        <p>Bladder</p>
                        <p>senna</p>
                        <p>Gorse or Furze</p>
                        <p>Locust-tree</p>
                        <p>Native Clianthus</p>
                        <p>Cape Broom (Genista Canariensis)</p>
                        <p>White Portugal Broom</p>
                        <p>Yellow English Broom</p>
                        <p>Lupin</p>
                        <p>Leguminous plants which have produced Seeds abundantly the first year before the introduction of the Hive Bee.</p>
                        <p>Abundantly</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>less abundant </p>
                        <p>Leguminous plants which have produced Seeds <hi rend="underline">very</hi> abundantly the second year and ever since.</p>
                        <p>very abundantly</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>"</p>
                        <p>less abundant</p></figure></p>
                    
<p>The Common Furze is always in bloom and universally used for fences. My present employer has sold more than 100,000 one-year old Seedling Gorse plants this winter. In a warm sheltered situation in his Nursery-grounds one old Hive <anchor xml:id="ann.a3" type="annotationStart"/>cast off six swarms during the short time of two months.</p>
<p>English Bee Keepers would open their eyes with astonishment if they were out here to see the produce of a single hive. I have had the pleasure several times of partaking of their industry and most delicious it is. Bee Keeping is different here to what it is in England. The perpetual succession of flowers, and the fine warm Summer, mildness of the winter, all tends to a great increase of the 〈bees. Our management of them is〉 very 〈simple. We furnish them with small boxes 18 inches〉 or 2 feet in length and a foot 〈or 18 inches in〉 depth with a small aperture on the Sunny side fo〈r in〉gress and egress. Inside the box we fix small rails 〈a〉cross for them to commence building their combs. I have seen very severe conflicts between them and the native Wasps. When a wasp approaches near the Hive the Bees give no quarters. They soon slay their enemy and down with him.<anchor xml:id="ann.a4" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>Dear Sir, you are perfectly welcome to the contents of my Letter and quite at liberty to make use of the same.</p>
<p>Very faithfully yours | W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Swale</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="cdnotes">
                <ab><ref target="#foot.f6"/></ab>
                <note>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Swale of Christchurch Canterbury New Zealand says in letter of July 13. 58 “the red, white &amp; common clovers are now everywhere dispersed over this immense plain, wherever the footprint of men &amp; animals can be tracked. The native grasses are fast disappearing to make way for the clovers, lucerne &amp; English grasses.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></note>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note target="#ann.a1" targetEnd="#ann.a2"><hi rend="italic">double scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a3" targetEnd="#ann.a4"><hi rend="italic">square brackets added, brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘40’<hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note/>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4635.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Swale</ref>, a Norfolk-born gardener, had emigrated to New Zealand and become a successful nurseryman.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter has not been found. He had written to several people in New Zealand during the spring of 1858 to inquire about the fertilisation of clover and other Leguminosae by bees. See letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2201.xml" resp="#automat">12 January [1858]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2222.xml" resp="#automat">23 February [1858]</ref>. CD included short extracts from Swale’s letter in his letter to the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [before 13 November 1858], on the agency of bees in fertilisation. A longer extract from Swale’s letter was printed separately in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural</hi> <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi>, 13 November 1858, pp. 828–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">At this point in the letter there are four specimens of bees attached, labelled ‘Naturalised Bee’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The letter is very fragile and partially destroyed. The missing text (indicated by angle brackets) has been supplied by the extracts published in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 13 November 1858, pp. 828–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">When CD quoted this sentence from the letter (see n. 2, above), he changed the order of the words to read: ‘and the adjoining flowers not so served have all proved blind.’ See letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [before 13 November 1858].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">This note is in DAR 205.4 (Letters).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD marked the note in brown crayon with ‘20’, the number of his portfolio of notes on the geographical distribution of plants.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>