<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10361">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. S. von Mansfelde   17 January 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10154</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10361 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10361.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10361.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 180: 15</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>180: 15</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4906.xml">Von Mansfelde, A. S.</persName>
                <placeName>Lincoln, Nebr.</placeName>
                <date when="1876-01-17">17 Jan 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Proposes an unorthodox theory of generation that explains sex determination and atavism.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reversion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Office of D<hi rend="superscript">trs</hi>. French &amp; Mansfelde | Lincoln Nebraska</placeName>
                    <date>Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1876.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">To D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charles Darwin | England</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My apology for addressing you, will be found in the humble belief, that I may be the tool in the hands of progressive science, to further its objects the unraviling of its apparent mysteries, and further, in my faith, which sees in you the master worker, well trained to handle tools, though crude in design effectively. You are aware of the high interest which two questions have and do yet claim from all enquirers. Namely. What is it that produces the sex of the embryo? and secondly. What is the cause of one of the propagation peculiarities, called atavism.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Neither of the questions, though speculation had its day with them to satisfaction, has as yet been settled; Nay, the fruit of all honest enquiry, has not even attained the dignity of a theory. hypotheses of the most imaginary kind are the offspring of all labour expended upon them.</p>
<p>I will not tire you with a recapitulation. You certainly are better acquainted with the history of these subjects, than the Doctor away back in the Prairies of beautiful Nebraska.</p>
<p>You are familiar with the attempt made by Ernest Haeckel of Germany in this Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte of erecting a pedigree for Man reaching to the beginning of time, in which all animals from the Monera to the Anthropoid have their place; you are also acquainted, with the stress he lays upon the similarity of the human Embryo with certain series of the animal world.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Yet he, as well as all physiologists and Embryologists commit the error of admitting only a <hi rend="underline">similarity</hi> when an <hi rend="underline">identity</hi> exists; They handle the human being before his birth as the passive thing, laying all activity on this side of his nativity, an error, which has placed man far beyond his actual position in the universe; I take liberty to reverse this subject. And the Consequences (1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.) I do not view the Spermatozoon as organised protoplasm, without the living attributes of the same; but I permit it to enjoy all the priviledges of such organization. It does not resemble the Monera of Haeckel, but it is a Monera with all its Characteristics of life and reproduction, nay even capacities for perfection.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>(2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.) The Ovum, while lodged in the Grafian follicle <hi rend="underline">is</hi> an Amoeba, not <hi rend="underline">resembling</hi> it, as D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Haeckel has it;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and this structure is not a Creation of the female organ, but the higher developed organized protoplasm, a Monera changed into an Amoeba; the Monera Spermatozoon, transformed into the Amoeba-Ovum. This transformation takes place precisely under the same natural laws <hi rend="underline">within</hi> the Ovary, as does the change of the Monera into an Amoeba at large</p>
<p>(3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>.) The ovary is therefore not the organ in which the ovum is formed, but simply the abode of the organized protoplasm, the Monera Spermatozoon, in which it passes from its Larva into its Puma state,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> thence to follow up the processes of Metamorphosis from the Embryonit infusorium to the perfect human form.</p>
<p>(4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>) In the ovary, as well as Uterus, the ovum owes nothing of its structural development to the Mother but the preparation and transmission of food, and if the offspring takes upon itself any of the Characters of the Mother, they are derived from the impressions, which the transmissions of nutrion may produce, together with certain characteristics derived from the offsprings grandfather, the Mother’s Father by true atavism</p>
<p>5 The Ovum, after it has broken its prison walls or being opened for it, I do not know which, is to all purposes a true infusorium, globular in form, with a mouth, surrounded by Cilias, the Micropyle and which has certainly been demonstrated to exist in insects and fishes, and the Spermotozoa have been observed to enter this opening.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Here is the vital Mistake again. I cannot conceive it as harmonizing with fact, that the lesser organized being should overpower the greater one and by creeping into the latter, should totally transform it. I am satisfied that the reverse takes place.</p>
<p>6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. The Ovum advanced to the dignity of the infusorium comes in contact with the spermatic fluid and its contents the Spermatozoa and as any active individual would, feeds upon this food, the only material which is congenial to its life and growth. It must either meet this, whilst it passes from the extremity of the fallopian tube to the Os, Uteri, or die.</p>
<p>7 It is, as you know a fact, that the more vigorous an individual, the greater its capacity to partake of its natural food, and via versa, The greater therefore the interval between the advance of the ovum from the ovary to the contact with the spermatic fluid, the less the ovum will partake of the latter; and the shorter the interval, the more it will imbibe, For its vigor lessons, as time advances.</p>
<p>8 The natural consequence of this partaking of food is a growth of the ovum and its subdivision until as many primary cells are formed as are necessary to constitute the 3 germinal layers from which the embryo is built.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> During this subdivision the ovum has already attached itself (it is not engulphed in a fold of the Uterine mucous membrane, as is thought) to the Uterine wall and commences to draw food from that source (The freely moving vorticella, attaching itself by its stern to the rock of the Sea, is a splendid picture of this state of Affairs<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>9 If the energetical ovum has partaken more of the Spermatic fluid, than was necessary for the construction of the primary cells, we will always find this surplus of organized protoplasm stored away in the forming Embryo, for already at the end of the fourth day we meet this surplus protoplasm in the not even completed ovary of the chicken, in the form of ova, not made by the ovary, but deposited here for perfection by nutrition, <hi rend="underline">and we have a female Embryo</hi>.</p>
<p>10 But if the ovum weakened by the above mentioned circumstance takes unto itself barely enough of this organized protoplasm, we will find the warehouse, the ovary, still preparing, yet no material being left over to be stored away, the natural stimulus for the erection of the house is wanting, and instead of progressing the work regresses only a trace of the ovary is left. <hi rend="underline">And we have a male Embryo</hi>.</p>
<p>11 The quicker therefore the contact of the ovum with the Spermatic fluid, the Stronger is the ovum and in consequence the greater is the amount of protoplasm absorbed and the result <hi rend="underline">always</hi> a <hi rend="underline">female</hi> offspring.</p>
<p>12 The later the meeting of the ovum with the Spermatic fluid, the weaker is the ovum and in consequence the smaller is the amount of protoplasm imbibed and the result <hi rend="underline">always</hi> a <hi rend="underline">male</hi> descendent.</p>
<p>13 The spermatic fluid with the Spermatozoa, which it contains, is always created <hi rend="underline">de novo</hi> in the sexual organs of the male</p>
<p>14 The ova, are remnants of the Spermatic fluid and its contents; higher organized by the nutrition and influences which the female as such, and through its ovaries, exerts upon the development of the ovum.</p>
<p>15 The female is not the producer of the ova, but simply the recipient of their elements, which she assists and influences to higher organization.</p>
<p>16 The impregnated ovum therefore consists:</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Of the organized protoplasm, the surplus amount retained by the Embryo, now represented by the female, and received directly from her father— <hi rend="underline">The imperfect ovum</hi></p>
<p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. The nutritive elements received from the female, by the Agency of her ovaries and their accessories— <hi rend="underline">The perfect Ovum</hi></p>
<p>3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. Of the organized protoplasm, which the ovum takes directly from the material, the Spermatic fluid, with which it comes in contact during its sojourn in the sexual organs of the female. The fecundated ovum</p>
<p>The structure then of the embryo consists of the plastic elements derived from its Grand father (Atavus) and its Father</p>
<p>17 The growth of the embryo depends entirely upon the nutritive elements, which it receives from its Mother.</p>
<p>My dear Doctor, the answer which I have endeavoured to give to the question of the causes of Sex production will, as you perceive, solve the second question, as to the causes of Atavism</p>
<p>This apparent inconsistency becomes at once a necessary consequence of physiological facts. And variable as the constituents of the ovum; as I tried to shew, as variable must we find the characters of the developed ovum, the offspring, still governed by this law of descent.</p>
<p>I will forbear to apply my conclusions, I know they will remove many apparent discrepancies, especially if <hi rend="underline">you</hi> should undertake to use them as a touchstone to questions still undecided.</p>
<p>Should I have been so fortunate as to put into your hands facts which will further Natural Science as you understand it, I will be well paid for my labors and if you should give me your opinion as to the importance of my assertions, I will consider myself under many obligations</p>
<p>Your respectful servant | A. S. v. Mansfelde. M.D.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Note</hi> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Geo. W. French of Lincoln, a native Kentuckian, tells me, that children begotten by a purely white woman and a Negro are blacker, than when born of a Negro woman, who was pregnant by a white man.</p>
<p>This seems to prove the preponderance of the elements of the father, over those of the Grandfather.</p>
<p>With the compliments of the new year, I am waiting for an answer, I have no doubt, that I can give facts to strengthen my theory. | Again yours. | A S Mansfelde.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>8.3 they … atavism 8.6] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin pencil</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> &amp; most eggs are <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> one way’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had discussed reversion or atavism in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 28–62. CD had not worked on the problem of sex determination in the embryo.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Natural history of creation; Haeckel 1868b) was a collection of lectures by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref> outlining theories of organic development from both a historical or genealogical perspective and an embryological one. Mansfelde evidently refers to a later, expanded edition of the book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3279.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1873</ref>). In a chapter on the developmental history of tribes (phylogeny) and the individual (ontogeny), Haeckel included a plate showing the similarity between the embryonic forms of a turtle, chicken, dog, and human (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, plate II, between pp. 272 and 273). Haeckel equated early stages in ontogenesis or embryonic development with historical stages in the development of organisms (phylogenesis) and produced a chart giving equivalent stages in both (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 444). For more on Haeckel’s representation of embryos and the ensuing controversy, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10101.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hopwood 2015</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haeckel had equated the ontogenetic stage ‘monerula’ with the earliest organisms, the Monera. He described the monerula as an animal egg without a nucleus, the nucleus having disappeared after fertilisation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3279.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1873</ref>, p. 444).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel had equated the ‘ovulum’ of ontogeny with the <hi rend="italic">Amoeba</hi> of phylogeny; the ovulum was described as an animal cell with a nucleus (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3279.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1873</ref>, p. 444).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Mansfelde may have intended to write ‘pupa state’. The term pupa is now generally reserved for the final metamorphic stage before the imago in insects that undergo complete metamorphosis. In the nineteenth century the term was also used to describe the final larval stage in the development of some of the Crustacea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Mansfelde evidently assumed, by analogy with insects and fish, that the human ovum possessed a micropyle, or small portal through which sperm would enter the egg, rather than having a penetrable membrane.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Three different cell types or germ layers form during the process of gastrulation: the ectoderm, mesoderm, and endoderm. Each layer differentiates into specific organs and tissue types. For more on the understanding of germ layers at this time, see Lankester 1873.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Vorticella</hi> is a genus of the ciliate protozoan family Vorticellidae. Its bell-shaped cell has a projecting stalk used to anchor it to a substrate.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>