<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-319">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. D. Fox   6 November [1836]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7049</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-319 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-319.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-319.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">D N0 7 1〈83〉6</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 188</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 277</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 516</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Christ’s College Library, Cambridge (MS 53 Fox 49)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_83.xml">CCLC</repository>
                    <collection>MS 53</collection>
                    <idno>Fox 49</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 43</placeName>
                <date when="1836-11-06">6 Nov [1836]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml">Fox, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>All his affairs are most prosperous. Has found many who will undertake description of animals; he will work at the geology. Lyell has been most friendly and kind.</p>
            <p>CD has been proposed to the Geological Society.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3051">Lyell, Charles</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Geological Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>43 Great Marlborough St<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Fox,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have taken a shamefully long time in answering your letter.— But the busiest time of the whole voyage has been tranquillity itself to this last month. After paying Henslow a short but very pleasant visit, I came up to town to wait for the Beagle’s arrival. At last I have removed all my property from on board, &amp; sent the specimens of Natural History to Cambridge, so that I am now a free man.— My London visit has been quite idle, as far as Nat: History goes but has been passed in most exciting dissipation amongst the Dons in science.— All my affairs indeed are most prosperous; I find there are plenty, who will undertake the description of whole tribes of animals, of which I know nothing. So that about this day month, I hope to set to work: tooth and nail at the Geology, which I shall publish by itself.—</p>
<p>I do not know how I shall be able to manage a visit to the Isle of Wight.— My plans are on Thursday to go to Shrewsbury by the way of Maer &amp; Overton staying at each place about a couple of days.— For Shrewsbury I hope to spare ten days, but I foresee, it will be a most uncomfortable visit,—a mere struggle how many people can be visited, to whom I am bound, &amp; indeed, (if time, just at present was not so precious) am most anxious to see.—</p>
<p>I shall return to London for two or three days &amp; then go and reside in Cambridge for some months, &amp; try if I can settle my jolted brains into some kind of order.— Have you during the winter any sort of business, or anything which will tempt you to pay Cambridge a visit.— It is too long a journey in the depth of winter, and I fear for your health, to take for any one motive; though you have offered to come up all the way to London, merely for a flying visit. When I leave Shrewsbury, I will write again, as by that time, I shall know more certainly about the future. At present I am exceedingly doubtful between the merits of London and Cambridge.—</p>
<p>It is quite ridiculous, what an immensely long period it appears to me, since landing at Falmouth. The fact is I have talked and laughed enough for years instead of weeks, so my memory is quite confounded with the noise.—</p>
<p>I am delighted to hear you are turned Geologist. when I pay the Isle of Wight, a visit, which I am determined shall somehow come to pass, you will be capital cicerone to the famous line of dislocation.— I really suppose there are few parts of the world more interesting to a Geologist than your island.—</p>
<p>Amongst the great scientific men, no one has been nearly so friendly &amp; kind, as Lyell.— I have seen him several times, &amp; feel inclined to like him much. You cannot imagine how good-naturedly he entered into all my plans. I speak now only of the London men, for Henslow was just like his former self, &amp; therefore a most cordial and affectionate friend.— When you pay London a visit I shall be very proud to take you to the Geological Society, for be it known, I was proposed to be a F.G.S. last Tuesday. It is, however a great pity that these &amp; the other letters, especially F.R.S. are so very expensive.—</p>
<p>I do not scruple to ask you to write to me in a week’s time in Shrewsbury, for you are a good letter writer, &amp; if people will have such good characters they must pay the penalty.</p>
<p>I wish I had the pleasure of being acquainted with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Fox, that I might beg to be remembered to her, but I hope the time is not far distant, when I shall be so.—</p>
<p>Pray tell me what relation I am your daughter, for I have been puzzling my brains &amp; can come to no conclusion. When formerly at Cambridge you explained to me my various relations, you little thought the next time you would be genealogist for your own daughter.</p>
<p>Good Bye | Dear Fox Yours C. D.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">4.3 the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">5.2 capital] ‘capilat’ <hi rend="italic">in MS</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">5.4 your] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 2.1 ‘know’; 5.4 ‘world’; 6.7 ‘proposed’; 8.2 ‘be’; 9.1 ‘me’</note>
                </div>

        </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>