<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1163">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To John Phillips   [12? March 1848]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20116</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1163 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1163.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1163.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 4: 122</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Oxford University Museum of Natural History Archive Collections (John Phillips collection))</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_313.xml">Oxford UMNH</repository>
                    <collection>John Phillips</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1848-03-12">[12? Mar 1848]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3773.xml">Phillips, John</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks JP for his note and reference. CD’s paper will not deal with the general question of erratics but only their transportal from a lower to a higher level ["The transportal of erratic boulders", <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 218–27]. His notion is that the boulders were transported by coast-ice, not drifting icebergs, and that during the period of transportal the land was subsiding. Can JP tell him whether the raised conglomerate boulders he observed were rounded or angular?</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Phillips</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I am extremely much obliged by your full &amp; most satisfactory note. I instantly turned to Lardner’s Encyclop.,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> &amp; there found every point, put as clear as daylight, as if in answer to my mental queries. It was uncommonly stupid my not looking there before, for on rereading it, I remembered well having formerly been much interested by all that you had written on this subject.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am not going to discuss the general question of erratics, but only the one point of their transport from a lower to a higher level, &amp; secondarily the gradual diminution of the size of the boulders in going from their parent source.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> My notion will at first strike you as monstrous but when worked out, I feel sure, whether true or not, it will not appear monstrous. It is that the boulders have been transported by coast-ice, &amp; not by icebergs (a distinction which will, I believe explain many points &amp; which I briefly noticed in my paper on the Erratics of the southern hemisphere)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; that during the period of such transportal, the level of the land was subsiding. If you will call to mind the manner, as described by Bayfield &amp; Bowen in Lyell’s principles,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> in which coast-ice on the N. American shore, annually acts, you will at once perceive, how the boulders will rise, as the land sinks, or rather not to speak paradoxically, how the boulders are kept at the same level, whilst the land sinks. If this can be proved true, it will be pretty, for it will allow us to measure to a foot the amount of subsidence, during the glacial period: thus I have no doubt that the Lake district subsided <hi rend="underline">at least</hi> 900 feet; each winter your Conglomerate boulders, being pushed (so to speak) an inch or so upwards.— Some objections will occur to you at once; but I think can I answer the more obvious ones.—</p>
<p>You <hi rend="underline">most kindly</hi> offer me any further information: literally one line will answer me, are the upper conglomerate boulders, which now stand about, say from 700 to 900 feet above their parent rock, (I do not care about the others) rounded or angular. Hopkins speaks of all those in neighbourhood of Stainmoor as being well rounded.— It is very probable that you may not have attended to the state especially of the conglomerate boulders, &amp; therefore to save you writing, I shall understand, if I do <hi rend="underline">not</hi> hear, that you cannot answer me.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Most sincerely yours | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Hopkins does not speak so much as if he himself doubted the identification of the conglomerate boulders, but as if some one else had; but he seldom condescends to give references: nor, I suspect, does he read much:—if he had read your statements in Lardner, he c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not have doubted.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 as clear] ‘as’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.7 lower] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘level’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.15 on the N. American shore, annually] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.18 measure to] ‘to’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.21 (so to speak)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.22 more] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.2 upper] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.2 about, say from 700 to] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">4.2 if some] ‘if’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">4.3 give] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘quote’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1837–9</ref>, 1: 268–70, published in the <hi rend="italic">Cabinet cyclopædia</hi> edited by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2818.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dionysius Lardner</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">On 25 February 1839, CD recorded reading ‘Phillips Geology Lardner’s 2<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> d vol’ (DAR 119; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV). CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">According to the coast-ice theory of transport, the larger boulders would be dropped first, the smaller ones continuing over longer distances and also becoming smaller and more rounded from being repeatedly stranded and subjected to littoral sea action (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 224–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘On the distribution of the erratic boulders … of South America’, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 160.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_334.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Wolsey Bayfield</ref> and his assistant, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_565.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Augustus Frederick James Bowen</ref>, who surveyed the St Lawrence River and the coast of Labrador, 1827–40. In his paper, CD incorrectly cited ‘Brown’ and Bayfield (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 222).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Apparently Phillips did not reply. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1162.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Phillips, 7 March [1848]</ref>, n. 5, for CD’s comments on the boulders.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>