<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6106">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Giovanni Canestrini<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   8 April 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16209</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6106 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6106.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6106.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 86: A28–9</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>86: A28–9</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_815.xml">Canestrini, Giovanni</persName>
                <placeName>Trient</placeName>
                <date when="1868-04-08">8 Apr 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on Prof. Cornalia’s observations on the proportion of sexes in bees, and in healthy and sick silk moths, in nature and under domestication.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">bees</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">moths, silk</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1077">Cornalia, Emilio</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-11">Facsimile information added by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00060_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3662px" height="6662px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00060_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3662px" height="6662px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="A28r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00060.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3662px" height="6662px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00060_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3662px" height="6662px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00060.dzi" width="3662px" height="6662px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="A28v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00061.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3542px" height="6597px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00061_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3542px" height="6597px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00061.dzi" width="3542px" height="6597px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="A29r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00062.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3511px" height="6598px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00062_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3511px" height="6598px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00086-000-00062.dzi" width="3511px" height="6598px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Trient</placeName>
                    <date>8 April 1868.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrtester Herr,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ich hoffe dass Sie mein letztes Schreiben von Modena aus werden erhalten haben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Ich muss nun hinzufügen, besonders durch die Beobachtungen eines unserer besseren Bacologen, prof. Cornalia,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> veranlasst, dass, wenn eine Partie Seidenwürmer <hi rend="doubleUnderline">gesund</hi> ist, die hervorgehenden Männchen und Weibchen sich ungemein in der Zahl dem Gleichgewichte nähert. Dieses Gleichgewicht wurde besonders beobachtet, wenn die Zucht im <hi rend="underline">Freien</hi> vorgenommen wurde.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Bei häuslicher Zucht und Vorhandensein von Krankheit, soll nach der Beobachtung von prof. Cornalia die Zahl der Männchen grösser sein als die der Weibchen. Diese Ansicht ist im Missklang gegen die in meinem letzten Briefe ausgesprochene und gegen die allgemeine Ansicht der erfahrensten Züchter; habe sie aber doch hier angeführt wegen der Autorität von der sie stammt.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Die Weibchen, sobald geboren, werden von den Männchen umgeben, und die lebhafteren kommen zur Begattung. Das Weibchen, das sich begattet, legt immer fruchtbare Eier; die Fälle umbefruchteter Eier nach stattgefundener Begattung, sind äusserst selten. Wenn sich unbefruchtete Eier vorfinden, so hat in den allermeisten Fällen keine Begattung stattgefunden. Oft begatten sich die Weibchen nicht und oft liegt der Grund davon in der fehlerhaften Struktur der Paarungsorgane.</p>
<p>Wenn man verschiene Racen zur Paarung bringt, so herrscht in der Nachkommenschaft der Charakter des männlichen Geschlechtes vor.</p>
<p>Ich muss nun eine Beobachtung hinsichtlich der Bienen hinzufügen. Befruchtete Bieneneier geben Weibchen, unbefruchtete Männchen. Man hat nun angenommen, es liege in der Gewalt und dem Willen der Königinn sie zu befruchten oder nicht.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Dies ist, glaube ich falsch. Die Sache steht so. Die Zellen für die weiblichen Eier sind kleiner als die für die männlichen. Wenn daher die Königin ein Ei in eine weibliche Zelle legt, so wird durch das Hineinzwingen des Hinterleibes in die Zelle, der Hinterleib zusammengedrückt und das Sperma aus dem Samenbehälter auf das Ei gespritzt, wodurch Befruchtung stattfindet. Diess geschieht nicht, wenn das Ei in die grössere mannliche Zelle gelegt wird. Der Wille der Königin kommt bei der Befruchtung nicht in Spiel.</p>
<p>Daher kommt es, dass aus alten Bienenzellen fast nur Weibchen geboren werden, indem auch die männlichen Zellen durch die zurückgelassenen Häute der Larven verengt werden und daher gerade in denselben Verhältnissen sind, wie die weiblichen Zellen.</p>
<p>Ich bitte ganz frei über mich zu verfügen und, wenn nöthig, mir nach Modena zu schreiben.</p>
<p>Hochachtungsvoll | Ergebenster | Prof. Canestrini</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 Bei … der Weibchen. 3.2]. <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon and ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Trient</placeName>
                    <date>8 April 1868.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope you have received my previous letter from Modena.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Prompted above all by the observations of one of our best sericulturists, prof. Cornalia,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I must now add that, when a group of silkworms is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">healthy</hi>, the ratio of males to females approaches equilibrium. This equilibrium has been observed above all when they were bred <hi rend="underline">outdoors</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In household cultivation and when they suffer from disease, the number of males is larger than that of females, according to the observations of prof. Cornalia. This view does not accord with that presented in my last letter and with the general opinion of experienced breeders; I have mentioned it here, however, because of the prestige of its author.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>As soon as they are born, the females are surrounded by the males, and the more lively ones mate. The females that have mated always lay fertile eggs; the cases of unfertilised eggs being laid after mating are extremely rare. If unfertilised eggs are found, in virtually all cases mating has not taken place. Often the females do not mate and the reason for this frequently lies in the faulty structure of the reproductive organs.</p>
<p>When different races are mated, the characteristics of the male parent predominate in the progeny.</p>
<p>Now I must add an observation with regard to bees. The fertilised eggs of the bee produce females, the unfertilised ones males. It has been assumed that it was subject to the will of the queen bee whether they were fertilised or not.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> But this, I believe, is incorrect. What really happens is the following. The cells for female eggs are smaller than those for the male. Therefore, when the queen lays an egg into a female cell, the act of forcing the abdomen into the cell causes it to be squeezed together, and sperm thus get spurted from the spermatheca onto the egg, whereupon fertilisation takes place. This does not happen when the egg is laid into the larger male cell. The will of the queen hence does not come into play in fertilisation.</p>
<p>Thus it is the case that from old bee cells females are born almost exclusively; for over time, the male cells become smaller due to the skins the larvae leave behind, which results in the cells being exactly the same size as the female cells.</p>
<p>Please feel free to command my services as you please and, if necessary, to write to me at Modena.</p>
<p>Most respectfully | Your most devoted | Prof. Canestrini.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of the letter in its original German, see part I: 384–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter from Giovanni Canestrini, 13 March 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emilio Cornalia</ref>. Canestrini wrote ‘Bacologen’, evidently a Germanisation of the Italian ‘bacòlogo’, a sericulturist, or breeder of silkworms (the German word is ‘Seidenraupenzüchter’).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his monograph on silkworms (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1577.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cornalia 1856</ref>, pp. 332–66, 384–5), Cornalia had discussed sexual differences in silkworms. Cornalia was a strong proponent of the benefits of raising silkworms in an open-air environment rather than indoors (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1578.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cornalia 1860</ref>, p. 270).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Giovanni Canestrini, 13 March 1868</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Jan Dzierzon, who was the first to observe parthenogenesis in bees, had argued that the queen was able to choose whether to lay fertilised or unfertilised eggs (Abbott ed. 1882, pp. 17–18).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>