<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13113">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Fritz Müller   12 April 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1715</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13113 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13113.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13113.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 460a</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 367</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Loan MS 10 no 51)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Loan MS 10</collection>
                    <idno>51</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-12">12 Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Earthworm book with printer.</p> 
<p>Has sent FM’s observations on paraheliotropism to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> ["Movement of leaves", <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 228–9].</p> 
            <p>Plants with differently coloured anthers.</p>
            <p>Intends gathering together his notes on "bloom".</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Collected papers</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Earthworms</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Nature</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1053">printer</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">bloom</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">worms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-09-17" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-27" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi> | (<hi rend="print">Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi>)</placeName>
                    <date>April 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1881</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have delayed answering your last letter of Feb. 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, as I was just sending to the printers the M.S. of a very little book on the habits of earth-worms, of which I will of course send you a copy when published.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have been very much interested by your new facts on paraheliotropism, as I think that they justify my giving a name to this kind of movement, about which I long doubted. I have this morning drawn up an account of your observations, which I will send in a few days to ‘Nature’.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have thought that you would not object to my giving <hi rend="underline">precedence</hi> to paraheliotropism, which has been so little noticed.— I will send you a copy of ‘Nature’ when published.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>I am glad that I was not in too great a hurry in publishing about Lagestrœmia   I have <hi rend="underline">procured</hi> some plants of Melastomaceæ, but I fear that they will not flower for two years &amp; I may be in my grave before I can repeat my trials. As far as I can <hi rend="underline">imperfectly</hi> judge from my observations, the difference in colour of the anthers in this family depends on one set of anthers being partially aborted. I wrote to Kew to get plants with differently coloured anthers, but I learnt very little as describers of dried plants do not attend to such points. I have, however, sowed seeds of 2 kinds, suggested to me as probable.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have, therefore, been extremely glad to receive the seeds of <hi rend="underline">Heteranthera reniformis</hi>. As far as I can make out it is an aquatic plant; &amp; whether I shall succeed in getting it to flower is doubtful.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Will you be so kind as to send me a postcard, telling me in what kind of station it grows.—</p>
                    <p>In the course of next autumn or winter, I think that I shall put together my notes (if they seem worth publishing) on the use or meaning of “bloom”, or the waxy secretion which makes some leaves glaucous.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I think that I told you that my experiments had led me to suspect that the movement of the leaves of Mimosa, Desmodium &amp; Cassia, when shaken &amp; syringed, was to shoot off the drops of water.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> If you are caught in heavy rain, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be very much obliged, if you would keep this notion in your mind, &amp; look to the position of such leaves.—</p>
                    <p>You have such wonderful powers of observation that your opinion w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be more valued by me than that of any other man.— I have among my notes one letter from you on the subject, but I forget its purport. I hope, also, that you may be led to follow up your very ingenious &amp; novel view on the two-coloured anthers or pollen, &amp; observe which kind is most gathered by bees.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>Believe me | Yours ever sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 (<hi rend="italic">Railway … S.E.R.</hi>)] <hi rend="italic">parentheses added</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.4 in this family 2.5] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘here’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.2 (if … publishing)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.2 use] ‘us’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘m’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.4 suspect] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘believe’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.5 kind] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘on’ </note>
            </div>
            
        </div> 
         
         
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD probably refers to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13068A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 28 February 1881</ref>; the letter is known only from a printed source (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>, 2: 409), and most of the text is missing. Either CD or <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml">Alfred Möller</ref> may have made an error about the date. CD hoped that <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>  would soon be in print (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13110.xml">letter to R. F. Cooke, 10 April 1881</ref>).  It was published on 10 October 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml">Freeman 1977</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13117.xml">letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 14 April [1881]</ref>; CD included information from Müller that was probably in the now missing part of the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13068A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 28 February 1881</ref>. For Müller’s earlier observations on paraheliotropism (a term coined by CD to describe the movement of leaves during the day to reduce intense illumination), see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12996.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 9 January 1881</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s letter was published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 28 April 1881, pp. 603–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had studied plants of <hi rend="italic">Lagerstroemia indica</hi> (crape myrtle, a member of the family Lythraceae) in 1863, when he was working on dimorphism and trimorphism; he noted the two different kinds of anthers and pollen and speculated about differences in stylar length (notes in DAR 109: B116–17 and DAR 27.2: A17), but concluded that the evidence for heterostyly in the species was ‘curiously conflicting’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 168). In his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13041A.xml">7 February 1881</ref>, Müller had suggested that one type of anther served to attract insects, while the other type ensured cross-fertilisation. In reply, CD had mentioned his earlier experiments on plants in the family Melastomaceae (a synonym of Melastomataceae), noted for possessing different types of pollen and anthers (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13091.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 20 March 1881</ref> and nn. 2, 3, and 6). CD received dried plants of <hi rend="italic">Monochaetum ensiferum</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">M. calcaratum</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">Centradenia floribunda</hi> from Kew and made observations on them on 3 April 1881 (notes in DAR 205.8: 21, 43).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13041A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 7 February 1881</ref> and n. 5. No record has been found of Müller having sent seeds of <hi rend="italic">Heteranthera reniformis</hi> (kidneyleaf mudplantain).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had begun studying bloom (the epicuticular coating on the leaves and fruit of many plants) in August 1873 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9007.xml">letter to J. D. Hooker, 13 August 1873</ref> and n. 2). He carried out experiments to compare the effects of water on berries and leaves with the bloom left on and on those that had the bloom removed (notes in DAR 66: 8, 24). He suspended his work on the subject in 1874 in order to concentrate on finishing <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9571.xml">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 28 [June 1874]</ref> and n. 7). CD never published on bloom, but <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> published some of the results of their experiments, made in 1878, in his paper ‘On the relation between the “bloom” on leaves and the distribution of the stomata’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml">F. Darwin 1886</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had mentioned his observations on the behaviour of leaves of <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi> throwing off water in a letter to Müller of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10960.xml">14 May 1877</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 25). He had asked Müller to make similar observations on any sensitive species of <hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 128, CD had noted that leaves of <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi>, though not sensitive to touch, partially assumed their nocturnal position if shaken or syringed with water. He also noted movement in terminal but not lateral leaflets of <hi rend="italic">Desmodium gyrans</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Codariocalyx motorius</hi>, telegraph or semaphore plant) when syringed (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 363). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Müller had mentioned that bees of the genera <hi rend="italic">Trigona</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Melipona</hi> were attracted by the bright yellow pollen of flowers of <hi rend="italic">Lagerstroemia</hi>, while ignoring the less noticeable green pollen (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-13041A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 7 February 1881</ref>).</note> 
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>