<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8231">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alfred Espinas<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   March 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16806</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8231 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8231.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8231.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 163: 33</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>163: 33</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1537.xml">Espinas, A.-V.</persName>
                <placeName>Le Havre</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1872-03-01" notAfter="1872-03-31">Mar 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>AE, philosophy professor, is disposed to accept natural selection, but argues that it lacks direction. Suggests that direction would be given if one assumed the appearance of multiple advantageous traits in a single individual. Cites Herbert Spencer, Rudolf Virchow, Claude Bernard, and Carl Vogt.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_411">Bernard, Claude</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">philosophy professor</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4495">Spencer, Herbert</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4897">Virchow, R. C.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4902">Vogt, Carl</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">individuals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-01-14" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-01-14" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-01-14" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00114_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00114_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="33:1r" xml:id="i114">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00114.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00114_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00114.dzi" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:1v" xml:id="i115">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00115.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00115_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00115.dzi" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:2r" xml:id="i116">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00116.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00116_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00116.dzi" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:2v" xml:id="i117">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00117.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00117_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00117.dzi" width="3623px" height="6017px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:3r" xml:id="i118">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00118.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00118_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00118.dzi" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:3v" xml:id="i119">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00119.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00119_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00119.dzi" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:4r" xml:id="i120">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00120.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00120_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00120.dzi" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="33:4v" xml:id="i121">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00121.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00121_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00121.dzi" width="3533px" height="5975px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Après une lecture attentive de vos ouvrages, je prends la liberté de vous soumettre les deux observations suivantes. Je vous serai reconnaissant de me dire quelle valeur vous leur accordez.</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Je n’ai pas trouvé dans l’exposé de votre théorie l’explication de ce fait que les espèces ont varié dans le sens d’une complication progressive à partir des formes les plus basses jusqu’aux formes les plus élevées. Que de nouvelles espèces se forment, c’est ce que le fait de la variation individuelle conservée et développée par la sélection, et la lutte pour l’existence expliquent très suffisamment. Mais pour quelle raison les cas de rétrogradation ne sont pas aussi nombreux que les cas de progression, pourquelle raison la sélection et la concurrence vitale ne conservent pas autant de caractères inférieurs que de caractères supérieurs, c’est ce que je ne puis comprendre. En effet d’une part la sélection s’attache souvent à des caractères défavorables à la lutte, comme la petite étendue des ailes chez l’oiseau, l’éclat des couleurs chez les insectes, le développement exageré des cornes chez les mammifères … etc. Vous le constatez vous-même. Il y aurait donc dans ce cas diminution de force, abaissement, rétrogradation au moins aussi souvent que profit et perfectionnement.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> D’autre part la lutte pour l’existence est souvent soutenue avec avantage par des formes animales inférieures contre de plus élevées. Ainsi dans l’Afrique centrale la <hi rend="underline">tsetsé</hi>, simple mouche, détruit sans peine tous les chevaux et tous les boeufs qui sont amenés dans ces parages.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Vous avez certainement dans la pensée une foule d’exemples analogues. Ce sont précisément les animaux les plus insaisissables (miasmes, microdermes)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> qui sont le plus redoutables par les maladies qu’ils engendrent et dont la cause reste le plus souvent inconnue. Pourquoi donc les formes supérieures triompheraient-elles, si mal armées qu’elles sont par rapport aux formes inférieures? Il se produira donc plutôt des retrogradations que des progrès et votre arbre généalogique, en admettant qu’il pousse quelques ramaux, s’étiolera bientôt, comme une plante semée dans le désert ou sur le sommet d’une montagne.</p>
<p>Vous me répondrez que cela arriverait si la lutte se livrait dans une aire déterminée et comme en champ clos: Mais que la facilité qu’ont les espèces pourchassées de se réfugier en de nouveaux milieux laissera le champ libre à des créations perfectionnées. Mais suffit-il que le fait <hi rend="underline">puisse</hi> se produire, et ne se produise que par hazard? Ne faut-il pas qu’il se produise nécessairement et normalement en vertu d’une loi positive? Car, toutes choses restant égales, il pourra arriver aussi souvent que le milieu, par l’adaptation qu’il exige, opère une diminution dans la perfection organique, comme c’est le cas pour les phoques, mammifères dégénérés sous l’action du milieu,<ref target="#foot.f5"/>—quand encore il n’arrivera pas, ce qui est supposable cependant, que ce passage, toujours difficile, d’un milieu à un autre, détruise précisement cette espèce, sur laquelle reposent les chances de progrès! Il y a donc là, si je vous ai bien compris, une lacune dans votre théorie. Il faudrait qu’une loi positive, normale, vint communiquer à la puissance sélective une direction déterminée et que cette direction soit celle de la complication organique progressive, ou de la perfection.</p>
<p>Voici comment l’explication demandée me parait possible. La variation individuelle peut susciter des êtres qui sont doués exceptionnellement, non pas d’un caractère spécial comme la force ou la vitesse ou la beauté, mais de tous les caractères avantageux à la fois. Je crois ce point de départ incontestable et très conforme à vos vues. Or de tels êtres l’emporteront nécessairement, 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. sur leurs semblables 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. sur les espèces avoisinantes. En effet, quant à ce qui concerne la transmission héréditaire, ils auront beaucoup plus de chances de se reproduire, puisque s’il s’agit de combattre, ils seront les plus forts, s’il s’agit de courir ils seront les plus agiles, s’il s’agit de plaire, ils seront les plus séduisants. Quel que soit le caprice de la femelle, ils pourront toujours y répondre, tandisque d’autres, n’ayant comme dit le proverbe français qu’<hi rend="underline">une corde à leur arc</hi> ne réussiront que par un concours inespéré de circonstances. Quant aux espèces avoisinantes, de tels individus lutteront avantageusement avec elles, se servant successivement de toutes les armes que comporte la constitution de leur organisme contre chacun de leurs ennemis, opposant à l’un la force, à l’autre la course, à l’autre l’invulnérabilité, à l’autre encore la ruse. Mais c’est surtout par l’aptitude qu’ils possèderont de se plier aux exigences des différents milieux que de tels êtres attesteront leur supériorité. Voyons l’amphibie; quelles ressources ne gagne-t-il pas pour la recherche de la nourriture, la fuite du péril, et la défense contre la sécheresse excessive ou l’inondation par ce fait seul qu’il est apte à se mouvoir dans deux milieux au lieu d’un seul? Et cependant cet avantage ne résulte pour lui que d’une complication nouvelle, toute fortuite, de son organisme, qui l’a rendu propre à respirer plus longtemps l’air en nature, pourvu que cet air soit suffisamment humide! C’est ainsi que l’homme dont l’organisme est le plus parfait ou le plus compliqué (tout en restant un) est celui de tous les animaux qui est le plus apte à changer de milieu, et qui le fait le plus impunément. De là pour lui la ressource de l’emigration, si avantageuse à l’Angleterre et à l’allemagne, etc. En sorte que la nation la plus probablement destinée à la victoire dans le concert Européen n’est pas la plus artiste, ni la plus féconde, ni la plus commerçante, ni la plus savante, ni la plus militaire, mais celle qui par un phénomène de variation originelle réunira en plus grand nombre et au degré le plus haut ces qualités diverses. (Sa fécondité ne sert en rien à la Chine)</p>
<p>Admettons maintenant ce que vous avez si abondamment prouvé que l’espèce peut varier, il arrivera dès lors qu’une transformation s’accomplira nécessairement et normalement des formes moins riches aux formes plus riches en complication, c’est à dire des formes moins parfaites aux formes plus parfaites, et que la sélection, (sans faire intervenir la divinité <hi rend="underline">ex machinâ</hi>)<ref target="#foot.f6"/> prendra le sens du progrès. L’homme particulièrement, en qui a brillé pour la première fois la pensée réfléchie, disposant par là de l’<hi rend="underline">instrument par excellence de l’adaptation variée</hi>, (Spencer)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> se pliera à toutes les exigences de tous les milieux, trouvera le frais sous l’équateur et le chaud parmi les glaces, pêchera sur les côtes, chassera sur les montages, labourera dans la plaine prêtera des ailes à sa flèche pour atteindre l’oiseau, sera de plus en plus riche en puissances variées, et réunira en lui-même les facultés de toute la nature vivante. Nos navires en effet nous font amphibies, nos ballons, oiseaux, nos chevaux, coureurs, et il n’y a pas de limite assignable à cette complexité de l’organisme humain. C’est elle seule qui nous a donné la victoire sur le reste des formes vivantes.</p>
<p>En résumé je propose d’ajouter à votre principe de sélection naturelle, agent selon moi indifférent de transformation, le principe de complication organique progressive, qui détermine la force sélective dans le sens de la perfection croissante. Je vous serai reconnaissant de me dire d’un mot ce que vous pensez de tout cela. Ce n’est d’ailleurs qu’un développement de votre doctrine.</p>
<p>2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Vous avouez quelque part ne pas comprendre pourquoi les individus stériles, pourquoi les neutres eux-mêmes impriment à la descendance de leurs congénères leurs caractères individuels.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Voici une hypothèse que je soumets à votre jugement. Tant que ces animaux stériles sont considérés comme individus absolument séparés, la transmission de leurs caractères est incompréhensible. Mais considérez le groupe congénère dont ils font partie comme un tout organique indivisible, l’hérédité des caractères appartenant même aux neutres pourra être facilement entendue. Mais comment et pourquoi considérer une famille, une ruche comme un tout vivant indivisible? La est la question.</p>
<p>J’observe d’abord que depuis les travaux de Virchow et de Claude Bernard la vie ne peut être regardée que comme une association d’éléments individuels et je soupçonne que ce fait, universel quant à la structure des individus, doit aussi jeter quelque lumière sur les rapports externes des individus entre eux.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Si d’autre part je considère, suivant le principe énoncé à la page précédente, l’humanité comme un résumé de la nature inférieure, je vois en elle trois fonctions principales réalisées par l’association 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. la nutrition, (vie individuelle), réalisée par un groupement de cellules, 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. la génération (vie domestique) réalisée par un groupement d’individus sexués, 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. la civilisation (vie politique, πολιτικὸν ζῶον)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> réalisée par un groupement de familles et plus tard de tribus. Je me demande donc si la nature ne renferme pas à l’état d’ébauches partielles cette organisation complexe qui nous a valu la victoire dans ce que vous appelez la plus décisive des épreuves, la bataille de la vie.</p>
<p>Or je trouve en effet au bas de l’échelle 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. <hi rend="underline">les polypiers</hi> qui sont d’après Vogt des associations en vue de la nutrition, organes multiples, vie unique, mais faiblement concentrée.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Chaque polype absorbe la nourriture (corail, Lacaze Duthiers) et en commence la digestion; mais la circulation est confiée au polypier.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Ailleurs c’est la digestion qui est commune, ailleurs l’excrétion, ailleurs la préhension ou la locomotion, mais peu importe, le but est toujours la vie nutritive, et cette fonction est toujours l’oeuvre propre de l’individu total composé. 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. <hi rend="underline">La famille</hi>, fondée sur une communication non plus permanente, mais passagère des conduits et liquides vitaux, et qui force cependant dans presque toute l’échelle les deux sexes à s’agréger physiquement comme le polype. L’arbre généalogique ne peut d’ailleurs être représenté que par la figure d’un polypier. La famille est constituée d’après différents types, dont le plus bas est celui du poisson, et le plus élevé celui des mammifères, types parmi lesquels on peut distinguer trois plans principaux d’abord l’absence de rapport entre les sexes, ensuite le rapport des sexes accordant la prédominance à l’élément feminin (abeilles, fourmis, termites etc) enfin le rapport des sexes fondé sur la prédominance de l’élement mâle. Ici nous sommes au terme d’une progression constante marquée entre autres caractères par la diminution du nombre des accouplés et des rejetons, et d’autre part, par l’importance de plus en plus grande accordée à l’intelligence dans la conservation des jeunes (partout où le mâle joue un rôle considérable dans la famille, l’<hi rend="underline">éducation</hi> en est la fonction capitale)— 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Enfin la cité ou la tribu</hi>, préparée dans le règne animal par la bande, le troupeau, le vol, la Tribu, quel que soit le nom qu’on donne à l’association animale qui n’a plus exclusivement la reproduction ni même l’éducation pour fin. Vous avez dans votre dernier ouvrage analysé ce phénomène et vu le premier l’importance des instincts sociaux dans la conservation vitale.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Cette function, aussi capitale que celle de la nutrition quoique plus élevée, repose sur les rapports ou mouvements harmoniques des centres nerveux et des organes sensoriels. Je le répète: la vie, dans son sens le plus strict n’est pas moins intéressée à ces mouvements coordonnés qu’à ceux des viscères et des appareils reproducteurs. Séparés, les individus doivent périr.</p>
<p>Cela étant, il faut voir dans chaque polypier, dans chaque ruche, dans chaque fourmilière, dans chaque famille ou troupeau naturel, dans chaque tribu ou nation, un vaste animal unique, pénétré d’une même vie, concourant dans ses éléments multiples à une fonction commune. Comment donc nous étonner maintenant si les membres de l’un de ces organismes, même stériles, même neutres, communiquent aux descendants de l’organisme total certains caractères qui leur sont propres? L’hérédité des neutres est expliquée. Pour moi je ne m’étonne pas plus de voir les caractères des fourmis neutres se perpétuer par l’hérédité que je ne m’étonne de voir une particularité du sein chez une femme se transmettre à sa fille; la fourmi neutre n’étant à mes yeux qu’une sorte de mammelle de la reine douée d’une vie individuelle et chargée d’une fonction de nutrition, d’un rôle d’éleveuse que celle-ci ne pourrait remplir seule.</p>
<p>Voilà, Monsieur, le squelette bien sec de deux idées que vous saurez couvrir des muscles et pourvoir de la vie qui leur manque, grâce à la riche matière de faits dont vous disposez. Avec ces additions, il me semble que votre hypothèse répondrait à un plus grand nombre d’objections, expliquerait un plus grand nombre de faits. Or, (jen reviens toujours à mon principe de sélection par la complexité organique) une hypothèse qui offre les points de vue les plus variés, qui <hi rend="underline">s’adapte</hi> à un plus grand nombre de cas, est celle qui triomphera certainement dans la bataille des systêmes, et poussera sur l’arbre de la science en une vigoureuse branche nouvelle.</p>
<p>Recevez l’assurance de mon admiration respectueuse, | Alfred Espinas | professeur de philosophie <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Mars 1872   3 Place Richelieu, Hâvre.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>After reading your works attentively, I am taking the liberty of submitting the following two observations to you. I shall be grateful if you can tell me what value you place on them.</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. I did not find, in the statement of your theory, an explanation for the fact that species have tended to vary with progressive complexity from the lowest to the highest forms. That new species form, is very sufficiently explained by the fact of individual variation, preserved and developed by selection, and by the struggle for existence. But what I cannot understand is the reason why cases of retrogradation are not as numerous as cases of progression, the reason why selection and vital competition do not preserve as many inferior characters as superior characters. On the one hand, indeed, selection often attaches itself to characters that are unfavourable in the struggle, such as a small wingspan in birds, brilliant colours in insects, an exaggerated development of horns in mammals … etc. You confirm this yourself. So in such cases there would be a diminution of strength, a sinking, a retrogradation at least as often as there is an advantage and a perfection.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> On the other hand, the struggle for existence is often maintained advantageously by lower animal forms against higher ones. Thus, in central Africa, the <hi rend="underline">tsetse</hi>, a mere fly, easily destroys all the horses and cattle which are brought into those regions.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You will certainly have in mind a host of analogous examples. It is precisely the most elusive animals (miasmas, microderms)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> which are the most formidable through the diseases they engender and whose cause most often remains unknown. So why do the higher forms triumph, as poorly armed as they are in relation to the lower forms? There would then be retrogradations rather than progress and your genealogical tree, even allowing that it bears several branches, would soon wither, like a plant sown in the desert or on a mountain-top.</p>
<p>You will reply that this would occur if the struggle were taking place in a defined area and as if in an enclosed space: But that the ability of hunted species to take refuge in new environments leaves the field free for perfected creations. But does it suffice that the fact <hi rend="underline">may</hi> occur, and yet only occurs by chance? Isn’t it necessary for it to occur inevitably and normally by virtue of a positive law? For, all other things being equal, it might occur whenever the environment causes a diminution in organic perfection by necessitating adaptation, as in the case of seals, mammals which have degenerated under the action of the environment,<ref target="#foot.f5"/>—even, as is at any rate conceivable, should this transition, which is always difficult, from one environment to another not entirely destroy the species on which the chances of progress rest! So here we have, if I have understood you right, a lacuna in your theory. A positive, natural law would be required to transmit a definite direction to the selective power, and for the direction in question to be that of progressive organic complication, or perfection.</p>
<p>Here is how the explanation I am asking for seems possible to me. Individual variation can sustain beings that are exceptionally gifted, not with a special character such as strength or speed or beauty, but with all advantageous characters at once. I think that this starting point is undeniable and very consistent with your views. Now such beings would necessarily prevail, 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. over their own kind 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. over neighbouring species. Indeed, as regards hereditary transmission, they will have far more chances to reproduce, since when it is a matter of fighting, they will be the strongest, when it is a matter of running, they will be the most agile, when it is a matter of pleasing, they will be the most seductive. Whatever the female’s whim, they would always be able to respond to it, whilst others, having, as the French proverb says, but <hi rend="underline">a single string to their bow</hi>, will only succeed through an unexpected combination of circumstances. As for the neighbouring species, such individuals will struggle against them to advantage, making use of all the weapons that the constitution of their organism contains in succession against each of their enemies, opposing strength to one, running to another, invulnerability to a third, cunning to yet another. But it will be above all in the aptitude they possess to adapt to the demands of different environments that such beings will demonstrate their superiority. Consider the amphibian; what resources does it not gain in the search for food, the flight from peril, and the protection against excessive drought or inundation from the mere fact that it is fitted to moving in two environments instead of a single one? And yet it only acquires this advantage from a new and totally fortuitous complication of its organism, which has rendered it able to breathe pure air for longer, providing that the air is sufficiently moist! So it is that man, whose organism is the most perfect or most complex (which comes to the same thing), is the one among all the animals who is most fitted to changing environments, and who does so with most impunity. Hence he has the resource of emigration, which is so advantageous for England and Germany, etc. Such that the nation most probably destined for victory in the European concert is not the most artistic, nor the most fertile, nor the most commercial, nor the most learned, nor the most military, but the one that by means of a phenomenon of original variation unites these diverse qualities in the largest number and to the highest degree. (Its fertility is of little use to China)</p>
<p>Let us now admit what you have so abundantly proven, that species can vary; it will accordingly happen that a transformation from forms which are less rich in complexity to those which are richer in complexity, that is to say from less perfect to more perfect forms, will take place necessarily and naturally, and that selection, (without requiring the divinity to intervene <hi rend="underline">ex machinâ</hi>)<ref target="#foot.f6"/> will take a progressive direction. Man in particular, who was the first to display reflective thought, and in that way had at his disposal the <hi rend="underline">instrument par excellence of varied adaptation</hi>, (Spencer)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> will adapt to all conditions of all environments, will find cold below the equator and heat amidst the ice, will fish on coasts, hunt on mountains, farm on the plain, add wings to his arrow to reach the bird, will be ever richer in varied powers, and will unite the faculties of all living nature in himself. Our ships in fact make us amphibians; our balloons, birds; our horses, runners; and no limit can be assigned to this complexity of the human organism. It is this alone which has made us victorious over the other living forms.</p>
<p>In sum, I propose to add to your principle of natural selection, in my view an indifferent agent of transformation, a principle of progressive organic complication, which directs the selective force towards growing perfection. I shall be grateful for a word on your thoughts about all this. It is no more, indeed, than a development of your doctrine.</p>
<p>2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. You acknowledge somewhere that you cannot understand why sterile individuals or even neuters imprint their individual characters upon the descendents of their congeners.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Here is a hypothesis which I submit to your judgement. As long as these sterile individuals are considered as absolutely distinct individuals, the transmission of their characters is incomprehensible. But consider the kin group of which they are a part as an indivisible organic whole; then the heredity even of the characters belonging to the neuters is easily understood. But how and why can we consider a family or a hive as a living indivisible whole? That is the question.</p>
<p>Firstly I shall observe that since the work of Virchow and Claude Bernard, life can only be regarded as an association of individual elements and I suspect that this fact, universally applicable to the structure of individuals, must also throw some light on the external relations between individuals.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>If on the other hand I consider humanity as a compendium of lower nature, following the principle stated on the previous page, I see three principal functions realised in it through association 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. nutrition, (individual life), realised by a group of cells, 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. generation (domestic life), realised by a group of sexed individuals, 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. civilisation (political life, [textgreek[politikon zw=on]])<ref target="#foot.f10"/> realised by a group of families and subsequently tribes. I therefore ask myself whether nature does not include, in the form of partial sketches, that complex organisation which has earned us victory in what you call the most decisive of tests, the battle for existence.</p>
<p>Now I find indeed at the base of the scale 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. <hi rend="underline">polypidoms</hi> which are, according to Vogt, associations in regard to nutrition, with multiple organs and a single life, but weakly concentrated.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Each polyp absorbs nourishment (coral, Lacaze Duthiers) and begins its digestion; but circulation is allocated to the polypidom.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Elsewhere it is digestion that is shared, or excretion, or capture, or locomotion, but this is of little importance, the goal is always the nutritive life, and that function is always the proper task of the whole composite individual. 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. <hi rend="underline">The family</hi>, founded on a communication of vessels and vital liquids that is not permanent but transitory, and that nevertheless forces the two sexes, almost all across the scale, to unite physically like the polyp. The genealogical tree can only be represented, besides, in the form of a polypidom. The family is made up of different types, the lowest of which is that of the fish, and the highest that of mammals, types among which one can distinguish three principal plans: firstly an absence of relations between the sexes, next a relation between the sexes that accords predominance to the feminine element (bees, ants, termites etc) lastly a relation between the sexes founded on the predominance of the male element. Here we reach the limit of a constant progression, marked by, among other characters, a diminution in the number of mated individuals and descendants, and on the other hand, by the ever greater importance accorded to intelligence in the protection of the young (wherever the male plays a significant role in the family, <hi rend="underline">education</hi> is its capital function)— 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Lastly, the city or tribe</hi>, prepared in the animal kingdom by the pack, herd, flock, Tribe, whatever name one gives to the animal association that no longer exclusively has reproduction or education as its goal. In your last work, you analysed this phenomenon and were the first to see the importance of the social instincts in vital preservation.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> This function, as crucial as that of nutrition though higher, rests on harmonic relations or movements of the nerve centres and sensory organs. I repeat: life, in its strictest sense, is no less interested in these coordinated movements than in those of the viscera and reproductive apparatus. Apart, individuals must perish.</p>
<p>This being so, every polypidom, every hive, every anthill, every natural family or herd, every tribe or nation, must be seen as a vast individual animal, filled with a single life, cooperating through its multiple elements towards a common function. Should we now be astonished if the members of one of these organisms, even the sterile and neuter ones, communicate certain characters specific to themselves to the descendants of the total organism? The heredity of neuters is explained. For my part, I am no more astonished to see the characters of neuter ants perpetuated through heredity than to see a peculiarity of the breast in one woman transmitted to her daughter; the neuter ant being no more, in my eyes, than a sort of teat of the queen, endowed with individual life and charged with a nutritional role, a rearing role which the queen cannot accomplish alone.</p>
<p>Here, dear Sir, you have the very dry skeleton of two ideas that you will be able to cover with muscles and supply with the life they lack, thanks to the rich supply of facts at your disposal. With these additions, it seems to me that your hypothesis would respond to a larger number of objections and explain a larger number of facts. Now, (to return again to my principle of selection through organic complexity) the hypothesis which offers the most varied points of view, which <hi rend="underline">adapts</hi> to a greater number of cases, is the one which will certainly triumph in the battle of systems, and grow into a vigorous new branch on the tree of science.</p>
<p>Be assured of my respectful admiration, | Alfred Espinas | professor of philosophy <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">March 1872   3 Place Richelieu, Le Hâvre.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 90–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">On retrogression, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, p. 144, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 206, 2: 368. CD thought that retrogression might occur when external conditions made greater complexity unnecessary.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Tsetse are flies in the genus <hi rend="italic">Glossina</hi>; they were believed to cause the horse and cattle disease nagana. For the history of the relationship between the tsetse and both animal and human disease, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7471.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Steverding 2008</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The belief that miasmas or bad air were agents of contagious disease was popular until the last decades of the nineteenth century (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3345.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hannaway 1993</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Espinas probably refers to the development (or degeneration) of seals’ flippers from a five-toed foot, as CD described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 200. Espinas’s use of the term degeneration is reminiscent of earlier type-theory (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sloan 2010</ref>). For CD, the reduction of an organ was simply an environmental response (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 32).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Ex machina</hi>: from a device (Latin). The <hi rend="italic">deus ex machina</hi> was a Greek theatrical convention (gods were brought on-stage by a sort of crane); the phrase had come to refer to a contrived or inartistic solution to a difficulty in the plot.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Espinas was translating <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Principles of psychology</hi> into French (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7372.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer 1870–2</ref> and Espinas and Ribot trans. 1874–5). The passage Espinas refers to has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 230, CD argued that the inheritance of characteristics of sterile organisms could be explained by the fact that natural selection operated on the family (that is, groups of related individuals) as well as on the individual.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Espinas refers to Rudolf Carl Virchow and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_411.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claude Bernard</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">πολιτικὸν ζῷον: political animal (Greek); a reference to Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Politics</hi> (see 1.2.1253a 1–4, 7–18).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Espinas probably refers to a description of corals in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Vogt’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Altes und neues aus Thier- und Menschenleben</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7995.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vogt 1859</ref>, 2: 245–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Félix Joseph Henri Lacaze-Duthiers described the circulation and nourishment of polyps and polypidoms in <hi rend="italic">Histoire naturelle du corail</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lacaze-Duthiers 1864</ref>, pp. 76–83).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 74–86.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>