<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10924">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Colby   9 April 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16476</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10924 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10924.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10924.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 208</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 208</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1005.xml">Colby, John</persName>
                <placeName>Pantyderi</placeName>
                <date when="1877-04-09">9 Apr 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Notes on competition among tree species in South Wales.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">tree</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Wales, South</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">struggle for existence</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Pantyderi— Blaenffos R.S.O | South Wales.</placeName>
                    <date>9 Ap 77</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much obliged to you for your letter anent the blue bell.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In this part of the country the tendency of the dioecious principle to win the race of life is very marked. This place has, from time unknown, been called Pantyderi (Vale of Oaks) and there are still some good old oak trees standing. But very rarely now do I find a seedling oak tree, though <hi rend="underline">ash</hi> seeds itself in abundance &amp; grows up like a weed— It seems to push all other trees out of the premises.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The only one which holds its own against it being sycamore. This beats ash on the higher grounds, exposed to the S.W &amp; W winds off the Sea.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But is beaten by ash in sheltered places. Of other trees, Alder does well along rivers; wild cherry formerly seeded itself freely, but seems now to get less common; Holly grows freely; Mountain ash fairly; Beech seedlings are occasionally found; Elm never seeds itself but young trees occasionally grow up from root suckers.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Laurel, &amp; Silver fir occasionally grow from seed without assist<hi rend="superscript">ce</hi>.. But Spruce fir, scotch fir, larch, poplar, aspen would I believe soon die out but for artificial care. Rhododendron occasionally grows from seed.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I knew of one which grew high up in the hollow of an oak branch, near this—</p>
<p>But as I said before nothing comes near the <hi rend="underline">ash</hi> for taking care of itself in the lower grounds— In some places they grow up like corn &amp; could be mowed with a scythe—</p>
                    <p>By the way, turning from plants to animals, do you know if the Brown Owl has been known to build in chimneys? For this morning a nest with four young owls was taken from our kitchen chimney, although a “culm” fire burns in the kitchen without intermission day &amp; night.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I had seen the old owls about the house but had no idea they were chimney builders.</p>
<p>The other chimneys are frequented by jack daws, perhaps the owls thought the young daws would come in handy for feeding the owlets.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>This is a famous winter resort for birds for there are plenty of evergreens, &amp; running water which I have never known to freeze over, the birds however are mostly small the largest wild bird being the heron.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Hoping these brief notes may be of interest to you &amp; that you can tell whether the owls are singular in their chimney predilections I am yours faithfully | John Colby—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
               
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10872.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Colby, 27 February 1877</ref>. Colby had written about a peloric flower he had seen in Germany.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The native oak species of the region was <hi rend="italic">Quercus petraea</hi> (sessile oak), which is monoecious, having male and female flowers on the same tree. <hi rend="italic">Fraxinus excelsior</hi> (European ash) is usually dioecious, having male and female flowers on separate trees. CD discussed the advantages and disadvantages of monoecism and dioecism for trees in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. 411–14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Acer pseudoplatanus</hi> (sycamore) is monoecious and can tolerate both very poor soils and a marine environment.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Alnus glutinosa</hi> (European alder), <hi rend="italic">Sorbus aucuparia</hi> (mountain ash or rowan), and <hi rend="italic">Fagus sylvatica</hi> (beech) are monoecious; <hi rend="italic">Ilex aquifolium</hi> (common holly) is dioecious. <hi rend="italic">Prunus avium</hi> (wild cherry) and <hi rend="italic">Ulmus glabra</hi> (wych elm) are hermaphrodite, that is, have flowers with both male and female organs.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Laurus nobilis</hi> (laurel), <hi rend="italic">Populus alba</hi> (white poplar), and <hi rend="italic">Populus tremula</hi> (European aspen) are dioecious. <hi rend="italic">Abies alba</hi> (silver fir), <hi rend="italic">Picea</hi> (the genus of spruces), <hi rend="italic">Pinus sylvestris</hi> (Scots pine), and <hi rend="italic">Larix</hi> (the genus of larches) are, like most conifers, monoecious. The genus <hi rend="italic">Rhododendron</hi> has both monoecious and dioecious species.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Strix aluco</hi> (tawny owl or brown owl) typically nests in tree holes. Culm is coal dust or slack; the term was applied to the slack of anthracite or stone-coal from the Welsh collieries (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Corvus (Coloeus) monedula</hi> (Eurasian jackdaw) is well known for nesting in chimneys.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Ardea cinerea</hi> (grey heron).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>