<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7925">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Anton Dohrn   7 September 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16332</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7925 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7925.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7925.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Groeben (1982): 33</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 207</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 207</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml">Dohrn, F. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Lewisham</placeName>
                <date when="1871-09-07">7 Sept 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Reports on the international support he has obtained for the zoological station [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">7038</hi>]. Asks CD whether he will serve on a board of naturalists who would receive an annual report on the station.</p> 
            <p>Huxley is now convinced by AD’s views on homologies of the nervous system of arthropods, annelids, and vertebrates. Kovalevsky takes the same line but does not go far enough.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">7038</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">annelids</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">arthropods</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">vertebrates</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2486">Huxley, T. H.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2751">Kovalevsky, V. O.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">homology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Once more over to this country I should have made my personal appearance before You, had I not been afraid of being troublesome to You.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>But I cannot help writing and giving You a short abstract of the march of my affair, in which You have been so kind as to take interest. All the more I must do so, as I hope You will continue to lend Your great moral assistance to the enterprise, which I now have entered at full length.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>The Napolitan affairs get on very well, and I am prepared to begin building October next. I have secured the assistance of the Berlin Minister of Instruction and the personal sympathy of the German ambassador at Rome.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I have got some eminent German Naturalists,—Helmholtz, Dubois-Reymond, Leuckart, Haeckel, Carl Vogt, Siebold etc. to write me letters, stating the great importance for Science of the complete carrying out of my plans. These letters I am about to print together with a short explanation of my undertaking.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I have got the “Times”, “Nature”, “Athenaeum”, “Pall Mall Gazette” and some others to write in favour of the “Zoological Stations”.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Mr. Norman Lockyer besides has promised me to secure the assistance of the most important American Papers.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I myself am able of doing every thing in the great German Periodicals and Papers; Italy too is at my disposal,—so that, including the different travelling books, Murray, Baedeker etc,—all these Elements of the Press have been won.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I am quite satisfied with the result of the Edinbourgh Meeting.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The new Comittee formed by Prof. Huxley, Rolleston, Percival Wright, Dr. Sclater and Ray Lankester will, I hope, be sufficient to carry on the subject in this Country.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I am about to visit the German Meeting and get its assistance too.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> In the first week of October the International Meeting of Anthropologists will be held at Bologna and I think I may bring them to testify their adherence to the Stations.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Thus a general agreement may be reached at and the Stations may realize, what they are intended for.</p>
<p>But I find it necessary to add one more important element. I think it necessary, that the whole affair may lie as long as possible in one hand. But this hand,—just now happening to be mine—ought to enjoy a general confidence. Therefore I intend to give an annual Report of the Management of the Station to a select Committee of Naturalists of high standard and after they have examined it, to publish it in all the Papers that lend their assistance to the enterprise. I intend to prove by that, that I personally do’nt enjoy the least undue advantage of the Station except what is necessary for the Chief of it. Creating thus a public controll I keep for the Stations the benefit of Centralisation being not to much subdue to Parliamentarism of any kind. I am especially anxious to make known, that the money got by entrance-fee or by private grants is completely saved for science and may never be used for private purposes of whatever kind. I am to engage one of the German bankers at Naples to controll the financial part of the Station and signing the annual Report.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> By these measures every one who spends his two francs entrance fee may be sure, that, besides his pleasure of looking at the beautiful marine creatures, he enjoys the higher pleasure of contributing to the advancement of Science in the most efficient way,—thus securing his personal interest in the whole scheme.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Would you, Mr. Darwin, lend me Your name to be placed among the series of Naturalists, who receive that annual Report, testifying thus their interest in the matter and giving it their moral assistance. Professor Huxley, who did so, told me You would most likely do the same,—and I therefore wait anxiously, You might do it, as this would be a very important help to the final result.— —</p>
<p>Professor Huxley will probably tell You, that he is almost completely convinced now of the righteousness of my view regarding the homologisation of the nervous chain of Arthropods, Annelids and Vertebrates<ref target="#foot.f14"/>   Kowalewsky has gone quite the same line, as You would easily find in looking through his last book, or into a short review which I made of it for the Academy.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> In that review I stated too, what I believed to be the shortcoming of Kowalewsky in demonstrating the necessity of accepting this new doctrine.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> I did so because I am rather sure, that my own investigations especially in Insects and Fishes have brought the problem to a complete solution. I am about to enlarge my proofs by adding the embryologies of several other fishes, and by treating Ascidians and Amphioxus, whom both I consider to be aberrant forms not ancestors of Vertebrates. I hope I may bring that out altogether in one or two years.—<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>I am to leave this country either on Sunday next or Monday. I should be very thankful, if You would let me know Your opinion about the above made demand by way of a short letter adressed to Mr. Stainton. Mountsfield Lewisham.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>I hope You will remember me most kindly to Mrs. Darwin and to Mr.  Darwin jr.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>Trusting that You will excuse this trouble and the great length of this lettre, I once more thank You for all the former kindness You have shewn to me.</p>
<p>Yours ever truly devoted | Anton Dohrn <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Mountsfield. 7.9.1871.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In 1871, Dohrn visited England to seek advice and moral support from scientists for his proposed zoological station at Naples (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 111–12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For more on the difficulties Dohrn faced in building the zoological station at Naples, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 114–52.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6397.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich von Mühler</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5522.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harry Arnim-Suckow</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Dohrn refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2207.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann von Helmholtz</ref>, Emil Heinrich Du Bois-Reymond, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rudolf Leuckart</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref>, and Karl Theodor Ernst von Siebold. He published the letters as a pamphlet in 1871 (Dohrn [1871b]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 24 August 1871, p. 242; <hi rend="italic">Daily News</hi>, 23 August 1872, p. 3; <hi rend="italic">Glasgow Herald</hi>, 24 August 1872, p. 3; <hi rend="italic">Leeds Mercury</hi>, 12 September 1872, p. 8; <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 29 February 1872, p. 337; <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 30 July 1872, p. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Joseph <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2971.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Norman Lockyer</ref>. An article about the zoological station appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Cincinnati Daily Gazette</hi>, 29 November 1871, p. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">After the station opened in 1873 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref> p. 153), John Murray published an account of it in his <hi rend="italic">Handbook for travellers in southern Italy</hi> of 1874; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_709.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Blewitt] 1874</ref>, p. 143, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9394.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Anton Dohrn, 6 April 1874</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 9394). An account was also published in Baedeker 1874, the fourth edition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5754.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Baedeker’s</ref> guide to southern Italy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The annual meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science was held in Edinburgh in 1871 (<hi rend="italic">Report of the 41st meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science</hi> (1871)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Rolleston</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5255.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Perceval Wright</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4251.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Lutley Sclater</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester</ref> were members of a committee appointed to promote the foundation of zoological stations in different parts of the world (see Dohrn 1871c).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The Assembly of German Naturalists and Physicians was held at Rostock in September 1871 (<hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 3 October 1871, p. 6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Dohrn refers to the second International Congress of Prehistorians in Bologna (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, p. 112).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">From 1876, Dohrn published annually the <hi rend="italic">Jahresbericht der zoologischen Station in Neapel.</hi> <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6331.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto Beer</ref> approved the financial report (<hi rend="italic">Erster Jahresbericht der zoologischen Station in Neapel</hi>, p. 19.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">The station included a public aquarium that was opened to visitors in January 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, p. 157).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Dohrn refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>. For Dohrn’s views on homologies of the vertebrate notochord (chorda dorsalis) in arthropods and annelids, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>, pp. 13–28.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Dohrn refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Onufrievich Kovalevsky</ref>, to his ‘Embryologische Studien an Würmern und Arthropoden’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. O. Kovalevsky 1869</ref>), and to Dohrn 1871d. The <hi rend="italic">Academy</hi> was a journal published in London.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">For Dohrn’s criticisms of Kovalevsky, see Dohrn 1871d, p. 498.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Dohrn later published <hi rend="italic">Der Ursprung der Wirbelthiere und das Princip des Functionswechsels</hi> (The origin of vertebrates and the principle of functional change; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>), in which he introduced the idea that morphological change could result from functional changes in organs. Ascidians are sea squirts (the class Ascidiaceae). <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus</hi> was the genus name for lancelets (a primitive fish). The terms ‘amphioxus’ and ‘lancelet’ are now common names that refer to the class Cephalochordata. For more on Dohrn’s views on ascidians and amphioxus, see Maienshein 1994.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Tibbats Stainton</ref> was a friend of Dohrn’s father, Carl <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anton Dohrn</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heuss 1991</ref>, p. 77).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Dohrn visited CD at Down on 26 September 1870; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Erasmus Darwin</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin</ref> may have been at Down (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7328.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 27 September [1870]</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>