<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-317">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. S. Henslow   [30–1 October 1836]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5235</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-317 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-317.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-317.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 39</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Darwin and Henslow</hi>: 118;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 273</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 512</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Henslow letters: 32 DAR/1/1/32)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Henslow letters: 32 DAR/1/1/32</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 43</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1836-10-30" notAfter="1836-10-31">[30–1 Oct 1836]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml">Henslow, J. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD in London to meet with naturalists about his collections. Lyell and Owen are helpful, but no one else, except R. E. Grant, seems to want to examine his specimens.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1951">Grant, R. E.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3051">Lyell, Charles</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">London</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>43. Great Marlborough St</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Henslow</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have delayed writing, as I daily expected the Beagle would arrive, and I should be better able to tell you how my prospects go on.— I spent yesterday on board at Greenwich, &amp; brought back with me the Galapagos plants; they do not appear numerous, but are I hope in tolerable preservation.— Tomorrow I will procure a box &amp; will send them to Cambridge.— I will keep this letter till I do so.— I called on your brother, but he was not at home, I left a card asking him to send anything he might happen to have, to my brothers, where I am now staying.— I have not made much progress with the great men, I find, as you told me, that they are all overwhelmed, with their own business. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell, has entered in the <hi rend="underline">most</hi> goodnatured manner, &amp; almost without being asked, into all my plans. He tells me, however, the same story, namely that I must do all myself.— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Owen seems anxious to dissect some of the animals in spirits;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> &amp; besides these two I have scarcely met anyone who seems to wish to possess any of my specimens.— I must except D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grant, who is willing to examine some of the corallines.— I see it is quite unreasonable to hope for a minute, that any man will undertake the examination of an whole order.— It is clear the collectors so much outnumber the real naturalists, that the latter have no time to spare.— I do not even find that the collections care for receiving the unnamed specimens.— The Zoological Museum<ref target="#foot.f2"/> is nearly full &amp; upward of a thousand specimens remain unmounted. I daresay the British Museum, would receive them, but I cannot feel, from all I hear, any great respect even for the present state of that establishment. Your plan will be not only the best, but the only one, namely to come down to Cambridge, arrange &amp; group together the different families &amp; then wait till people, who are already working in different branches may want specimens.— But it appears to me, to do this, it will be almost necessary to reside in London.— As far as I can yet see, my best plan will be to spend several months in Cambridge, &amp; then, when by your assistance, I know on what grounds I stand, to emigrate to London, where I can complete my geology, &amp; try <hi rend="underline">to push on the Zoology</hi>.— I assure you I grieve to find how many things make me see the necessity of living for some time in this dirty odious London.— For even in Geology, I suspect, much assistance &amp; communication will be necessary in this quarter: for instance in fossil bones of which none, excepting the fragments of Megatherium, have been looked at. And I clearly see without my presence never would be.— Fossil shells.—charts, maps, communication with FitzRoy. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell says also, that the power of taking any odd specimen, to the different societies, where many Naturalists are met together is a very essential point.— However true this may be, I am very sure the assistance I shall get in Cambridge will be infinitely more, than I ever should receive in London.— Prof. Sedgwick very kindly hunted out my quarters, &amp; I breakfasted with him.— I am sorry to find he will leave Cambridge so soon.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> From the delay in the Beagle’s arrival, I do not know whether I shall be able to come down before the end of the month, for I have yet to visit Shrewsbury.— If you have opportunities, talk a little with him, on those points you said his advice would be most valuable; namely the form of publication. I think from what I hear, that a volume, would be less troublesome &amp; pleasanter, than detached papers.— Also about fossil shells. Is Sowerby<ref target="#foot.f4"/> a good man? I understand his assistance can be purchased.—</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clift says he will ask Prof. Buckland to look at the bones;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I should think he would rather like it, as M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clift says some belong to forms which he himself does not at all know.— I am anxious to know, whether Prof. Sedgwick recommends any particular nomenclature for the rocks.— I have often thought of your really most kind offer of talking with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Henslow about my taking up my quarters with you. Few things could give me more happiness, and at the same time do me more real good. But I fear I should me much in the way, &amp; I have been thinking of another plan which would be better for the work; that is to take lodgings with two sitting rooms &amp; a bedroom, (which I daresay could be procured), in one of which my servant could work &amp; it would at the same time serve for a warehouse for the skins &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c.— Perhaps my servant might live in the house.— In College I should only have one room, which, although a large one, would be inconvenient; and as it may turn out more advisable not to remain a whole year, it is a great expence to buy furniture crockery &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c for any shorter period. If I subsequently live in London, I shall follow my brothers plan take the whole of an unfurnished house, excepting the shop or office, then furnish two rooms, &amp; keep the others for lumber.— Such a house can be got for less than 100£ per annum. I believe M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ash clearly understood it was quite a chance, whether I intended coming to reside the whole yea〈r.〉 If you should happen to meet him (but otherwise not) just mention that I shall probably not reside for such a time, &amp; he will then understand, that I should not trouble him about rooms.—</p>
<p>I find this letter, which is a most unmerciful long one all about myself, extending over so much paper, that I will send it with the plants, &amp; write another just to forewarn you of the Box. Perhaps also I shall be able by that time to announce the heavy cases with geolog. &amp; other specimen〈s.〉 Would it not be the best plan, <hi rend="underline">if it can be so managed</hi>, to leave the heavy geolog: boxes at the warehouse, so that when I come down &amp; the room is ready to take them direct there? I have forgotten to mention one bad bit of news, namely that Cuming was at the Galapagos.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Did he collect plants, I doubt it, because the far greater part of the plants only live near the summit of the mountains, some miles from the coast? I shall grieve, if you lose your tiny botanical feast,— I only wish I had known the Botanists cared so much for specimens &amp; the Zoologists so little; the proportional number of specimens in the two branches should have had a very different appearance. I am out of patience with the Zoologists, not because they are overworked, but for their mean quarrelsome spirit. I went the other evening to the Zoological Soc. where the speakers were snarling at each other, in a manner anything but like that of gentlemen.</p>
<p>Thank Heavens, as long as I remain in Cambridge there will not be any danger of falling into any such contemptible quarrels, whilst in London I do not see how it is to be avoided. Of the Naturalists; F. Hope is out of London, Westwood,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have not seen; so about my insects I know nothing.— I have seen M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Yarrel, twice, but he is so evidently so oppressed with business, that it is too selfish to plague him with my concerns.— He has asked me to dine with the Linnæan on Tuesday; and on Wednesday I dine with Geolog: so that I shall 〈    〉 all the great men.— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bell I 〈    〉 is so much occupied that there is no chance of his wishing for specimens of reptiles.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have forgotten to mention M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lonsdale,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> who gave me a most cordial reception, &amp; with whom I had much most interesting conversation.— If I was not much more inclined for geology, than the other branches of Natural History, I am sure M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell’s &amp; Lonsdale kindness ought to fix me.— You cannot conceive anything more thoroughily goodnatured, than the heart &amp; soul manner, in which he put himself in my place &amp; thought what would be best to do.— At first he was all for London versus Cambridge, but at last I made him confess that for some time at least the latter would be for me much the best. There is not another soul, whom I could ask, excepting yourself, to wade through &amp; criticize some of those papers which I have left with you.— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell owned that second to London, there was no place in 〈Engl〉and, so good for a naturalist as Cambridge. 〈U〉pon my word I am ashamed of writing so many foolish details; no young lady ever described her first ball with more, particularity.— With respect to the Mathematical instruments, I told the Captain, that I was sure you would allow him to leave the boxes for a week or two longer till he was established &amp; knew where to have them directed to.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Monday evening</hi> I have determined to send the plants by wagon with the bird skins, for reason which you will know by the letter which announces the boxes.</p>
<p>Yours ever most sincerely | Chas Darwin—</p>
<p>Again I have been compelled to change my plans.— I send the plants, per coach, &amp; this letter with them.— I will also write one line by the post in case of any accident. On Thursday the four boxes will arrive at Camb〈rid〉ge by Marsh’s Wagon.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.6 card] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘to’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.13 I] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘do’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.24 people] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘any one’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.27 several] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘some’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.29 you] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.30 see] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">1.31 For] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘But’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">1.36 societies] ‘ies’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘y’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.1 think] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">2.2 which] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">2.2 himself] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">2.16 plan] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">2.18 clearly] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">3.4 announce] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘send’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">3.6 I … &amp;] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">3.8 far] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">3.12 the two] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">3.12 had] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘worn.’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">3.16 that of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">4.15 was] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘all’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">4.18 some] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘those’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.12 ‘animals’; 1.13 ‘met’; 1.19 ‘Museum’; 1.23 ‘Cambridge’; 1.40 ‘with’; 1.41 ‘whether’; 2.9 ‘lodgings’; 2.12 ‘College’; 2.12 ‘large’; 3.3 ‘Perhaps’; 3.5 ‘leave the heavy’; 3.11 ‘Botanists’; 7.3 ‘boxes’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had met <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> at dinner with the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell</ref>s the day before (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. S. Owen 1894</ref>, 1: 102).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The Museum of the Zoological Society, then at 33 Bruton Street. The collection was dispersed some years later (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 1: 273).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4276.xml">Adam Sedgwick’s</ref> duties as a Prebendary of Norwich Cathedral required that he be in residence in December and January of each year (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1418.xml">Clark and Hughes 1890</ref>, 1: 433–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4480.xml">George Brettingham Sowerby</ref> described CD’s specimens of fossil shells in appendixes to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Buckland</ref> added a ‘Supplementary note’ about CD’s fossil bones to the second edition of his <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater treatise</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1038.xml">Buckland 1837</ref>, p. 603).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1149.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Cuming</ref>, famous for his collections of shells, visited the Galápagos Islands in 1829. He collected only a few plants. They were described, together with CD’s specimens, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3747.xml">Hooker 1846a</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3753.xml">1846b</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Obadiah Westwood</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_379.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Bell</ref> did agree to describe CD’s specimens for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi></ref> and, after much delay, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6607.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Reptiles</hi></ref> was published (1842–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2989.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Lonsdale</ref> described some of CD’s coral specimens for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>