<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-348">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. D. Fox   [12 March 1837]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7051</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-348 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-348.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-348.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 190</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 10</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Christ’s College Library, Cambridge (MS 53 Fox 51)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_83.xml">CCLC</repository>
                    <collection>MS 53</collection>
                    <idno>Fox 51</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 43</placeName>
                <date when="1837-03-12">[12 Mar 1837]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml" resp="high">Fox, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Finished going over his geological specimens at Cambridge, and is now in London.</p> 
<p>Describes his plans for writing the journal, and later the geology and zoology of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Cambridge</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">Beagle</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[43 Great Marlborough Street]</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday Evening</date>
                    <salute>My dear Fox</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is a long time since I wrote to you, from Cambridge, but I was determined to wait till I was fairly settled, which however I can hardly say I am yet, but on Tuesday I go into lodgings, at No<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 36 Gr<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Marlborought St. which I have taken for the year.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am at present in my brothers house no 43.— It is very pleasant our being so near neighbours.— My residence at Cambridge was rather longer, than I expected, owing to a job, which I determined to finish there, namely looking over all my geological specimens was finished.— Cambridge yet continues a very pleasant, but not so half so merry a place as before.— To walk through the courts of Christ Coll: and not know an inhabitant of a single room gave one a feeling half melancholy.— The only evil I found in Cambridge, was its being too pleasant;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> there was some agreeable party or another every evening, and one cannot say one is engaged with so much impunity there as in this great city.— It is a sorrowful, but I fear too certain truth, that no place is at all equal, for aiding one in Natural History pursuits, to this odious dirty smokey town, where one can never get a glimpse, at all, that is best worth seeing in nature.—</p>
<p>In your last letter you urge me, to get ready <hi rend="underline">the</hi> book. I am now hard at work and give up every thing else for it. Our plan is as follows.— Capt. FitzRoy writes two volumes, out of the materials collected during both the last voyage under Capt. King to T. del Fuego and during our circumnavigation.— I am to have the third volume, in which I intend giving a kind of journal of a naturalist, not following however always the order of time, but rather the order of position.— The habits of animals will occupy a large portion, sketches of the geology, the appearance of the country, and personal details will make the hodge-podge complete.— Afterwards I shall write an account of the geology in detail, and draw up some Zoological papers.— So that I have plenty of work, for the next year or two, and till that is finished I will have no holidays.— Do you recollect telling me, the new ostrich should be called “<hi rend="underline">darwinii</hi>”. By an odd chance M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gould has actually so named it!—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> We are going to read a paper to the Zoological on Tuesday about it.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I hope you will pay London a visit this spring; surely you will be able to find some good excuse, some necessary business, which will oblige you to come up.— I trust M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>Fox is pretty well.— My Father often makes enquiries through letters, and I have been ashamed lately, that I have been not been able to send any tidings.— I will not make any excuse about this letter being almost every word about myself, for I want you do the same, indeed, we have been so long separated, that there is not much else to do.— My good dear old brother lives the same life of tranquillity as usual. Going to Shrewsbury he considers a dreadful journey, only to be undertaken once a-year, and as far anything further, as altogether impossible.— He seems very well contented and happy, but for my own part, I would not care for a hundred years of life without a little more excitement. As for the good sisterhood at home, they remain, in statu quo, and long may they so remain.— You cannot imagine how gloriously delightful my first visit was to home. It was worth the banishment. How lucky I have been not to lose one near friend.</p>
<p>Good Bye, Dear Fox. | Yours affectionly, C Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.7 my] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.9 know] <hi rend="italic">final</hi> ‘n’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.8 hodge-podge] ‘podge’ <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘poge’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.2 oblige] ‘e’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘ed’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.4 not been] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘able’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.5 tidings] ‘ings’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.9 undertaken] ‘under’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi> : 1.6 ‘finish’; 2.14 ‘Tuesday’; 3.7 ‘brother’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In the ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, Appendix II) CD states that he entered his lodgings in Great Marlborough Street, London on the 13th, but that entry was made retrospectively in August 1838 when he started the ‘Journal’; hence it is more likely to be mistaken than ‘Tuesday’ (the 14th).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref>, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 1: 278–9, adds the following to his excerpt from this letter: <quote>A trifling record of my father’s presence in Cambridge occurs in the book kept in Christ’s College combination-room, where fines and bets were recorded, the earlier entries giving a curious impression of the after-dinner frame of mind of the fellows. The bets were not allowed to be made in money, but were, like the fines, paid in wine. The bet which my father made and lost is thus recorded:—</quote> <quote>“<hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 23, 1837.— Mr. Darwin <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Mr. Baines, that the combination-room measures from the ceiling to the floor more than (x) feet. 1 Bottle paid same day.</quote> <quote> “N.B. Mr. Darwin may measure at any part of the room he pleases.”</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Rhea darwinii</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">R. penata</hi>; see <hi rend="italic">Birds,</hi> p. 123, Plate 47).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘Notes upon the Rhea americana’, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 38–40.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>