<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8984">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. T. Moggridge   22 July 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">18046</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8984 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8984.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8984.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 219</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 219</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3353.xml">Moggridge, J. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
                <date when="1873-07-22">22 July 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>He will repeat the experiments in which CD found that formic acid vapour killed seeds [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">8866</hi>]. John Lindley describes effects of other acids on germination.</p>  
<p>He has tabulated the large amount of variation in English <hi rend="italic">Ophrys apifera</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Ophrys apifera</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">killing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>2 Montague Villas | Richmond | (Surrey)</placeName>
                    <date>22 July | 1873</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am greatly obliged to you for your valued letter of the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. in<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>., &amp; especially for the account you give in it of your suggestive experiments on seeds with Formic acid.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I have purchased a small bottle of this acid, &amp; hope to make a few experiments on my return to Mentone.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I gather from your letter that the <hi rend="underline">vapour</hi> of pure formic acid (not contact with the liquid) sufficed to kill the seeds outright, &amp; this without allowing them to sprout. If I understand right I might try to repeat this curious &amp; novel experience by placing seeds of a dozen sorts on damp sand under a tumbler, with a glass tube (say a homæopathic bottle), partly filled with acid, planted in the middle.—</p>
<p>Then I should propose to vary the quantity of formic acid, diluting measured amounts with water, &amp; noting the results—</p>
<p>This is a kind of experiment with which I am quite unacquainted, &amp; I do not feel at all sure that I shall get any reliable results, but I hope to amuse myself by trying—</p>
<p>I do hope, however, that you will be able yourself to carry on this enquiry, which is surely one of great practical importance; for, even though my small attempts should prove tolerably successful, my want of experience &amp; many other wants must make my results worthless by the side of yours.—</p>
<p>Lindley <hi rend="underline">Theory &amp; Practice of Horticulture</hi> Ed. 2 (1855) p. 136 et<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.) gives some account of experiments made with various acids (not formic acid) on seeds.— Soaking in Oxalic acid is stated to hasten germination! but the general results appear conflicting &amp; dubious.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I am glad that you were pleased with the <hi rend="underline">Ophrys</hi> drawings—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I must however tell you that variation is really not uncommon in the English <hi rend="underline">apifera</hi>, though it sometimes happens that one form, whether <hi rend="underline">aurita</hi> or <hi rend="underline">apifera</hi> proper, predominates.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I was myself much interested by the fact of the variation of the English plant, &amp; I have, since the writing of this paper, made a tabulated series of observations shewing the variation in different parts of the flower in large numbers of specimens obtained from several distant parts of England.</p>
<p>In most cases in England the possibility of intercrossing is excluded, &amp; it is surely important to observe that under these conditions many characters vary, &amp; often do so to a marked degree—</p>
<p>Since the writing of my paper the curious &amp; submonstrous variety <hi rend="underline">Trollii</hi>” has been found near Reigate!—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I should be very glad to furnish you with a condensed account of these observations if they could be of service to you— —</p>
<p>Believe me y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. very sincerely | J. Traherne Moggridge.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter from CD has not been found; see, however, the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8805.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. T. Moggridge, 10 March 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Mentone (now Menton) is a town in south-eastern France on the French Riviera near the the border with Italy; Moggridge spent most winters there owing to his chronic ill health (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1994</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For the discussion of seeds soaked in oxalic acid and other substances to promote germination, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4778.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lindley 1855</ref>, pp. 236–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Moggridge had sent CD copy of his German paper on <hi rend="italic">Ophrys insectifera</hi> (the fly orchid; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5518.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1869</ref>) with his letter of 12 July 1873.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Ophrys apifera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">O. apifera</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">aurita</hi> are bee orchids. CD discussed the adaptations of this species for self-fertilisation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 52–9. He noted that in Britain the forms were more differentiated than on the Continent, where cross-fertilisation might have taken place.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Moggridge refers to the wasp orchid (<hi rend="italic">Ophrys apifera</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">trollii</hi>). Reigate is in Surrey.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>