<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11204">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From T. F. Cheeseman   23 October 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19911</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11204 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11204.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11204.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 27 December 1877, pp. 163–4<ref target="#foot.f5"/> </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature 17 1877: 163</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_900.xml">Cheeseman, T. F.</persName>
                <placeName>Museum, Auckland</placeName>
                <date when="1877-10-23">23 Oct 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends his paper on <hi rend="italic">Selliera</hi> fertilisation [<hi rend="italic">Trans. &amp; Proc. N. Z. Inst.</hi> 9 (1876): 542–5]; contrasts it to CD’s description of <hi rend="italic">Leschenaultia</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 162–5].</p>  
<p>Describes the irritability of <hi rend="italic">Glossostigma elatinoides</hi> which he concludes is a mechanism to ensure cross-fertilisation.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Glossostigma elationoides</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Selliera</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Trans. &amp; Proc. N. Z. Inst.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Cheeseman, T. F. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">vibration, including sound</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Museum, Auckland,</placeName>
                    <date>October 23, 1877</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I forward to you a copy of a paper on the fertilisation of <hi rend="underline">Selliera</hi>, one of the <hi rend="underline">Goodeniaceæ</hi>, which perhaps you may care to glance over.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> When I wrote it I did not know of your notes on <hi rend="underline">Leschenaultia</hi>, published in the <hi rend="underline">Gardener’s Chronicle</hi> for 1871.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In both plants the pollen is shed before the expansion of the flower, and neatly collected in the indusium, but in <hi rend="underline">Selliera</hi> the stigma is situated within the indusium, and by its gradual upward growth after the flower expands slowly forces out the pollen, which is then transferred by insects to older flowers. When mature, the stigma protrudes considerably beyond the indusium. This appears to differ entirely from what takes place in <hi rend="underline">Leschenaultia</hi>.</p>
<p>I have recently been much interested with the curious irritability displayed by the stigma of <hi rend="underline">Glossostigma elatinoides</hi>, one of the Scrophularineæ.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The style is dilated towards its apex into a broad spoon-shaped stigma, which, when the flower expands, is closely doubled over the four stamens, entirely concealing them from view. If the front of the bent part of the style is touched it at once springs up, uncovering the stamens, and moves back to the upper lobe of the corolla, to which it becomes closely applied. In this position it remains for a few minutes, and then slowly moves back to the stamens and curves over them as at first. It appears to me that this irritability of the stigma is simply a contrivance to insure cross-fertilisation, for an insect crawling into the flower must inevitably touch the stigma, which would then uncover the stamens. On withdrawing, the insect would be certain to dust itself with pollen, but it would not by this effect the fertilisation of the flower, for the stigma would be then closely applied to the upper lobe of the corolla, entirely out of its way. If the insect were, however, to visit another flower it is evident that it must come into contact with the stigma at its first entrance and would doubtless leave some pollen thereon. The movement of the stigma is remarkably rapid, and its apex must pass through an angle of at least 180<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. I have been unable to find a record of a similar case, or of so pronounced a degree of irritability in the stigma of any plant. The movement of the lobes of the stigma in <hi rend="underline">Mimulus</hi> is much weaker, and is through a much less angle.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Yours faithfully | T. F. Cheeseman <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq., F.R.S.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
           
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Cheeseman’s paper ‘On the fertilization of <hi rend="italic">Selliera</hi>’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cheeseman 1876</ref>) has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL. <hi rend="italic">Selliera</hi> is a New Zealand and Australian swampweed belonging to the family <hi rend="italic">Goodeniaceae</hi>, which contains twelve genera.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s paper <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2497.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilisation of Leschenaultia’</ref> was published in <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 9 September 1871, p. 1166. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7927.xml">letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [31 August 1871]</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Leschenaultia</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Lechenaultia</hi>) is in the family <hi rend="italic">Goodeniaceae</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Glossostigma elatinoides</hi> is a New Zealand aquatic plant in the family <hi rend="italic">Scrophulariaceae</hi> (figworts).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The genus <hi rend="italic">Mimulus</hi> (monkey-flower), formerly in the family <hi rend="italic">Scrophulariaceae</hi>, is now in the family <hi rend="italic">Phrymaceae</hi> (lopseeds).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD sent Cheeseman’s letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> for publication. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin to T. F. Cheeseman, 12 December 1877</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>