<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1148">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Smith of Jordanhill<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   28 January [1848]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">829</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1148 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1148.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1148.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1848-01-28">28 Jan [1848]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4418.xml">Smith of Jordanhill, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD asks if he may have the use of the cirripedes JS collected in Portugal. He will need to break up or make a section of at least one of each species.</p> 
<p>Expresses admiration for JS’s paper on Malta ["On recent depressions in the land", <hi rend="italic">Q. J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</hi> 3 (1847): 234–40], with its striking demonstration of the change of level between land and water there discovered.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cirripedes</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Q. J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Malta</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Portugal</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Smith, James 1847a</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Jan 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope that you will excuse the liberty I take in asking you a great favour. I have been employed for the last year &amp; shall be for, I suppose, the next two years on a Monograph, anatomical &amp; systematic on the whole class of Cirripedia. In the last number of the Geolog. Journal I see that you found in Portugal at least six species of Balanus.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Will you entrust me with your specimens to describe,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> that is if I find I can make any hand at the fossil species of which I have already got some, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lyell, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stutchbury having placed their collections at my disposal. I shall, however, require to keep them sometime &amp; it is absolutely indispensable for me to break up or make section of at least one specimen of each. The characters, hitherto generally used from external aspect, I find, are usually quite valueless; &amp; the internal structure of shell must be in each case examined. In some genera, as far as I yet see, the included animal alone offers distinguishable characters; so that I have some fears about the fossil species, but I mean to try at them.</p>
<p>My friends have been most generous in placing collections at my disposal. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stutchbury has sent me the whole of his magnificent collection &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cuming has placed his at my disposal. Did you collect any recent species on the coast of Portugal &amp; especially at Madeira; if you have any from these quarters or elsewhere (especially if in Spirits) &amp; would entrust them to me, I should feel very grateful.—</p>
<p>I wish to see the species from as many quarters as possible on account of their Geographical Range. I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be much obliged for any information, on habits frequency &amp;c depths, abundance at bottom of sea in dead state &amp;c, which you would kindly take the trouble to supply me with.</p>
<p>Pray believe me, my dear Sir | Yours very faithfully | C. Darwin</p>
<p>I must express to you, how delighted I was with y〈ou〉r paper on Malta;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> if I was asked for the most striking fact ever discovered, exhibiting the changes of level between land &amp; water &amp; the power of denudation, I should certainly refer to your old roads leading under the sea &amp; over the brink of precipices:<ref target="#foot.f5"/> such facts seize the imagination with astonishment. It is my belief that if you were confined a prisoner in a Square in London, you would find some demonstrative proof of the level having changed!</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.1 have] ‘h’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.2 years] ‘y’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.7 &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stutchbury] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.7 their] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘his’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.9 or make section of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.9 of each.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.3 between] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘of’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The cover is addressed to ‘<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4418.xml">James Smith</ref> Esq. | Jordan Hill | Glasgow’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Smith’s paper, originally read on 30 June 1841, was not published in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of the Geological Society</hi> until 1847 (J. Smith 1847b). The six species of <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi> are mentioned on p. 412 but are not identified by Smith.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD used Smith’s collection from a Tertiary bed near Lisbon as one of several sources of specimens of fossil <hi rend="italic">Balanus concavus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fossil</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cirripedia</hi> (1854): 17). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>237–40, CD described how he had to use both living and fossil specimens to make out the species of this difficult genus (p. 277). Despite considerable variation in the characters of the shell, he made all of these into one species.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">J. Smith 1847a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The reference is to the evidence of very recent subsidence at Malta (J. Smith 1847a, p. 240): <quote> A great part of the surface of the island of Malta is composed of a soft stone (miocene tertiary); across it may be observed the tracks of wheels, about 4 feet apart and very deeply marked on the rocks, the depth being rarely less than 18 inches. They cross the island in every direction, but have no connexion with any of the existing lines of communication, neither is there any tradition concerning them. On the south side of Malta they terminate in the mural escarpments which skirt that part of the coast.</quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>