<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11152">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Samuel Butler to Francis Darwin   24 September 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19649</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11152 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11152.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11152.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 199.5: 100</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>199.5: 100</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Butler, Samuel (b)</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1877-09-24">24 Sept 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Offers to send MS of part of his new book [<hi rend="italic">Life and habit</hi>] which gently pokes fun at CD. His book will offer an alternative to Pangenesis.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Life and habit</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">habit</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>15—Clifford’s Inn | Fleet Street E.C.</placeName>
                    <date>Sep. 24. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">                     
<p>I am half ashamed to write to you— I have behaved so badly—after all the kindness I received from your father &amp; brother’s hands not to say your own— I assure you I feel a beast for not having endeavoured to draw you in some way long ago— but partly I have been in the wars some time—and—at any rate I have left undone things that I ought to have done &amp;c—&amp;c.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>However—I am bringing out a little book to appear before Xmas.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As mad mad mad as a book can be—utterly disclaiming the smallest pretence to scientific value, but at the same time trying if I can to <hi rend="underline">steal</hi> a little science more or less all over the book.</p>
<p>I have a passage in it in which I <hi rend="underline">laugh</hi> at a passage of your father’s very gently—&amp; I shd hope genially—still it is distinctly poking fun at the passages (there are two)— shall I or rather may I send you the M.S of this bit, and of the bit wh: leads up to it, and I will cut the whole thing out immediately if you think he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> mind— the passages are “No doubt in every case there must have been some exciting cause”. (Pl. &amp; An. and. dom<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. Vol II. p. 275 ed. 1875) and again six or seven pages later “No doubt each slight variation must have its efficient cause—”— I am pretending that it is to people’s unconscious perceptions &amp; utterances that we must turn for their deeper beliefs and having given one or two passages in which I imagine I have caught theologians napping I say “on the other hand it rather shocks me to find M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin writing “&amp;c &amp;c—” The repetition within so short a space of this expression of confidence in the impossibility of causeless effect w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> suggest that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin’s mind at the time of writing was unconsciously to himself in a state of more or less uneasiness as to whether effects might not sometimes come about of themselves without cause of any sort—that he may have been standing in fact for a short time upon the brink of a denial of the indestructibility of force &amp; matter”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Do you think your father will mind?</p>
<p>Also I have read the Pangenesis three times with great care and think I understand the drift of it— I want in my new book to summarise it and make it as clear and easy as I possibly can—&amp; I want so far as I can make sure of my own meaning to add to it because I feel the want of something to “boss” the whole embryological process to “run” the concern and settle what <hi rend="underline">is</hi> the “due order,” &amp; “next in succession” &amp;c. &amp;c. and also I <hi rend="underline">cannot</hi> stand the dormancy of the gemmula &amp; their transmission through many generations &amp; propose a simpler (as it seems to me) way—and one too which explains why the development of any animal should cease soon after puberty— which I do not remember to have seen in your father’s book—and otherwise to come in handy generally—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I shall be yet I shd think another three weeks before I go to press &amp; have not yet begun to put my notes on Pangenesis together— but if you wd like to see them when I have done them, or any part of what I have done already— by all means propose either a meeting I mean come &amp; see me when you are next in town—for I am very hard at work just now, or when they are ready I wd send you the part of the M.S. which I think wd interest you—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>With kind regards to your people | believe me y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. very truly | S. Butler—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            

        </div>
                   
                   
                   <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">Butler had first been invited to visit Down in 1872 following the publication of <hi rend="italic">Erewhon</hi> ([Butler] 1872a; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8361.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Samuel Butler, 30 May 1872</ref>) and had become friendly with Francis and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8305.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Samuel Butler to Francis Darwin, [before 30 May 1872]</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9157F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. H. Darwin to Emma Darwin, [before 24 November 1873]</ref>).  He had spent the summer in Switzerland for his health, and also had financial problems (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jones 1919</ref>, 1: 251). ‘We have left undone those things which we ought to have done’ is a quotation from the ‘General confession’ in the Anglican order of service (<hi rend="italic">Book of common prayer</hi> (1662)).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Life and habit</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>) was published in December 1877. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11254.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Samuel Butler to Francis Darwin, 25 November 1877</ref>.</note>
<note xml:id="foot.f3">The discussion is in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>, pp. 25–6. The quotations are from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref> 1: 275 and 282.</note>
<note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s ‘Provisional hypothesis of pangenesis’, a proposed mechanism for inheritance, was published as chapter 27 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>. CD suggested that throughout the life of an organism, its cells throw off minute particles or ‘gemmules’, capable of developing into new cells: the gemmules circulate in the body and can be passed on to offspring, either to combine with others and develop into new cells, or to lie dormant through several generations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 374–402).  Butler quoted CD extensively in <hi rend="italic">Life and habit</hi>, but argued that both physical attributes and instinctive behaviour were passed on as a form of inherited memory, and that organisms could therefore only inherit characteristics already developed by the normal age of breeding (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>, pp. 196–7). For a later summary of Butler’s ideas on heredity and puberty, see his essay ‘Deadlock in Darwinism’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10119.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Streatfield ed. 1908</ref>, pp. 234–340, especially pp. 335–6).</note>
<note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> lunched with Butler at Clifford’s Inn on 26 September 1877, and they exchanged further letters afterwards (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jones 1919</ref>, 1: 256–7).</note>
            </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>