<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10531">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. R. Wallace   5 June 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1791</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10531 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10531.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10531.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">7pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 274</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 12;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Marchant (1916) 1: 286</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Add MS 46434)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <idno>Add 46434</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Hopedene Down letterhead</placeName>
                <date when="1876-06-05">5 June 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Response to ARW’s "grand and memorable work" [<hi rend="italic">Geographical distribution</hi> (1876)]. Most interesting part to CD is ARW’s "protest against sinking imaginary continents".</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">continents</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Wallace, A. R. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi> [Hopedene, Surrey.]</placeName>
                    <date>June 5 76</date>
                    <salute>My dear Wallace</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I must have the pleasure of expressing to you my unbounded admiration of your book, tho’ I have read only to page 184,—my object having been to do as little as possible while resting.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I feel sure that you have laid a broad &amp; safe foundation for all future work on Distribution. How interesting it will be to see hereafter plants treated in strict relation to your views; &amp; then all insects, pulmonate molluscs, and fresh water fishes, in greater detail than I suppose you have given to these lower animals. The point which has interested me most, but I do not say the most valuable point, is your protest against sinking imaginary continents in a quite reckless manner, as was started by Forbes, followed alas by Hooker and caricatured by Wollaston &amp; Murray.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> By the way the main impression which the latter author has left on my mind is his utter want of all scientific judgement. I have lifted up my voice against the above view with no avail, but I have no doubt that you will succeed, owing to your new arguments and the coloured chart.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Of a special value, as it seems to me, is the conclusion that we must determine the areas, chiefly by the nature of the mammals.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>When I worked many years ago on this subject, I doubted much whether the now called Palæarctic &amp; Nearctic regions ought to be separated; &amp; I determined if I made another region that it should be Madagascar.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have therefore been able to appreciate the value of your evidence on these points.</p>
<p>What progress Palæontology has made during the last 20 years; but if it advances at the same rate in the future, our views on the migration &amp; birth place of the various groups will I fear be greatly altered   I cannot feel quite easy about the Glacial period &amp; the extinction of large Mammals, but I much hope that you are right.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I think you will have to modify your belief about the difficulty of dispersal of land molluscs; I was interrupted when beginning to experimentize on the just hatched young adhering to the feet of ground-roosting birds.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I differ on one other point, viz in the belief that there must have existed a Tertiary Antarctic continent, from which various forms radiated to the Southern extremities of our present continents.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> But I could go on scribbling for ever. You have written, as I believe, a grand &amp; memorable work which will last for years as the foundation for all future treatises on Geographical Distribution.</p>
<p>My dear Wallace | Yours very sincerely | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. | You have paid me the highest conceivable compliment, by what you say of your work in relation to my chapters on distribution in the Origin, and I heartily thank you for it.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">There is an annotated copy of Wallace’s <hi rend="italic">Geographical distribution of animals</hi> (Wallace 1876a) in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 837–40). The Darwins stayed at Hopedene, Holmbury St Mary, Surrey, from 24 May to 7 June 1875 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 36–7. Pulmonate molluscs were formerly considered to constitute a taxonomic class (Pulmonata) but the term is now used informally to refer to air-breathing snails and slugs. CD complained to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> about the submerged continents hypothesised by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1680.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Forbes</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Vernon Wollaston</ref> in his letters to Lyell of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1902.xml" resp="#automat">16 [June 1856]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1910.xml" resp="#automat">25 June [1856]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3459.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Murray</ref> had tentatively supported Forbes’s hypothesis that South America and West Africa had been joined or nearly so by a land bridge in an article on the Coleoptera of Old Calabar (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Murray 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Wallace 1876a included as the frontispiece to vol. 1 a fold-out map of the world showing Wallace’s zoo-geographical regions and the contours of the sea-bed.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 56–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The terms Palaearctic and Nearctic were coined by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4251.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Lutley Sclater</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sclater 1857</ref>), as two of his six zoological regions. Wallace maintained the separation of the Palaearctic (temperate Europe and Asia) from the Nearctic (temperate North America and Greenland; Wallace 1876a, 1: 71, 79–80). He made Madagascar and the adjacent islands a subdivision of the Ethiopian region, while admitting its claims to be a region in itself (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 74–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Wallace had speculated that large mammals such as elephants and mastodons had become extinct in Europe owing to the glacial period and the subsidence of land connecting Europe with Africa (Wallace 1876a, 1: 113–14).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 30–2. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5659.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 31 October [1867]</ref>. In his Experimental notebook (DAR 157a: 84), CD made a note dated November 1867 commenting that small snails and slugs crawled onto a goose’s foot that he put on the ground.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In Wallace 1876a, 1: 156, Wallace wrote: ‘To those who would create a continent to account for the migrations of a beetle, nothing would seem more probable than that a South Atlantic continent, then united parts of what are now Africa and South America.’ However, in <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 460, he rejected the existence of an Antarctic continent joining New Zealand, Australia, South Africa, and South America. See also Wallace’s reply of 7 June 1876.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In Wallace 1876a, 1: xv, Wallace wrote that he hoped his book would bear the same relation to chapters 11 and 12 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> as CD’s own <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> bore to chapter 1. The title of chapter 1 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> was ‘Variation under domestication’; the title of chapters 11 and 12, up until the fifth edition, was ‘Geographical distribution’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>