<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6584">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From David Forbes   30 January 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14234</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6584 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6584.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6584.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp encl</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 164: 143–143/2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>164: 143–143/2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1678.xml">Forbes, David</persName>
                <placeName>London, York Place, 11</placeName>
                <date when="1869-01-30">30 Jan 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>DF’s opinion of Gustav Jenzsch’s book [<hi rend="italic">Mikroskopische Flora und Fauna</hi> (1868)]. Encloses extract of a letter from Ferdinand Zirkel also mentioning Jenzsch’s work.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Mikroskopische Flora und Fauna</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Jenzsch, G. J. S. 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">11, York Place, | Portman Square, | London. W.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>30 Jany. 1869.</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you for Jenzsch’s book which I had previously read (after a trial of patience) and put down as consummate rubbish.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Ideal wanderings of the brain and as I today have received a letter from Professor Zirkel of Kiel the most eminent of the Continental petrologists and observers (of the microscope in reference to rocks)—&amp; in which he also mentions Jenzschs book I enclose you herewith a copy of his remarks in the original—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It certainly would be a rather severe reflection on the microscopic powers of Sorby<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Zirkel and myself who have so many years worked on the subject if such a Flora and Fauna could exist—rocks which we have examined—and I know that Zirkel has carefully examined the Metaphysics alluded to by Jensch<ref target="#foot.f4"/>—who undoubtedly is <hi rend="underline">mad</hi> or something like it—</p>
<p>I am always thinking about writing a monograph on the Aymara Indian race of Bolivia, for the Ethnological but since Xmas I have been quite out of sorts with a very severe attack of Bronchitis which has also affected my head and made me very confused—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Might I ask you when you purpose to bring out your book on man?—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I really must endeavour to find some leisure for getting up some data for you—but I have been so thoroughly overwhelmed with work that I have not had an instants rest to sit down and collect my notes or thoughts on the subject.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Wishing you a very happy new year and many of them believe me | My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin | Yours most sincerely | David Forbes</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f8"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Extract from a letter from Professor Zirkel of Kiel to DF. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>Was sagt man denn in England zu der neuen Entdeckung von Jenzsch: eine mikroscopische fossile Flora und Fauna in den gemengtheilen von Eruptivgesteinen? Alle, mit denen ich mündlich oder brieflich darüber verhandelt habe, halten die Sache für Humbug— Das ist, bis ich eines bessern belehrt werde auch meine Ansicht. Ein neues heiteres Landschaftsbild: gegend Quarz im Melaphyr<ref target="#foot.f9"/> im Vorgrunde ein idyllisch weidendes ‘Infusorium’, welches mit ausgestrecktem Rüssel gemüthlich grüne Algenzellschichten benagt, daneben ein Räderthierchen in geburtswehen begriffen, in Hintergrund einige Fluidcavities mit beweglichen Bläschen. Ein Bild, würdig der Pinsels von Sir Edwin Landseer!<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Da <hi rend="underline">uns</hi> eine solche Entdeckung entschlüpfen muste! Ich habe an Jenzsch geschrieben und ihn gebeten, mir für einen Tag einige Praeparate zu schicken und mir einige Melaphyr scherben zu schenken, damit ich mich selbst Praeparate machen könne; ich erhielt zur Antwort, er brauche seine Praeparate <hi rend="underline">selbst</hi> und seine Melaphyrhandstücke seien so fest verpackt, das er selbst nicht mehr dazu kommen könne. “Sapienti sat.”<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Wenn Sie diese famose Schrift die natürlich allen Ultrametamorphiken und Dilettanten fabelhaft imponieren etwa noch nicht haben, so kann ich Sie Ihnen sc〈hic〉ken, ich besitze sie dreimal.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Forbes refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2562.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Jenzsch</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jenzsch 1868</ref>, a copy of which CD evidently sent to Forbes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Forbes refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5300.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferdinand Zirkel</ref>. See enclosure.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4469.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Clifton Sorby</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Forbes may refer to Jenzsch’s explanation of how volcanic rock was capable of supporting the microscopic flora and fauna he claimed to have discovered (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jenzsch 1868</ref>, pp. 17–21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Forbes’s paper ‘On the Aymara Indians of Bolivia and Peru’ was published in 1870 in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Ethnological Society of London</hi> (D. Forbes 1870).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Forbes refers to <hi rend="italic">Descent.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">For more on Forbes’s work on the Aymara, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6054.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from David Forbes, 26 March 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">For a translation of the enclosure, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Melaphyre: ‘any of various dark-coloured porphyritic (esp. basaltic) rocks. Later: (specifically) an altered basalt, esp. of Carboniferous or Permian age’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6109.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Henry Landseer</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Sapienti sat.</hi>: abbreviation of ‘<hi rend="italic">Verbum sapienti satis est</hi>’, a word to the wise is sufficient. (Latin.)</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>