<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7029">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   18 December 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7855</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7029 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7029.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7029.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp inc ††, CD note</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 109: B125–6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>109: B124–B126</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1869-12-18">18 Dec 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses dimorphic and trimorphic plants; mentions especially Rubiaceae and a dimorphic monocotyledon.</p> 
<p>Notes observations on the monstrous male flowers of <hi rend="italic">Begonia</hi>,</p> 
            <p>and on self-sterile plants.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Begonia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">monocotyledon</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Rubiaceae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Itajahy, S<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                    <date>Decbr. 18. 1869</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you for having kindly favoured me with a copy of your “Notes on the fertilization of Orchids” which contain a large number of interesting facts quite new to me.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>A few days ago I returned from an excursion, on which I made a rich harvest of dimorphic and trimorphic plants. There were about half a dozen dimorphic Rubiaceæ, and among them the beautiful <hi rend="underline">Rudgea eriantha.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f2"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[RUDGEA SPECIMEN]</p> </figure> 
<p>But the most interesting plant was a <hi rend="underline">Pontederia</hi>, which I had long ago suspected to be trimorphic and which now indeed I found to be so.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">equivalent of 5 or 6 lines excised</hi>〉</p>
<p rend="left">This is, I think, the first case of trimorphism or dimorphism among monocotyledons and in irregular flowers. The three longer stamens do not alternate with the shorter ones, nor belong to the same whorl; one of the longer stamens is inserted to the anterior sepal, two to the lateral petals; one of the shorter ones to the posterior petal, which is marked with a yellow spot, and two to the lateral sepals. (In the allied monomorphic genus <hi rend="underline">Heteranthera</hi>, at least in <hi rend="underline">H. reniformis</hi>, the three shorter stamens of Pontederia are wanting.)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I was much surprised, that among hundreds of plants I could not find a single mid-styled one, and I have have hardly any doubt, that this form does not exist in the <hi rend="underline">Itajahy-mirim</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> where this species grows abundantly.— The long-styled and short-styled plants could be distinguished even from a distance, the flowers of the former being paler, than those of the latter; in the dried flowers this difference has disappeared.— In a former letter I have sent you a mid-styled flower of a second species of <hi rend="underline">Pontederia</hi>, which has been introduced here some years ago from Rio de Janeiro.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>As to dimorphic Rubiaceæ, Professor Hildebrand told me, that Bernouilli (in Guatemala) had observed <hi rend="underline">Coffea arabica</hi> to be dimorphic, producing hermaphrodite and small female flowers; but this is an error.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The small flowers are rudimentary and sterile ones which occasionally appear among the normal flowers. I have lately seen these aborted flowers in unusual number on coffee-trees, which had been damaged by hail some weeks before.</p>
<p>Of the <hi rend="underline">Begonia</hi> with monstrous male flowers I have raised four lots of seedlings and it is curious, in how odd a manner the monstrosity has been transmitted.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The female flowers, from which the seeds were obtained, had all been fertilized with pollen of monstrous male flowers.</p>
<p>〈    〉 seeds of a normal female flower. 〈    〉 〈o〉f which have normal and 2 monstrous 〈    〉 of 〈    〉 male 〈    〉</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> lot</hi>. Seeds of a female flower, which had 6 petals instead of 5.— 20 plants; 17 have flowered, all having normal male flowers.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> lot.</hi> Seeds of two female flowers of a second plant, which also had 6 petals.—22 plants, of which 7 are flowering, only one of them producing monstrous male flowers.— Some of the 9 plants of the second lot, which had monstrous male flowers, showed this monstrosity only for a short time; the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> male flowers were monstrous, but afterwards they produced and are now producing normal male flowers. <hi rend="underline">Gærtner</hi> has already observed, that the first flowers (“Erstlingsblumen”) are often distinguished from the later ones by a greater number of stamens or pistils, by greater fertility etc. and I have myself lately observed some curious instances of this.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> In a plant of <hi rend="underline">Eschscholtzia</hi> the first six or eight flowers had from 5 to 7 petals; afterwards not a single flower with more than 4 petals has appeared on this plant.</p>
<p>On a plant of <hi rend="underline">Siphocampylus</hi> the first flowers of several branches had six petals instead of 5; the first of all flowers which this plant produced, had even 7 petals. A few sixpetaled flowers have also appeared among the other flowers of this plant; but these 6 petaled flowers are at least 100 times more numerous among the first flowers of the branches, than among the rest.—</p>
<p>On an umbel of <hi rend="underline">Agapanthus</hi> the first flower had 5 segments instead of six.— On a <hi rend="underline">Jussieua</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> which is extremely common on the banks of the Itajahy, and the flowers of which have normally 4 petals, the first flowers of the branches have not unfrequently 5 petals, and in this case there are generally also 5 sepals, 10 stamens and a 5 locular germen; but in one single flower there were 6 sepals, 5 petals, 10 stamens and a 4 locular germen.—</p>
<p>—To the list of self-impotent plants I may now add <hi rend="underline">Tabernæmontana</hi> <hi rend="underline">echinata</hi>, on which I lately tried some experiments. A <hi rend="underline">Calonyction</hi> with very large white flowers appears to be self-impotent also;<ref target="#foot.f11"/> at least a plant in my garden is quite sterile with its own pollen; but I have no second plant and am therefore unable to say, whether it would be fertile with pollen of a distinct plant.—</p>
<p>A very strange case of graft-hybrids is recorded in one of the last numbers of the “Auxiliador da Industria nacional” (April 1869 pg 158). A “fazendeiro” of the province of Rio de Janeiro, Señr J. F. Silveira da Motta, says that he has obtained a green and red striped variety of sugar-cane by planting close together plants of the green and of the red sugar-cane; as well as yellow and red striped sugar-cane by planting in the same hole cuttings of yellow and of red sugar-cane.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I confess that I have some doubts, whether these statements may be trusted; but I hope that I shall soon be able to repeat the experiments of Señr Silveira da Motta.</p>
<p>Permit me to repeat my thanks for all your kindness and believe me, dear Sir, with profound respect</p>
<p>very truly yours | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.2 There were … <hi rend="italic">eriantha</hi>. 2.3] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>10.6 <hi rend="italic">Gærtner</hi> … this. 10.8] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>10.8 In a … germen.— 12.6] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>14.1 A very … sugar-cane. 14.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Law of Variation Keep’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘J Jenner Weirs case’<ref target="#foot.f13"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘In a second letter he mentions case of a Cassia,— in which the first flowers on several racemes produced 2 carpels.— Hooker, mentions genus in which 2–5 carpels are normally produced.—’<ref target="#foot.f14"/> <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Müller refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 8 September [1869]</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">A specimen of <hi rend="italic">Rudgea eriantha</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">R. coriacea</hi>), long-styled, is stuck to the letter at this point.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Specimens of <hi rend="italic">Pontederia</hi> species were evidently attached to an excised portion of the letter beneath the <hi rend="italic">Rudgea</hi> specimen. There is an empty envelope in DAR 109: B124 on which CD had written, ‘Pontederia from F. Müller introduced from Rio Janeiro &amp; new seeds. suppose trimorphic   Measure Pollen—’. On Müller’s earlier observations of <hi rend="italic">Pontederia</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6085.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 3 April [1868]</ref> and n. 5. Müller published a description of three forms of <hi rend="italic">Pontederia</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5678.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1871</ref>. CD described heterostyly in <hi rend="italic">Pontederia</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Eichhornia</hi>, the water hyacinth), including Müller’s specimens, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 183–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Heteranthera</hi> (mudplantains) and <hi rend="italic">Pontederia</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Eichhornia</hi>) are genera in family Pontederiaceae. <hi rend="italic">Heteranthera reniformis</hi> is the kidneyleaf mudplantain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The reference is to a tributary of the Itajahy river (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">West 2003</ref>, map, p. 70); the main river is now called Itajaí Açu.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Müller may have sent a specimen of <hi rend="italic">Pontederia aquatica</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Eichhornia azurea</hi>) with a now incomplete letter in which he evidently discussed the plant; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence </hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5264.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, [2 November 1866]</ref> and n. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The references are to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Hildebrand</ref> and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6554.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Gustav Bernoulli</ref>, a German coffee planter in Guatemala. Müller and CD had been discussing dimorphic flowers in the family Rubiaceae since 1866; see especially <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 31 October 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6943.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 18 October 1869</ref> and n. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For examples of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Friedrich von Gärtner’s</ref> observations of differences in early flowers, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gärtner 1844</ref>, pp. 68, 100, and 220. There is a heavily annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gärtner 1844</ref> in the Darwin Library–CUL (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 248–98).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Jussieua</hi> was a common misspelling of <hi rend="italic">Jussiaea</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Ludwigia.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Müller and CD had been exchanging information on self-sterile plants since 1866 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 14–16). CD included Müller’s reference to <hi rend="italic">Tabernaemontana echinata</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Calonyction</hi> in his notes (DAR 76: 154b), and referred to the self-sterility of the former as observed by Müller in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 331. The name <hi rend="italic">Tabernaemontana echinata</hi> has since been rejected (see <hi rend="italic">Taxon</hi> 50 (2001): 1180); Müller probably referred to what is now called <hi rend="italic">T. siphilitica.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Calonyction</hi> is a synonym for <hi rend="italic">Ipomoea.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The article by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6390.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ignácio Francisco Silveira da Mota</ref> was published in the Brazilian journal <hi rend="italic">O Auxiliador da Industria Nacional.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Fazendeiro</hi>: plantation-owner, rancher (Portuguese). For CD’s interest in graft-hybrids, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 390–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7184.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 12 May 1870</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Jenner Weir</ref> reported to CD the case of a horse born to a mare that had previously had a foal by a quagga; the horse had quagga-like characteristics (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7137.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter from J. J. Weir, 17 March 1870)</ref>. In his reply to Weir, CD quoted a similar case reported to him by Müller in a letter that has not been found (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7138.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. J. Weir, 17 March [1870]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Müller mentioned <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi> in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 29 March 1870</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18). CD also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>