<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6939">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Brodie Innes    15 October 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8794</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6939 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6939.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6939.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Stecher (1961): 230</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 167: 25</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>167: 25</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2502.xml">Innes, J. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Milton Brodie</placeName>
                <date when="1869-10-15">15 Oct 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>R. H. Hutton has given a paper about CD at Liverpool Church Congress.</p>
            <p>JBI has seen four milk-white partridges among brown ones this year.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">partridges, milk-white</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2471">Hutton, R. H.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Liverpool</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Church Congress</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Milton Brodie | Forres | N.B.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1869.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It seems sad to lose sight of old friends, and this perhaps is one chief reason for my taking up my pen to write a line to you today. We are often reminded of you by our admiration of the most beautiful photograph you were so kind as to give me, which hangs in a post of honour in the drawing room looking at another good friend, now gone to his rest, Archbishop Longley, the photograph being however far behind that of yourself—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> And I have just been reading a paper about you which has given me much pleasure by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hutton, at the Liverpool Church Congress.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I hope you have seen it.</p>
<p>I wonder how you are getting on in Church matters at Downe   I do not hear much from Powell   Perhaps he thinks I have not helped him as I should in the matter of the proposed parsonage. When Sir John asked me about it I could do no less or more than simply say how the case actually stood.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I conclude you saw my letter. It would be a great advantage to restore and re-seat the Church, and for this I should gladly contribute, and probably had the parsonage question been disposed of as I hoped this would soon have been undertaken—</p>
<p>We jog on in a quiet hum drum sort of existence here. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Innes’ violent headaches being I hope rather less frequent of late, but distressing when they come. Johnny is off again to Cambridge after a short holiday.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He spent the early part of the vacation in College and had less out door amusement here than he should, having been laid up with bronchitis caught at the opening of the Inverness Cathedral on a wet day.</p>
<p>I think I told you I had one milk white partidge last year.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> This year I have seen four among brown ones. If they should escape guns and other enemies it is possible a race may be established. I avoid injuring them myself. I wish I had something of interest to tell you. With our kindest regards to your party</p>
<p>Believe me Dear Darwin | Faithfully yours | J Brodie Innes</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Innes refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Thomas Longley</ref>, who was archbishop of Canterbury from 1862 until his death in 1868. The photograph of CD has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2471.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Holt Hutton</ref> delivered a paper on 6 October 1869 to the Church Congress held at Liverpool in which he discussed Darwinism, scepticism, and faith (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3980.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hutton 1869</ref>). In it he argued that CD’s theory not only did not increase any moral difficulty in the apparently cruel competition of nature, but in fact made clearer the intellectual purpose at work in creation (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3980.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hutton 1869</ref>, pp. 102–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Powell</ref>, the curate of Down, had asked <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref> to subscribe to build him a house (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Lubbock, 20 July [1869]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Innes refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2501.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eliza Mary Brodie Innes</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2504.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John William Brodie Innes</ref>, who was a student at Cambridge (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_144.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Alum. Cantab.</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">No letter has been found in which Innes told CD about a white partridge.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>