<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6040">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   23 March 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5284</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6040 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6040.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6040.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 47</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 47</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1868-03-23">23 Mar 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has received English edition of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>. First volume of German edition came three months ago. Comments on book.</p>  
<p>Will send copy of recent lectures on human evolution [<hi rend="italic">Entstehung des Menschengeschlechts</hi> (1868)]. Gegenbaur much interested in the subject.</p>  
<p>Considers <hi rend="italic">Selachius</hi> the ancestral form of the fish and hence of all higher vertebrates. Believes their swim-bladder became lung of amphibians.</p> 
            <p>Mentions cases of hybrid crosses between rabbits and hares producing fertile offspring.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">amphibians</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fish</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">hares</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Selachius</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">vertebrates, higher</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Entstehung des Menschengeschlechts</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1834">Gegenbaur, Carl</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>23 März 68.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Soeben erhalte ich von meiner hiesigen Buchhandlung (durch Williams &amp; Norgate) übersandt die englische Ausgabe Ihres Werkes “Variation under Domestication”, welche Sie die Güte hatten, für mich zu bestimmen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Den ersten Band der deutschen Ausgabe erhielt ich schon vor 3 Monaten. Denselben erhielt auch Prof. Gegenbaur von Prof. Carus geschenkt, so dass es nicht nöthig ist, ihm mein Exemplar zu geben, wie Sie in Ihrem letzten Briefe wünschten für den Fall, dass ich beide Ausgaben erhielte.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Wenn Sie nun wünschen, dass ich die eine von beiden Ausgaben an Jemand Anderen senden soll, bitte ich mir dies zu schreiben. Im anderen Fall behalte ich sehr gern <hi rend="underline">beide</hi> Editionen für mich, weil immer viele Studenten zu mir kommen, um Ihre Werke von mir zu leihen. Auch von Ihrem ersten Werke habe ich fast immer ein Exemplar verliehen, so dass ich sehr zufrieden bin, mehrere davon zu besitzen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Den ersten Band Ihres Werkes “Variation under Domestication” habe ich jetzt mit grossem Interesse gelesen und darin eine Fülle von trefflichen Belegen für die Vererbungs- und Anpassungs-Gesetze gefunden. Ich bewundere immer aufs Neue Ihre reichen Kentnisse, und die Geduld und Sorgfalt, mit welcher Sie seit so langer Zeit so viele Einzelheiten studirt und gesammelt haben.</p>
<p>Sehr begierig bin ich auf Ihr Buch über die Abstammung der <hi rend="underline">Menschen</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Ich glaube ebenfalls, dass die “<hi rend="underline">Sexual Selection</hi>” dabei eine sehr wichtige Rolle spielt, und habe das auch im II Bd der gen. Morphol. angedeutet (p. 247).<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Im letzten Jahre habe ich hier 2 populäre Vorträge über “Ursprung und Stammbaum des Menschengeschlechts gehalten, welche ich Ihnen nächstens zusenden werde, sobald sie gedruckt sind.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Mein Freund Gegenbaur interessirt sich für diese Frage jetzt sehr von ihrer <hi rend="underline">osteologischen</hi> und myologischen Seite.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Da giebt es noch sehr viel zu thun.</p>
<p>Was die neulich Ihnen übersandte Abhandlung über die rudimentäre <hi rend="underline">Schwimmblase</hi> der Selachier betrifft, so halte ich sie desshalb für sehr wichtig, weil ich mit Gegenbaur glaube, dass die <hi rend="underline">Selachier die gemeinsamen Stammformen der übrigen Fische einerseits</hi>, <hi rend="underline">der Amphibien</hi> und dadurch der höheren Wirbelthiere <hi rend="underline">andererseits</hi> sind.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width50">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6040.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
<p rend="left">Wenn dies richtig ist, <hi rend="underline">mussten nothwendig</hi> die Selachier bereits eine Schwimmblase besitzen, welche bei den Ganoiden und Teleostiern Schwimmblase blieb, bei den Amphibien aber Lunge wurde. Da nun bisher bei keinem Selachier eine Schwimmblase bekannt war, scheint mir jenes Rudiment sehr wichtig.</p>
<p>Vielleicht interessirt es Sie zu hören, dass einer meiner Freunde, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Conrad, Bastarde von Hasen und Caninchen (Lepus timido=cuniculus) züchtet, und jetzt schon die <hi rend="underline">dritte</hi> Generation aus <hi rend="underline">seiner Inzucht</hi> hat, ohne Kreuzung mit den Stammeltern.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Ich arbeite jetzt an der Herausgabe meiner öffentlichen Vorlesungen dieses Winters.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Ausserdem befinde ich mich in meiner stillen Häuslichkeit, im freundlichen “Universitäts-<hi rend="underline">Dorfe</hi>” Jena, sehr glücklich, und wünschte, Ich könnte Ihnen dieselbe vortreffliche Gesundheit hinüberschicken, deren ich mich erfreue. Gegenbaur empfiehlt sich Ihnen bestens. Für Ihr Buch nochmals <hi rend="underline">herzlichsten Dank</hi>.</p>
<p>Mit der Bitte meine ergebensten Empfehlungen an Ihre Frau Gemahlin und Fräulein Tochter<ref target="#foot.f12"/> zu bestellen, | in unveränderlicher Treue | Ihr von Herzen ergebener | Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.7 Wenn … schreiben. 1.8] ‘Keep both copies.—’ <hi rend="italic">added in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.3 Im … gehalten, 3.5] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 Was … wichtig. 4.8] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Vielleicht … Stammeltern. 5.3] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi> ‘Hybrids’ <hi rend="italic">added above pencil</hi></note>
                <note>7.2 Ihr … Haeckel 7.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter:</hi> ‘Keep about Hybrid Hares’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>23 March 68.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Just now I have received from my bookshop here (through Williams and Norgate) the English edition of your work “Variation under Domestication”, which you kindly designated for me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I already received the first volume of the German edition three months ago. Prof. Gegenbaur also received a copy from Prof. Carus, and so it will not be necessary for me to give him my copy as you suggested in your last letter in case I received both editions.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> If you should now wish that I send one of them to someone else, please let me know. Otherwise I should be very happy to keep <hi rend="underline">both</hi> myself, because there are many students who come to borrow your works from me. I also almost always have a copy of your first work lent out, so that I am very happy to possess several.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I have now read the first volume of your work “Variation under Domestication” with great interest and found an abundance of excellent evidence in favour of the laws of inheritance and adaptation. I always admire afresh your rich knowledge, and the patience and care with which you have for so long studied and collected so many details.</p>
<p>I am very keenly awaiting your book on the descent of <hi rend="underline">man</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I, too, believe that “<hi rend="underline">Sexual Selection</hi>” plays a very important role in it, and I have also pointed this out in the second volume of the gen. Morphol. (p. 247).<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Last year I gave two popular lectures here on “Origin and genealogy of mankind, which I will send you before long, as soon as they are printed.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> My friend Gegenbaur is interested in this question now, very much from its <hi rend="underline">osteological</hi> and myological side.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> There is still very much to be done here.</p>
<p>As concerns the treatise on the rudimentary <hi rend="underline">swim bladder</hi> of selachians that I sent you recently, I consider it of great importance because I believe with Gegenbaur that <hi rend="underline">selachians are the common ancestral form of other fish, on the one hand</hi>, and of <hi rend="underline">amphibians</hi> and thus also of higher vertebrates <hi rend="underline">on the other hand</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width50">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_6040.jpg"/>
                    </figure>  
<p rend="left">If this is correct, the selachians <hi rend="underline">must of necessity</hi> already have a swim bladder which in ganoids and teleosteans remained a swim bladder, but in amphibians developed into lungs. Since until now none of the selachians has been known to have a swim bladder, that rudiment to me appears to be of great importance.</p>
<p>Perhaps it would interest you to know that one of my friends, Dr. Conrad, is breeding hybrids of hares and rabbits (Lepus timido=cuniculus), and that now he has already the <hi rend="underline">third</hi> generation purely <hi rend="underline">from inbreeding</hi>, without cross-breeding with the original parents.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I am currently working on an edition of my public lectures for this coming winter.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Also I am very happy in my quiet domesticity in the pleasant “university-<hi rend="underline">village</hi>” of Jena, and I wish I could send on to you the same excellent health that I myself enjoy. Gegenbaur sends his kindest regards. Again my <hi rend="underline">most cordial thanks</hi> for your book.</p>
<p>Please give my most humble regards to your wife and daughter<ref target="#foot.f12"/> | in steadfast loyalty | your wholeheartedly devoted | Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see part I: 297–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haeckel’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for the English edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (Appendix IV). Haeckel’s bookseller was probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7215.xml">Wilhelm Engelmann</ref>, a publisher of scientific books (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">NDB</hi></ref>; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4973.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 11 January 1866</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5147.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Williams &amp; Norgate</ref>, booksellers and publishers of Covent Garden, London, and of Edinburgh, specialised in foreign and scientific literature (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Modern English biography</hi></ref> s.v. Williams, Edmund Sidney).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Victor Carus</ref> was the translator of the German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (Carus trans. 1868). CD suggested that Haeckel pass on the German edition to Carl Gegenbaur in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5841.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Haeckel of 6 February [1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>; Haeckel received a presentation copy of the fourth edition, published in 1866 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5841.xml">letter of 6 February [1868]</ref>, CD told Haeckel that he had begun a small book on the descent of humans and sexual selection.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel refers to <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>), in which he noted morphological differences in the sexes. The passage is scored and annotated in CD’s copy in the DAR Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 357).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD’s heavily annotated copy of the published lectures (Haeckel 1868a) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Gegenbaur had already published two volumes of his <hi rend="italic">Untersuchungen zur vergleichenden Anatomie der Wirbelthiere</hi> (Researches on the comparative anatomy of vertebrates; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2764.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gegenbaur 1864–72</ref>); these dealt with bones of the foot and pectoral bones, respectively. He was working on a third volume, which would focus on cranial bones. CD had cited the first volume in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 13 n. (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, [after 10] August – 8 October [1864]</ref> and n. 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The reference is to a paper by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6337.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nikolai Nikolaievich Miklucho-Maclay</ref> on the identification of a rudimentary swim-bladder in sharks (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5423.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Miklucho-Maclay 1867</ref>). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 6 February [1868]</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> pp. 190–1, CD discussed the supposed development of lungs in higher vertebrates from the swim-bladder of fishes. For more on the relation of the swim-bladder to lungs, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2971.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">S. J. Gould 1993</ref>, pp. 111–19, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pauly 2004</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Haeckel mentioned <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5433.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johannes Ernst Conrad’s</ref> results in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3265.xml">Haeckel 1868b</ref>, p. 222. <hi rend="italic">Lepus timidus</hi> is the mountain hare while <hi rend="italic">L. cuniculus</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Oryctolagus cuniculus</hi>) is the European rabbit.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Haeckel refers to <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3265.xml">Haeckel 1868b</ref>). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>