<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-248">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Catherine Darwin   20–9 July 1834</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5058</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-248 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-248.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-248.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 154: 59</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi>: 100</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 391</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 223</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>223: 22</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>A hundred miles south of Valparaiso</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1834-07-20" notAfter="1834-07-29">20–9 July 1834</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1212.xml">Darwin, E. C.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>In the past six months he has done much geology and natural history. His geological pursuits are a source of high pleasure. Has lately determined to work chiefly on corals.</p>
            <p>Spent three weeks going up the Santa Cruz with a party; they ran out of provisions 20 miles from the Cordilleras. Winter at present prevents his doing much natural history.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">corals</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Santa Cruz</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seasons</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>a hundred miles South of Valparaiso.</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday.— July 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.— 1834—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Catherine.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Being at sea &amp; the weather fine, I will begin a letter, which shall be finished when we arrive in Port.— I have received the whole series of letters up to yours of November, 1833.— I wrote last from the Falkland Is<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi>. (where the Conway left for us a letter Bag); in this I mention receiving a Box; which must have come from Henslow; The next Man of War that comes round the Horn will bring the one from you.— We left the Island of Chiloe a week since; for which place a succession of gales compelled us to bear up.— We staid there some days in order to refresh the men.— Pigs &amp; potatoes are as plentiful as in Ireland. With the exception of this weighty advantage, Chiloe, from its climate is a miserable hole.— I forget whether you were at home, when my friend M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Proctor<ref target="#foot.f1"/> was there, &amp; told us about the place, where his Uncle says it never ceases to rain; I am sure he must have meant Chiloe.—</p>
<p>Altogether the last six months since leaving the Plata, has been a most prosperous cruize.— Much as I detest the Southern Latitudes, I have been enabled, during this period to do so much in Geology &amp; Natural History, that I look back to Tierra del Fuego with grateful &amp; almost kindly feelings. You ask me about the specimens which I send to Cambridge I collect every living creature, which I have time to catch &amp; preserve; also some plants.— Amongst Animals, on principle I have lately determined to work chiefly amongst the Zoophites or Coralls: it is an enormous branch of the organized world; very little known or arranged &amp; abounding with most curious, yet simple, forms of structures.—</p>
<p>But to go on with our history; when I wrote from the Falklands we were on the point of sailing for the S. Cruz on the coast of Patagonia.— We there looked at y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Beagle’s bottom, her false keel was found knocked off, but otherwise not damaged.— When this was done, the Captain &amp; 25 hands in three boats pro-ceeded to follow up the course of the river of S. Cruz.— The expedition lasted three weeks; from want of provisions we failed reaching as far as was expected, but we were within 20 miles of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> great snowy range of the Cordilleras: a view which has never before been seen by Europæan eyes.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The river is a fine large body of water, it traverses wild desolate plains inhabited by scarcely anything but the Guanaco.— We saw in one place smoke &amp; tracks of the horses of a party of Indians: I am sorry we did not see them, they would have been out &amp; out wild Gentlemen. In June, in the depth of winter we beat through the Straits of Magellan; the great chain of mountains, in which Sarmiento stands presented a sublime spectacle of enormous piles of snow.— Scenery however, is not sufficient to make a man relish such a climate. We passed out by the Magdalen channel, an unfrequented &amp; little known exit; on our passage up, before we were driven into Chiloe, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rowlett, the purser, died; Having gradually sunk under a complication of diseases.—</p>
<p>So much for the past; our future plans are as yet very uncertain: After Valparaiso, we shall go to Coquimbo to refit.— Here the climate is fine, but every thing else bad; the desert of Peru may be said to extend so far South; where man-kind is only enticed to live by the richer metals.— Next summer there is a good deal of work to be done behind &amp; around Chiloe; how far I shall accompany the vessels I do not yet know.—</p>
<p>Amongst all the things you &amp; Susan have told me in the last letters; you do not ever mention Erasmus; I hope the good lazy old Gentleman is alive; tell him, I should like very much to have one more letter from him; perhaps the box will bring one: if he would write to me four letters during the whole voyage, I would not grumble at all.— As for all of you, you are the best correspondents a brother, 3000 miles off, ever had.— I wish you could inspire Erasmus with a little of the superabundance of your virtues.— I am afraid he thinks your stock is sufficient for the whole family.— I am much pleased to hear my Father likes my Journal: as is easy to be seen I have taken too little pains with it.— My geological notes &amp; descriptions of animals I treat with far more attention: from knowing so little of Natural History, when I left England, I am constantly in doubt whether these will have any value.— I have however found the geology of these countries so different from what I read about Europe, &amp; in consequence when compared with it so instructive to myself; that I cannot help hoping that even imperfect descriptions may be of some general utility.—</p>
<p>Of one thing, I am sure; that such pursuits, are sources of the very highest pleasures I am capable of enjoying.— Tell my Father also, how much obliged I am for the affectionate way he speaks about my having a servant. It has made a great difference in my comfort; there is a standing order, in the Ship, that no one, excepting in civilized ports, leaves the vessel by himself By thus having a constant companion, I am rendered much more independent, in that most dependent of all lives, a life on board.— My servant is an odd sort of person; I do not very much like him; but he is, perhaps from his very oddity, very well adapted to all my purposes.</p>
<p>July 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>., Valparaiso.— I have again to thank you all, for being such good sisters, as you are.— I have just received 3 letters, one from each of you, in due order the last being from Susan, Feb 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.— Also the box of books, with sundry notes &amp; letters.— I am much obliged for your chain, I wear Caroline’s pencil case, suspended by it round my neck.— Thank Granny for her purse &amp; tell her I plead guilty to some of her <hi rend="italic">[two words obliterated]</hi>, but the others are certainly only accidental errors— Moreover I am much obliged for Carolines criticisms (see how good I am becoming!) they are perfectly just, I even felt aware of the faults she points out, when writing my journal.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The little political books are very popular on board; I have not had time yet to read any of them.— Everything came right in the box; the shoes are invaluable, tell Erasmus he is a very good old gentleman for doing all my commissions, but he would be still better if he would write once again.—four letters are too much, it will frighten him, so I will change my demand into two, &amp; they may be as short as he likes, so that they really come from him.— One other message &amp; I have done, it is to my Father, that I have drawn a bill of eighty pounds.— I must now hold out, as the only economical prospect, the time when we cross the South Seas.— I hope this will not be considered as a little “South Sea scheme”.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Valparaiso is a sort of London or Paris, to any place we have been to.— it is most disagreeable to be obliged to shave &amp; dress decently.— We shall stay here two months, instead of going North-ward, during which time the ship will be refitted &amp; all hands refreshed. You cannot imagine how delightfull the climate feels to all of us, so dry, warm &amp; cheerful: it is not here as in T. del Fuego where one fine day, makes one fear the next will be twice as bad as usual.— The scenery wears such a different aspect, I can sit on the hills &amp; watch the setting sun brighten the Andes, as at Barmouth we used to look at Cader-Idris.— The time of year, being now winter, is very unfortunate for me, it is quite hopeless to penetrate the Cordilleras; There is a mountain, near here, at Quillota, 4700 feet high. I am going in a few days to try to ascend it; I fear however the snow will be too thick. R. Corfield is living here, I cannot tell you how very obliging &amp; kind he is to me.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> He has a very nice house &amp; before long I am going on shore to pay him a visit; he presses me most goodnaturedly to make his house my headquarters.—</p>
<p>I have had some long &amp; pleasant walks in the country; I am afraid it is not a very good place for Natural History; after my first ride I shall know more about it. I have received two letters from Henslow, he tells me my treasures have arrived safe &amp; I am highly delighted at what he says about their value.— What work I shall have, when I return; there will be a glorious mass of what Wickham calls d— —d beastly devilment. Although Wickham always was growling at my bringing more dirt on board than any ten men, he is a great loss to me in the Beagle.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> He is far the most conversible being on board, I do not mean talks the most, for in that respect Sulivan quite bears away the palm. Our new artist, who joined us at M. Video, is a pleasant sort of person, rather too much of the drawing-master about him; he i〈s〉 very unlike to Earles eccentric character.—</p>
<p>We all jog on very well together, there is no quarrelling on board, which is something to say:— The Captain keeps all smooth by rowing every one in turn, which of course he has as much right to do, as a gamekeeper to shoot Partridges on the first of September.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> When I began this long straggling letter, I had intended to have sent it per Admiralty; but now it must be sent by Liverpool, so there will be double postage to pay.— Thank most affectionately those good dear ladies, Sarah W. &amp; Fanny B: I am very sorry to find I have lost the second of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Owen’s letters Remember me at Maer, Woodhouse &amp; I believe those two houses will include every one, I shall care any thing about, when I return. How every thing will be altered by that time; looking at things from a distance, they appear to be undergoing changes far faster than when living amongst them.— Will Erasmus be married? all these gay doing with Cab &amp; horses portend something eventful: Can he build a castle in the air, where he does not quarrel with his wife in the first week? If he has arrived at such a pitch, I know well I shall find him a well-broken-in subjected husband.</p>
<p>Give my best love to my Father, Erasmus &amp; each of the Sisterhood.— Dear Katty, Your most affectionate brother | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>There are several good dear people, whom I should like much to write to, but at present I really have not the time. Thank Fanny for her nice, goodnatured note; I have just re-read it. The sight of her hand writing is enough alone to make me long for this voyage to come to some end.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.7 chiefly] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘principally’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.3 y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>] <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.5 follow] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘<hi rend="italic">[</hi>dir<hi rend="italic">]</hi>’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.7 y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>] <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.8 view] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’; <hi rend="italic">before omitted comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.13 Sarmiento] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘M.’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.16 exit] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘passage’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">5.2 ever] ‘r’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘n’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">5.10 more] <hi rend="italic">above del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">5.14 with it] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">5.15 even] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘de’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">5.15 descriptions] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘of them’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">6.7 lives] ‘v’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘f’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">7.6 the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">7.6 others] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘they’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">8.2 most] ‘m’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">8.7 setting] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">9.3 he tells me] <hi rend="italic">before omitted comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">9.8 me in] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">10.7 the second] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘one’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">10.9 shall] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘care’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">10.14 ?] <hi rend="italic">above omitted comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.2 ‘whole’; 2.5 ‘collect’; 7.1 ‘July’; 8.5 ‘del’; 8.8 ‘Cader-Idris— The’; 10.8 ‘two’; 11.2 ‘Charles’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3875.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Proctor</ref>, a fellow student at Christ’s College. His uncle, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3876.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Proctor</ref>, had lived and travelled in Peru and Chile in 1823–4. (See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6444.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Proctor 1825</ref>, of which a copy, signed ‘C. Darwin’ on the inside front cover, is in Christ’s College Library, Cambridge. There is no evidence that CD had it on board the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s account is in Chapter X of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> read a paper about the expedition at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Geographical Society</ref> on 8 May 1837 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">FitzRoy 1837</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Five lines of the manuscript (‘tell her … journal’) have been deleted in black ink, presumably by one of CD’s sisters.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">A reference to the speculation and fraud of the famous ‘South Sea Bubble’ of the early eighteenth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1073.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Henry Corfield</ref> attended Shrewsbury School, 1816–19; CD entered in 1818 (<hi rend="italic">Shrewsbury School Register</hi>). Corfield’s letters to CD, 26–7 June 1835 and 14–18 July 1835, indicate that he was engaged in trading or shipping business at Valparaiso.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Clements Wickham</ref> had been placed in command of the <hi rend="italic">Adventure</hi> by FitzRoy shortly after he bought her in March 1833.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The opening day of the English shooting season.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>