<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-221">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fanny Myddelton Biddulph   [<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 21 October 1833]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5161</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-221 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-221.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-221.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 56</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 56</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3619.xml">Biddulph, F. M.</persName>
                <placeName>Chirk Castle</placeName>
                <date when="1833-10-21">[c. 21 Oct 1833]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Shropshire news of relatives and friends.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shropshire</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">news</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Chirk Castle]</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Charles,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Catherine writes to tell me she is going to send a packet to you— I cannot therefore lose the opportunity of adding my little scrawl— I do flatter myself you have not quite forgotten me altho’ I am become a <hi rend="underline">steady stupid old matron</hi>, the pleasant times we have passed together in the good old times of the <hi rend="underline">Housemaid</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Postillion</hi> at the Forest, <hi rend="underline">I</hi> shall not easily forget, &amp; steady &amp; dull as I am I assure you I still look forward to some pleasant times again with you when you are cured of your <hi rend="underline">roving</hi> turn, and settle quietly with the <hi rend="underline">little Wife</hi> in the <hi rend="underline">little Parsonage</hi>!! News I have little to tell you, innumerable letters you will receive with this from more able Pen’s than mine— I have been laid up for the last 5 months, one illness after another, has pulled me down very much— Your good Father I think has now nearly set me up, for I am much better this last month &amp; hope soon to be quite off the Invalid list which does not suit me at all— My <hi rend="underline">little Daughter</hi> (how odd it sounds) is 6 months old, &amp; a nice little creature she is— How I should like to see you here my dear Charles, I long for you to return, &amp; I hope this next year will certainly bring you back— I have seen none of your letters, &amp; know little or nothing of your proceedings. they tell me now &amp; then where you are but I never can collect any particulars of your adventures— Susan has paid me two visits here &amp; we were very merry, but now my Mother &amp; Sister in Law have taken up their quarters for the Winter &amp; as they are rather of a <hi rend="underline">serious</hi> or <hi rend="underline">kill joy</hi> turn of mind, they put a stop a little to our merrymakings— I like this place very much, &amp; it is a delightful distance from the old Forest. I often pay it a morning visit— Emma is now a young Lady on her promotion, Matty Cotton is also turn’d loose a <hi rend="underline">blazing</hi> <hi rend="underline">meteor</hi> — Clare Leighton, now Miss Leighton much the same as when you left her, I think there is little new or amusing in Shropshire— Francis has just got an Ensigncy in the 63<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. Regiment which is on its way to Madras but I believe he will go to the Depot in Ireland for the first year or two, &amp; as the Reg<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. has not long to remain abroad he will only have a short time of India— Arthur is doing <hi rend="underline">very well</hi> there—</p>
<p>How prosy I am my dear Charles I am really ashamed of sending such a dull little effusion feel more than half inclined to throw it into the fire—but my hope that you will take the <hi rend="underline">will for the deed</hi> when you read it encourages me to let it go— I shall be very glad to hear from you but do not expect it I know you have enough to do without writing to me</p>
<p>Adieu my dear Charles. Believe me always | Yours most | affect<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi>. | F. Myddelton Biddulph</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>