<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11403">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From James Torbitt   6 March 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14602</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11403 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11403.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11403.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 138</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 138</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4777.xml">Torbitt, James</persName>
                <placeName>Belfast</placeName>
                <date when="1878-03-06">6 Mar 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Problems of continuing with his crossing experiments; financial help from CD.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, miscellaneous</term>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Belfast</placeName>
                    <date>6 March 1878</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Ch. Darwin Esqr. | Down</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Confirming my telegram of yesterday “Hope tone of letter indicates recovery &amp;c” (and it is very naturally a very sincere hope) I really do not know what to say in return for all your kindness.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>I shall keep the £100 check and use it in the last resort, and if it has to be used I think it will be a deep disgrace to the men now in office.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>I know Mr Carruthers and his idea that the line of possible cultivation of the potato, as a matter of profit, is moving eastward. I should have sent the seed and tubers to the Society as you wished, but had no hope of anything coming of it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I would rather give up the thing than that you should labour in it further at present, but will hope that next season you may be able to prosecute it.</p>
                    <p>My letter to the Chancellor was not in expectation of any aid but merely, having obtained your liberty to publish it, thinking that in that form it might be better calculated to attract the attentions of the Editors of the Papers.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>I need not say I will be glad to peruse your letter.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I shall go on raising new cross-fertilized varieties, and hope not to be compelled to reduce the scale.</p>
                    <p>I believe I can get several people to grow potatos in the west of Ireland and have written to two today.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>As regards my own opinion, the principal and only real difficulty in the reintroduction of the plant seems to me to be this—a “variety” in its first year of life weighs only a few ounces, in its second year a few pounds and so forth, and that by the time it has attained a magnitude to enable it to be widely distributed, it has become so old, as to be less able to resist the attack of the fungus, than it was when young, that its yield has fallen off, and that consequently large numbers of new varieties should be always being brought forward wherever the plant is grown.</p>
                    <p>The first result of my cultivation of the potato was a saving of upwards of a hundred thousand a year to the Revenue as per enclosed note,—one of a lot accompanying potato seed sent to our legislators and refused to be received.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I trust to hear of your better health and remain dear Sir with profound respect ever faithfully yours, James Torbitt</p> 
                </div>
            </div> 
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>0.1 Belfast] ‘58 North St’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
            </div>
            </div>
            
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">Torbitt’s telegram has not been found. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11399.xml">letter to James Torbitt, 4 March 1878</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had enclosed a cheque for £100 to enable Torbitt to continue his potato experiments for another season if a government grant could not be obtained (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11399.xml">letter to James Torbitt, 4 March 1878</ref>). </note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_845.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Carruthers</ref>, botanist to the Royal Agricultural Society of England, had objected to Torbitt’s project (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11394F.xml">letter from James Caird to T. H. Farrer, 2 March 1878</ref>).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4">Torbitt had asked for permission to quote from CD’s letters in a printed letter addressed to the chancellor of the Exchequer, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stafford Northcote</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11373.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 24 February 1878</ref> and enclosure).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had agreed to send Torbitt his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11389.xml">letter to T. H. Farrer, 2 March 1878</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11399.xml">letter to James Torbitt, 4 March 1878</ref>).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had agreed with the suggestion of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_845.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Carruthers</ref> that new potato varieties should be trialled in the damper conditions of western Ireland (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11399.xml">letter to James Torbitt, 4 March 1878</ref>).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f7">The enclosed note has not been found. In 1876, Torbitt had sent packets of potato seeds to members of both Houses of Parliament (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10440.xml">letter to James Torbitt, 4 April 1876</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9034.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">DeArce 2008</ref>).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>