<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4574">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Robert Thomson   24 July 1864</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10978</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4574 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4574.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4574.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="12">12</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 117</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 117</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4733.xml">Thomson, Robert</persName>
                <placeName>Botanic Garden, Jamaica</placeName>
                <date when="1864-07-24">24 July 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Observations on insects visiting Melastomataceae.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Melastomataceae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Botanic Garden | Golden Spring P.O. | Jamaica</placeName>
                    <date>24 July 1864</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Being informed by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wilson<ref target="#foot.f1"/> about a year ago that you were desirous of ascertaining if any Insects visit the flower of Melastomaths,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I accordingly give you the result of my observations on one species, a specimen of which, together with several of the insects, I enclose to you.</p>
<p>It may here be desirable for me to state that I was appointed M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilson’s assistant by Sir W. Hooker<ref target="#foot.f3"/> in Kew Garden two years ago. I am engaged in the formation of a new Botanic Garden.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>There is not the slightest attempt at botanical arrangement, or the representation of the Flora of the Island. The chief object of the garden is as a Nursery for the propogation of useful and ornamental plants for gratuitous distribution; at the same time ornamental gardening is not disregarded</p>
<p>I am of oponion that if a selected collection of the Flora of the Island which is as yet very imperfectly developed, were systematically represented, the garden would acquire an important position, and be of great and general service to the scientific world.</p>
<p>I look forward with a little more time and an increased knowledge of Botany at command, to devote myself to the development of the Flora of the Island</p>
<p>Observations on the species above referred to:—</p>
<p>I have repeatedly examined with care for the last few months, and have without a single exception found the Insects occupied in almost every flower around the base of the style, and in the cavity formed by the calyx, whence the object in which the Insect is in search of, is obviously obtained. Minute radiate hairs are appended to the organs with which the Insects are in contact.</p>
<p>Pollen masses are also copiously strewed in their midst.</p>
<p>The anther previous to the full expansion of the flower (if fully expanded the pollen is discharged from its cell) are densely filled with pollen. When the loculament in a special condition is slightly pressed the pollen issues from the apical pore; the mass appearing to the naked eye amorphous particles, but under the microscope the pollen are exceedingly minute ovate cohesive granules. If the part magnified happens to be a single layer they are aggregated so closely together that there is not the smallest apparent interstice perceptible: thereby a beautiful example of simple cellular tissue</p>
<p>I remain | Sir | Your most humble servant | Robert Thomson</p>
<p>The insects are attached to the under surface of the fragments of leaves enclosed with Cotton</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5191.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathaniel Wilson</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had sent queries to many gardeners and botanists for information on the habits of insects visiting flowers of the family Melastomataceae (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4378.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 2 January 1864</ref> and n. 13).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Jackson Hooker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Thomson had been appointed an assistant gardener to Wilson in 1862. Wilson, who was curator of the oldest botanical garden in Jamaica, located at Bath, was also overseeing the establishment of a new botanical garden at Castleton, nineteen miles north of Kingston on the road to Annotto Bay. Land for the garden at Castleton had been purchased in 1857. Thomson was stationed at Castleton and, under Wilson’s direction, helped to establish the new garden (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5600.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Morris 1898</ref>, pp. 137–44).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>