<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7262">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Camille Dareste<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   2 July 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16669</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7262 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7262.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7262.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp † (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 47</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 47</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1196.xml">Dareste, G. M. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Muséum d’Histoire Naturelle, Lille</placeName>
                <date when="1870-07-02">2 July 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has found a remarkable anatomical character in the niata skull of which he wrote [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">5540</hi>]. Asks whether the skull CD brought from South America [at the Royal College of Surgeons] shows the same character. If so, it would provide incontestable evidence of the origin of this race of cattle.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cattle</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">niata ox</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, South</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Royal College of Surgeons</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Ville de Lille</hi> | <hi rend="print">(Nord)</hi> | <hi rend="print">Museum d’Histoire Naturelle</hi> | <hi rend="print">rue</hi></placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="underline">des Fleurs, 1</hi> | <hi rend="underline">Lille</hi> %%D <hi rend="underline">le</hi> 2 juillet <hi rend="underline">18</hi>70 %%S Monsieur</p>
<p>Permettez-moi de recourir encore une fois à l’inépuisable obligeance dont vous m’avez déjà donné beaucoup de preuves.</p>
<p>Il s’agit toujours de la race des boeufs <hi rend="underline">niata</hi>. La discussion que j’ai soutenue à ce sujet après avoir porté sur l’existence même de cette race en Amérique, a été actuellement portée sur un tout autre terrain. On conteste que les caractères ostéologiques de la race <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> soient les mêmes que j’ai décrits dans la tête d’un Veau né de race flamande dont je vous ai envoyé la description, il y a trois ans.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Pour ma part, j’avais cru d’abord à l’existence de quelques différences, légeres il est vrai; tant que je n’avais pu connaître la tête du <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> que vous avez rapportée d’Amérique que par la brève description d’Owen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Mais ayant pu tout récemment, étudier la figure qui en a été donnée par Rütimeyer dans son mémoire sur les races de boeufs, je me suis convaincu que ces différences n’existaient point;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> et que, du moins en ne considérant que les profils il y a, sauf les différences d’âge, une véritable identité de forme et de structure.</p>
<p>Mais un point reste indécis pour moi. En étudiant de nouveau la tête dont je vous ai adressé la description,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> je me suis aperçu d’un caractère nouveau et fort intéressant qui m’avait complètement échappé dans ma première étude. Ce caractère consiste en ce que le vomer vient s’interposer entre les deux os intermaxillaires, et qu’il forme ainsi partie de la voûte palatine. Caractère d’autant plus remarquable qu’il ne se rencontre que chez les Dauphins et un certain nombre de Cétacés.</p>
<p>Pourriez-vous me dire si la tête osseuse que Vous avez rapportée, et qui est au Collège des chirurgiens, présente un semblable caractère? S’il en était ainsi, nous aurions bien évidemment un document incontestable sur l’origine de la race <hi rend="underline">niata</hi>.</p>
<p>Je Vous prie encore une fois d’excuser mon importunité. Mais il s’agit pour moi d’une question fort importante, par suite des contradictions que j’ai rencontrées lorsque j’ai publié ces faits pour la première fois.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> D’ailleurs il s’agit ici d’une question beaucoup plus vaste encore de Votre belle théorie sur l’origine des espèces que nous aurons je le crains bien, beaucoup de peine à faire accepter en France.</p>
<p>Veuillez agréer, je vous prie, l’expression de mon sincère et profond respect. | Camille Dareste. | Prof. à la fac. des Sc. de Lille.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>4.3 Ce caractère … Cétacés. 4.6] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi>; <hi rend="italic">enclosed in square brackets, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.3 Ce caractère … palatine 4.5] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Ville de Lille</hi> | <hi rend="print">(Nord)</hi> | <hi rend="print">Museum d’Histoire Naturelle</hi> | <hi rend="print">rue</hi></placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="underline">des Fleurs, 1</hi> | <hi rend="underline">Lille</hi> %%D 2 July <hi rend="underline">18</hi>70 %%S Dear Sir</p>
<p>Allow me to appeal once more to the infinite obligingness of which you have already shown me so much evidence.</p>
<p>My subject is still the race of <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> cattle. The debate I have sustained on this matter, after having turned on the very existence of this race in America, has now been carried into quite a different domain. Some are now questioning whether the osteological characteristics of the <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> race are the same as those I described in the head of a Calf born of the Flemish race, the description of which I sent you three years ago.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>For my part, I had at first believed in the existence of certain differences, though admittedly slight ones, for all I was only able to know the <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> head which you brought back from America from Owen’s brief description.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But having very recently been able to study the picture Rütimeyer gives in his memoir on the races of cattle, I have become convinced that these differences do not exist;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and that, at least when considering the profiles alone, there is, differences of age excepted, a true identity between form and structure.</p>
<p>But one point remains inconclusive for me. While looking again at the head whose description I sent you,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I became aware of a new and most interesting character that had completely escaped me during my first investigation. This character consists of the fact that the vomer is interposed between the two intermaxillary bones, thus forming part of the hard palate. A character the more remarkable in that it is only found among the Dolphins and a certain number of Cetaceans.</p>
<p>Can you tell me whether the skull that You brought back, and which is at the College of surgeons, exhibits a similar character? If it were so, we would very evidently have an incontestable document concerning the origin of the <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> race.</p>
<p>Once again, I beg You to excuse my importunity. But for me this is a most important question, because of the conflict I encountered when I published these facts for the first time.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Besides, there is also a far more extensive question here of Your fine theory on the origin of species which we shall have, I greatly fear, much trouble in getting accepted in France.</p>
<p>Please allow me to express my sincere and profound respects. | Camille Dareste. | Prof. at the Sc. fac. of Lille.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Dareste refers to his work <hi rend="italic">Rapport sur un veau monstreaux</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dareste 1867</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Camille Dareste, 19 May 1867</ref> and n. 8). Niata cattle are an abnormally small race from South America, whose peculiarities are now seen as the result of a form of dwarfism. CD discussed niata cattle in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 145–6, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 90–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen’s</ref> description of the skull that CD had brought back from South America, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6085.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Owen] 1853</ref>, 2: 3832. The skull was in the Hunterian museum of the Royal College of Surgeons, London.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The illustration for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig Rütimeyer’s</ref> description of the niata was a woodcut made from a photograph of the skull in the Hunterian museum (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rütimeyer 1866</ref>, p. 28).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Camille Dareste, 19 May 1867</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Dareste refers to his exchange of papers with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">André Sanson</ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus hebdomadaires des séances de l’Académie des sciences</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Camille Dareste, 19 May 1867</ref> and n. 9).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>