<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12337F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">From E. S. Galton   19 November 1879</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">22009</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12337F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12337F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12337F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt> 
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Private collection</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_653.xml">Private collection</repository>
                        <collection/>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1794.xml">Galton, E. S.</persName>
                    <placeName>Leamington</placeName>
                    <date when="1879-11-19">19 Nov 1879</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc><abstract>
                <p>Her brother-in-law, Edward Wheler, died on Sunday.</p>
                <p>Sends some corrections for <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-07-02" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2019-07-15" status="transcribed">6 more pages transcribed <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2020-06-19" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
            <change when="2020-12-09" status="sup-footnoted">Footnoted <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2021-07-09" status="sup-reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
            <change when="2022-03-08" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">AMP</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>5. Bertie Terrace. Leamington</placeName>
                        <date>Nov 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> | 1879</date>
                        <salute>My dear Cousin,</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>When I wrote to you on Thursday last, I had read the life of our Grandfather rather hurriedly, as we were daily expecting the death of my Brother in-law—Edward Wheler— he lingered on till early on Sunday morn, when he ceased to breathe, at the age of 81—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In him, I have lost a most kind friend— My sister is dreadfully cut up—but she has one Son &amp; one Daughter—who will be real comforts to her—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> She begs me to tell you, how much interested she has been, in reading the Book, you kindly gave her—at times when able— She is sure you will excuse her writing herself—.</p>
                        <p>A few mistakes, the Printer has made, which I dare say, you have already noticed— viz</p>
                        <p>Page 29—Last line but 3. B<hi rend="italic">ou</hi>lton (not Bolton)<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                        <p>" 87.—Line 10. He died Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 184<hi rend="doubleUnderline">8</hi> (not 1849) I always remember the year your Father died, as my Sister Lucy Moilliet died the week before; &amp; the two deaths, quite upset my Mother<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                        <p>Page 41. I have those lines, in my Grandfather’s writing “From Lichfield famed two giant critics come”</p>
                        <p>Page 7.8.9 The letters to &amp; from Susannah Darwin are excellent—&amp; one of my Grandfather’s earliest attempts to poetry was this, my Mother has often told us—</p>
                        <lg><l>“My dearest Sue</l>
                        <l>Of lovely hue</l>
                        <l>No sugar, can be sweeter</l>
                            <l>You do—as far</l>
                        <l>Excel Su-gar</l>
                        <l>As Sugar, does Saltpetre”</l></lg>
                        <p>Page 40 &amp; 81. The stammering— D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E Darwin’s daughter—Violetta<ref target="#foot.f5"/> also inherited his Stammering to a great degree &amp; till the age of 12. could hardly make herself understood— He sent for a Person fr. Edinburgh, who cured her in a great degree   She could not pronounce the liquids L. M. N. R &amp; Y— His remedy was, to put a vowel before each of those letters, when beginning a word—such— as Er—<hi rend="italic">Yes</hi>— Er—<hi rend="italic">NO</hi>— In the same way an E—between the letters Br—in Brothers, Bread, so B<hi rend="italic">er</hi>-others, Ber-ead— She always managed to do it so well, it was scarcely perceptible, to those who did not know her infirmity—&amp; she cured many, who stammered in the same way</p>
                        <p>Page 54—I often heard my mother say, that the small pox so raged in Derby, when she was born (Ap<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. 1783) that her Father innoculated her when only six weeks old—tho’ it was a risk, but he thought the risk greater, as she was in a Doctor’s House where so many Patients came—</p>
                        <p>64. My Mother used to say, that when her Father visited the Robber in prison— He said— “Now tell me, as you are condemned, what is the best preservative against thieves”— The man replied—a little dog, so fastened that we cannot give him any thing to quieten him—a Light, or a Baby in the House—&amp; an old fashioned rusty lock which makes a noise, when trying to do anything to it— My Mother, in consequence, always had one Light, burning all night in the House—</p>
                        <p>Page 116. Line 6. f<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. the Bottom   D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E Darwin had always a great objection to Nurses who squinted, &amp; who had an unpleasant expression of countenance— He thought children were much influenced by it</p>
                        <p>118— Amongst other curious inventions, was a Clock, to watch the Watchman—it was invented by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E Darwin &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. William Strutt—&amp; we long had one in our possession— I think my Brother Darwin must have it now—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                        <p>126. I always understood my Grandfather had only <hi rend="italic">regularly</hi> taken up his abode at the Priory about 3. weeks before his death, as several rooms had to be built after his Son Erasmus died<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                        <p>Page 127—line 5—Evidently a mis-print   died April <hi rend="italic">18</hi><hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. (not the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.)<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                        <p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E Darwin had a severe illness 2 or 3. years before his death, &amp; in his delirium, he often fancied himself a tree—&amp; my Mother used to say, how painful it was, as she sat by his bedside—he would point to his heart &amp; say— “If you would only cut out this decayed part, the tree would live”—</p>
                        <p>The Picture by Rollason was taken after his illness—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                        <p>In the Book—of Holland House, published ab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. 1874— Some lines on one of the trees there, was quoted, as having been written by Rogers— An old friend of ours, &amp; especially of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Keir’s (D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Alex<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Blair) then much upwards of 90—wrote to us saying, the lines were not Rogers, but Dr. Darwin’s— An ode to Swilcar Oak in Needwood Forest— On making enquiries, we found it, in the Phytologia—&amp; originally written to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mundy—who wrote on Needwood forest &amp; received complimentary verses f<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E Darwin—His Son, Erasmus, Sir Brook Boothby &amp; others—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                        <p>How well you have explained at Page 80—about my Grandfather having a large appetite—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                        <p>We are glad to hear that your Son Horace is going soon to be married, in a way you all like<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                        <p>With our kind regards to yourself &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Darwin &amp; y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. family | Believe me | Your’s very sincerely | E. S. Galton</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="annotations">
                    <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Errata’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                </div>
                
              
                
                
                
                
                
            </div>
           
           
           <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12314.xml">letter from E. S. Galton, 12 November 1879</ref> (although 12 November 1879 was a Wednesday). CD had sent her a copy of his <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5088.xml">Elizabeth Anne Wheler</ref>’s children were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7002.xml">Lucy Elizabeth Wheler</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8781.xml">Edward Galton Wheler</ref>.</note><note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8434.xml">Matthew Boulton</ref>.</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s father was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin (1766–1848)</ref>. Wheler’s mother was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1796.xml">Violetta Galton</ref>.</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f5">Wheler’s mother.</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1792.xml">Darwin Galton</ref>. The point of the watch-clock was to ensure that watchmen did their appointed nightly rounds when and where they were supposed to do them; it was a predecessor of a punch-clock or clocking-in system. The clocks were distributed around the town of Derby, and the watchmen each had a personal key that enabled them to move a particular peg on the clocks on their round; but each peg could only be moved within fifteen minutes of a certain time. In the morning a superintendent would check which pegs had not been moved at the right time and ask the watchmen concerned to account for themselves. (<hi rend="italic">First report of the commissioners appointed to inquire into the municipal corporations in England and Wales</hi> (1835), pp. 1851–2.)</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f7">In <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, pp. 124–6, CD wrote that Erasmus had been living at Breadsall Priory for about two years before he died in 1802. The house was previously occupied by his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8435.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> (1759–99).</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f8">The death date is that of Erasmus Darwin (1731–1802).</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8443.xml">James Rawlinson</ref> made two portraits of Erasmus Darwin (1731–1802) (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4339.xml">Keynes 1994</ref>).</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f10">The lines on the Swilcar oak are in <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi>, pp. 528–9 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1793.xml">E. Darwin 1800</ref>), but have not been found in the book on Holland House (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9909.xml">Liechtenstein 1874</ref>). Galton also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8440.xml">James Keir</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9407.xml">Alexander Blair</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9406.xml">Francis Noel Clarke Mundy</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9911.xml">Mundy 1776</ref>.</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f11">In <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 80, CD wrote: ‘With regard to the charge of gluttony, as Dr. Darwin was a tall, bulky man, who lived much on milk, fruit, and vegetables, it is probable that he ate largely, as every man must do who works hard and lives on such a diet.’</note>
               <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml">Horace Darwin</ref> married <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1227.xml">Ida Farrer</ref> on 3 January 1880 (Emma Darwin’s diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            </div>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>