<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6174">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Otto Staudinger<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   15 May 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16054</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6174 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6174.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6174.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp (French) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 82: A103-6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>82: A103–6</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4535.xml">Staudinger, Otto</persName>
                <placeName>Dresden</placeName>
                <date when="1868-05-15">15 May 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has often thought CD would find vast material for his ideas in study of entomology and Lepidoptera. His price-list of specimens proves only that collectors of Lepidoptera catch more males than females, not that there are more. He accounts for this by the less active habits of the females. [See <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 1: 312.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Lepidoptera</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">accounting for</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">habit</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00208_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00208_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="A103r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00208.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00208_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00208.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="A103v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00209.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00209_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00209.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="A104r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00210.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00210_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00210.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="A104v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00211.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00211_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00211.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i5" n="A103v &amp; A104r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00212.jpg" rend="landscape" width="6780px" height="6529px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00212_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="6780px" height="6529px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00212.dzi" width="6780px" height="6529px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i6" n="A105r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00213.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00213_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00213.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i7" n="A105v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00214.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00214_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00214.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i8" n="A106r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00215.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00215_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00215.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i9" n="A106v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00216.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00216_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00082-000-00216.dzi" width="3612px" height="6347px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Dresden</placeName>
                    <date>mai 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1868.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>excuse if I write you in French, because I have not exercise to write the English; I should be more happy if I could write you in Germain.</p>
<p>Si vous sauriez, Monsieur, comme votre nom est aujourd’hui celèbre chez nous en Allemagne, comme l’une partie des naturaliste, et bien certainement la majeure, est enchanté de vos idées, pendant qu’une autre petite partie vous combat, alors il est inutile de vous dire que cela me fera le plus grand plaisir du monde de vous pouvoir servir dans quelle chose que ce sera. Bien souvent j’ai dit: oh! si Mr. Darwin voulait étudier un peu l’entomologie et principalement les Lépidoptères, quel matérial énorme en pourrait-il tirer pour ces sublimes idées! Combien des formes n’y-a-t-il pas où il y a la plus grande discussion si ce sont des espèces séparées ou des races etc. Bien souvent on peu faire les observations les plus intéressantes surtout quand on a eu même l’occasion d’étudier les espèces dans les différentes pays où elles se trouvent, et on peut affirmer sur une manière tout positive les variations faits par le clime ou des autres circonstances.</p>
<p>Mais pardon je reviendrai à la question que vous me faites.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Quoique malheureusement j’ai depuis quelques années très peu de temps à sacrifier pour les observation, j’en ai fait assez à son temps et j’espères que dans peu de temps je serai assez heureux d’en faire beaucoup plus.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Mon premier principe est d’être consciencieux à la rigeur et de n’affirmer rien comme certaine, quand je n’en ai pas fait l’expérience suffisante. Mais voilà, Monsieur, il y a peu des questions, où les entomologistes se puissent plus tromper que sur la quantité prévalante de l’une ou l’autre sexe. Ma liste X avec ses prix, pardonnez moi, ne prouve rien du tout que seulement le fait, que des certaines espèces sont trouvées par les chasseurs principalement dans l’une ou l’autre sexe.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Si vraiment dans la nature existent par exemple de l’Anthocharis Gruneri, plus les ♂ ♂ sont notées avec 20 les ♀ ♀ avec 50 silbergr.,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> c’est bien douteux, quoique justement de cette espèce mon chasseur m’a envoyé dans une année entre 2–300 ♂ ♂ et seulement 3 ♀ ♀!! La raison que principalement chez les Rhopalocères les ♂ ♂ sont pris dans un plus grand nombre, c’est d’abord que les ♀ ♀ volent beaucoup moins, et que chez la plupart des espèces la masse des ♀ ♀ éclot un peu plus tard que les ♂ ♂. Les chasseurs alors, voyant que les ♂ ♂ qui volent en quantité sont presque tout passés ou gâtés ne se donnent pas la peine à chercher les ♀ ♀, ce qui du reste est toujours beaucoup plus difficile. Comme la plupart des papillons diurnes est pris seulement au vol, vous avez le clef pourquoi les ♀ ♀ <hi rend="underline">semblent</hi> être plus rare. Chez les Diurnes élevés ordinairement les deux sexes s’élèvent en même quantité, ou les ♀ ♀ en majeure quantité.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Mais, très honoré Monsieur, je pense de même que l’on est bien en erreur, en supposant que chez les espèces que l’on élève et où bien souvent les ♀ ♀ prévalent d’une manière exclusive, ce sexe prévale aussi en nature.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Je ne sais guère quelle experience on a fait sur les autres animaux, mais chez les insectes je crois que comme chez le premier animal, l’homme, la femelle en génerale prévale, et par le même motif. La nature de la ♀ qui doit soigner particulièrement pour la réproduction et conservation de l’espèce doit être toujours plus forte, ou bien plutôt doit supporter plus que le ♂. Eh voilà chez l’éducation des chenilles, ou nous leur donner, pouvons donner, bien rarement tous les conditions favorables à eux, naturellement ce sexe le plus faible, les ♂ ♂, doivent succomber les premiers. Je me suis persuadé que les chrysalides mortes d’une espèce qui donnait particulièrement des ♀ ♀ en éclosion, étaient pour la plus grande nombre des chrysalides des ♂ ♂.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Cé doit être encore plus le cas chez les chenilles où seulement (excepté très peu de cas) on ne peut guère distinguer les sexes.</p>
<p>Un certain Monsieur de Münster, je crois, s’adressait à moi, pour que je lui devais constater, que chez les Lépidoptères, dont les chenilles sont entophages (Cossides, Sesiae etc) les ♀ ♀ prévalaient toujours.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Il voulait conclure cela des abeilles, où seulement par la nourriture plus opulente etc les reines deviennent des ♀ ♀ reproduisantes. Il pensait parceque les chenilles entophages étaient pour ainsi dire enveloppés dans leur nourritures et en pourrait prendre tout ce qu’elles veulent, la sexe female devrait prévaler. J’ai élevé masses des Sesiae et en trouvant les chrysalides en nature j’ai eu les deux sexes à peu près en même quantité, souvent même plus des ♂ ♂; mais en cherchant les chenilles, surtout encore un peu jeunes, une partie est morte, parceque c’est encore plus difficile de les soigner comme en nature, et principalement les ♀ ♀ par leur nature plus forte se sont sauvé.</p>
<p>Néanmoins il est bien sûr que dans certaines espèces l’un sexe prévale dans des certains ans. Cela prouvent d’abord les espèces dont les ♀ ♀ sont aptères; dont nous ne connaissons pas encore le ♂ d’une manière positive de la Fumea Helix. Mais même dans ces genres il arrive que dans des certains années et certaines localités on trouve aussi plus des fourreaux ♂ d’une Psyche que des ♀ ♀.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Je me permets de vous observer un autre fait assez curieux. Il y a des Hybrides assez connus dans les Lepidoptères et je ne possède ni connais pas un Hybride incontestable, qui soit une vraie ♀. Ainsi j’ai élevé et obtenu plus d’une soixantaine de <hi rend="underline">Smerinthus Hybridus Westwood</hi> (Smerinth. Ocellata ♂ et Smer. Populi ♀)<ref target="#foot.f11"/> qui tous était des ♂ ♂, excepté deux qui se laissent regarder comme les commencement d’Hermaphroditisme, parceque les antennes seules sont females, tout le reste mâles. A-propos des Hermaphrodites, dont j’ai réuni dans ma collection une bonne quarantaine, presque toujours le sexe ♀ prévale chez eux, à ce que je crois je n’ai qu’un seul ou le sexe ♂ prévale et seulement 8–10 qui sont nettement moitié ♂ et moitié ♀.</p>
<p>Sans vouloir et pouvoir me permettre un jugement positif, je crois que le sexe ♀ prévale ordinairement en nature, et que dans les cas, surtout chez les Rhopalocera, où nous l’appelons rare, c’est seulement parceque nous ne les savons pas trouver comme les ♂ ♂. J’observe encore le fait que j’ai plusieurs fois chez l’<hi rend="underline">Ocnogyna Corsica</hi> vu qu’<hi rend="underline">un</hi> ♂ féconde jusqu’à trois ♀ ♀ (les ♀ ♀ sont demiaptères)<ref target="#foot.f12"/> pendant que je ne sais aucun cas qu’une ♀ se laisse féconder par plusieurs ♂ ♂.</p>
<p>Enfin, Monsieur, je ne veux pas vous ennuyer plus et je regrette que je ne peux pas vous donner des dates aussi sûrs que vous devez le désirer. Mais je repète et je l’ai constaté en nature dans assez des cas, où par example on croyait les ♀ ♀ beaucoup plus rares, qu’il y a aussi beaucoup et même plus de ♀ ♀ en trouvant la vrai <hi rend="underline">localité</hi> et <hi rend="underline">époque</hi>, et étudiant un peu les <hi rend="underline">moeurs</hi> différents des ♀ ♀.</p>
<p>Je serais heureux, Monsieur, si je pourrais vous servir encore dans quelque chose, | et je vous prie de me croire | votre bien devoué | O. Staudinger.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.7 Ma] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 Je … moitié ♀. 7.10] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Dresden</placeName>
                    <date>May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>excuse if I write you in French, because I have not exercise to write the English; I should be more happy if I could write you in Germain.</p>
<p>If you knew, Sir, how celebrated your name is among us in Germany nowadays, how one party of naturalists, and most certainly the majority, is enchanted with your ideas, while another smaller party combats you, then it is useless to tell you that it would give me the greatest pleasure in the world to be able to serve you in anything whatsoever. How often have I said: oh! if Mr. Darwin were to study entomology a little, and especially the Lepidoptera, what an enormous amount of material he would be able to draw from it for his sublime ideas! How many forms there are over which there is the greatest debate as to whether they are separate species or races etc. Very often the most interesting observations can be made, especially when one has also had the opportunity to study species in the different countries in which they are found, and the variations produced by climate or other circumstances can be confirmed in a most positive manner.</p>
<p>But pardon me, I will return to the question you asked.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Although for some years I have unhappily had very little time that could be given to observations, I have made enough of them in the past and I hope that soon I shall be so happy as to make a great many more.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> My first principle is to be conscientious to the point of rigour and to confirm nothing as certain when I have not carried out adequate experiments on it. But indeed, Sir, there are few questions, in which entomologists are more capable of being mistaken than over the predominant quantity of one or the other sex. My list X with its prices, pardon me, proves nothing at all other than the fact that certain species are found by collectors principally in one or the other sex.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Whether in nature there really exist, for example in Anthocharis Gruneri, more ♂ ♂ are noted with 20 the ♀ ♀ with 50 silvergr.,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> that is very doubtful, even though my collector sent me in one year between 2–300 ♂ ♂ and only 3 ♀ ♀ of this very species!! The reason why especially in the Rhopalocera the ♂ ♂ are taken in greater numbers, is that to begin with the ♀ ♀ fly far less, and that in most species the mass of ♀ ♀ hatches a little later than the ♂ ♂. Then the collectors, seeing that the ♂ ♂ which are flying in quantity are almost all faded or spoilt do not give themselves the trouble of looking for the ♀ ♀, which besides is always far more difficult. Since most diurnal butterflies are only taken in flight, you have the key to why the ♀ ♀ <hi rend="underline">seems</hi> to be rarer.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>But, most honoured Sir, I also think that it is a great mistake to suppose that among species that have been reared, and where often the ♀ ♀ predominate in an exclusive way, this sex also predominates in nature.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I hardly know what experiments have been done on other animals, but among the insects, I believe that, as in the first animal, man, the female in general predominates, and for the same reason. The nature of the ♀, which must care particularly for reproduction and preservation of the species, must always be stronger, or rather must stand more than the ♂. Hence in the culture of caterpillars, where we very rarely give them, or can give them, all the conditions that are favourable to them, this weaker sex, the ♂ ♂, must naturally succumb first. I am persuaded that the dead chrysalids of a species that produces ♀♀ especially, upon hatching, were for the most part the chrysalids of ♂♂.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> This must be still more the case for caterpillars where (except in very few cases) one can hardly distinguish the sexes.</p>
<p>A certain gentleman, from Münster, I believe, addressed himself to me, asking me to confirm, whether in the Lepidoptera whose caterpillars are entophages (Cossides, Sesiæ etc) the ♀ ♀ always predominate.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> He wanted to conclude this of the bees, where just from a richer diet etc the queens become reproductive ♀ ♀. He thought that because the entophage caterpillars were, so to speak, enveloped by their nourishment and could take as much of it as they wished, the female sex ought to predominate. I have raised masses of Sesiæ and when I have found the chrysalids in nature, I had the two sexes in nearly the same quantity, often even more of the ♂ ♂ ; but when collecting caterpillars, especially while they are still rather young, a proportion of them dies, because it is even more difficult to care for them as in nature, and the ♀ ♀, by means of their stronger nature, have principally survived.</p>
<p>Nevertheless it is certain that in some species one sex predominates in certain years. In the first place the species with wingless ♀ ♀ prove this; of which we still do not know the ♂ in a positive manner for Fumea Helix. But even in these genera it happens that in certain years and certain localities, more ♂ than ♀ ♀ cocoons of Psyche are found.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I shall allow myself to remark on another rather curious fact to you. There are some quite well-known Hybrids among the Lepidoptera and I neither possess nor know of an incontestable Hybrid, which is a true ♀. Thus, I have reared and obtained over sixty <hi rend="underline">Smerinthus Hybridus Westwood</hi> (Smerinth. Ocellata ♂ and Smer. Populi ♀),<ref target="#foot.f11"/> which were all ♂ ♂, except for two which may be regarded as the beginnings of Hermaphroditism, because the antennae alone were female, all the rest was male. Concerning Hermaphrodites, a good forty of which I have added to my collection, the ♀ sex almost always predominates among them, as far as I am aware I have only one in which the ♂ sex predominates and only 8–10 which are clearly half ♂ and half ♀.</p>
<p>Without wishing for or being able to allow myself a positive judgement, I believe that the ♀ sex usually predominates in nature, and that in cases, especially in the Rhopalocera, where we call them rare, it is only because we do not know know how to find them like the ♂ ♂. I also observe the fact that in <hi rend="underline">Ocnogyna Corsica</hi> I have several times seen <hi rend="underline">one</hi> ♂ fertilise up to three ♀ ♀ (the ♀ ♀ are demiaptera)<ref target="#foot.f12"/> while I know of no case in which a female allows herself to be fertilised by several ♂ ♂.</p>
<p>So, Sir, I do not wish to trouble you further and I regret that I am not able to give you data which are as certain as you must wish. But I repeat and I have confirmed this in nature in numerous cases, in which for example the ♀ ♀ were believed to be far rarer, that there are also a great many or even more ♀ ♀ by finding the right <hi rend="underline">locality</hi> and <hi rend="underline">time period</hi>, and by studying the different <hi rend="underline">habits</hi> of the ♀ ♀ a little.</p>
<p>I should be happy, Sir, if I could serve you again in any matter, | and I beg you to believe me | your most devoted | O. Staudinger</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see part I: 500–2. The first sentence of the letter is written in English.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6164.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Otto Staudinger, 6 May [1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Staudinger published a number of papers, many in the <hi rend="italic">Stettiner entomologische Zeitung</hi>, from 1855 onward, as well as a number of books on entomology. During the early to mid 1860s, Staudinger probably reduced his collecting while he built baths and the Villa Sphinx in Dresden (<hi rend="italic">Iris</hi> 13 (1900): 341–58).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Staudinger refers to his ‘Lepidopteren-Doubbletten Liste’ (List of duplicate Lepidoptera), no. X. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6164.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Otto Staudinger, 6 May [1868]</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In CD’s table drawn from Staudinger’s list, <hi rend="italic">Anthocharis gruneri</hi> (Gruner’s orange tip) is listed as having twenty male and fifty female specimens (DAR 81: 84). Silbergr.: <hi rend="italic">silbergroschen</hi>, a German unit of currency.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 312.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6164.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Otto Staudinger, 6 May [1868]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 311 and 312, CD reported, apparently erroneously, that Staudinger thought that in specimens reared from the caterpillar stage more females than males died in the cocoon.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The family Cossidae (carpenter and leopard moths) and family Sesiidae (clear-winged moths) are both wood-boring in their larval stage. Staudinger wrote on the Sesiidae (Sesiae; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Staudinger 1854</ref> and 1856).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The snailcase bagworm, <hi rend="italic">Fumea helix</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">Psyche helix</hi>), is now <hi rend="italic">Apterona helicoidella</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4692.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LepIndex</hi></ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2467.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Fauna Europaea</hi></ref> (internet resources), consulted 3 October 2005). <hi rend="italic">Apterona helicoidella</hi> is parthenogenetic.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Staudinger refers to the eyed hawk-moth, <hi rend="italic">Smerinthus ocellatus</hi>, and the poplar hawk-moth, <hi rend="italic">S. populi</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Laothoe populi</hi>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Obadiah Westwood</ref> described specimens of a hybrid of <hi rend="italic">S. ocellatus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. populi</hi> in Westwood 1838.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Demiaptères</hi>: Staudinger probably meant small-winged.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>