<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10881">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From James Torbitt to the House of Commons   6 March 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14600</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10881 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10881.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10881.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">1p</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 136</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 136</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4777.xml">Torbitt, James</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1877-03-06">6 Mar 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_7863.xml">House of Commons</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Exposes means whereby considerable amounts of whisky are being produced duty-free.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">58, North Street, Belfast,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>6th March, 1877.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental"><hi rend="italic">TO THE RIGHT HON. AND HON. THE MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS.</hi></seg>
                    <salute><hi rend="print">My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi></salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="underline">In your capacity, as guardians of the public purse, I beg leave to bring under your notice a leak in the Revenue which exists at this port.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">The amount I do not know, of course, but I take it to be several times the amount of the cost of the Viceregal establishment in Dublin. £300 per week is supposed to be about the amount of profit realized from it by one firm alone.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">The</hi> modus operandi <hi rend="underline">is this—and I acknowledge that in self-defence I have been compelled to become a participator in the matter— A dealer, or distiller, fills ten puncheons of whisky, or a hundred, or a thousand, and in the course of a few days the staves of the casks drink up about one gallon and a-half of proof spirit each, the duty on which amounts to fifteen shillings on each cask.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">The dealer then sends a thousand empty puncheons to the bonded warehouse, and pumps into them the thousand puncheons whisky. These second thousand casks proceed to suck up each another gallon and a-half of whisky, and the operator, in the meantime, brings home the first thousand casks, pours into each of them a few gallons of boiling water (steam is better, and is used by the more scientific operators), and extracts the gallon and a-half of whisky free of duty. The strength of this spirit is then brought up by the addition of 65 over proof spirit,</hi>* <hi rend="underline">and the amount of duty “saved” here is £750 on this one “operation,” and this is repeated</hi> ad infinitum.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">I have myself “blended” (this operation is called “blending”) whisky down from 124°° to 109°°, thereby clearing £9 per puncheon, at the expense of the general tax payers of the community; and to stop this all that is requisite is an order that whisky shall be blended only once in the bonded stores.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">I have the honour to be, | My Lords and Gentlemen, | Your most obedient servant, | J. TORBITT.</hi></p>
<p>* in order to make it of saleable strength.</p>
<p>In relation to this. Sir Stafford Northcote was informed by the Customs that in the previous year £13.000 was lost in our warehouse, alone and it was a <hi rend="underline">suppressio vere</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The firm alluded to (Dunville’s) cleared as they have admitted just double that per annum and they have now bought these landed estates.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>My gain was about £600 a year, but in consequence of cultivating the potato I was compelled give the whiskey to my Bankers and cease “blending”—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have not yet got much thanks for this saving to the people nor do I want any. J.T.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stafford Northcote</ref> was chancellor of the Exchequer. <hi rend="italic">Suppressio veri</hi>: suppression of truth (Latin).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Dunville &amp; Co. was a Belfast firm of whiskey blenders and tea importers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For Torbitt’s scheme to improve the cultivation of the potato, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10466.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Torbitt, 22 April 1876</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>