<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11445">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. I. Rogers to Francis Darwin   25 March 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10555</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11445 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11445.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11445.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description"/>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp † (by CD)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 196</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 196</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4057.xml">Rogers, J. I.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Cannon St, 119</placeName>
                <date when="1878-03-25">25 Mar 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Suggests movements of sensitive plants may protect against insects.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">119, Cannon Street, | London, | E.C.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. March <hi rend="italic">187</hi>8</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Referring to your lecture on the “Analogies between Animal &amp; plant life” and to the use of the movements of the Sensitive plant not having been accounted for—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> my attention was directed to this subject by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwins book on climbing plants,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; from some <hi rend="underline">very</hi> rough experiments, I was led to the conclusion that the movements of the Sensitive plant were protective agains〈t〉 insect depredations. I am, to my great loss, not a botanist &amp; therefore what follows may be well known to you in which case I must apologize for taking up your time.</p>
                    <p>On raising some sensitive plants in an in〈n〉er con〈ser〉vatory case together with some other seeds, I found that all the plants from the latter were much injured by woodlice while the Sensitive plants were untouched. On putting caterpillars &amp; slugs on to the stem of the full grown Sensitive plants, I found that the down pointing thorns caused them such annoyance that they could hardly be forced to climb up. On placing them on the leaves or branches, the movements 〈caus〉ed the caterpillars much 〈in〉convenience &amp; apparently frightened them, so that they generally dropped off as soon as they could. If not they remained quite still &amp; if left on at night they had disappeared by morning leaving the plant untouched. Sometimes t〈he〉 caterpillar got on to the flower which is apparently not sensitive &amp; then began to browse at ease. When the caterpillar remained on the branchlet &amp; the leaves closed up, they presented a hard edge with hairs or thorns so as to increase the difficulty of eating them.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> A bee alighting on the leaves &amp; finding them yield would naturally settle on the flower—thus promoting fertilization.</p>
                    <p>An Indian friend told me that on brush〈ing〉 through an inviting looking green patch of Sensitive plants they suddenly move &amp; the leaves disappear, leaving exposed the horribly sharp thorns which clothe the join〈ts〉 of the stems. This may be protective as a〈g〉ainst g〈ra〉zing animals; for the thorns like those of furze or brambles in waste places, would be unattractive, &amp; the disappearance of the leaves would divert the animals’ attention.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps the leaf motions of the Indian “Telegraph plant” (botanically called Desmodium gyrans I believe)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> may shoot off insects.</p>
                    <p>Believe me to be dear Sir | Yours faithfly | J Innes Rogers <lb/></p>
                    <p> 〈Fra〉ncis Darwin Esq.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘On causes of movements in Mimosa’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>
        </div>
            
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">Francis’s lecture was given at the London Institution on 11 March 1878, and published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 14 March 1878, pp. 388–91, and 21 March 1878, pp. 411–14 (F. Darwin 1878c). He described the sleep of leaves in <hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi>, remarking, ‘no satisfactory explanation of the use which the movements are to the plant has ever been given’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 413).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1458.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi> 2d ed.</ref></note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi> is the genus of sensitive plants; most of CD’s experiments for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref> were performed on <hi rend="italic">M. pudica</hi> (shame plant), which, like many species of <hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi>, has stipular thorns along its branches. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3058.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Irwin Lynch</ref> had described the plant as highly sensitive to mechanical irritation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11118.xml">first letter from R. I. Lynch, [before 28 July 1877]</ref>); however, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 127, CD remarked that the cotyledons were less sensitive to touch than those of other plants he observed.</note> 
                <note xml:id="foot.f4"> <hi rend="italic">Desmodium gyrans</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Codariocalyx motorius</hi> (telegraph or semaphore plant); CD discussed its circumnutation and nyctitropic movements in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, pp. 357–65.</note>
            </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>