<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2998">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   26 November [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3525</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2998 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2998.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2998.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 186</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 34;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 353</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 496</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (27)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>27</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-11-26">26 Nov [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has reread AG’s third <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> article. It is admirable, but CD cannot go as far as AG on design.</p>  
<p>Mentions other opinions and reviews of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p>  
<p>Relates some experiments on <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> showing its extreme sensitivity; requests some observations on orchids.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Drosera</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Atlantic Monthly</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1860a</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">instructions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent.</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My dear Gray.</p>
<p>I have to thank you for two letters.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The latter with corrections, written before you received my letter asking for an American Reprint &amp; saying that it was hopeless to print your Reviews as a pamphlet, owing to impossibility of getting pamphlets known.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am very glad to say that the August or second Atlantic Article has been reprinted in Annals &amp; Mag of N. History;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> but I have not yet seen it there.</p>
<p>Yesterday I read over with care the third Article;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; it seems to me, as before, <hi rend="underline">admirable</hi>. But I grieve to say that I cannot honestly go as far as you do about Design. I am conscious that I am in an utterly hopeless muddle. I cannot think that the world, as we see it, is the result of chance; &amp; yet I cannot look at each separate thing as the result of Design.—   To take a crucial example, you lead me to infer (p. 414) that you believe “that variation has been led along certain beneficial lines”.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I cannot believe this; &amp; I think you would have to believe, that the tail of the Fan-tail was led to vary in the number &amp; direction of its feathers in order to gratify the caprice of a few men. Yet if the fan-tail had been a wild bird &amp; had used its abnormal tail for some special end, as to sail before the wind, unlike other birds, everyone would have said what beautiful &amp; designed adaptation. Again I say I am, &amp; shall ever remain, in a hopeless muddle.—</p>
<p>Thank you much for Bowen’s 4<hi rend="superscript">to</hi> Review.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The coolness with which he makes all animals to be destitute of reason is simply absurd. It is monstrous at p. 103, that he should argue against the possibility of accumulative variation &amp; actually leaves out entirely Selection!<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The chance that an improved Short-Horn, or improved Pouter-pigeon should be produced by accumulative variation, without Man’s selection is as almost infinity to nothing; so with natural species without natural selection. How capitally in the Atlantic, you show that Geology &amp; Astronomy are according to Bowen Metaphysics;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> but he leaves out this rubbish in the 4<hi rend="superscript">to</hi>. Memoir.—</p>
<p>I have not much to tell you about my Book.—   I have just heard that Dubois Reymond agrees with me.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> The sale of my Book goes on well, &amp; the multitude of Reviews has not stopped the sale. Murray sold a few days ago at his sale 700 copies; &amp; he has not half; so I must begin at once on new corrected Edition.—   I will send you a copy; for chance of your ever rereading; but good Heavens how sick you must be of it.—</p>
<p>Hooker has returned “rosy fat &amp; jolly”, I am glad to say; but I have not seen him &amp; not heard much news; except that he found traces of Glacial action on Lebanon.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I have gone on working at Drosera, but shall not publish till next summer, as I am frightened at my results &amp; must retest them; (By the way I have been rereading in consequence some part of your Lesson in Botany,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> &amp; have been so much pleased with the extremely clear way you put things), but you may rely on the truth of the fact that the <hi rend="underline">prolonged</hi> weight of an innutritious atom, placed with all care on <hi rend="underline">one</hi> of the glands, though it weighed only <hi rend="superscript">1/78,000</hi> of one grain caused conspicuous movement. I got the weight by weighing a length of fine hair &amp; cutting off atoms &amp; measuring them with micrometer. This weight is 78 times less than that with which best balance will turn with; &amp; yet you may rely on it, this suffices to start the movement. Moreover it produces such changes within the cells of the glandular hairs; that an hour after weight had been put on, I could distinguish which hair had carried this fairy weight from all the other 100 &amp; more hairs on the leaf.—</p>
<p>I suppose in summer you take walks in the country: I see in your Flora, you say that Apocynum androsæmifolium is common &amp; another species.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Will you observe whether the flowers of both species catch numbers of flies by their probosces, as the former does in England. <hi rend="underline">And whether Bees visit the flowers</hi>. I mean to get this plant, if I can, &amp; observe it; as a Boy I was surprised at number of flies captured.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Please make a memorandum about this plant &amp; <hi rend="doubleUnderline">the Spiranthes</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>My daughter improves very slowly &amp; I have now the heart to work again nearly as hard (strictly as lightly) as I ever can.—</p>
<p>My dear Gray | Ever yours most truly | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Have you read Olmsted Journey in the Back Country; what a remarkably interesting Book.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 asking … Reprint &amp;] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.4 very] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.1 over] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘over’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.4 The chance] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘It would be’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.4 corrected] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.4 I will … of it.—- 4.6] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.8 the glands] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">5.8 of one grain] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">5.11 that with which] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">5.14 100 &amp; more hairs] ‘hairs’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">6.3 the flowers of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">6.5 it;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon altered from colon</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">7.2 (strictly as lightly)] <hi rend="italic">parentheses over commas</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to reprinting the second part of [Gray] 1860b (see n. 4, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Neither of Gray’s letters has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-2969.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to Asa Gray, 31 October [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to the second part of Gray’s review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> published in the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> ([Gray] 1860b, pp. 229–39). On CD’s recommendation, it was published in the <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</hi> 3d ser. 6 (1860): 373–86. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2930.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 26 September [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD received the third part of the article ([Gray] 1860b, pp. 406–25) in September. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2930.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 26 September [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD annotated this passage ([Gray] 1860b, p. 414) in his copy of the paper (Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL): ‘Look at variation in domestic productions leading to all sorts of mutations. Fantail    Pouter’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_825.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bowen 1860b</ref>. There is an annotated copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_566.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Bowen</ref> stated that CD’s theory was unphilosophic in its dependence on accidental variations. In his copy of the paper, CD wrote (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_825.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bowen 1860b</ref>, p. 103): ‘<hi rend="italic">Without selection</hi> it is fatal.’ At the top of the page, he added: ‘The chance of an improved Short-Horn being produced by accumulative variation, without man’s selection, is as nothing, so with species <hi rend="italic">not</hi> acted on by natural selection’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The third part of [Gray] 1860b, pp. 406–25, included a critique of an earlier review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> by Bowen ([Bowen] 1860a). The point mentioned by CD is in [Gray] 1860b, p. 419.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Emil Heinrich Du Bois-Reymond. According to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2986.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 16 November [1860]</ref>, CD had learned about Du Bois-Reymond’s favourable opinion from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2392.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Horner</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD learned of the find in a letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> passed on to CD by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2972.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 1 November [1860]</ref>). CD added a sentence to the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> describing Hooker’s assessment of evidence of glaciation in the Lebanon mountains (Peckham ed. 1959, pp. 591–2). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2972.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 1 November [1860]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Gray 1857. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Gray 1856, p. 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD remembered the plant growing in the garden of his father, Robert Waring Darwin; he had ascertained its name by questioning <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref>. See letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 November [1860]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2987.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[21 November 1860]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2995A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Daniel Oliver, 23 November 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">CD had sent Gray a memorandum outlining observations he hoped Gray would make on the American species of the orchid genus <hi rend="italic">Spiranthes</hi>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2969.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 31 October [1860]</ref> and the enclosure.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">CD had read <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3592.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick Law Olmsted’s</ref> two previous books about his tours through the slave states of America with great interest, remarking that <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5993.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Olmsted 1856</ref> was ‘excellent’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV, 128: 23, 25). Olmsted’s third book, <hi rend="italic">A journey in the back country</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5995.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Olmsted 1860</ref>), chronicled Olmsted’s travels from New Orleans to Richmond, Virginia. Many believed it to be an unbiased and accurate picture of conditions in the South. Gray knew Olmsted, having met him in England in 1850 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, p. 192).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>