<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-490">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Emma Wedgwood   [20–1 January 1839]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5189</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-490 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-490.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-490.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">22 JA 22 1839</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 161</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 161</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Wedgwood, Emma</persName>
                <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1839-01-20" notAfter="1839-01-21">[20–1 Jan 1839]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Preparations for the wedding, various callers, and other bits of news.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1211">Darwins</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">wedding</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I sat growling &amp; shivering over the fire most of the day on Friday making “pillow cases” &amp; such like &amp; yesterday I was very poorly in myself not I am sorry to say with grief at parting with you, but all owing to that horrid little bit of stewed beef we had on Thursday &amp; again on Friday &amp; half poisoned two or three of us. So I was rather grieved to receive a call from Mrs Butt &amp; Miss Edwards who were very friendly &amp; gracious &amp; always take me in to believe it all when I am with them. Jos came on Friday in his way to Shrewsbury &amp; had heard from Caroline a very good account of the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>&amp; the baby. No news from the Langtons yet which is vexatious. I am longing to see dear old Charlotte</p>
<p>Yesterday Eliz. went to Seabridge dined there &amp; came home in the evening. I have not been able to catch her in a reflecting mood, to make y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> observation but she told me a fact which I think quite worthy to go down in your book along with the baby’s nods &amp; winks<ref target="#foot.f1"/> viz. that when she coughs very sharply in the dark sparks come out of her eyes as if she had received a blow. What are you doing today my dear old soul. Thinking of me I hope, at any rate wishing yourself well out of the scrape. It is a very fine day today, which piece of information I think the more worth giving as I am sure you will not find it out for yourself. I have no more to say so I will put by my letter &amp; then perhaps you will like to hear what sort of a day it is tomorrow.</p>
<p>Monday Are not you pleased at the frost going &amp; the canal being open. Today the Miss Northens are coming very early &amp; I shall have to do a prodigious quantity of friendship with Ellen who <hi rend="underline">adores </hi> me extremely &amp; will want to know all about every thing &amp; my chief aim will be to tell her nothing about any thing. I shall treat her like your sisters do the Owens pretend to be very open &amp; carefully never tell anything. I like her very much however, &amp; she is very superior to the rest of the family. This last week does feel so odd &amp; yet sometimes I think I must be very unfeeling not to mind leaving home &amp; these dear ones more than I do. Caroline Tollet sends word that she wishes to attend the wedding &amp; that they would come on the Tuesday morning supposing there was no bed for her, but we shall manage to find one. The Aclands insist upon having a better account of the wedding than the one I gave Ellen which is very unreasonable so I shall ask Mrs Frank<ref target="#foot.f2"/> to write to them after it is over &amp; I am sure she will do every justice to the subject. I dont believe you read any of Lambs<ref target="#foot.f3"/> letters. Have you read the poor lady’s travels by the railroad in Belgium in the last Athenæum<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>for once I found the Ath. entertaining. The description of the whirling along is very good.</p>
<p>Goodbye my dear dear Charley yours Emma W.</p>
<p>I shall be very glad to have your letter.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In July 1838 CD had started a separate notebook, ‘Metaphysics on Morals &amp; Speculations on Expression’. This (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5910.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebook M</hi></ref>) was continued in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebook N</hi></ref> during 1839. The baby was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hensleigh Wedgwood’s</ref> son Ernest, born in 1838 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebook N</hi></ref>: 37). When his own son William was born in December 1839, CD began to keep systematic notes on the child’s development (DAR 210.17) which he later summarised and published as <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘A biographical sketch of an infant’</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi> 2 (1877): 285–94 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers </hi></ref> 2: 191–200). His interest in the expression of the emotions, which continued for more than thirty years, led to the publication of his book on the subject in 1872.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Frances Mosley Wedgwood, wife of Francis (Frank) Wedgwood.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7618.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Talfourd 1837</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3745.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hood 1839</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>