<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6742">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. C. Tait   10 May 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10914</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6742 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6742.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6742.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 58.1: 19–20, DAR 178: 47</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 47</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4655.xml">Tait, W. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Oporto</placeName>
                <date when="1869-05-10">10 May 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Development of the horns of local sheep.</p>
            <p>Results of breeding tailless pointers: of six puppies, three had stumps like parents.</p> 
<p>Observations on <hi rend="italic">Drosophyllum</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pointers</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sheep</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Drosophyllum</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Oporto</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Oporto</placeName>
                    <date>May 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1869.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Charles Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was sorry to see from your letter of the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. ult<hi rend="superscript">mo</hi>. that you had met with an accident and hope that ere this you have quite recovered from its effects.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I have received the “Fertilization of Orchids” and pamphlet on climbing plants and am very much obliged indeed to you for them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have looked into them here and there and find them very interesting   I hope soon to read them attentively   such subjects as these make me feel inclined to study botany— Curiously I yesterday afternoon when out for a walk found an orchis (of what species I do not know) which practically illustrated the mode of adhesion of the pollinia— How curious that a vegetable should be dependant on an animal— I suspect that many other instances will be discovered—</p>
<p>With respect to sheep I have written to a Portuguese agricultural periodical without as yet having received any answer regarding the rate of development of their horns.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I have examined a few sheep on the Candal side of the river Douro<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and found the rams horned and some of the ewes had very small and shrivelled horns of about an inch or two in length—</p>
<p>Another shewed only two white spots where the horns usually spring from and some did not seem to shew signs of horns—</p>
<p>I shall not relinquish the subject until I get the opinion of experienced people—</p>
<p>I suppose you are trying to prove the elimination under domestication of the horns in the ewes of the merino breed— I think the effect of the pasturage should always be kept in view— We see the effect of soil on the vine for Port Wine cannot be produced at Oporto even with the proper vine but only (as yet) in a certain district in the neighbourhood of Regoa and Lamego—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Tail-less Dogs</hi>— My pointer bitch only brought forth 6 pup 3 of them have stumps of tails like the father and mother two have <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of a tail and another an apparently entire tail— 5 were dogs and one with <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of tail was the only bitch. Here we have a new breed of dog! I do not know how I am to prove that it proceeds from mutilation with inheritance but the length of the stump seems to make it somewhat probable—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I have examined minutely with glasses of different powers the Drosophyllum Lusitanicum but cannot see any motion—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>The purple disc on the top of the pedicle seems to become darker after an insect has clung to it for some time and they also appear drier   the liquid forms into white crystals. Three of the flowers have not come to maturity and one of the two remaining plants seems to be drying but we have really had such shockingly bad weather that all plants seem to have suffered—</p>
<p>The glands on the flowers differ somewhat from those on the leaves looking more like vegetable hairs—</p>
<p>It would be interesting to know whether the plants cross through <hi rend="underline">insect</hi> agency   I should think it scarcely possible and a curious paradox. Also whether the plant can exist without insect food or be proved to be another plant dependant on animal life.</p>
<p>I beg to enclose Brotero’s description of the plant which may prove useful to you.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> There is a kind of beetle which swarms on flowers and may carry pollen about whilst feeding on some other part of the flower—</p>
<p>I am dear Sir | Yours very truly | William C. Tait.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f9"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
              
<p>Description of Drosophyllum Lusitanicum from Brotero’s Flora Lusitanica page 215.</p>
<p>“4 Spergula droseroides.</p>
<p>S Radice caulescenti: caulibus superne ramosis; foliis subulatis, carinatis, apice spiraliter tortis, pilsis, pilis rorido-glandulosis: seminibus pedicellatis</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Lusit</hi> Herva Pinheira orvalhada</p>
<p>Drosera Lusitanica Linn.</p>
<p>Chamaeleontioides. Grisl Vir Lusit<ref target="#foot.f10"/> N 1351.</p>
<p>(Grisleyus in Virid Lusit nonnumquam eandem unicam plantam sub duplice nomine indicavit sic Apium hortense, Seleri dictum N 122 Seleri, sive Apium palustre sativum N 1309.</p>
<p>Quibus ambobus denotare voluit, Apium graveolens Linn var <figure type="inlinediagram"/></p>
<p>symbol )</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Hab.</hi> in Sabulosis aridis trans Tagum circa Seixal et Arrentella, circa Torres Vedras, Montejunto, Chaõ de Maçãas, Redinha, et alibi in collibus siccis ex Olisipone usque Aveiro ad quinque leucas ab Oceani littoribus   Fl æstate Perenn et quasi suffrutex.</p>
<p>Radix perennis, ramosa, superne crassitudine pennæ anserinæ, sensim quotannis extus terram sese erigens, seu duas ad quatuor uncias caulescens, foliis emortuis superne cincta: ibi nova folia, quasi ut in Palmis, progerminant, cum ad terram nulla, nisi á seminibus germinatione anno primo. Caulis in ætate plantæ tenera unicus, postea duo tres quatuorve ex apice radicis caulescentis, semipedales aut paulo altiores, teretes, paucifolia, erecti, superne ramosi, ramis alternis, erectis, unifloris, inferioribus sæpe altioribus, omnibus, uti caulio, pilosis, pilis apice capitato-glandulosis succumque glutinosum exsudantibus. Folia radicalia, et quæ in apice radicis caulescentis, in orbem congesta, erectiuscula, caule paulo breviora, subulata, carinata, super planiuscula apice spiraliter retorta, ad oras præsertim piloso glandulosa: caulina similia, alternum sursum versus caulis apicem sensim breviora. Flores quatuor ad septem, caulem et ramos terminantes. Calyx pentaphyllus, foliolis ovato-lanceolatis, acuminatis, intus glabris, extus ad oras piloso-glandulosis, corolla brevioribus.</p>
<p>Corolla petula lutea obovata.</p>
<p>Stamina constanter decem. Pistilla quinque   Capsula calyce fere duplo longior, glabra, glabra, unilocularis, quinquevalvis, valvis ovato-lanceolatis. Semina conica unam lineam longa, nigricantia, basi lata subconcava, ibique in media umbilicata, decem ad duodecem, nonnulla abortientia, omnia in fundo capsulæ, singulaque pedicello parvo imposita. Integumenta duo, membranacea.</p>
<p>Albumen semini conforme, sordide albidum, cartilagineum, apice ubi embryo, excavatum, Embryo inversus, minutus, albus, conicus, in apice angusto et excavato albuminis sedens— Cotyledones obovatæ, crassæ, hinc ad plumulum subconcavæ, inde convexæ. Plumula conica, alba, apice bifida, cotyledonibus dimidio brevior: radicula brevissima, acutiuscula.</p>
<p>Planta, carpologice considerata, sui generis; fructus enim nec Droseræ nec Spergulæ: loco tamen habitationibus sabuloso et arido, caule ramoso et foliato, numeroque staminum perpenso, potiori jure Spergulis, quam Droseris eam associandam esse, maxime in tyronum commoditatem, crediti. Succus glandularum papyrum colore saturate purpureo tingit.’</p> 
<table>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left">Portuguese names—</cell>
            <cell rend="left">Pinheiro moncoso</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">Caça <hi rend="italic">[</hi>moscas<hi rend="italic">]</hi></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">Herva dos <hi rend="italic">[</hi>Impigemo<hi rend="italic">]</hi></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell rend="left">Herva Pinheira Orvalhada</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. C. Tait, 18 April [1869]</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6705.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. C. Tait, 18 April [1869]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6644.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. C. Tait, 5 March 1869</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Douro (Spanish ‘Duero’) river flows from north central Spain into Portugal to the Atlantic Ocean at Oporto. Candal is a suburb of Oporto on the left bank of the Douro.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Regoa (now Peso da Régua) and Lamego are towns on the Douro river in the centre of the port wine grape growing region of Portugal.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See letters from W. C. Tait, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6577.xml" resp="#automat">26 January 1869</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6623.xml" resp="#automat">19 February 1869</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. C. Tait, 24 February 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Tait had sent CD specimens of <hi rend="italic">Drosophyllum lusitanicum</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6644.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. C. Tait, 5 March 1869</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Drosera lusitanica</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Drosophyllum lusitanicum</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Tait refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Félix de Avellar Brotero</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Brotero 1804</ref>, 2: 215–17. Aside from minor errors, Tait’s transcription of Brotero’s diagnosis is correct.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For a translation of the Latin part of the enclosure, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3151.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Grisley [1661]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>