<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7775">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From V. O. Kovalevsky   28 May [1871]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17790</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7775 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7775.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7775.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 63</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 63</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2751.xml">Kovalevsky, V. O.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1871-05-28">28 May [1871]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on the wholesale murder in Paris.</p>
            <p>His wife, Sofya Kovalevsky, is working for her examinations.</p>
            <p>VOK is studying embryology.</p>
            <p>Alexander has left Suez and is now in Jaffa.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2749">Kovalevsky, A. O.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2750">Kovalevsky, Sophie</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Jaffa</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Paris</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Suez</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">murder</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">examinations</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin Georgenstrasse 7.</placeName>
                    <date>28 May</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I got the small book of Körte and mustered it through without finding anything that could be of interest or use for You, but to clear all doubts, I send the volume to You that You may judje by Your own eyes.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The book is from the Royal library and if possibly it should be returned in two weeks. You said quite true in Your last letter about the strange life we led these five months, and really we have seen much not to be forgotten. The end is more terrible I could ever think, and the wholesale murders going now in Paris are heartrending.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Many of our friends are no more and the brave Docteur Parisel who opened for me all the Collections and gave full liberty for studying the palaeontological treasures of the Ecole des Mines is shot by order of some scoundrel as Gallifet or the like.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Really I think that the Indian thugs were pleasant and tenderhearted people, if we compare them with what is known in all countries under the name of “friends of Order”. Have You read the circular of Favre, do You think possible that England shall deliver the few who escaped to be murdered by Picard &amp; C<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>, I hope not, it would be an eternal shame.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The events are so dreadful that they must disgust every man from politics,—nearly 40,000 perishing for the wish to have their own Lord Mayor and Aldermens as You have in London, and as every small town have them in Germany; this and the absence of troops of the line from the city were the only wishes of the working population of Paris.</p>
<p>I am very busy now at Embryology and hope to finish it till August and then go to England for three months to see You and work in the London collections.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If I am ready with my general studies I have an idea of a special investigation on which I should like very much to consult You, but I leave this matter till I shall be so happy as to see You personally and speak about it. I dont know did my brother anything about Your Queries, he leaved Suez two weeks ago and is now at Jaffa.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> My wife is working very hard and hopes to pass her examination this winter, the Parisian events robbed us of a precious time and peace of mind indispensable for serious study.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>With compliments to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Darwin and the ladies<ref target="#foot.f9"/> | I am | Yours very truly | W. Kowalevsky</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to V. O. Kovalevsky, 3 May 1871</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had requested a translation of a passage in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Körte 1829</ref>; however, the short title that CD gave to Kovalevsky corresponded to another work by Körte (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4454.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Körte 1828</ref>), and this is apparently the volume that Kovalevsky sent. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to V. O. Kovalevsky, 3 May 1871</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Kovalevsky refers to the fighting that had broken out in Paris following the defeat of France in the Franco-Prussian war. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7752.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 10 May 1871</ref> and n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6477.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">François Parisel</ref> served on a scientific delegation to the Paris Commune; he was sentenced to death but escaped to England (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupont 1999</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5622.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gaston Alexandre Auguste</ref>, marquis de Galliffet, was a French general who played a leading role in the suppression of the Paris Commune in May 1871 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tombs 1981</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Jules Claude Gabriel Favre and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6531.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Joseph Ernest Picard</ref> were both ministers for the French provisional government (known as the Government of National Defence) during the Franco-Prussian war (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DBF</hi></ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>). Favre’s circular identifying the French ‘insurgents’ as criminals, and calling for their immediate arrest and extradition, was reported in <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 29 May 1871, p. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Kovalevsky visited Down House on 15 October 1871 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7583.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 14 March 1871</ref> and n. 3. Kovalevsky’s brother was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Onufrievich Kovalevsky</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Kovalevsky’s wife, Sofia Vasilyevna Kovalevskaya, was studying mathematics in Berlin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koblitz 1983</ref>, pp. 100–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Kovalevsky refers to Emma, Henrietta Emma, and Elizabeth Darwin.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>