<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6686">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Armand de Quatrefages<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   29 March 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10343</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6686 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6686.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6686.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 175: 5</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>175: 5</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3892.xml">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1869-03-29">29 Mar 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on their differences regarding evolution. Acknowledges that CD alone has produced an evolutionary theory that is scientific and all-embracing. Appreciates grandeur of CD’s work.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_839">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-05-04" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-24" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes">Addition to n. 2; minor change within n. 2</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00015_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00015_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="5:1r" xml:id="i15">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00015.jpg" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00015_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00015.dzi" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="5:1v" xml:id="i16">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00016.jpg" width="3799px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00016_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00016.dzi" width="3799px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="5:2r" xml:id="i17">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00017.jpg" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00017_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00017.dzi" width="3977px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="5:2v" xml:id="i18">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00018.jpg" width="3799px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00018_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3799px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00175-000-00018.dzi" width="3799px" height="6294px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>29 Mars 69</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Confrere</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je voulais ne répondre à votre lettre que lorsque j’aurais eu le plaisir de voir M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> votre fils.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Mais il parait que le destin ne veut pas que j’aie ce plaisir. Il est venu deux fois chez moi, je suis allé deux fois chez lui, toujours sans que nous nous soyons rencontrés. Et pourtant je passe des trois mois entiers sans sortir si ce n’est pour aller à l’Institut au le soir.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> J’espère que je finirai par être plus heureux et que j’aurai le plaisir de faire sa connaissance un de ces jours.</p>
<p>Je vous remercie de la manière dont vous avez apprécié mes études sur votre théorie. Il m’était devenu impossible de ne pas entreprendre cette discussion. Au nom du transformisme en général, au nom de vos idées en particulier, je voyais chaque jour attaquer et représenter comme des vieilleries usées, ce que je regarde précisément comme les fondements des Sciences naturelles. J’avais été souvent personnellement désigné comme un homme arrièré et qui fermait volontairement les yeux aux progrès de la Science.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> J’ai donc été obligé de me défendre. A mon tour, j’ai du discuter les théories qu’on m’opposait. Vous êtes incontestablement le chef de toutes les théories transformistes, le seul qui ayez proposé une théorie fondée uniquement sur des considérations scientifiques et embrassant l’ensemble des problêmes posés par la nature vivante. C’est donc avec vous que j’avais surtout à lutter. J’ai fait mon possible pour montrer que la raison scientifique est de mon coté. Mais j’espère n’avoir jamais méconnu la grandeur de votre œuvre, et en terminant cette longue etude dans un dernier article qui paraitra le 1<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> Avril, j’ai été heureux d’exprimer publiquement toute l’estime que je porte en vous à l’homme et au savant— Dès que j’aurai reçu mes <hi rend="underline">tirés-à-pàrt</hi> le premier exemplaire vous sera envoyé.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je profite de l’occasion pour vous exprimer mes regrets au sujet d’une inexactitude qui s’est glissée dans mon troisieme article.— En examinant ce que vous dites de la <hi rend="underline">mesange</hi> et du <hi rend="underline">casse-noix</hi> dans votre livre sur l’espèce, j’avais mis une note dans la quelle je faisais remarquer que vous ne parliez pas précisément d’une généalogie; que vous n’affirmiez rien positivement. Cette note a disparu à l’impression définitive avec beaucoup d’autres. Probablement des arrangements typographiques auront été cause de sa disparition. Elle sera rétablie dans l’édition en volume qui sera faite de mes articles Mais je tiens à vous dire dès à présent que je ne suis pas coupable du fait.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>J’espère bien, Monsieur et cher confrere, que des dissidences d’opinion n’altereront jamais nos relations. C’est dans cet espoir que je vous prie d’agréer l’expression de mes sentiments les plus cordialement dévoués | De Quatrefages</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName>Paris</placeName>
        <date>29 March 69</date>
        <salute>My dear Colleague</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>I wanted to put off replying to your letter until after I had had the pleasure of seeing your son.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But it seems that fate does not want me to have that pleasure. He came twice to my house and I went twice to his, without our ever meeting each other. And yet for three months in a row I do not go out except to visit the Institute in the evenings.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I hope that I shall end by being more fortunate and that I shall have the pleasure of making his acquaintance one of these days.</p> 
        <p>I must thank you for the way in which you have appreciated my studies concerning your theory. It had become impossible for me not to undertake this discussion. In the name of transformism in general, in the name of your ideas in particular, I saw what I regarded as the very foundations of the natural sciences attacked every day and represented as outworn ideas. I have often personally been pointed out as a man behind the times, wilfully shutting his eyes to scientific progress.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> So I was obliged to defend myself. In my turn, I had to discuss the theories with which I was being opposed.  You are incontestably the leader of all transformist theories, the only person to have proposed a theory founded solely on scientific considerations and embracing all the problems posed by living nature. So I had to combat you above all. I did what I could to show that scientific reason is on my side. But I hope that I have never failed to recognise the greatness of your work, and on completing this lengthy study with one final article, which is due to appear on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of April, I was happy to express publicly all my esteem for you as a man and a man of science— As soon as I have received my <hi rend="underline">offprints</hi> the first copy shall be sent to you.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
        <p>I shall take the opportunity to express my regrets about an inaccuracy that has crept into my third article.— In examining what you say concerning the <hi rend="underline">titmouse</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">nuthatch</hi> in your book on species, I had added a note in which I drew attention to the fact that you were not precisely speaking of a genealogy; that you were not affirming anything positively. This note vanished in the final printing along with many others. Probably some  typographical arrangement was the cause of its disappearance. It will be restored in the book edition in which these articles are due to appear But I am anxious to let you know at this point that I am not guilty of the matter.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
        <p>I dearly hope, dear Sir and colleague, that schisms of opinion will never affect our relationship. It is in that hope that I beg you to accept my most cordial and devoted regards | De Quatrefages</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 162–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 30, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6645F.xml">letter to Armand de Quatrefages, 6 March 1869</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> planned to travel to Paris on 5 March 1869 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6636.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. H. Darwin, [23 February 1869]</ref> and n. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Quatrefages refers to the Institut de France. The institute was the home of five learned societies, including the Académie des Sciences, of which Quatrefages was a member (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For more on the French debates over transformism, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1547.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Conry 1974</ref>, pp. 359–92. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6088.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Camille Dareste, 3 April 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Quatrefages later sent CD an offprint of a series of five articles he had written for the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> between December 1868 and April 1869, ‘Origines des espèces animales et végétales’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1868–9</ref>). CD’s annotated copy of the offprint is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1868–9</ref>, p. 63, Quatrefages had questioned whether CD had demonstrated that the nuthatch was the ‘grandson’ of the titmouse. When Quatrefages later published a book based on these articles, a note was added giving a reference to the section of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> where CD had commented on the titmouse and nuthatch (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 281), but there was no mention in the note that CD had not, in fact, suggested a genealogical connection between these species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages 1870</ref>, p. 156).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>