<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8808">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Otto Caspari   12 March 1873<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16388</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8808 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8808.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8808.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 117</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 117</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_851.xml">Caspari, Otto</persName>
                <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                <date when="1873-03-12">12 Mar 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends CD a copy of his book [<hi rend="italic">Die Urgeschichte der Menschheit</hi>, 2 vols. (1873)].</p> 
            <p>In Germany CD’s views have achieved great recognition among naturalists, but in other disciplines there is great controversy. OC’s book seeks to resolve the controversy by showing how state, morals, religion, and church have developed from natural beginnings.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die Urgeschichte der Menschheit</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Caspari, Otto 1873</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#religious_beliefs">Religious Beliefs</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                    <date>d. 12 Maerz 73.</date>
                    <salute>Sehr hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Das Werk welches ich Ihnen hiermit durch die Ihnen sehr wohlbekannte Verlagsfirma F. A. Brockhaus zu Leipzig zugehen lasse und von mir im Laufe der letzten Jahre ausgearbeitet wurde, ist dem Versuche gewidmet die von Ihnen so geistvoll vertretene Descendenztheorie auf das Gebiet des menschlichen Geisteslebens zu übertragen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Da Sie sehr hochgeehrter Herr der deutschen Sprache wie ich höre mächtig sind, so darf ich wohl hoffen, dass Sie dieser Arbeit, die sich so iig mit Ihren eigenen Bestrebungen berührt, ein aufmerksames Studium widmen. In Deutschland sind, wie Sie aus meiner Arbeit ersehen Ihre Anschauungen zu einer hohen Anerkennung gelangt unter den Naturforschern; aber unter den Geistern anderer Wissenschaften ist grosser Streit entbrannt.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Diesen Streit zu schlichten habe ich dieses Buch geschrieben. Ich gehe aus von Ihren Gesichtspuncten und zeige bis in’s Einzelne wie sich folgerichtig Staat, Moral Religion und Kirche aus natürlichen Anfängen entwickelt haben.</p>
<p>Indem ich Ihnen dieses Werk freudigen Herzens mit seinen Resultaten unterbreite, lebe ich der Hoffnung, dass Sie die Gelegenheit nicht vorübergehen lassen werden sich über dasselbe in seinen Bemühungen öffentlich auszusprechen, vielleicht auch für eine Übersetzung in’s Englische einen tüchtigen Gewährsmann nachzuweisen im Stande sind.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Mit dem freundlichsten Grusse und in wissenschaftlicher Gesiungsgemeinschaft | zeichne hochachtungsvoll | Otto Caspari. | Verfasser beiliegenden Werkes | u. Docent an der Universitaet | zu Heidelberg.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                    <date>12 March 73.</date>
                    <salute>Highly honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The work which I am having sent to you by the well-known publishing house of F.A. Brockhaus of Leipzig, and which was completed by me in the course of the past few years, is an attempt to apply the theory of descent so brilliantly advocated by you to the realm of human mental life.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Since I hear that you, most honoured Sir, have command of German, I venture to hope that you will attentively study this work, which so closely converges with your own endeavours. In Germany, as you can see from my work, your views have won considerable recognition among natural scientists; but great controversy divides minds within other sciences.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have written my book to settle this controversy. I proceed from your viewpoint and show in detail how the state, morality, religion and the church have developed logically from natural origins.</p>
<p>In joyfully presenting this work with its results to you, I live in the hope that you will not forego the opportunity to discuss its merits in public, and that you will perhaps even be able to direct me to a capable authority for a translation into English.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>With the kindest greetings and in scientific fellowship | I sign with my highest respect | Otto Caspari. | author of the enclosed work | and teacher at the university | of Heidelberg.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 122–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s copy of Caspari’s book on human prehistory and the evolution of mind (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1303.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Caspari 1873</ref>) is in the Darwin Library–Down; it is not annotated and some of the pages are uncut (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 160). The firm F. A. Brockhaus was well known for publishing dictionaries and encyclopaedias (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8527.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Würffel 2000</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Two editions of the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> had already appeared (Carus trans. 1871 and Carus trans. 1871–2); on its reception in Germany, see Backenköler 2008, pp. 111–15.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">No English translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1303.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Caspari 1873</ref> was made.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>