<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6425">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Karl von Scherzer   20 October 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10631</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6425 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6425.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6425.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 50</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 50</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4206.xml">Scherzer, Karl von</persName>
                <placeName>Ministry of Commerce, Vienna</placeName>
                <date when="1868-10-20">20 Oct 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes departure of expedition to China, Japan, and South America.</p>
            <p>Copy of CD’s queries provided to expedition.</p>
            <p>Invites CD to make suggestions for scientific work to be carried out.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, South</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">China</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Japan</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Ministry of Commerce | Vienna,</placeName>
                    <date>Octb. 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I take the liberty to inform you that the Expedition for Eastern Asia and South America has left Trieste on the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Octbr consisting of the Screw-frigate Donau (Danube) and the Screw Corvette friedrich, with together 590 men crew.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Although the principal object of the mission is a commercial one, yet I have endeavoured to make the expedition likewise as useful to science as possible and hope that we shall also gather some valuable scientific results.</p>
<p>We have with us a good Zoologist, who is sent to China and Japan to study there the sériculture and report on the condition of the silkworm in Eastern Asia—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Besides, there are three medical officers who are good botanists and one of them will take up the bodily measurements.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> We have also with us a very first rate photographer.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The Expedition will make a short stay at the Cape of Good Hope and then proceed to Singapore where I expect to meet the vessels early in february. from Singapore the vessels will continue the voyage to Bangkok, where a treaty will be negotiated with the King of Siam and then go to China and Japan.</p>
<p>When the Treaties with these two Empires have been concluded, the mission will return to Europe by the Pacific and call at the Sandwich Islands, at San francisco, Punto Arenas, Panama, Callao, Valparaiso, Montevideo and Buenos Ayres.</p>
<p>If during this cruise I should be able to become in any way serviceable to you, I beg to dispose of me freely. I shall not leave Vienna before <hi rend="underline">December</hi> as I intend to take the Overland Route &amp; I shall feel most happy to be entrusted with your Commands. I send you also a copy of the instructions for the commercial Reporters, which however contains also a number of Scientific Desiderata and to which I have added a <hi rend="underline">german</hi> translation of your own queries.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I remain | With heart and hand | your most devoted | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Scherzer.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Scherzer refers to the Austro-Hungarian East Asian expedition of 1868 to 1871. For the official report of the expedition, produced by the ministry for trade, see Scherzer ed. 1872.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6834.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Szymon Syrski’s</ref> reports on sericulture in China and Japan, see Scherzer ed. 1872, pp. 122–74, 228–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The medical officers on the <hi rend="italic">Donau</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Friedrich</hi> were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6973.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Wawra</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6991.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emanuel Weiss</ref>, and Dr Janko, who has not been further identified. Wawra and Weiss collected plants, while Janko specialised in anthropology (Scherzer ed. 1872, p. xv).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Wilhelm Burger (Scherzer ed. 1872, p. v).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The printed version of the instructions (‘Instruktionen für die fachmännischen Begleiter der k. u. k. Mission’; Scherzer ed. 1872, pp. 388–418) contained only material relevant to the commercial goals of the expedition (see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 388 n.). CD’s copy of the instructions, which evidently contained a translation of his queries on expression, has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL. For a printed version of the queries, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix V.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>