<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10820">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. B. Saint-Lager<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   30 January 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10606</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10820 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10820.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10820.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 7</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 7</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4146.xml">Saint-Lager, J. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Lyons</placeName>
                <date when="1877-01-30">30 Jan 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends CD parts of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Soc. Bot. Lyon</hi>] in response to his request for a particular article.</p> 
            <p>States that, despite CD’s work, he does not believe that any plants, including insectivorous ones, can utilise organic material, and that they live solely on mineral elements in the soil and air.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Annales Soc. Bot. Lyon</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-09-19" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2016-09-19" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00021_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00021_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="7:1r" xml:id="i21">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00021.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00021_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00021.dzi" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="7:1v" xml:id="i22">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00022.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00022_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00022.dzi" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="7:2r" xml:id="i23">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00023.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00023_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00023.dzi" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="7:2v" xml:id="i24">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00024.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00024_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00024.dzi" width="3903px" height="6417px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lyon</placeName>
                    <date>30 janvier 1877</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur et illustre Maître,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Mon ami M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mulsant m’a communiqué la lettre par laquelle vous demandez un article de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Magnin sur l’<hi rend="underline">hétérostylie chez les Primulacées</hi>, publié dans nos Annales.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Bienque l’article demandé ne soit qu’une simple note ne correspondant pas aux espérances que le titre a pu vous faire concevoir, je vous envoie les années 2 et 3 de nos Annales, regrettant de n’avoir plus d’exemplaire disponible de la 1<hi rend="superscript">ere</hi> année.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>J’ai remis à notre Collègue M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grenier de Tenay un exemplaire de la 4<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> année N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1 de nos Annales, pour vous être envoyé, et je pense qu’il vous est parvenu.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Vous y trouverez un extrait de votre admirable ouvrage <hi rend="underline">insectivorous plants</hi> dont la lecture a vivement intéressé nos Collègues, même ceux d’entre eux qui ne partagent pas vos opinions; j’ai le regret d’ajouter que je suis au nombre de ces derniers.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Je ne conteste pas que le suc visqueux excrété par les Drosera, et probablement par beaucoup d’autres plantes, ne facilite une décomposition des substances animales, à l’instar des sucs digestifs contenus dans l’estomac des animaux. Mais je crois qu’on peut faire vivre de la manière la plus prospère des <hi rend="underline">Drosera</hi> qu’on aurait soin de préserver de toute approche d’insectes et que, par conséquent, ces plantes vivent, comme toutes les autres, des éléments empruntés au sol et à l’aïr.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Grenier dit à la fin de son mémoire que vous pensez que la meilleure démonstration à l’appui de votre doctrine consisterait à cultiver deux lots de plantes à l’un desquels on fournirait des insectes.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Il me semble que cette expérience n’aurait pas la portée que vous lui attribuez; car il n’y aurait rien d’étonnant à ce que des plantes qui ont été soumises aux émanations résultant de la décomposition de matières animales reçoivent un surcroît d’activité, comme il arriverait par l’emploi d’un fumier riche en matières azotées.</p>
<p>Je crois donc que l’utilité des sucs visqueux des plantes, si toutefois elle est réelle, n’est pas encore connue, malgré vos très-intéressantes recherches, et je persiste à penser que les plantes ne vivent que de substances minérales. Les matières organiques ne sont utiles aux plantes qu’autant qu’elles sont réduites, par une décomposition avancée, à l’état d’éléments minéraux.</p>
<p>Le Végétal a pour rôle dans la nature de fabriquer des produits organiques et, comme je le dis dans un article sur l’influence chimique du sol, ce serait un cercle vicieux et une véritable anarchie s’il fallait qu’il trouve des substances organiques déjà faites pour en produire lui-même.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Je vous prie d’excuser la liberté que je prends de vous adresser mes observations, sans avoir pu y être invité par vous et malgré mon peu d’autorité. Croyez d’ailleurs à mes sentiments de vive et profonde admiration. | S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Lager<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Lyon 8 cours de Brosses.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lyon</placeName>
                    <date>30 January 1877</date>
                    <salute>Sir and illustrious master,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My friend M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mulsant has passed on your letter requesting an article by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Magnin on <hi rend="underline">hétérostylie chez les Primulacées</hi>, published in our Annales.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Although the article requested is only a simple note that does not live up to what the title may have led you to expect, I am sending you the years 2 and 3 of our Annales, with regrets that no more copies of the first year remain.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I have sent our colleague M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grenier of Tenay a copy of the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1 of our Annales, to have forwarded to you, and I think it arrived.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> You will find in it an extract from your admirable work <hi rend="underline">insectivorous plants</hi> the reading of which has greatly interested our colleagues, even among those who do not share your views; I regret to add that I am among them.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I do not argue that the viscous sap excreted by Droseras, and probably by many other plants, does not promote a decomposition of animal substances, in the manner of the digestive juices contained in the stomachs of animals. But I believe that <hi rend="underline">Drosera</hi> that have been protected from all insects can be made to thrive most favourably and that, it follows, these plants live, like all others, on elements taken from the sun and air.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Grenier says at the end of his note that you think the best demonstration in support of your doctrine would be to cultivate two sets of plants one of which would be supplied with insects.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> It seems to me that this experiment would not have the significance that you attribute to it; for there would be nothing surprising in plants which had been subjected to the products of decomposition of animal material getting an increase in activity, since it would result from the use of a manure rich in nitrogen.</p>
<p>I believe therefore that the utility of the viscous saps of plants, even if it is real, is not yet known, in spite of your very interesting research, and I continue to think that plants only live on mineral substances. Organic substances are of no use to plants unless they are reduced, by advanced decomposition, to the state of mineral elements.</p>
<p>The role of the plant kingdom in nature is to make organic products and, as I have said in an article on the chemical influence of the soil, it would be a vicious circle and veritable anarchy if it was necessary to find organic substances already made in order to produce the same.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Please forgive the liberty I take in telling you my observations, without having been asked and in spite of my meagre authority. Please believe moreover in my keen and profound admiration. | S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Lager<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Lyon 8 cours de Brosses.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7934.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Étienne Mulsant</ref> has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Antoine Magnin’s</ref> short article ‘Sur l’hétérostylie chez les Primulacées’ (On heterostyly in the Primulaceae; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10165.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Magnin 1875</ref>) was published in the third volume of <hi rend="italic">Annales de la Société botanique de Lyon</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">No copies of the journal have been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD gave <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1978.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Grenier</ref> permission to summarise <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Annales de la Société botanique de Lyon</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10212.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Louis Grenier, 22 December 1875</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Louis Grenier, 20 May 1876</ref>). Grenier’s article was read at a meeting of the society on 10 February 1876 and published in <hi rend="italic">Annales de la Société botanique de Lyon</hi> 4 (1875–6): 96–114 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8882.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Grenier 1876</ref>). The article has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Grenier translated CD’s description of the leaves of <hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> (common sundew) from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, pp. 4–5 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8882.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Grenier 1876</ref>, pp. 97–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Grenier had written to CD asking whether CD had new observations on insectivorous plants and whether CD’s theory could be tested by growing plants in a sealed container (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Louis Grenier, 20 May 1876</ref> and nn. 2 and 5). CD evidently responded in a now missing letter that a set of plants cultivated under fine netting to protect them from insects could be compared to another set exposed to insects in order to determine whether the latter set was more vigorous. Grenier presented the additional material to the botanical society on 27 July 1876, and it was added to the published version of his original resumé (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8882.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Grenier 1876</ref>, p. 114; see also <hi rend="italic">Annales de la Société botanique de Lyon</hi> 4 (1875–6): 185).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10168.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Saint-Lager 1876</ref>, p. 78.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>