<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12493">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J.-H. Fabre<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   18 February 1880</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16815</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12493 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12493.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12493.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="28">28</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 164: 2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>164: 2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1578.xml">Fabre, J.-H.</persName>
                <placeName>Sérignan, Vaucluse</placeName>
                <date when="1880-02-18">18 Feb 1880</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On instinct in insects. Intends to experiment as CD proposes.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">instinct</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-10-08" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-12-11" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2019-01-08" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-05-28" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2019-05-28" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00003_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3711px" height="6117px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00003_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3711px" height="6117px"/>
        <surface n="2:1r" xml:id="i3">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00003.jpg" width="3711px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00003_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3711px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00003.dzi" width="3711px" height="6117px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="2:1v" xml:id="i4">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00004.jpg" width="3706px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00004_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3706px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00004.dzi" width="3706px" height="6117px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="2:2r" xml:id="i5">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00005.jpg" width="3706px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00005_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3706px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00005.dzi" width="3706px" height="6117px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="2:2v" xml:id="i6">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00006.jpg" width="3665px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00006_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3665px" height="6117px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00164-000-00006.dzi" width="3665px" height="6117px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>                    
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Votre lettre a été pour moi tout à la fois une source de satisfaction et une source de regret.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>De Satisfaction, car elle m’a appris qu’au milieu du l’obscurité où m’avait plongé le texte erroné dont je disposais, la rigueur de la logique et la précision de l’expérience m’avaient néammoins conduit juste au tracés de petit drame observé par le savant Erasme Darwin.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>De regret, car elle m’a montré en quelle erreur j’etais en suivant l’auteur que je cite, l’entomologiste Lacordaire, qui a designé par le mot Sphex, la Guêpe réellement observée.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> La faute remonte plus haut que votre humble serviteur, aussi j’espère que vous voudriez bien excuser mon inadvertance.</p>
                    <p>On me parle d’une traduction Anglaise. Si cette traduction se fait, le passage erroné sera modifié en conséquence.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Toutefois la conclusion n’en restera pas moins la même. Il m’est impossible de voir le moindre indice de raison dans le fait d’un insecte qui detourné du travail instinctif qu’il fait pour prèparer le manger de ses larves, effrayé peut-être, dérangé en son oeuvre, remet pied à terre pour achever le travail interrompu.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Mon impartialité pour l’homme est encore plus vive que pour l’insecte, je négligerai donc rien, soyez en persuadé, pour réparer l’érreur commise.</p>
                    <p>Vous vous étonnez de mon peu de goût pour les théories si réduisantes qu’elles soient. Ce travers d’esprit, si c’en est un, tient un peu à mes longues études mathèmatiques qui m’ont habitué à ne reconnaitre la verité qu’à la lueur d’un irrisistible faisceau de lumière.</p> 
                    <p>Ne jurant pas aucun maître, libre d’idées préconçues, pas enclin aux séductions des théories, je cherche avec passion la vérité, prêt à admettre quelle qu’elle soit et de quelque part qu’elle vienne. Et comme moyen de recherche, je ne connais qu’une chose: l’expérience. </p>
                    <p>J’ai déjà preparé pour le mois de Mai prochain les matériaux pour l’expérimentation que vous me proposer au sujet du Insectes retournant à leurs nids. L’idée de la boîte qui tourne rapidement dans un sens puis dans l’autre, pour désorienter les insectes, me paraît fort ingénieuse, et je ne saurais trop vous remercier de me l’avoir suggérée. En temps propice, au mois de Mai prochain, je la mettrai en application; et si vous voulez bien me le permettre, je vous tiendrai au courant de mon résultats. Si je peux me procurer les appareils nécessaires, j’essaierai aussi les courants d’induction.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Parmi la population de paysans de mon village, l’habitude est de faire tourner dans un sac le chat que l’on se propose de porter ailleurs, et dont on voit empêcher le retour. J’ignore si cette pratique obtient du succès. Je l’expérimenterai à mon tour. J’ai été très frappé de voir si bien concorder l’opération que vous me proposez au sujet des insectes et la pratique des gens de la campagne dans mes environs. Cette pratique a-t-elle aussi cours en Angleterre, au sujet du chat bien entendu? Je serais bien désireux de le savoir</p>
                    <p>Je suis avec le plus profond respect | Monsieur | Votre très humble serviteur | J. H. Fabre</p>
                    <p>Sérignan (par Orange) | Vaucluse</p>
                    <p>18 Fev. 1880.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>Your letter was at the same time both a source of satisfaction and a source of regret for me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Of satisfaction, since it made me aware that in the midst of the darkness into which I had been plunged by the erroneous text, the rigour of logic and the precision of experiment led me nevertheless to discern the little drama observed by the learned Erasmus Darwin.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Of regret, because it showed me into what error I had fallen in following the author I cite, the entomologist Lacordaire, who had used the word Sphex to describe the Wasp that was actually observed.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The fault went further back than your humble servant, so I hope that you would kindly excuse my mistake.</p>
                    <p>There has been talk of an English translation. If this translation is made, the erroneous passage will be altered as a result.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Notwithstanding, the conclusion at least will remain the same. It is impossible for me to see the slightest indication of reasoning in the fact of an insect which is deterred from instinctive work that it does in preparing food for its larvae, frightened perhaps, disturbed in its work, coming back to complete the interrupted task.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>My fair-mindedness for man is even more lively than that for insects, so I will never fail, once convinced, to rectify an error I committed.</p>
                    <p>You are surprised by the lack of taste I have for theories, no matter how succint. This idiosyncrasy of intellect, if it is one, is somewhat due to my lengthy mathematical studies, which accustomed me to recognise the truth only in the gleam of an irresistible ray of light.</p> 
                    <p>Not pledged to any master, free of preconceived ideas, not subject to the seduction of theories, I search passionately for truth, ready to accept whatever it may be and wherever it may come from. And as a method of research, I recognise only one thing: experiment. </p>
                    <p>I have already prepared for the forthcoming month of May the material for the experiment that you suggested to me on the subject of Insects returning to their nests. The idea of a box rapidly spinning in one direction then another, in order to disorient the insects, seems very ingenious to me, and I could not thank you enough for having suggested it to me. At the appropriate time, next May, I will put it into practice; and if you will kindly allow me, I will keep you apprised of my results. If I can get the necessary equipment, I will also try the induction currents.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Among the peasant population of my village, it is customary to turn a cat round in a bag if one wants to take it elsewhere, and thus one looks to prevent its return. I am ignorant as to the success of the practice. I will try the experiment myself. I was really astounded to see how well the operation you propose regarding insects agrees with the practice of country folk in my neighbourhood. Does this practice also take place in England, regarding cats of course? I would very much like to know</p>
                    <p>I am with the deepest respect | Sir | Your humble servant | J. H. Fabre</p>
                    <p>Sérignan (by Orange) | Vaucluse</p>
                    <p>18 Feb. 1880.</p>
        </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 99—100.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12443.xml">letter to J.-H. Fabre, 31 January 1880</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his letter to Fabre of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12443.xml">31 January 1880</ref>, CD had pointed out  an error in Fabre’s work, <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs entomologiques</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10935.xml">Fabre 1879</ref>, p. 124), that stemmed from a mistranslation of a name in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi>; Darwin had described a wasp removing the wings of a fly (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 1: 183; see also n. 4, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Sphex</hi> is the genus of digger wasps; these wasps, unlike the common wasp that Erasmus Darwin observed (probably <hi rend="italic">Vespula vulgaris</hi>), paralyse prey but leave them alive in the nest for larvae to feed on. Common wasps, on the other hand, kill prey and have powerful mandibles for chewing (malaxation); larvae are fed the masticated prey. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2778.xml">Jean Théodore Lacordaire</ref> had discussed the case in his <hi rend="italic">Introduction à l’entomologie</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4533.xml">Lacordaire 1834–8</ref>, 2: 460–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">No translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10935.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Fabre 1879</ref> was made during CD’s lifetime; a translation appeared in 1913 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11004.xml">Fabre 1913</ref>). The original text was translated, but the error about the wasp was explained in a note (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 123). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12443.xml">letter to J.-H. Fabre, 31 January 1880</ref> and n. 2. </note>    
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12443.xml">letter to J.-H. Fabre, 31 January 1880</ref> and n. 5. </note>  
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>