<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3162">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>   [17 May 1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20102</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3162 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3162.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3162.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 42</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 129</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 151 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">J. Hortic. n.s. 1 1861: 151</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1861-05-17">[17 May 1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2615.xml">Journal of Horticulture</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks Mr Beaton for his answer [to <hi rend="doubleUnderline">3147</hi>].</p>  
<p>Asks further questions on points raised in Beaton’s previous papers: whether crossing white and blue varieties of <hi rend="italic">Anemone apennina</hi> produced many pale shades; whether the <hi rend="italic">Mathiola incana</hi> and <hi rend="italic">M. glabra</hi> which crossed freely were artificially or naturally crossed.</p> 
            <p>CD is delighted by Beaton’s assertion that "not a flower in a thousand is fertilised by its own immediate pollen".</p> 
<p>Recounts his experiments with <hi rend="italic">Leschenaultia formosa</hi> to show insect fertilisation.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">3147</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insect</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Anemone apennina</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Leschenaultia formosa</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Mathiola glabra</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Mathiola incana</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_345">Beaton, Donald</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Much obliged am I to Mr. Beaton for his very interesting answer to my question.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> When Mr. Beaton says he does “not know of an instance of the natural crossing of varieties,” I presume he intends to confine his remark to the plants of the flower garden;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> for every one knows how largely the varieties of the Cabbage cross, as is likewise the case (as I know from careful trial) with Radishes and Onions. It was this fact which led me to suppose that varieties of flower-garden plants would naturally cross.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I can quite understand, after reading Mr. Beaton’s remarks, that it would be very difficult, perhaps impossible, to detect such natural crossing from the degree to which most of these varieties vary. I should, however, think that those who raise for sale seeds of distinct varieties of the Hollyhock, Stocks, &amp;c., must know whether it is indispensable to keep the parent plants apart.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I will not trouble Mr. Beaton again if he will have the kindness to procure for me answers on one or two points quoted in his paper (June 26, 1860) from the “king of British cross-breeders”—namely, whether I understand rightly that the white <hi rend="underline">Anemone apennina</hi> seeding in a mass with the blue (<hi rend="underline">Anemone apennina?</hi>) produced many pale shades?<ref target="#foot.f6"/> For this seems to be a case of two varieties naturally crossing, though I want to know the fact for another reason—namely, because Anemone does not secrete nectar; and secondly, whether <hi rend="underline">Mathiola incana</hi> and <hi rend="underline">glabra</hi>, which the writer speaks of as “crossing freely,” were artificially crossed.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Mr. Beaton’s statement (July 24, 1860) that if the pollen of five kinds of Geranium (I presume what botanists call varieties, and not what are called species, are here referred to) are placed on the stigma of a flower, one kind alone takes the lead and produces an effect, seems to me a most curious observation. It is, I fear, unreasonable to ask for a few precise cases on this head; for, as I gather from Mr. Beaton, it must be difficult to know whether one or more kinds have produced an effect, owing to the great variability of crossed varieties.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I have been delighted to observe how strongly Mr. Beaton insists that “not a flower in a thousand is fertilised by its own immediate pollen.”<ref target="#foot.f9"/> This is a subject which I have attended to for the last twenty years.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> From my experiments on a small scale I would not venture to put the case nearly as strongly as Mr. Beaton does; but on the other hand, some of the plants which Mr. Beaton advances as self-fertilisers seem, as far as I can trust my own observations, doubtful.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I will give one instance, as it might possibly induce some one to try the experiment. <hi rend="underline">Leschenaultia formosa</hi> has apparently the most effectual contrivance to prevent the stigma of one flower ever receiving a grain of pollen from another flower; for the pollen is shed in the early bud, and is there shut up round the stigma within a cup or indusium. But some observation led me to suspect that nevertheless insect agency here comes into play; for I found by holding a camel-hair pencil parallel to the pistil, and moving it as if it were a bee going to suck the nectar, the straggling hairs of the brush opened the lip of the indusium, entered it, stirred up the pollen, and brought out some grains. I did this to five flowers and marked them. These five flowers all set pods; whereas only two other pods set on the whole plant, though covered with innumerable flowers. The seeds in these pods were bad, or else I had not skill to make them germinate.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I became so strongly convinced that insects would be found concerned in the fertilisation of these flowers, that I wrote to Mr. James Drummond, at Swan River in Australia, and asked him to watch the flowers of plants of this order; and he soon wrote to me that he had seen a bee cleverly opening the indusium and extracting pollen;<ref target="#foot.f13"/> and a bee with its mandibles thus covered with pollen would very likely effect a cross between one individual and another of the same species. I have been told that this pretty plant, the <hi rend="underline">Leschenaultia formosa</hi>, never sets seed in this country. I wish some skilful cultivator would rout up the pollen within the indusium in the manner described, and see whether he could not thus get seeds.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Charles Darwin, <hi rend="underline">Down, Bromley, Kent.</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the reference in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3151.xml" resp="#automat">letter to C. W. Crocker, 18 May [1861]</ref> to CD’s having sent this letter off to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi> ‘yesterday’. It was published in the issue of 28 May 1861 under the heading: ‘Cross-breeding in plants. Fertilisation of Leschenaultia Formosa.’ See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 42.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, [before 14 May 1861]. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_345.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Donald Beaton’s</ref> response to CD’s queries was published directly following the letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Beaton had written in response to CD’s previous letter (see n. 2, above) (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentlemman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 113): <quote type="quote"> My own experience of variable plants was given last week, and I do not exactly comprehend what is meant by natural varieties, for all the so-called varieties in cultivation have been artificially obtained either by a change of cultivation, or by crossing with pollen such kinds or species as would sport from seeds under cultivation. These kinds I call variable plants, their own progeny being constantly variable in aspect, and just as variable when the pollen of another flower is applied to them. It is a difficult thing for a gardener to see or comprehend the meaning of what botanists call varieties, or natural varieties of plants, because there is no limit, or sign, or any other indication in their outward aspect to distinguish them from the oldest species on record, and there is nothing in the botanical structure of even a variable seedling to distinguish it from a genuine species. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For CD’s efforts to ascertain information on this point through his own experiments and through queries to various botanists and practical gardeners, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 5, letters to William and Julius Fairbeard, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1467.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[October 1855 – May 1856]</ref>, and to J. S. Henslow, 10 November [1855] and 12 November 1855; and <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., vol. 6, especially <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 19 July [1856]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Beaton included hollyhocks among those plants that he called ‘fixed varieties’, ‘as gardeners say when a variable plant comes true from seeds after sporting for some years’ (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 112).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his article on begonias in the <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>, 26 June 1860, pp. 193–5, Beaton included the following statement on the authority of ‘the king of all the British cross-breeders’ (p. 194): ‘ “I have the white <hi rend="italic">Anemone apennina</hi>, which some folks do not believe in, and many pale shades from its seeding in a mass with the blue.” ’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD refers to Beaton’s statement that ‘<hi rend="italic">Mathiola incana</hi> and <hi rend="italic">glabra</hi> cross freely notwithstanding Darwin’s theory of species.’ (<hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>, 26 June 1860, p. 195). <hi rend="italic">Mathiola glabra</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">M. incana</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The reference is to Beaton’s article entitled ‘Crossing flowers’, published in the <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>, 24 July 1860, pp. 253–5, in which he disputed the scientific view of ‘superfoetation’, or the fertilisation of a plant ovary by two or more kinds of pollen. Beaton gave as a counter-example the case of fertilisation in geraniums (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 254–5): <quote type="quote"> No flower on earth is more easy to prove by if more than one pollen can influence a cross than any of the common Geraniums. Their stigma is parted into five parts, and each part rolls back from the rest, or from the centre; and there are five seeds for every flower, corresponding to the five divisions of the stigma, or mother, as we say. Now, by applying five kinds of pollen, one kind to each division of the stigma, it is easy to conceive the possibility of each seed being influenced by that pollen only which dusted its corresponding division; and if the scientific explanation of the process by which the pollen reaches the ovum, or skeleton seed, were correct, superfœtation would be inevitable, and five kinds of progeny must be obtained from that flower so operated upon. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Beaton made this statement in his article of 14 May 1861 (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 113).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See Notebook E, pp. 144, 183, and Questions &amp; experiments notebook, pp. 2, 14 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5912.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi></ref>). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-503.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from William Herbert to J. S. Henslow, 5 April 1839</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Beaton listed among those flowers ‘every one of which must, of necessity, be fertilised by its own pollen in the great majority of instances’ sweetpeas, bellworts (<hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi>), and wheat (see <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 113).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">For descriptions of CD’s experiments, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">18 [April 1860]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">26 April [1860]</ref>, and letters from J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2764.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[20 April 1860]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[28 April 1860]</ref>. The results of some of CD’s experiments on <hi rend="italic">Leschenaultia</hi> are recorded in his Experimental book (DAR 157a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1388.xml">James Drummond</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2803.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 May 1860</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">20 December [1860]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2920A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Drummond, 17 September 1860</ref>. The letter in which Drummond related this information, however, has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD himself tried the experiment again in 1862 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10). He published a short note on the topic in 1871 (see <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 9 September 1871, p. 1166; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 162–5).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>