<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6836">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Adolph Reuter   18 July 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10500</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6836 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6836.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6836.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp, encl Amem 8pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 125</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 125</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3987.xml">Reuter, Adolf</persName>
                <placeName>Sans Souci, Potsdam</placeName>
                <date when="1869-07-18">18 July 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends notes on lack of variation in seedlings of trees and shrubs</p>
            <p>and on climbers changing their character with age.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbers</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">shrubs</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">trees</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Sanssouci near Potsdam</placeName>
                    <date>the 18. 7. 1869</date>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am uncapable to express you my feeling, when I did have the honour to receive your very amiable letter and I beg your pardon, that I have retarded so long-times my answer, because one of my colleagues is dead and I am now obliged to conduct two gardens till to the next October.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I assure you my dear Sir, I am not only very glad—no I am proud indeed, that you have been so kind to give me the permission, by entering with you in correspondence and I should be only sorry when it would be seeming as when I would publish my small German knowledge— no Sir not at all, my intention is <hi rend="underline">only</hi> to send it to <hi rend="underline">you</hi>, perhaps that then one or the other object would be interesting for you and worth to find a small place in your publications.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I should be glad, when I could give you more then only some proofs of my practical experience, but you know very well, the Gardener has much business and so you may excuse me when I talk about an object not quite scientifically and sometimes also more as it would be necessary.—</p>
<p>For the first, I send you some arguments about the more or less constancy of trees and shrubs variety’s seedling’s and also some remarkable facts of some woody climbers, changing their character in an older state; with the next letter I suppose to deliver to you interesting examples; where grafted trees have changed their characteristic etc.—</p>
<p>But forgive me my very dear Sir, when I am unpolite, molesting you so long-times.—</p>
<p>I wish, that your weakness may not derange you longer and my letter may find you healthy and happy.—</p>
<p>With my greatest respects and the assurance of my attraction at all times | I am dear Sir | Your very obedient servant | Ad. Reuter</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" n="1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The <hi rend="underline">propagation</hi> by <hi rend="underline">seeds</hi> of different trees and shrubs’ <hi rend="underline">varietys</hi> and <hi rend="underline">their resultance</hi>:</p>
<p>1. <hi rend="underline">Acer Pseudoplatanus foliis variegatis</hi>: Travelling with Mr. Linné, the late Director of our Royal Gardens, I did find near Aachen (Aix-la-Chapelle) in the Garden of a medicine a very fine looking exemplar of Acer Pseudoplat. foliis variegatis.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The tree was nearly 1 foot big and the ground round the Acer covered with white spotted seedlings, what is most remarkables indeed, because the possessor did affirm me that it were the same appearance every year.</p>
<p>2. <hi rend="underline">Acer Pseudoplatanus foliis purpureis</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> which has the <hi rend="underline">under</hi> site of the leaves red coloured, exist also in our Botan. Garden at Berlin as a beautiful tree. Mr. Bouché, Inspector of the Garden, was so kind to show me last autumn some pots full of seedlings, where all the young plants did have the <hi rend="underline">same</hi> peculiarity like the <hi rend="underline">mother</hi>-tree.</p>
<p>3. <hi rend="underline">Berberis vulgaris foliis purpureis</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> from this fine coloured shrub exist at Sanssouci a strong exemplar and I was sawing very often the fruits, but (between 100 plants) I was only so happy to find 1–2 <hi rend="underline">red</hi> exemplars; all the others were <hi rend="underline">green</hi> leaved like the mother plant.—</p>
<p>An argument, that no rule is without exception may be, that we did receive very often Seedlings for our nursery of trees etc. from Mr. Grundel at Offenbach and Mr. Dauveli at Orléans,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> where between 100 and more <hi rend="underline">red</hi> leaved plants seldom one <hi rend="underline">green</hi> leaved was discovered.—</p>
<p>4. <hi rend="underline">Corylus Avellana foliis laciniatis</hi> (urticaefolia), I saw this shrub (at Magdeburgh in the Garden of Mr. Häneb) propagated by seeds and it was about <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of the seedlings <hi rend="underline">constant</hi>, the other did have the <hi rend="underline">common</hi> character.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>5. <hi rend="underline">Corylus Avellana foliis purpureis</hi> has sometimes the affection so <hi rend="underline">generate</hi> by seeds <hi rend="underline">mostly red</hi> seedlings but also sometimes <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> <hi rend="underline">red</hi> plants, <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> with <hi rend="underline">red brown</hi> leaves and <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> with common <hi rend="underline">green</hi> leaves. The first case passed in the Garden of Mr. Vogel at Potsdam, the other in my garden at Sanssouci.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>6. From the common <hi rend="underline">Daphne Mezereum</hi> (with <hi rend="underline">red</hi> flower and berry), we did have in our nursery of trees etc also a variety with <hi rend="doubleUnderline">yellow</hi> <hi rend="underline">flower</hi> and <hi rend="underline">fruit</hi> — Daphne Mezereum fructa lutea.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> More then six times I was sawing the fruits of the last variety and allways I was so happy to bring up again plants <hi rend="underline">like</hi> the <hi rend="underline">mother</hi> shrub (without any exception.).—</p>
<p>7. <hi rend="underline">Fagus sylvatica foliis purpureis</hi> <ref target="#foot.f10"/> Seedlings I have seen not only in Germany also in Belgium and the resultance was: <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> with <hi rend="underline">fine red</hi> coloured, <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> with <hi rend="underline">rust-brown</hi> and the other <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> with quite <hi rend="underline">green</hi> leaves.</p>
<p>8. Some years ago I did receive by a Gentleman a great quantity of seeds, from <hi rend="underline">Fraxinus excelsior monophylla</hi> (simplicifolia), which I was sawing directly. The resultance has been extraordinarily because between more then 3–400 seedlings were not more then about 30 exemplars, looking like the mother-plant, <hi rend="underline">all the other</hi> seedlings were <hi rend="underline">common</hi> ashs.—</p>
<p>9. <hi rend="underline">From Quercus pedunculata var. pyramidalis</hi> <ref target="#foot.f11"/> I did saw also often the glans and mostly the seedlings has been again fine looking pyramidal trees, the rest allways more or less slightly or quite complete common Oaks.</p>
<p>10. <hi rend="underline">Quercus pedunculata foliis argent. variegatis</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I did also propagate by glans but the essays has been <hi rend="underline">not</hi> succeeding because between about 100 plants only <hi rend="underline">two</hi> did have the leaves a <hi rend="underline">little</hi> spotted.</p>
<p>11. Very interesting indeed has been the resultances of the <hi rend="underline">Quercus pedunculatæ foliis argent. marginalis</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f13"/> one of the finest varietys, where all the leaves have <hi rend="underline">small white edges</hi> and the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">glans</hi> also is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">white striped</hi>.</p>
<p>I was so glad to receive 30 Seedlings but all and every plant was covered with leaves so <hi rend="underline">white</hi> as <hi rend="underline">snow</hi> and curious fact the little oaks were expiring in some months, because the nature did not like to protect the existence of them.</p>
<p>12. <hi rend="underline">Ribes nigrum crispum</hi> (aconitifolium) (spectabile) I propagated 8 years ago also by seeds and obtained <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> common black currants, <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> like the mother plant and <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> with <hi rend="underline">frizzled</hi> leaves, which was called by Prof. Koch <hi rend="underline">Ribes nigrum apiifolium</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>The last again to propagate by seeds, was quite impossible because my seedling did never show a flower, he was a regular monstrosity and I was allways obliged to propagate by cuttings.</p>
<p>13. For to be sure, that berry varietys could be also propagated sometimes by seeds, I slected <hi rend="underline">Ribes rubrum var. cerasiferum</hi> (Grosseille à cerise).<ref target="#foot.f15"/> In the fourth year all the seedlings did show their fruits and alltogether so also the leaves were looking like the mother plant.</p>
<p>14. <hi rend="underline">Rubus laciniatus</hi> I was very often sawing nd between all the seedlings and the mother was never a difference, so that I believe it will be perhaps a <hi rend="underline">pure</hi> species!— <ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>15. <hi rend="underline">Thuja orientalis var. aurea</hi> <ref target="#foot.f17"/> is also sometimes propagated by seeds and a great quantity of the young plants has then the same originellity as the old plant.</p>
<p>16. <hi rend="underline">Thuja occidentalis var. Wareana</hi> <ref target="#foot.f18"/> was also propagated in our Botan. Garden at Berlin by seeds and all the seedlings did have a similar appearance as the mother tree.</p>
<p>17. <hi rend="underline">Taxus hibernica</hi> (fastigiata.)<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>A friend at England was so kind to give me one day a small portion of Seed, which rised in the second year, but also not one plant did have the character like T. hibernica. The were alltogether looking like the <hi rend="underline">common</hi> Yew with the exception of <hi rend="underline">3</hi> exemplars, growing more pyramidal like <hi rend="underline">Taxus baccata var. erecta</hi>.</p>
<p>At least I mention yet two examples of <hi rend="underline">2 very known species of Spiraea</hi>, which I was propagating by seeds: Spiraea callosa and Douglasii.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>18. <hi rend="underline">Spiraea Douglasii</hi> one of our oldest red flowering Spiraees, I was allways obliged to propagate by cuttings, because between more then 400 seedlings scarsely 10 exemplars has been, which did have the same figure like Sp. Douglasii, the seedlings were representing the forms: Billardi, eximia, carpinifolia etc.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> so that I believe, we are not more in the possession of the <hi rend="underline">right</hi> old Spiraea Douglasii or what also possible — it is only a variety.—</p>
<p>The same resultance was stated at Muskau in Prussia (Possession of His Roy. H. the Prince of Low-land.)<ref target="#foot.f22"/></p>
<p>19. <hi rend="underline">Spiraea callosa</hi> this nice and very much estimated Spiraea was propagated all and every year in our nursery in great quantity and allways the curiosity has been, that some exemplars (between 5-600) did have <hi rend="underline">red grape</hi>-like flowers and not like all the other <hi rend="underline">umbelliferous</hi>, also the leaves were differently looking.</p>
<p>Because the variety was trained at Sanssouci so Prof. Koch did give her the signification Spiraea <hi rend="underline">Sanssouciana</hi>. Some times later we did receive from England Sp. Nobleana, trained at Bagshot (?) and Sp. Regeliana from Frankfurth trained in Mr. Rinz’s nursery, but all the three varietys seemed me to have the same mother— that is to say—Sp. Callosa!—<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p>
<p>Climbers changing their character in an elder state:—</p>
<p>1. <hi rend="underline">Hedera Helix</hi> the common Ivy with all his varietys is allways changing the physicomie, when he is beginning to show his flowers and it is a very curious fact that propagated in this period by cuttings the Ivy will not accept again his original character. We find this form announced in the Catalogues of the nursery men as <hi rend="underline">Hedera Helix arbuscula</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f24"/></p>
<p>2. <hi rend="underline">Lonicera brachypoda</hi> has as a creeper allways more tender leaves but because the plant in our country will be very often attacked by the frost, so we find her sometimes cultivated in pots on sticks, 2-3’ long, where the leaves are changing their character in a manner that they are looking like evergreen as the leaves of a Viburnum Tinus.—<ref target="#foot.f25"/></p>
<p>3. In a similar way as the first it is also the case with <hi rend="underline">Decumaria barbara</hi>.—</p>
<p>4. <hi rend="underline">Cissus acuminata</hi>, a fine looking climber from the Himalaya is allways in my country a very sensible plant and is to be covered in the winter. Some plants standing on a wall are at once producing on the top very notable leaves (Cissus acuminata. [symbol].) what is indeed very curious, because I never saw such a fact at the similar Cissus quinquefolia (Ampelopsis hederacea).<ref target="#foot.f26"/></p>
<p>5. <hi rend="underline">Ficus stipulata (a)</hi> is no dought the most interesting example of all because planted on the wall one our houses (for forcing beans) would not change her character till to the time where she was showing the fruits, then the now leaves at once were beginning to be larger and longer, so that no person would know again the Ficus stipulata<ref target="#foot.f27"/></p>
<p>In our Botan. Garden at Berlin is such a shrub propagated by a fruit-branch in a pot, which is every year full of fruits and which will never return again to his true character.</p>
<p>The fact is almost incredible, but Mr. Bouché,<ref target="#foot.f28"/> Inspector of the Roy. Botan. Garden at Berlin is capable to affirm the truth.—</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" n="2">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>[Reuter enclosed a number of leaves: see plates on pp. 324 and 325.]</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure:</hi></note>
                <note>2.1 <hi rend="italic">Acer</hi>] ‘acer’ <hi rend="italic">added above pencil</hi></note>
                <note>34.1 In … character. 34.3] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of enclosure</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> Plants &amp; <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of enclosure</hi>: ‘Herr Reuter | of Sanscouci, Potsdam | <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Inheritance</hi>. Difference (like Ivy) between leaves of Branches &amp; flowering Branches can be propagated &amp; do not <hi rend="italic">[</hi>revert<hi rend="italic">]</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6772.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Adolph Reuter, 2 June 1869</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his letter of 2 June 1869, CD advised Reuter to publish his observations on horticulture.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">‘Foliis variegatis’: with variegated leaves (Latin) <hi rend="italic">Acer pseudoplatanus</hi> is the sycamore maple; there is a cultivar ‘variegatum’. Reuter also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6151.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter Joseph Lenné</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘Foliis purpureis’: with purple leaves. The cultivar <hi rend="italic">Acer pseudoplatanus</hi> ‘Atropurpureum’ has leaves that are dark green above with purple undersides.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Berberis vulgaris</hi> is the common barberry; there is a cultivar ‘variegata’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Offenbach is a city in Hesse, Germany, on the river Main near Frankfurt; Mr Grundel has not been identified. Orléans is a city in north-central France in the Loire valley. Mr Dauveli has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">‘Foliis laciniatis (urticaefolia)’: with slashed leaves (nettle-like leaves). <hi rend="italic">Corylus avellana</hi> is the hazel tree; the modern cultivar is called <hi rend="italic">C. avellana</hi> ‘heterophylla’ (the cutleaf hazel).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">There are now several red or purple cultivars of <hi rend="italic">Corylus avellana</hi>; in some varieties, like ‘Rote Zeller’ the anthocyanins (red pigments) are affected by temperature and humidity.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The more common form of <hi rend="italic">Daphne mezereum</hi> (‘rubrum’) has pink flowers and red berries. The form Reuter describes as ‘fructa lutea’ (yellow fruit) is the modern ‘album’, which has cream flowers and yellow fruit.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Fagus sylvatica</hi> is the beech tree; ‘purpurea’ is the most common purple-leaf variety.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Quercus pedunculata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Q. robur</hi> (the English oak or pedunculate oak); the variety ‘pyramidalis’ is now ‘fastigiata’ (cypress oak).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">‘Foliis argent. variegalis’: with silver variegated leaves.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">‘Foliis argent. marginalis’: with silver-edged leaves.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><hi rend="italic">Ribes nigrum</hi> is the blackcurrant. ‘Crispum (aconitifolium) (spectabile)’: curled (with aconite-like leaves) (showy). <hi rend="italic">Ribes apiifolium</hi> is now considered to be a synonym of <hi rend="italic">R. nigrum.</hi> Reuter also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Heinrich Emil Koch</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4417.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koch 1869–73</ref>, 1: 661.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><hi rend="italic">Ribes rubrum</hi> is the redcurrant. ‘Cerasiferum’: bearing wax (Latin). ‘Grosseille à cerise’ (cherry currant) is not a currently recognised variety, however, there is a western North American species, <hi rend="italic">Ribes cereum</hi>, the wax currant.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><hi rend="italic">Rubus laciniatus</hi> is the cut-leaved blackberry and is a distinct species.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><hi rend="italic">Thuja orientalis</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Platycladus orientalis</hi>, the oriental arborvitae; ‘aurea nana’ is a modern golden-leaved variety.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><hi rend="italic">Thuja occidentalis</hi> is the eastern white cedar; ‘Wareana’ is a cultivar with blue-green leaves.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><hi rend="italic">Taxus hibernica</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">T. baccata</hi> ‘hibernica’ (the Irish yew); <hi rend="italic">T. baccata</hi> ‘fastigiata’ is a synonym. <hi rend="italic">T. baccata</hi> ‘erecta’ is a cultivar of the English yew.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><hi rend="italic">Spireaea</hi> is meadowsweet. <hi rend="italic">S. douglasii</hi> is sometimes called western spiraea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21"><hi rend="italic">Spiraea</hi> x <hi rend="italic">billardii</hi> is a hybrid of <hi rend="italic">S. douglasii</hi> x <hi rend="italic">S. salicifolia</hi>; <hi rend="italic">S. eximia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. carpinifolia</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">S. salicifolia</hi> (willow spiraea).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Muskau Park is a large English-style park founded in 1815 in Prussia (the park is now in both Germany and Poland). It was taken over by Prince Frederick of the Netherlands and extended from 1852 to 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6127.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Oxford companion to gardens</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23"><hi rend="italic">Spiraea sanssouciana</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">S. douglasii</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Berliner allgemeine Gartenzeitung</hi> 25 (1857): 214 for Koch’s description). <hi rend="italic">Spiraea nobleana</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">S. douglasii</hi>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6441.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Noble</ref> was the owner of a nursery in Bagshot (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6375.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office directory of the six home counties</hi></ref>). Reuter also refers to the nursery in Frankfurt am Main founded by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6627.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sebastian Rinz</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">The cultivar <hi rend="italic">Hedera helix</hi> ‘arbuscula’ (‘small tree’) has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25"><hi rend="italic">Lonicera brachypoda</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">L. japonica</hi> (Japanese honeysuckle). <hi rend="italic">Viburnum tinus</hi> is laurustinus.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26"><hi rend="italic">Decumaria barbara</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Hydrangea barbara</hi>. Reuter refers to <hi rend="italic">Cissus acuminata</hi> A. Gray (now <hi rend="italic">Cayratia acuminata</hi>) and to <hi rend="italic">C. acuminata</hi> Thwaites (now <hi rend="italic">C. latifolia</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Cissus quinquefolia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ampelopsis hederacea</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Parthenocissus quinquefolia</hi> (American ivy).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27"><hi rend="italic">Ficus stipulata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">F. pumila</hi> (climbing fig).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl David Bouché</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>