<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12008">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Wilhelm Pfeffer<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   22 April 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9349</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12008 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12008.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12008.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp † German</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 209.14: 187</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>209.14: 187</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3766.xml">Pfeffer, Wilhelm</persName>
                <placeName>Tübingen</placeName>
                <date when="1879-04-22">22 Apr 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>In response to CD’s query, discusses sleep movements of plants. Recommends papers on subject.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">sleeping plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-11">Facsimile information added by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-02-13" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-18" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00419_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00419_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="187ar">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00419.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00419_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00419.dzi" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="187av">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00420.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00420_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00420.dzi" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="187br">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00421.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00421_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00421.dzi" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="187bv">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00422.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00422_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00209-00014-000-00422.dzi" width="4049px" height="7074px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Tübingen</placeName>
                    <date>d 22 April 1879</date>
                    <salute>Geehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Gestern aus Italien zurückgekehrt beeile ich mich Ihr werthes Schreiben vom 23 März zu beantworten.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Leider muss ich bedauren Ihnen nicht in dem Maasse Auskunft geben zu können, wie ich es selbst wünschte, da ich bei meinen Untersuchungen über periodische Bewegungen auf die habituellen Erscheinungen des Schlafens, sowie auf Verbreitung dieses Phänomens nur nebenbei geachtet habe.</p>
                    <p>Was zunächst Siegesbekia flexuosa anbelangt, so habe ich mich hier auf die angeblich richtige Bestimmung des Marburger Gartens verlassen; vielleicht ist die Pflanze identisch mit Siegesbekia jorullensis.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Wie bei anderen Pflanzen ist auch bei dieser mit dem Alter der Blätter Tag und Nachtstellung variabel. Für noch nicht ganz zu voller Grösse gelangte Blätter ist nach meinen Skizzen die Stellung der Blätter am Tage und bei Nacht durch nebenstehende Skizzen veranschaulicht.
                        <figure rend="blockCentred width20">
                            <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_1_german.png"/>
                        </figure>
Aeltere Blätter näheren sich mehr der Horizontalen während des Tages und erreichen in Nacht eine weniger weit gehende Senkung.</p>
                    <p>Die Blätter von Wigandia urens führen überhaupt nur mässige Amplitude der Bewegung aus.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Die Neigung mittelalter Blätter am Tage ist etwa wie nebenstehend.
                    <figure rend="inline width10">
                        <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_2_german.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    </p> 
<p>Dabei sind die Blätter am Tage öfters (in Blattstiel und Lamina) schwach concav nach Unterseite und werden Abends mit der Hebung mehr oder weniger eben.</p>
                    <p>Bei der unbestimten Malva (aus Verwandschaft von Malva sylvestris)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> stander am Tage Blätter etwa so
                        <figure rend="inline width10">
                        <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_3_german.png"/>
                    </figure> 

und erhoben sich theilweise so weit, dass sie trichterförmig zusammenneigten; so dass Stellung des einzelnen Blattes etwa wurde: 
                    <figure rend="inline width10">
                        <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_4_no_text.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>Der Variabilität der Stellung halber, wie sie bei Nutationsbewegungen sich immer mit Alter der Objecte abspielt, habe ich die Neigungen gegen Verticale und Horizonte nicht näher bestimmt, sondern gewöhnlich nur die Stellungsänderungen an entsprechend angebrachten Gradbogen abgelesen.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Einige andere nicht publicirte Beobachtungen will ich, Ihrem Wunsche entsprechend, hier noch kurz anschliessen; sie beziehen sich auch auf Nutationsbewegungen.</p>
                    <p>Silybum Marianum. Die noch wachsenden Cotyledonen spreizen Tags in spitzem Winkel nähern sich Nachts und können sich eventuell aneinanderlegen.— Aehnliches gilt für Cotyledonen von Mimulus tigrinus und Brassica Napus.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>Schwächer ist Erhebung und Annährung der Cotyledonen bei Cucurbita Pepo und Mirabilis Jalapa.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>Bei allen diesen Pflanzen zeigen auch andere <hi rend="underline">junge</hi> Blätter merkliche, doch theilweise schwache Erhebungen am Abend. Gleiches gilt auch für die Blätter von Petunia und Celosia cristata;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Verticalstellung wird normalerweise von diesen Blättern nicht erreicht.</p>
                    <p>In den Literaturangaben welche sich auf periodisch bewegliche Blätter beziehen ist, soviel ich weiss, nicht viel zu den in meiner Arbeit (p 161) citirten Angaben hinzugekommen.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Eine Beobachtung Chatin’s (Compt. rendus 1876, Bd 82, p. 171) über Nadeln von Abies Nordmanniana wird Ihnen wohl ohnedies bekannt sein.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Einige faktische Angaben finden sich auch bei C. Kraus in Flora 1879, p. 11 ff., in einer Arbeit die sonst wie die anderen Publicationen dieses Autors besser nicht geschrieben wäre.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Mit dem Bedauern Ihnen nicht reichlicher Notizen mittheilen zu können verbleibe ich mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung | Ihr | ergebenster | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W Pfeffer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Sleep | All used’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>
                       
            
            
               
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Tübingen</placeName>
                    <date>22 April 1879</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Having returned from Italy yesterday, I hasten to reply to your esteemed letter of 23 March.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Unfortunately, I regret not to be able to provide you with the amount of information I would wish, since in my researches into periodic movements I only incidentally paid attention to the habitual occurrences of sleep, as well as to the extent of this phenomenon.</p>
                    <p>Firstly, as far as Siegesbekia flexuosa is concerned, I relied on the ostensibly correct classification of the Marburg garden; perhaps the plant is identical with Siegesbekia jorullensis.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> As with other plants, so with this one, the daytime and night-time position of the leaves varies depending on their age. For not yet fully grown leaves, the leaf positions during the day and at night, according to my drawings, are illustrated in the adjacent sketches. 
                        <figure rend="blockCentred width20">
                            <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_1_english.png"/>
                        </figure>
Older leaves move closer to the horizontal during the day, and at night do not dip down as far.</p>
                    <p>The leaves of Wigandia urens demonstrate only moderate amplitude of movement.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The inclination of middle age leaves during the day is roughly as opposite.
                        <figure rend="inline width10">
                            <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_2_english.png"/>
                        </figure>
                    </p> 
                    <p>Also, during the day the leaves (in the leafstalk and lamina) are frequently slightly concave on the undersurface and in the evening become more or less flat as they rise.</p>
                    <p>Regarding the unidentified Malva (a relative of Malva sylvestris),<ref target="#foot.f5"/> the leaves were positioned roughly like this during daytime
                    <figure rend="inline width10">
                        <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_3_english.png"/>
                    </figure>
and in some cases they rose so far that they bent together into a funnel-shape; so that the single leaves were positioned roughly like this:
                        <figure rend="inline width10">
                            <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12008_4_no_text.png"/>
                        </figure>
                    </p> 
                    <p>Due to the variability of the position, as is always the case in nutation movements depending on the age of the object, I did not determine in greater detail the inclinations from the vertical and the horizontal, but usually recorded only positional changes of the respective graduated arcs.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I will, to comply with your request, briefly add a number of other unpublished observations; they also concern nutation movements.</p>
                    <p>Silybum Marianum. The still developing cotyledons spread out during the day at an acute angle, converge at night and can potentially touch each other.— The same goes for the cotyledons of Mimulus tigrinus and Brassica Napus.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>In Cucurbita Pepo and Mirabilis Jalapa, the lifting and convergence of the cotyledons is weaker.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>In all of these plants other <hi rend="underline">young</hi> leaves demonstrate distinct, yet partial weak elevation in the evening. The same also holds for the leaves of Petunia and Celosia cristata;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> the vertical position will not normally be reached by these leaves.</p>
                    <p>In the literature on periodically moving leaves not much, as far as I know, has been added to the details listed in my work (p 161).<ref target="#foot.f10"/> An observation of Chatin’s (Compt. rendus 1876, vol. 82, p. 171) on needles of Abies Nordmanniana you will probably already know.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> A number of factual details can be found in C. Kraus in Flora 1879, p. 11ff, in a work which otherwise ought not to have been written, like the other publications by this author.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>With regret at being unable to communicate more copious details I remain with the deepest respect | Your | most devoted | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Pfeffer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
             
            
                   
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11948.xml">letter to Wilhelm Pfeffer, 23 March 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11948.xml">letter to Wilhelm Pfeffer, 23 March 1879</ref> and n. 2. <hi rend="italic">Siegesbeckia flexuosa</hi> is an unknown combination (‘Siegesbeckia’ is a common misspelling of ‘Sigesbeckia’, the genus of St Paul’s-wort); <hi rend="italic">S. jorullensis</hi> is an accepted name. CD added Pfeffer’s information, referring to the plant as ‘<hi rend="italic">S. jorullensis</hi>?’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 385. Pfeffer refers to the University of Marburg arboretum and botanical garden at Pilgrimstein.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Wigandia urens</hi> is the Caracus wigandia; CD cited Pfeffer for information on its leaf movements, but used only the genus name in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 248.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Pfeffer had not identified the species of <hi rend="italic">Malva</hi> he had observed in <hi rend="italic">Die periodische Bewegungen der Blattorgane</hi> (The periodic movements of foliage organs; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10116.xml">Pfeffer 1875</ref>, p. 29). <hi rend="italic">Malva sylvestris</hi> is common or high mallow (see <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, p. 324).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">For Pfeffer’s experimental protocol and an image of the apparatus used to measure changes, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10116.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Pfeffer 1875</ref>, pp. 32–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Silybum marianum</hi> is blessed milk-thistle; <hi rend="italic">Mimulus tigrinus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Erythranthe lutea</hi>, yellow monkeyflower; <hi rend="italic">Brassica napus</hi> is rape.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Cucurbita pepo</hi> is squash or pumpkin; <hi rend="italic">Mirabilis jalapa</hi> is marvel of Peru.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Celosia cristata</hi> is crested cock’s-comb.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10116.xml">Pfeffer 1875</ref>, pp. 161–70; Pfeffer had reviewed the literature on leaf movement from ancient times up to his contemporaries.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7647.xml">Joannes Chatin</ref>’s note on the movement of leaves in <hi rend="italic">Abies nordmanniana</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10009.xml">Chatin 1876a</ref>) had been translated into English in <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10834.xml">Chatin 1876b</ref>). CD’s notes on this species, referred to by a synonym, <hi rend="italic">Picea nordmanniana</hi> (Caucasian fir), dated from 14 July 1879 to 26 January 1880, are in DAR 209.6: 1a–1b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2756.xml">Carl Kraus</ref>’s work ‘Beiträge zur Kenntniss der Bewegungen wachsender Laub- und Blüthenblätter’ (Contributions to the understanding of the movements of growing foliage leaves and petals; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10835.xml">Kraus 1879 </ref>was published in instalments in <hi rend="italic">Flora, oder allgemeine botanische Zeitung</hi> between 1 January and 21 February 1879. Pfeffer had dismissed as simplistic Kraus’s earlier explanation of the mechanical cause of geotropic movements (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10809.xml">Pfeffer 1877</ref>, p. 215, n. 1).</note>
          
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>