<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3644F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. E. Darwin   8 July [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21671</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3644F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3644F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3644F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
                <relatedItem type="publication">
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 24: 450</bibl>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Cornford Family Papers (DAR 275: 3)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                        <collection>DAR</collection>
                        <idno>275: 3</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">Darwin, W. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Southampton</placeName>
                <date when="1862-07-08">8 July [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>WED reports on studying the pollen of grass and Valerian through his microscope.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Southampton</placeName>
                    <date>July 8.</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very glad to hear that you are better, I suppose it is your face that is right.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I went and got some grass yesterday, and have been looking at it this morning  I found pollen grains sticking to the treelike stigmas, but it takes a high power, and I expect it will take a lot of fiddling and looking at different spec. before one sees how they stick, I mean to get a bit of wheat today.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> it is very odd but I dont feel quite certain what you wanted me to look for in Valerian or Lithrum,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> unless it is whether the stigmas are of different lengths. Yesterday I gathered 15 bits of <hi rend="underline">V</hi>. and examined them carefully writing note of each examined the stigma in some were certainly longer than others, but then they seemed almost to graduate from short to long, and I think the old flowers had them much longer than the young. if it is about the stigmas you want to know, I will mark a plant and see whether they do get so much longer as they get old. Also about the Lithrum though I am no so sure after all that I can find any.</p>
<p>Some of the stigmas in <hi rend="underline">V</hi>alerian were twice as long as others above the base of the petals.</p>
<p>I am sorry to hear old pouter is bad, I suppose his banishment is over.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I was going to have Clement down from L.H.P, for Sunday but a two day’s post upset his plans so that he is now at Hartfield<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I am your affect son | W. E. Darwin</p>
<p>did not you tell me something about Boragineæ?</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 4 [July 1862]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 4 [July 1862]</ref>, which mentioned that CD was better and that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> had suggested that he wear a beard. In April 1862, Emma had reported that CD’s health was poor and his ‘face terribly inflamed’ (letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> to W. E. Darwin, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 27 April 1862] (DAR 219.1: 54)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had suggested that William investigate the fertilisation of wheat by observing the stigma and pollen-tube under a high-powered microscope (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 4 [July 1862]</ref>). William’s botanical sketchbook (DAR 186: 43) contains a note dated 10 July 1862, describing pollen-masses and pollen-tubes of grasses.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Valerian: <hi rend="italic">Valeriana officinalis</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Lythrum</hi>: a genus of loosestrife. CD’s query has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Pouter was a nickname for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin</ref>, who had developed swollen glands after having scarlet fever (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 4 [July 1862]</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242) records that Leonard ‘went to Mrs Parslow’ on 19 June 1862 after contracting scarlet fever on 12 June. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7645.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eliza Parslow</ref>, wife of CD’s butler <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3699.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Parslow</ref>, lived at 18 Home Cottage, Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5000.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clement Francis Wedgwood</ref>, William’s cousin, was visiting Leith Hill Place, Dorking, Surrey, home of Josiah and Caroline Sarah Wedgwood, and Hartfield Grove, Sussex, home of Charlotte and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2809.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Langton</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>