<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12316">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   14 November 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5470</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12316 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12316.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12316.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B49–50</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B49–B50</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-11-14">14 Nov 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for English edition [of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>]. John Murray has not answered letters of German publisher. Questions CD about persons mentioned in book, in order to annotate German edition.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-02-15" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-28" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-05" status="editorResponseCompleted"><name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-13" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-09-11" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00216_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00216_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
        <surface n="B:49r" xml:id="i216">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00216.jpg" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00216_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00216.dzi" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:49v" xml:id="i217">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00217.jpg" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00217_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00217.dzi" width="3713px" height="6300px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:50r" xml:id="i218">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00218.jpg" width="3713px" height="6233px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00218_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3713px" height="6233px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00218.dzi" width="3713px" height="6233px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:50v" xml:id="i219">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00219.jpg" width="3713px" height="6233px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00219_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3713px" height="6233px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00219.dzi" width="3713px" height="6233px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II</placeName>
                    <date>den 14.11.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Zunächst sage ich Ihnen herzlichen Dank für Ihren freundlichen Brief vom 10<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. c., sowie für das Exemplar der englischen Ausgabe, welches Sie die Güte hatten, mir zu senden.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Das Buch macht einen so gewinnenden Eindruck und enthält soviel Interessantes aus dem intimen Leben Englands aus dem vorigen Jahrhundert, dass ich überzeugt bin, es wird vielen Beifall finden. Das Portrait ist sehr schön ausgefallen, und ich werde unter allen Umständen darauf dringen, dass es der deutschen Ausgabe nicht fehlen darf. Wie ich nachträglich erfahren habe, ist an der hässlichen Geschichte zunächst der Umstand, dass Mr. Murray nicht einen einzigen Brief des deutschen Verlegers beantwortet hat, woraus sich bei diesem eine Empfindlichkeit entwickelt hat, die ihn gewiss heute selbst am allermeisten schmerzt, nachdem ich ihm geschrieben habe, dass die Angelegenheit Sie unangenehm berührt habe.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ich werde nunmehr die Bestellung durch einen Londoner Commissionär in meinem Namen machen und die Vorausbezahlung, wenn verlangt, bewirken.</p>
<p>Leider muss ich Sie nun, hochverehrter Herr, nochmals in dieser Angelegenheit bemühen, nämlich mit der Bitte, über einige der in dem Buche erwähnten Persönlichkeiten und Vorkomnisse mir einige kurze Notizen geben zu wollen soweit sie Personen betreffen, die in unsern Nachschlagewerken nicht erwähnt werden. Natürlich würden für die Anmerkungen je 2–3 Zeilen genügen. Auch möchte ich Sie bitten, nur die jenigen Fragen, gütigst beantworten zu wollen, deren Beantwortung Ihnen keine Mühe und Umstände bereitet. Verzeihen Sie nur, wenn ich wieder wie ein Examinator frage, aber meine Lage ist weniger angenehm, denn ich muss Ihnen mit jeder Frage eine Lücke meines Wissens verrathen.</p>
<p>1. Ist der p. 4 erwähnte Mr. Stukeley derselbe, welcher über Stonehenge und Abury geschrieben hat?<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>2 Was war der Spalding-Club (p. 4) für eine Gesellschaft, und wo hatte Sie ihren Sitz?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>3. War der p. 8 erwähnte “Scribelerus” eine Wochenschrift wie der “Tatler”, oder sonst ein Buch?<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>4. War Dr. Okes<ref target="#foot.f7"/> (p. 14) ein Arzt, oder sonst eine allgemeinbekannte Persönlichkeit?</p>
                    <p>5. War Dr. Bentley (p. 16) ein Sohn des berühmten Kritikers und ein Vorfahr des berühmten Botanikers dieses Namens?<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>6. War Sir Brooke Bothby<ref target="#foot.f9"/> als Naturforscher oder Dichter berühmt? (p. 36)</p>
<p>7. Ist Ihnen bekannt, was für Versuche Dr. Crawfords<ref target="#foot.f10"/> (p. 51) gemeint sind?</p>
<p>8. War der p. 53 erwähnte Lord Cavendish ein Bruder des berühmten Naturforschers?<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>9. Prof. Duncan (p. 82) war wohl Mediciner? und ist der gleichzeitig erwähnte Sir H. Raeburn als Juwelier berühmt geworden?<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>10. Wer war Mr. Cradock (p. 89)?<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>11. Soll “Darwinian snowdrops” (p. 90) nur von Dr. Darwin <hi rend="underline">gepflanzte</hi> Schneeglöckchen bedeuten, oder handelt es sich um eine nach ihm benannte Art?<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>12. Wer war Foot (p 102)?<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>13. Hatte der Lunar Club (p 121) seinen Sitz zu Lichfield?<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Es sind das leider eine grosse Anzahl von Fragen, mit denen ich Sie belästen muss, aber ich hoffe nun auch, dass dies die letzte Plage sein wird, die Sie mit diesem kleinen Buche haben. Die Anmerkungen über diese und manche andre Punkte zu machen, erscheint mir für den deutschen Leser unerlässlich; sie sollen sammt dem Original-Text der poetischen Citate in einen Appendix kommen, während der übrige Theil der englischen Ausgabe gänzlich entsprechen wird.</p>
<p>Indem ich Ihnen, hochverehrter Herr, meinen innigsten Dank sage, dass Sie meine kleine Arbeit mit Ihrer Einleitung in die Oeffentlichkeit bringen, zeichne ich | Mit herzlichster Verehrung | Ihr | treulich ergebener | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II</placeName>
                    <date>14.11.79.</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>First let me thank you cordially for your kind letter of 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of this month, as well as for the copy of the English edition, which you kindly sent me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The book makes such an engaging impression and contains so many interesting details about the private life of England in the previous century that I am convinced it will be greeted with much acclaim. The portrait turned out very well and I shall press for it not to be missing from the German edition under any circumstances. As I found out subsequently, the ugly story was initially caused by the circumstance that Mr Murray did not reply to a single letter from the German publisher, as a result of which he developed an oversensitivity, which surely now pains him himself most all of, for I wrote to him that the matter was distasteful to you.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will now place the order through a London agent in my name and arrange for advance payment, if required.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, highly esteemed Sir, I must now trouble you again on this matter, namely with the request to supply me with a few notes regarding characters and events that are mentioned in the book, insofar as they concern persons who are not mentioned in our reference works. Of course 2–3 lines each would suffice for the notes. Also, I would ask you to kindly answer only those queries that will not cause you trouble and inconvenience. Please forgive me if I ask like an examiner, but my position is less pleasant, for with every question I must betray to you a gap in my knowledge.</p>
                    <p>1. Is Mr Stukely who is mentioned on p. 4 the same as the one who wrote about Stonehenge and Abury?<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>2. What kind of society was the Spalding Club (p. 4) and where were its premises?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>3. Was the “Scriblerus” mentioned on p. 8 a weekly like the “Tatler” or a book?<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>4. Was Dr Okes<ref target="#foot.f7"/> (p. 14) a physician, or some generally known personality?</p>
                    <p>5. Was Dr Bentley (p. 16) a son of the famous critic and an ancestor of the famous botanist of this name?<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>6. Was Sir Brooke Bothby<ref target="#foot.f9"/> famous as a naturalist or as a poet? (p. 36)</p>
                    <p>7. Do you know what kind of experiments by Dr Crawford<ref target="#foot.f10"/> (p. 51) are referred to?</p>
                    <p>8. Was Lord Cavendish who is mentioned on p. 53 a brother of the famous naturalist?<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                    <p>9. Prof. Duncan (p. 82) was no doubt a medical man? and did Sir H. Raeburn who is mentioned at the same time become famous as a jeweller?<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                    <p>10. Who was Mr Cradock (p. 89)?<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
                    <p>11. Does “Darwinian snowdrops” (p. 90) just mean snowdrops that were <hi rend="underline">planted</hi> by Dr. Darwin, or are they a species named after him?<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
                    <p>12. Who was Foot (p. 102)?<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
                    <p>13. Were the premises of the Lunar Club (p. 121) at Lichfield?<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Unfortunately there are a large number of questions that I need to burden you with, but I do hope that this is the last bother you will have with this little book. It seems essential to me to supply the German reader with notes about these and a few other points; together with the original text of poetical quotations, they will form an appendix, while the remainder will conform to the English edition in every respect.</p>
<p>Offering my most heartfelt thanks to you, most esteemed Sir, for bringing my little labour to the attention of the public with your introduction, I remain | With most cordial respects | Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12304.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 10 November 1879</ref>. Krause’s name is on CD’s presentation list for <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> (Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had paid <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">John Murray (1808–92)</ref> in advance for photographs of the frontispiece of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> for the German edition; he had been upset when the German publisher <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_61.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Alberts</ref> cancelled the order (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12291.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 4 November 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4603.xml">William Stukeley</ref> was the author of medical and antiquarian works, including <hi rend="italic">Stonehenge: a temple restor’d to the British druids</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10525.xml">Stukeley 1740</ref>) and <hi rend="italic">Abury: a temple of the British druids</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10526.xml">Stukeley 1743</ref>). Abury is Avebury in Wiltshire.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 4, CD mentions that Erasmus Darwin’s father, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1237.xml">Robert Darwin</ref> (1682–1754), was a member of the ‘Spalding Club’; this was the Spalding Gentlemen’s Society (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10527.xml">Leveritt and Elsden 1986</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">‘Turned over a few pages in Scribelerus’ (<hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 8): probably a misspelling of ‘Scriblerus’, a common pseudonym, most famously used by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3821.xml">Alexander Pope</ref> in <hi rend="italic">The Dunciad</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10541.xml">Pope 1729</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8666.xml">Thomas Okes</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6510.xml">Thomas Bentley</ref>. Krause probably refers to the classical scholar <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9019.xml">Richard Bentley</ref> and to the botanist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6505.xml">Robert Bentley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8459.xml">Brooke Boothby (1744–1824)</ref> was a poet and translator.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9017.xml">Adair Crawford</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8663.xml">George Augustus Henry Cavendish</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12202.xml">letter from E. A. Wheler, 18 April 1879</ref>) was not the brother of the naturalist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9018.xml">Henry Cavendish</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1417.xml">Andrew Duncan</ref> was a professor of medicine at <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1454.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edinburgh University</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3914.xml">Henry Raeburn</ref> was a Scottish portrait painter who had been apprenticed to a goldsmith as a young man (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8669.xml">Joseph Cradock</ref> (see enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12017F.xml">letter from W. E. Darwin, 29 April [1879] and n. 8).</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The snowdrops were planted by Erasmus Darwin in his garden near Lichfield (see <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 90).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">‘Every <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2458.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hunter</ref> must expect a Jessy Foot to pursue him, as a fly bites a horse’ (<hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 102): the passage alludes to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9030.xml">Jesse Foot’s</ref> hostile biography of the surgeon and anatomist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2458.xml">John Hunter</ref> (see <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi> s.v. Foot, Jesse).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">The Lunar Society of Birmingham met for dinner and discussion at a member’s home each month (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6963.xml">Schofield 1963</ref>, pp. 3–4; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11953.xml">letter from E. A. Wheler, 25 March 1879 and n. 3</ref>). </note>
        </div> 
     
    </body>
       
    </text>
</TEI>