<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11509">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Naphtali Lewy<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   14 May 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9446</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11509 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11509.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11509.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 201: 21</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>201: 21</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2916.xml">Lewy, Naphtali</persName>
                <placeName>Whitechapel</placeName>
                <date when="1878-05-14">14 May 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Believes that weakness of hybrids explains Biblical injunctions against improper unions.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00076_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00076_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
        <surface n="21:1r" xml:id="i76">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00076.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00076_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00076.dzi" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:1v" xml:id="i77">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00077.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00077_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00077.dzi" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:2r" xml:id="i78">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00078.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00078_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00078.dzi" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:2v" xml:id="i79">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00079.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00079_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00201-000-00079.dzi" width="5105px" height="8367px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>29 Baker’s Row | Whitechapel | London E.</placeName>
                    <salute>Sr Hochwohlgeboren | dem Weltberühmten Naturforscher | Charles Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Noch im Jahre 1876 im Monate April hatte ich die Ehre von Er. Hochwohlg. Briefe zu empfangen (in Radom in Polen); nun soll es mich freuen, wenn nachstehender Artikel auch Beifall finde, und Er. Hochwohlg. mit einer Antwort mich zu beehren geruhe.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich gedenke immer ein fassungsreiches Buch über Ihre Theorie in Betreff der Mosaischen Verfassung zu schreiben und eben dieser vorliegender Artikel ist ein Beitrag zu demselben,</p>
                    <p>“In meinem Werke “Toldot-Adam” (die Abs. des. Mensch.) Wien 1875., habe bewiesen dass die biblische Schöpfungsgeschichte ganz nach der Darwinischen Theorie erklährt und comentirt werden kann, und die Ursprache eignet sich sehr der Transmutationstheorie im Ausdruck und Inhalt.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Nun wollen wir jetze versuchen im Urtext in Betreff d. Bastardbildung was die Wissenschaft behauptet, dasselbe dort zu finden, und zu beweisen dass die Darwinische Lehre eigentlich uns den Schlüssel gibt zur Biblischen-Geheim Verfassung—</p>
<p>Wollen wir die Haupt-Momente d. Dar. L. hervor heben. In der Abstammung Cap. 9 <hi rend="underline">Bastardbildung</hi> heisst es:</p>
                    <p>1) der frühe Tod der Bastardembryone tritt wahrscheinlich in gleicher Weise bei Pflanzen ein; wenigstens ist es bekannt dass von sehr verschiedenen Arten erzogene Bastarde zuweilen schwach und zwerghaft sind ung jung zu Grunde gehen—.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>2) daselbst: In beiden Fällen kommt die Unfruchtbarkeit in vielerlei vor:<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>3) das   die obige Ansicht dass die Sterilität der Bastarde durch das Vermischen zweier Constitutionen zu einer verursacht sei, ist vor kurzem sehr entschieden v. Max Wichura vertreten worden.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>Was die Wissenschaft “Bastard” nennt, das will die Bibel mit dem “unehlichen Kind” bezeichnen; sie heisst es “<hi rend="smallCaps">eine schändliche vermischung</hi>  תֶּבֶל III Buch Moses Cap 20 V12)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> oder besser für das Vermischen zweier Arten gibt sie den Ausdruck <hi rend="smallCaps">le_rivoh</hi> לְרִבְעָה (ibid. Ve. 16)<ref target="#foot.f8"/> und jedes Abkömmling von Blutsverwandeten Eltern welche ihre Blösse aufdecken, das heisst sie “<hi rend="underline">Bastard</hi>” (d. Cap 18. Ve 6)<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Nun wollen wir lesen was die Bibel über solche, “Unzucht” verhängt: es heisst (ibid Cap 18. Vers 24) “Vermischt euch nicht (das die Grundbedeutung im Hebrai: von תְמַמְאוּ) mit diesen— —das Land hat sich vermischt und deshalb hat es die Bewohner ausgespieen”—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>Ist etwa hier nich gesagt “dass von verschiedenen Arten erzogene Bastarde schwach, zwerghaft und jung zu Grunde gehen? ist etwa nicht das Ausspeien des Landes, der frühe Tod der Bastardembryone”— ? lesen wir nicht deutlich (das. Cap 20. V. 21) “Wer die Blösse aufgedeckt die werden Kinderlos sterben”<ref target="#foot.f11"/> ist etwa mehr da Geheimnis als die Natur-Lehre nach Darwin? Verhängt nicht die Bibel dasselbe was die Wissenschaft heimsucht? “in beiden Fällen kommt die Unfruchtbarkeit”—? (v das Vers 25)<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Liegt nicht etwa in der Warnung d. Bibel “Ihr müsst Arten von Arten unterscheiden”, was die Wissenschaft droht der “Vermischung”?—</p>
                    <p>Sagt uns nicht deutlich die Bibel was der Darwinismus uns lehrt? (V. Buch Mos. 28. Ver. II) dass die Sterilität der Bastarde durch das Vermischen zweier Constitutionen zu einer verursacht sei?<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Und eben diesen Fluch spricht aus die Bibel “Mangel an Leibesfrucht u.s.w. und den “Wahnsinn” an Blutsverwandeten Abkömmlinge (c 29. v. 62)<ref target="#foot.f14"/> ist gewiss zu bestätigen mit Darwin’s Theorie!!!.</p>
<p>Wer den Darwinismus anerkennen will, glaube ich, der kan bei dem mosaischen Verfassungen recht getrost bleiben, und zwar noch mit <hi rend="underline">Licht</hi> und <hi rend="underline">Wahrheit</hi> mehr darin forschen—</p>
<p>Es soll mein grösstes Vergnügen sein wenn Er. Hochwohlg. mit Gunst meine Ansicht anerkenne, und mich wissen lasse (laut obenstehende Adresse) seinen Wohlwollen</p>
<p>Ich habe die Ehre Er Hochwohlg | ganz ergebenster und | gehorsamster Diener | zu zeichnen | Naphtali Lewÿ <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">29 Bakers Row | Whitechapl London E. | Den 14 Mai 1878—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
             
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>29 Baker’s Row | Whitechapel | London E.</placeName>
                    <salute>Yr Honour | the world-famous scientist | Charles Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Already in the year 1876 in the month of April I had the honour of receiving a letter from Yr Hon. (in Radom in Poland); now I would be pleased if the following argument also met with your approval, and if Yr Hon. would deign to honour me with a reply.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have always been meaning to write a comprehensive work about your theory in regard to Mosaic Law and the argument in question is a contribution to the same.</p>
                    <p>“In my work “Toldot-Adam” (the desc. of man) Vienna 1875., I have demonstrated that the biblical history of creation can be explained and commented on in the light of the Darwinian theory, and that the original language is well suited to the theory of transmutation in expression and content.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> So, we now want to try to find in the original text the very same as what science claims regarding hybridisation, and to show that the Darwinian theory in fact provides us with the key to the secret biblical law—</p>
<p>Let us review the main features of Darwinian theory. In the Origin chap. 9 <hi rend="underline">Hybridism</hi> it says:</p>
                    <p>1) With plants, hybridised embryos probably often perish in a like manner; at least it is known that hybrids raised from very distinct species are sometimes weak and dwarfed, and perish at an early age—.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> </p>
                    <p>2) ibid.: in both cases the sterility occurs in various degrees:<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>3) ibid   The above view of the sterility of hybrids being caused by two constitutions compounded into one has been strongly maintained by Max Wichura.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>What science calls a “hybrid”, the Bible refers to as an “illegitimate child”; it calls this “<hi rend="smallCaps">A Shameful Hybridism</hi>” תֶּבֶל (III Book of Moses Chap 20 V12)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> or better even for mixing two kinds it offers the expression <hi rend="smallCaps">le _rivoh</hi> לְרִבְעָה (ibid. Ve. 16)<ref target="#foot.f8"/> and every offspring of consanguineous parents it calls “<hi rend="underline">bastard</hi>” (ibid. Chap 18. Ve 6)<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Now let us see what punishment the Bible inflicts on such “obscenities”: it says (ibid Chap 18. Verse 24) “Mix not ye (this is the original meaning in Hebrew of  תְמַמְאוּ) yourselves with any of these things— the land has mixed itself and therefore vomiteth out her inhabitants”—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>Does this not mean the same as “that hybrids from distinct species are weak and dwarfed, and perish at an early age? Isn’t the vomiting out of the land the perishing at an early age of the hybridised embryos”—? don’t we read clearly (ibid. Chap. 20 V. 21), “Who has uncovered nakedness, they shall die childless”<ref target="#foot.f11"/>   is this more mysterious than what Darwin teaches on nature? Does not the Bible inflict the same punishment as that pronounced by science? “In both cases sterility is the outcome”—? (v ibid Vers 25)<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Isn’t the warning from the Bible “You must keep kinds apart” the same as what science warns will happen through “hybridisation”?—</p>
                    <p>Doesn’t the Bible tell us clearly the same as Darwinism teaches us? (V. Book of Mos. 28. Ver. II) that the sterility of hybrids is caused by compounding two constitutions into one?<ref target="#foot.f13"/> And the very curse the Bible pronounces, “lack of offspring etc and “madness” of consanguineous offspring (c 29. v. 62)<ref target="#foot.f14"/> surely confirms Darwin’s theory!!!.</p>
<p>He who wants to recognise Darwinism can in my opinion stick with the Mosaic Law, can even inquire into it more deeply with <hi rend="underline">light</hi> and <hi rend="underline">truth</hi>.—</p>
<p>It would be a very great pleasure for me if Yr Honour would acknowledge with favour my opinion, and assure me (at the above address) of his goodwill</p>
<p>I have the honour Yr Hon’s | wholly devoted and | most obedient servant | to sign | Naphtali Lewÿ  <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">29 Bakers Row | Whtechapel London E. | On 14 May 1878—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter has not been found, but see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10430.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from  Naphtali Lewy, [26 March – 24 April 1876]</ref>.</note>           
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s copy of Lewy’s essay was later lost (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref> 1: 365). It was published both in a periodical (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9157.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lewy 1874</ref>), and in book form (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9023.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lewy 1875</ref>).  Lewy’s thesis is discussed in Colp and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4427.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kohn 1996</ref>, pp. 1721–4.</note>           
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lewy quotes from the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref> (Bronn and Carus trans. 1876, p. 345; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 249).</note>          
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See Bronn and Carus trans. 1876, p. 346; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 250.</note>           
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See Bronn and Carus trans. 1876, p. 347; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 251.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In the German translation of the Bible made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6234.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Martin Luther</ref>, the first five books are referred to as I to V Mose (Moses); III Mose is Leviticus and V Mose is Deuteronomy. Lewy did not use Luther’s German translation, but seems to be translating directly from the Hebrew. Lev. 20:12: in the King James translation reads, ‘And if a man lie with his daughter in law, both of them shall surely be put to death: they have wrought confusion; their blood shall be upon them.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Le-rivoh (לְרִבְעָה) means ‘to copulate’. Lev. 20:16 in the King James translation reads, ‘And if a woman approach unto any beast, and lie down thereto, thou shalt kill the woman, and the beast: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In German, <hi rend="italic">Bastard</hi> can also be translated ‘hybrid’. Lev. 20:6 in the King James translation reads, ‘And the soul that turneth after such as have familiar spirits, and after wizards, to go a whoring after them, I will even set my face against that soul, and will cut him off from among his people.’ </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Lev. 18:25 in the King James translation reads, ‘And the land is defiled: therefore I do visit the iniquity thereof upon it, and the land itself vomiteth out her inhabitants.’</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Lev. 20:21 in the King James translation reads, ‘And if a man shall take his brother’s wife, it is an unclean thing: he hath uncovered his brother’s nakedness; they shall be childless.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Lev. 20:25 in the King James translation reads, ‘Ye shall therefore put difference between clean beasts and unclean, and between unclean fowls and clean: and ye shall not make your souls abominable by beast, or by fowl, or by any manner of living thing that creepeth on the ground, which I have separated from you as unclean.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Deut. 28:2 in the King James translation reads, ‘And all these blessings shall come on thee, and overtake thee, if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Deut. 28:62 (there is no verse 62 in Deut. 29) in the King James translation reads, ‘And ye shall be left few in number, whereas ye were as the stars of heaven for multitude; because thou wouldest not obey the voice of the Lord thy God.’</note>
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>