<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3452">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Searles Valentine Wood   18 February 1862</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11114</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3452 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3452.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3452.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 181: 144</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 144</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5228.xml">Wood, S. V.</persName>
                <placeName>Brentwood</placeName>
                <date when="1862-02-18">18 Feb 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Variation in Mollusca. The most abundant forms vary most.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Mollusca</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Brentwood | Essex</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much obliged by your very friendly note &amp; for your commendatory remark upon my monog<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have been waiting to see if I co<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> procure any information you require but I fear after all my delay I shall not be able to give a very satisfactory answer to your question.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>As a general rule among the Mollusca I may say that the Genus most abundant in species &amp; the species most abundant in individuals will present the greatest variation as we might naturally expect altho this rule like most others is not without exceptions   I have found some species of fossils which are but rare or sparingly exhibited present very great diversity of character   this possibly may have arisen from a paucity of individuals in one locality—while another locality which has not been examined or perhaps removed might have furnished them more abundantly &amp; the apparently rare species might not in reality have been so altho no doubt some animals have a greater tendency to change than others or possess a less adaptability to altered conditions by which of course greater permanence of character will be maintained. In regard to the the special genus Lucina there is I believe every possible variation between what are called sectional divisions &amp; the line of demarkation is extremely shadowy fading away in a most evanescent manner. The same may I believe be said of any other extensive Genus such as Helix, Unio, Cerithium, Conus Cypræa &amp;c &amp;c which have been divided into sections but which merge imperceptibly the one into the other</p>
<p>I presume that you are still employed collecting &amp; arranging data for your work of which the essay published is you tell us but an outline   I hope that I may live to see it &amp; that you may have health &amp; strength to complete the work you have begun<ref target="#foot.f3"/>   I may add in reference to your remark about the obloquy thrown upon it that it has been a great surprise to me that so much toleration has been accorded to you as seems to me to have been the case   I admired your courage in so boldly avowing your opinions</p>
<p>The mistake into which Authors like that of the vestiges<ref target="#foot.f4"/> fell by treating the organic world as a chain of developement in a continuous line instead of as an ever diverging ramification of being had furnished the opponents of the Theory of the origin of beings by the natural process of production out of a preexisting form with the means of an easy victory &amp; it was in the midst of the general gratulation at this “scotching of the snake” that your sounder views came upon the world &amp; backed by the reputation that you had previously so justly acquired   they co<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not be so easily poohpoohed as might have been the case had they emanated from a less known man. I think that your thus boldly coming forwar〈d〉 is a merit of itself (apart from that attaching to the lucid developement of your argument〈)〉 &amp; I rather suspect that there are other naturalists who have by their studies been forced to regard this natural origin of being as the true one but have not the confidence to avow their conviction in the face of the opprobrium which has been attached to such opinions</p>
<p>Believe me Dear Sir | Yours very truly | Searles Wood <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Feb. 18. 62</p>
<p>Chas Darwin Esq</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.1 Genus … without 2.3] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 I presume … production 4.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘S. Wood | Feb 18 | 1862’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter has not been found. The reference is to the first part of Wood’s monograph on Eocene bivalves, which was published in December 1861 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">S. V. Wood 1861–77</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Evidently CD’s question concerned whether species belonging to large genera of molluscs were more variable and wider ranging than those from small genera; this had a bearing on his principle of divergence, first outlined in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 111–30 (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4426.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kohn 1985</ref>). In order to demonstrate the connection between large genera and variable species, CD had already given the results of his extensive tabulation of the genera listed in the floras of various countries in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 54–8. For a discussion of CD’s objective in relation to his botanical work, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_989.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Browne 1980</ref> and 1983.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the introduction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (pp. 1–6), CD explained that he regarded the work as an abstract of a larger work yet to be completed. The only part of this larger work that was published during CD’s lifetime was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (1868). The remaining draft chapters of what CD called his ‘big book’ were published posthumously as <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The first edition of <hi rend="italic">Vestiges of the natural history of creation</hi> was published anonymously in 1844 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1348.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Chambers] 1844</ref>). It argued for a designed progressive evolution of life, and aroused a storm of protest and criticism. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_875.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Chambers</ref> was thought by many to be the author of the work, but this was not confirmed publicly until 1884, well after his death. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7065.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Secord 1989</ref> and Secord ed. 1995.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>