<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13252F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [25 July 1881]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21539</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13252F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13252F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13252F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 67</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>271.1: 67</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>
                <date when="1881-07-25">[25 July 1881]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on a visit to Hermann Vöchting and discussion of Julius Sachs.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-15" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name> </change>
        <change when="2020-03-11" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-23" status="editorResponseCompleted">Responded <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
    <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bot Inst | Strassburg</placeName>
                    <date>Monday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I went on Sunday yesterday to Basel to see Vöchting<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and a very pleasant visit indeed, he gave me a warm welcome, &amp; shook hands at intervals of a few minutes, saying how glad he was I had come to see him. I had a great deal of interesting talk with him, one thing aggravates me a good deal. In my bramble paper I said that his exp on weeping trees were not a full proof against Sachs, because he (Sachs) might say that the shoot stuff was here geotrop instead of apogeotrop,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but Vöchting showed me that his experiments were a full proof because ultimately the strongest branches grow out
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width30">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13252F_1.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
at the side like <hi rend="underline">a</hi> just as they would if it had been an ordinary branch tied down. It was awfully stupid of me and aggravates me a good deal; I didn’t quite realise it when I was with him, not till I came back here &amp; re-read his paper in the Bot Zeitung,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> so my aggravation didn’t come on in time to spoil my time with him; it is all the more aggravating as I needn’t have said it at all.</p>
<p>He began telling me that he had been experimenting on the position of the flowers in Narcissus; &amp; found the same thing that I did namely that they straighten themselves 
    <figure rend="inline width25">
        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13252F_2.jpg"/>
    </figure> 
instead of
    <figure rend="inline width15">
        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13252F_3.jpg"/>
    </figure>  
when grown on the Klinostat, &amp; that they are dia-geotropic, he was very much astonished that I had been doing it, he has done a number of flowers in the same way &amp; it will be published in his new book.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I wish I had felt surer that it was worth going in more for; I shall perhaps repeat my experiments with Narcissus &amp; publish them, &amp; I shall go on with similar ones I began on the position of the anthers &amp;c in Azalea<ref target="#foot.f6"/>   He will make a splendid proof out of this that gravity acts as a stimulus   it is rather too complicated to explain   There is another coincidence, he said that he had made up his mind next summer to do my experiment with leaves in relation to light on the Klinostat, when he got my paper.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>He is a most pleasant man &amp; was over flowing with hospitality   he took me to dine at the Hotel &amp; to supper at a garden &amp; wouldn’t hear of my paying for myself   He is not married so he doesn’t dine at home. He was very enthusiastic about the Power of Movements<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; thinks it will have a great effect</p>
<p>He was continually saying But now tell me some more about your father &amp; was extremely interested in anything I could tell him, about your hours of work &amp;c. He told me a horrid piece of news about Sachs, he says he has heard it from two sources &amp; has no doubt about it; that M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Sachs<ref target="#foot.f9"/> is so little if at all insane that her friends have taken her out of the private asylum with his permission, &amp; now she lives at Bonn with her friends, &amp; he has a mistress at Würzburg (but not in his house)   if it wasn’t that I want to see Kunkel at Wzbg I really dont think I should go.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> If I go I will certainly call on Semper.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I shall try &amp; get home on Monday night the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Aug &amp; shall leave here either Wednesday or Thursday (27 or 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>)</p>
<p>I had sent off my notice about the nectary paper before I got yr letter</p>
<p>I never thought abt what you say about it being a reason for protecting the honey, it is a very true &amp; a neat reason—<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                    <p>Yr affec F.D.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
      
      
      <div type="footnotes">
          <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the reference to Francis’s leaving Straßburg (Strasbourg) on Wednesday 27 or Thursday 28. Francis worked at <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref>’s laboratory in Straßburg in 1881, arriving home on 1 August (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). In 1881, the Monday before 27 July was 25 July.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4851.xml">Hermann Vöchting</ref>.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml">Julius Sachs</ref>. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10539.xml">F. Darwin 1880b</ref>, p. 417.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11187.xml">Vöchting 1880</ref>.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi> is the genus of daffodil and narcissus. Vöchting experimented on two species, <hi rend="italic">N. pseudonarcissus</hi> (common daffodil), and <hi rend="italic">N. poeticus</hi> (poet’s narcissus; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9836.xml">Vöchting 1882</ref>).</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f6">Francis did not publish specifically on <hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi> or azaleas (<hi rend="italic">Rhododendron</hi>), but for remarks on <hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11108.xml">F. Darwin and Acton 1894</ref>, pp. 178–80, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9837.xml">F. Darwin 1901</ref>, p. 41.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10623.xml">F. Darwin 1880a</ref>.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8980.xml">Johanna Sachs</ref>.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8981.xml">Adam Josef Kunkel</ref> was a particular friend of Francis’s (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1804.xml">F. Darwin 1920a</ref>, p. 68).</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4291.xml">Carl Gottfried Semper</ref>.</note>
          <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD’s letter to Francis has not been found. For the notice, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13245F.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 16 July 1881</ref> and n. 4. The paper was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9835.xml">W. P. Wilson 1881</ref>. CD evidently speculated on the function of nectar secretion, which <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8978.xml">William Powell Wilson</ref> had described as being the result of osmosis rather than internal pressure (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9835.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">W. P. Wilson 1881</ref>, p. 5).</note>
      </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>