<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10280F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Quintino Sella<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   28 November 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20841A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10280F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10280F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10280F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp encl 1p</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 229: 43, DAR 230: 44</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>229: 43</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>230: 44</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent" subtype="personGrp">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4284.xml">Sella, Quintino</persName>
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_18.xml">Accademia dei Lincei</persName>
                <date when="1875-11-28">28 Nov 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Letter enclosing decree from the Accademia dei Lincei, with signatures dated 2 and 16 July 1875.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Accademia dei Lincei</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-08-13" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes">n.4</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Reale Accademia de’Lincei | Roma</hi></placeName>
                    <date>28 Novembre <hi rend="print">187</hi>5.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental"><hi rend="italic">Protoc<hi rend="superscript">lo</hi>. N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</hi> 448 | <hi rend="italic">Risposta al foglio N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. ——</hi> | <hi rend="italic">Del giorno</hi> —— | <hi rend="italic">Oggetto</hi> | Nomina a Socio dell’Accademia | <hi rend="italic">Allegati N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</hi> 1</seg>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Al Chiarissimo Signore | Sig<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carlo Roberto Darwin | Londra.</seg>
                    <salute>Illustre Signore.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Sua Maestà il Rè d’Italia con Suo decreto del 4 Febbrajo 1875, si degnò rifermare l’Accademia dè Lincei.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Nell’astratto delle sedute dell’Accademia del 24. e 25 Gennajo 1875, che ho l’onore di trasmetterle, Ella vedrà le ragioni, e la natura della riferma. Ella vi troverà pure il nuovo Statuto dell’Accademia.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Oltre al dividersi l’Accademia in due Classi, l’una per le Scienze Fisiche, Matematiche, e Naturali, e l’altra per le Scienze Morali, Storiche, e Filologiche, vennero assegnati a ciascuna delle due Classi 10 Soci Straniei (art 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> dello Statuto) i quali godono di tutti i diritti che spettano ai Soci Nazionali. Prendono parte alle adunanze, ed alle votazioni (Art<hi rend="superscript">i</hi> 18. 21). Quando sono in Italia prendono anche parte alla elezione dei Soci (Art<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 12).</p>
<p>La Classe di Scienze Fisiche, Matematiche, e Naturali procedette già alla elezione di otto de’ Suoi Soci stranieri.</p>
<p>Mi è ora gratissimo il potere annunziare alla S.V. Chiarissima, che Ella fù <hi rend="italic">[</hi>eletta<hi rend="italic">]</hi> uno dei X Soci stranieri della Classe di Scienze Fisiche, Matematiche, e Naturali, e che la Sua nomina fù approvata da S.M. il Rè d’Italia, con Suo Decreto del 2 Luglio 1875.</p>
<p>Mi faccio un dovere di mandarle copia del Decreto di Sua Maestà, ed a Suo tempo avrò l’onore di mandarle il Diploma Accademico.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Io mi rallegro coll’Accademia che hà acquistato in Lei un Collega, ed un Collaboratore che ha reso servizi così eminenti alla Scienza; e spero che del pari Ella gradirà la manifestazione di stima che Le volle dare l’Italia unita nell’eterna Sua Capitale, aggregandola come Suo Socio straniero effetivo alla più antica delle Accademie Scientifiche esistenti.</p>
<p>Tutti i Colleghi si terrebbero onorati, se Ella mandasse all’Accademia memorie, o communicazioni originali. Esse verranno tosto stampate nel Volume Accademico nella lingua in cui faranno scritte, e l’autore riceverà cento copie della stampa a parte della memoria, o communicazione.</p>
<p>Gradisca, Egregio Collega, i miei fraterni saluti.</p>
<p>Il Presidente | Q Sella</p>
<p>P.S. La S.V. riceverà presto il primo, e secondo volume della seconda Serie degli Atti dell’Accademia. Della prima Serie non si hanno copie sufficienti per poterne fare distribuzione ai Soci. Mi pregio però mandarle una copia del Volume 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. di detta Serie, il quale potrà interessarla pei ragguagli storici intorno all’Accademia, che contiene.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">VITTORIO EMANUELE II</hi></p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">PER GRAZIA DI DIO E PER VOLONTÀ DELLA NAZIONE</hi></p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">RE D’ITALIA</hi></p> 
<p>Visto lo Statuto dell’Accademia de’ Lincei di Roma approvato col Nostro Decreto del 14 Febbrajo 1875;</p>
<p>Vista la lettera del Presidente di detta Accademia del 16 Giugno 1875;</p>
<p>Sulla proposta del Nostro Ministro Segretario di Stato per la pubblica Istruzione:<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Abbiamo decretato e decretiamo:</p>
<p>Sono approvate le nomine, fatte dalla suddetta Accademia, de’ Signori:</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Carlo Roberto Darwin</hi> (Londra) a Soci Stranieri della classe di scienze fisische, matematiche e naturali dell’Accademia de’ Lincei di Roma.</p>
<p>Il predetto Nostro Ministro è incaricato della esecuzione del presente Decreto, che sarà registrato alla Corte dei Conti.</p>
<p>Dato a Sant’Anna a di 2 Luglio 1875</p>
<p>f<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Vittorio Emanuele | f. Ruggiero Bonghi</p>
<p>Reg.<hi rend="superscript">to</hi> alla Corte dei Conti | Li 16 Luglio 1875 | R<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 432 D. Lerf. a C<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>152 | f<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Ayres.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Visto conforme all’Originale esistente | nell’Archivo dell Accademia | Roma | Il Presidente | per | P. Volpicelli Seg<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Per estratto dall’originale Decreto | V<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Il Direttore Capo della Divisione 2<hi rend="superscript">ei</hi>. f<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Reale Accademia de’Lincei | Rome</hi></placeName>
                    <date>28 November <hi rend="print">187</hi>5.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental"><hi rend="italic">Protoc<hi rend="superscript">ol</hi>. N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</hi> 448 | <hi rend="italic">Reply to document N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></hi>. —— | <hi rend="italic">Of</hi> —— | <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi> | Nomination as Fellow of the Academy | <hi rend="italic">N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. of enclosures</hi> 1</seg>
                    <seg type="supplemental">To the most distinguished Sir | M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles Robert Darwin | London.</seg>
                    <salute>Esteemed Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>His majesty the King of Italy by His decree of 4 February 1875 has deigned to confirm the Accademia dè Lincei.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>From the minutes of the sessions of the Academy of 24 and 25 January 1875, which I have the honour of passing on to you, you will glean the reasons, and the nature of this confirmation. You will also find the new Statutes of the Academy.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>In addition to dividing the Academy in two Sections, one for Physical, Mathematical and Natural Sciences, the other for Moral Sciences, History and Philology, each of the two Sections were allotted 10 Foreign Members (art. 2 of the Statutes) who enjoy all the rights that are due to the National Members. They participate in the assemblies and in the elections (art.s 18, 21). When they are in Italy, they also participate in the election of Members (Art. 12).</p>
<p>The Section of Physical, Mathematical and Natural Sciences has already elected eight of its Foreign Members.</p>
<p>It is a great pleasure for me to be able to announce to your most distinguished highness that you have been nominated one of the X foreign members of the Section of Physical, Mathematical and Natural Sciences, and that your nomination has been approved by H.M. the King of Italy, in His Decree of 2 July 1875.</p>
<p>It is my duty to send you the Decree of His Majesty, and in due course I will have the honour of sending you the Academic Diploma.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I rejoice with the Academy to have acquired in you a Colleague, and a Collaborator who has rendered science such eminent service, and I hope that you, too, will appreciate the demonstration of esteem which Italy, united in its Eternal Capital, wants to make towards you by admitting you to the most ancient of existing Scientific Academies as Her Active Foreign member.</p>
<p>All your Colleagues would consider it an honour if you sent to the Academy papers or original communications. They will be speedily published in the Academic Volume in the language in which they have been written, and the author will receive a hundred offprints of the paper or communication.</p>
<p>May you, distinguished Colleague, accept my fraternal greetings.</p>
<p>The President | Q Sella</p>
<p>P.S. Your honour will soon receive the first and second volume of the second Series of the Atti dell’Accademia. Of the first Series there are not sufficient copies for distribution among the Members. I have however the honour of sending you a copy of the first Volume of the said Series, which may interest you since it contains historical information about the Academy.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">VITTORIO EMANUELE II</hi></p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">BY THE GRACE OF GOD AND THE WILL OF THE NATION</hi></p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">KING OF ITALY</hi></p> 
<p>We have seen the Statute of the Accademia de’ Lincei of Rome that was approved by Our Decree of 14 February 1875;</p>
<p>We have seen the letter of the President of the said Academy of 16 June 1875;</p>
<p>At the suggestion of our Minister the Secretary of State for public instruction:</p>
<p>We have decreed and we decree:</p>
<p>The nominations, made by the above-mentioned Academy, of the gentlemen:</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Charles Robert Darwin</hi> (London) | as Foreign Members of the class of physical, mathematical and natural sciences of the Accademia de’ Lincei of Rome are approved.</p>
<p>Our aforesaid Minister has been charged with the execution of this Decree, which will be registered at the State Audit Court.</p>
<p>Granted at Sant’Anna on 2 July 1875</p>
<p>Signed Vittorio Emanuele | signed Ruggiero Bonghi<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Registered at the State Audit Court | on 16 July 1875 | Reg. 432D. at the Court 152 | signed Ayres.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Certified as similar to the existing Original | in the Archive of the Academy | Rome | The President | per. | P. Volpicelli Secr.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>For the copy from the original Decree | V<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. The Director Head of Division 2<hi rend="superscript">ei</hi> signed</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 466–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The king of Italy was Victor Emmanuel II.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The minutes and statutes of the Accademia have not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The diploma has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Issues of the <hi rend="italic">Atti dell’Accademia dei Lincei</hi> from 1875–80 are in the collection of unbound journals in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7561.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ruggiero Bonghi</ref> was the minister of education from 1874 to 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1893.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DBI</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Ayres has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7566.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paolo Volpicèlli</ref> was a secretary of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_18.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Accademia dei Lincei</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EI</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>