<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5540">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Camille Dareste<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   19 May 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16665</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5540 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5540.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5540.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp French</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 43</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 43</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1196.xml">Dareste, G. M. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Lille</placeName>
                <date when="1867-05-19">19 May 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD’s letter [<hi rend="doubleUnderline">3992</hi>] gave him encouragement in his work [on monstrosities], which, he regrets, is little understood or appreciated in France. Hopes to be able to produce anomalies at will as a result of his experiments. Sends a recent paper ["Rapport sur un veau monstrueux", <hi rend="italic">Arch. Com. Agric. Arrondissement Lille</hi> (1867)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">3992</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">veal</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Arch. Com. Agric. Arrondissement Lille</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">France</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Dareste, G. M. C. 1867</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lille;</placeName>
                    <date>19 Mai 1867.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Vous n’avez peut-être pas oublié que vous avez reçu, il y a cinq ans, un travail d’un Professeur d’histoire naturelle de Lille, sur la production artificielle des monstruosités. La lettre que vous lui avez écrite, et qu’il conserve précieusement, lui prouvait que vous aviez bien voulu prendre connaissance de ce travail et le lire avec quelqu’intérêt.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Cette lettre a été pour lui, ou plutôt pour moi, car c’est de moi qu’il s’agit ici, le meilleur de tous les encouragements; car je le dis avec beaucoup de regret, mes travaux sont, pour le moment, fort peu appréciés en France. Un seul homme les avait bien compris, c’etait Is. Geoffroy Saint-hilaire. Depuis sa mort, on n’y a, malheureusement, attaché qu’une attention très distraite.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Depuis que je vous ai écris, j’ai continué mes travaux avec une grande persévérance, et j’ai pu assister au développement embryogènique de presque toutes les formes de la monstruosité. Ce travail sera, je l’espère, terminé dans un an, et je pourrai alors en entreprendre la publication.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Jusqu’à présent, j’ai dû me contenter d’en faire connaître les principaux résultats dans les comptes rendus de l’Académie des Sciences de Paris;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> et ces notes n’ayant pas été tirées à part, je n’ai pas pu vous les faire remettre. Quand ce premier travail sera terminé, je pourrai, je l’espère, arriver à déterminer les conditions de la production des monstres, et produire ainsi à volonté, telle ou telle anomalie. Je possède déjà un certain nombre d’indications à ce sujet; et j’ai tous lieu de croire que je pourrai les completer. Je vous tiendrai alors au courant de tous ce que j’aurai réussi sur un sujet, qui se rattache trop à vos propres études pour ne pas vous intéresser un peu.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>En attendant, je vous adresse un petit travail qui se rattache directement à une question que vous avez vous même observée. Elle est relative aux boeufs <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> de l’Amérique du Sud.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> J’ai eu occasion d’étudier un de ces Animaux qui eu né spontanément à Lille, d’une vache flamande ordinaire, et qui reproduisait exactement les Caractères des <hi rend="underline">niata.</hi> Si cet animal avait pu arriver à l’âge de la puberté, il aurait pu donner à ces descendants les caractères qui le distinguaient. Ce fait est parfaitement en rapport avec vos travaux sur l’espèce; j’ai donc pris le parti de vous l’adresser.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Et à ce propos je dois vous dire que les conclusions que j’en ai voulu tirer relativement à la formation de la race <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> ont été contredites assez vivement en France. Il y a des personnes, assez aveuglées par des fausses théories pour ne pas vouloir admettre l’existence de la race <hi rend="underline">niãta</hi>, et pour rejeter entièrement votre témoinage.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Je serais heureux si vous pouviez le donner de nouveau d’une manière bien evidente.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>J’ai eu occasion egalement de constater dans la race des poules Du Saxes, la production de deux individues qui portaient le caractère céphalique et cérébral des poules polonaises. Une hernie du cerveau, qui plus tard se revêt d’une enveloppe osseuse résultant de l’ossification de la fontanelle.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Veuillez m’excuser, Monsieur, de v〈ous〉 interrompre en vous parlant de mes travaux: mais je crois qu’ils se lient aux vôtres par des liens très étroits   J’espère toujours que mes études me conduiront à quelques considérations nouvelles sur la formation des espèces, et que mon travail pourra peut-être un jour prendre place dans la Science, après votre livre, quoiqu’ à une bien grande distance (<hi rend="underline">longo sed proximus intervallo</hi>)<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>C’est l’une des pensées qui me soutient la place dans la carrière souvent ingrate que j’ai entreprise.</p>
<p>Recevez je vous prie, l’expression de mon admiration et de mon respect. | Camille Dareste <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Professeur à la Faculté des Sciences de Lille.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lille;</placeName>
                    <date>19 May 1867.</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Perhaps you have not forgotten that you received, some five years ago, a paper from a Professor of natural history in Lille on the artificial creation of monstrosities. The letter that you wrote to him, which he preserves carefully, showed him that you really wished to understand his work and read it with some interest.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This letter was for him, or rather for me since I refer to myself, the greatest of all encouragements; for I regret to say that my work is at the moment very little appreciated in France. Only one man understood it well and that was Is. Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire. Since his death there has been alas, only a very faint interest in it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Since I last wrote to you, I have continued my work with great perseverance, and I have been able to observe the embryological development of almost every stage of the monstrosity. This work will, I hope, be completed in a year, and I will then be able to have it published.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Up to now, I have had to satisfy myself with making the major results known in the proceedings of the Académie des Sciences in Paris;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and since these notes are not published as offprints, I have not been able to send them to you. When this preliminary work is completed, I will be able, I hope, to discover the conditions under which monsters develop, and thus produce this or that anomaly at will. I already possess a certain number of preliminary indications on this subject; and I have every reason to believe that I can follow them up. I will then keep you informed about everything I succeed with in a subject that is too close to your own studies not to interest you a little.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Meanwhile, I am sending you a little work that is directly related to a question that you yourself have observed. This concerns the <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> cattle of South America.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I had occasion to study one of these animals which was born spontaneously in Lille from an ordinary Flemish cow and which exactly reproduced the characteristics of the <hi rend="underline">niata.</hi> Had this animal survived to the age of puberty, it would have passed on to its descendants its distinguishing characteristics. This fact accords perfectly with your work on species; I therefore decided to send it to you.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>And speaking of this, I must tell you that the conclusions that I wished to draw relative to the formation of the <hi rend="underline">niata</hi> race have been rather vigorously opposed in France. There are some people so blinded by false theories that they do not want to admit the existence of the <hi rend="underline">niãta</hi> race and reject your testimony completely.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I would be happy if you could give it once again in the clearest possible way.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Equally, I had occasion to observe the production of two individuals of the Du Saxe poultry breed that possessed cephalic and cerebral characters similar to Polish hens. A hernia of the brain that later becomes enclosed in a bony envelope results from the ossification of the fontanelle.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Please excuse me, Sir, for troubling you by speaking of my work: but I believe that it is linked to yours by very close bonds. I am always hoping that my research will lead me to some new discovery regarding the formation of species and that my work might one day take its place in Science, after your book, although at a rather great distance (<hi rend="underline">longo sed proximus intervallo</hi>).<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>That is one of the thoughts that sustains me in the often thankless career that I have undertaken.</p>
<p>Please accept the expression of my admiration and respect. | Camille Dareste <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Professor at the Faculté des Sciences of Lille</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 266–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Dareste wrote to CD on 8 February 1863, enclosing a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dareste 1863</ref>; CD replied in a letter dated 16 February [1863] (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11). There is a lightly annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dareste 1863</ref>, in which Dareste provides an account of monstrosities artificially induced in chicken eggs, in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1840.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire</ref> died in 1861; he had worked on teratology, like his father, Etienne Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, whose work influenced Dareste (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tort 1996</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Dareste published a book summarising his research in teratology in 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1778.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dareste 1877</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Dareste published articles on teratology regularly in the <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus hebdomadaires des séances de l’Académie des sciences.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD cited Dareste a number of times on teratology in the second volume of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>, and commended his work in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 338.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Niata: ‘An abnormally small variety of cattle, found in South America’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). CD discussed niata cattle in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 145–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">There is a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dareste 1867</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Rapport sur un veau monstreaux</hi>, in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Dareste suggested that monstrous forms, under the right conditions, could originate new races.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Dareste had been involved in an exchange of papers with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">André Sanson</ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus hebdomadaires des séances de l’Académie des sciences.</hi> Sanson denied the existence of a race of niata cattle in South America; Dareste had cited CD as one of his authorities. See <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus</hi> 64 (1867): 423–6, 669–70, 743–5, 822–4, 1101–3. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, letters from Armand de Quatrefages, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">[28 March –] 11 April 1863</ref> and n. 4, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">19 May [1863]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD discussed niata cattle in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 89–91; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5547.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Camille Dareste, 23 May 1867</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See Dareste’s first paper in <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus</hi> (see n. 9, above): ‘Mémoire sur le mode de production de certaines races d’animaux domestiques’. CD discussed the skulls of Polish and other crested breeds of fowl in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 262–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Longo sed proximus intervallo</hi>: ‘The next, but after a long interval. A poor second’ (H. P. Jones ed. 1900).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>