<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12504">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Adolf Ernst   29 February 1880</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16797</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12504 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12504.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12504.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="28">28</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 163: 21</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>163: 21</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1523.xml">Ernst, Adolf</persName>
                <placeName>Caracas</placeName>
                <date when="1880-02-29">29 Feb 1880</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Plants in Venezuelan plains.</p> 
<p>Observations on <hi rend="italic">Turnera</hi>: heterostyly, leaf-base glands’ secretion eaten by ants.</p>  
<p>Observations on role of leaf secretions in fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Marcgravia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Passiflora</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ants</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Marcgravia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Passiflora</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Turnera</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">plains</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Venezuela</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-10-22" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-12-12" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2019-01-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-05-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2019-05-29" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00061_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00061_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="21:1r" xml:id="i61">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00061.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00061_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00061.dzi" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:1v" xml:id="i62">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00062.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00062_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00062.dzi" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:2r" xml:id="i63">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00063.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00063_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00063.dzi" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:2v" xml:id="i64">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00064.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00064_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00064.dzi" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:3r" xml:id="i65">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00065.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00065_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00065.dzi" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="21:3v" xml:id="i66">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00066.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00066_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00163-000-00066.dzi" width="5569px" height="7455px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Caracas,</placeName>
                    <date>february 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1880</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Many thanks for your highly encouraging letters.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The first I did not answer hitherto, because I expected to find an opportunity to visit once more our plains, where I intended to pay a close attention to the point of your inquiry.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> However this opportunity is not yet come: my professional work at the University keeps me month after month in town, and when holidays come, there are examinations, and special commissions, and I do not know what not. When I first saw the plains (in February 1874), it was at the end of the dry season; and though there are undoubtedly a good many plants with glaucous leaves (especially Cyperaceæ and Eriocaulaceæ),<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I do not recollect that the general appearance of the flora struck me as glaucous. I think it would be best to make observations in the middle of the rainy season, where any difference ought to be more striking.</p>
<p>I am very glad that my observation on <hi rend="underline">Melochia</hi> was of any interest for you, and shall attend to your indications in further experiment.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I think heterostyled flowers are far more numerous than is generally believed. I lately noticed that <hi rend="underline">Turnera ulmifolia</hi> is in the same case, though there is scarcely any difference in the shape and size of the pollen grains.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am preparing to make a series of experiments with this species, and shall later report on them.</p>
                    <p>There is in this Turnera another point, which I think is sufficiently interesting to be studied carefully; unfortunately I am not able to do it. The two glands at the base of the leaves are very remarkable organs. Morphologically I believe them to be either modified teeth of the margin, or atrophied lateral leaflets. A vascular bundle enters each of them. The produce a sugary secretion, which appears on their surface as a clear drop, where it is eagerly sucked by ants. It is next to impossible to find one single plant without half a dozen or more of these insects fairly stationed among the rather densely crowded leaves on the upper end of the stems. Besides this secretion of sugar, there are <hi rend="underline">a great many sphaeraphides of oxalate of lime</hi> in the tissue of the gland. This circumstance appears to me of interest, and suggestive of the question whether there can be a certain relation between both substances. But this point I must leave to persons more versed in organic chemistry than I am. I may be allowed to add, that I never saw an ant, nor indeed, any other insect, in the corollas of Turnera.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>Just when I was examining the glands of Turnera, I received Bonnier’s memoir “On Nectaries”, publ. in the <hi rend="underline">Annales de Sciences naturelles</hi>. I must confess that I cannot agree with his conclusion that the physiological work of any kind of nectary is “<hi rend="underline">en relation</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">directe</hi> <hi rend="underline">avec la vie de la plante</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> If the nectaries produce <hi rend="underline">always</hi> substances <hi rend="underline">directly</hi> useful for the plant, how is it, I ask, that generally so much, if not the whole of these substances flows away, being thus exposed, as really happens, to be stolen by insects? Every physiological work has of course a certain purpose, but this may be either direct or indirect, and if the first is neither apparent nor demonstrable, it is but natural to look for the second.</p>
                    <p>I have made observations on two plants, where the <hi rend="underline">direct</hi> usefulness of similar productions appears to me out of any question. We have a species of Marcgravia, it is probably the <hi rend="underline">M. acuminata</hi> <hi rend="underline">Miq</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The flowers (about 30) occupy an inch more or less of the branch, whilst the 6 to 8 pitcher-like bracts grow all from the very end of the branch. These pitchers are somewhat of the shape of a Phrygian cap, and about two inches long, their peduncle included (see the sketch). 
                        <figure rend="blockCentred width10">
                            <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12504.svg"/>
                        </figure>                         
They hang of course perpendicular, whilst the flowers are so placed that nearly all of them are in the same horizontal plane. Now, there is honey in the pitchers up to the day when the floral envelops drop off, and fragments of them are still adhering. But as soon as these too are falling away, fecundation must be realized, the stamens wither very soon, and the pitchers are honey-less, dry up, and get black, but remain for some time hanging on the branch. Their honey-making function ends therefore with the opening of the flowers and the probably immediate fecundation of the same, so that there remains nothing for further reabsorption.</p>
                    <p>Another case is that of <hi rend="underline">Passiflora biflora</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> There is in the middle of each leaflobe, on its underface, a conspicuous gland, which produces a considerable quantity of sweet honey. The secretion is so energic, that plants which had been one night kept in my <hi rend="underline">vasculum</hi>, had on all their leaves drops of this substance. It is sought after by hymenopterous insects, as I had several times occasion to see. Of what <hi rend="underline">direct</hi> use can this secretion be to the plant? The leaves certainly would grow without, nor is the secretion as such useful for the plant, because it must lose by it a large quantity of sugar. It is on the contrary very easy to observe, how the insects in their search for the drops of honey, scramble over flowers on every part of the little creeper, and assist thus in fecundating the stigmata. I have planted some specimens in my little garden, and will try to find out whether there is any fecundation without insects, and whether the plants will grow, when the places of the leaves with the glands are punched out.</p>
<p>Is it known that the fierce little ants, which inhabit the hollow stems and branches of <hi rend="underline">Triplaris americana</hi>, keep <hi rend="underline">scale-insects</hi> in their lodgings?<ref target="#foot.f10"/> They are very abundant, and even in the thinnest branches it is easy to discover them among the brown felt-like substance which covers the inside of the wood.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">Abutilon striatum</hi> <hi rend="underline">Dicks.</hi> introduced here from Perú, as people say, thrives not any longer, and never set fruit.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I have seen humming-birds attacking the flowers from outside, perforating the calyx, and thus robbing the honey. I have been told that about 40 years ago, Señor Antonio L. Guzman, father of our actual President,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> brought <hi rend="underline">one</hi> plant from Peru, and that from this by cuttings all the other specimens were derived. In the last years all have small leaves with many yellow spots, and flower very poorly. The species is evidently dying out with us.</p>
<p>Some years ago a friend of mine discovered in the mountains towards the south of Caracas the very handsome <hi rend="underline">Ionidium anomalum HBK</hi> (Nov. Gen. et Sp. V, pl. 500), and brought seeds, which were sown in several gardens. The plants grew everywhere, but none produced ripe seeds. It is evident that insect help was wanted, as might have been expected, the large snow white labellum of the flower looking just like a beautiful landing-place for welcome visitors.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I have lately obtained good seeds by artificial fecundation, but only from two flowers.—</p>
<p>I apologize for this long letter, but hope that you will excuse me, as I am desirous to communicate to you some facts which perhaps are not entirely void of interest. Unfortunately this year I am bound to teach mineralogy, a study which is somewhat out of my line, so that it keeps up nearly all my time. We have here the queer old system of a Professorship of Natural History, so that I must lecture one year on botany, one year on Zoology, and another year on Mineralogy: rather hard work in our times! And this the more so, as with respect to Geology, there is no poorer place on God’s earth than the valley of Carácas, entirely built of metamorphic rocks, and showing nothing else but interesting examples of gigantic denudation. Field-work, with me the best thing I use to do with my students, is therefore not very productive. In this connection I take the liberty to make you a request. I have nearly every line you have published, but not your works on Coral Reefs and on the volcanic islands and parts of South America.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Would you honour me with a copy of each of them? It is needless to say that I would prize both as tokens of your kindness towards an humble, but sincere, fellow-worker in the extensive fields of your scientific researches.</p>
<p>Allow me to add that Venezuela belongs now to the postal Union, so that simple lettres pay no more postage than 2<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> pence, and printed matter a halfpenny for every 50 grammes.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> I think you had a shilling stamp on your last letter.</p>
<p>I am, dear Sir, very truly yours | A Ernst</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.7 and though … glaucous. 1.9] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>2.3 I lately … grains. 2.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1523.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolf Ernst</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11321.xml">16 January 1878</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 26), and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12402.xml">5 January 1880</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had asked whether plants growing on interior dry plains were more likely to be glaucous, that is, protected by a waxy or powdery secretion (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 26, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11321.xml">letter to Adolf Ernst, 16 January 1878</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Cyperaceae is the family of sedges; Eriocaulaceae is the family of pipewort. These families are widely represented in the Venezuelan llanos (plains) and tepuis (flat-topped mountain summits).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had suggested that Ernst try experiments on the fertility of illegitimate seedlings of <hi rend="italic">Melochia parvifolia</hi>, a neotropical species of the subfamily Byttnerioideae of the Malvaceae or mallow family (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12402.xml">letter to Adolf Ernst, 5 January 1880</ref> and n. 2). CD mentioned Ernst’s discovery of heterostyly in this species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9500.xml"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. v. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Turnera ulmifolia</hi> is ramgoat dashalong or sage-rose, a member of the Passifloraceae (passion-flower family). Most varieties of this species are heterostyled.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Turnera ulmifolia</hi> bears foliar nectaries on the petiole of the leaf. Oxalate of lime is now usually referred to as calcium oxalate (CaC<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>O<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>, the calcium salt of oxalic acid); sphaeraphides are globular clusters of raphides, needle-shaped crystals of calcium oxalate. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_532.xml">Gaston Bonnier</ref>’s doctoral thesis ‘Les nectaires. Étude critique, anatomique et physiologique’ (Nectaries. A critical anatomical and physiological study; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11008.xml">Bonnier 1879b</ref>) was published in <hi rend="italic">Annales des sciences naturelles</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botanique</hi>) in 1879. For Bonnier’s conclusion that the work of the nectary is directly related to the life of the plant (‘<hi rend="italic">en relation direct avec la vie de la plante</hi>’), see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 206.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Marcgravia acuminata</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">M. coriacea</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Passiflora biflora</hi> is twoflower passion-flower.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Triplaris americana</hi> is the ant-tree, a species of knotweed (family Polygonaceae). It has a mutualistic relationship with ants, particularly the species <hi rend="italic">Pseudomyrmex triplarinus</hi>. Ants of this genus raise scale insects (subfamily Coccoidea) in excavated cavities (domatia) in the stem and branches.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Abutilon striatum</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">A. pictum</hi>) is painted Indian mallow.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8724.xml">Antonio Leocadio Guzmán</ref> was a founder of the Liberal party of Venezuela; his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8725.xml">Antonio Guzmán Blanco</ref> was president of the country.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><hi rend="italic">Ionidium anomalum</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Pombalia prunifolia</hi> (family Violaceae); Ernst refers to the illustration in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3944.xml">Humboldt <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. 1818–25</ref>, 5: pl. 500. Its anterior petal (the term labellum is now usually restricted to orchids) is several times larger than its other petals and is used as a landing platform by some insects. For more on its breeding system, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11009.xml">Augspurger 1980</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">In his letter to Ernst of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12402.xml">5 January 1880</ref>, CD had offered to send a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>. CD later sent <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1572.xml"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> 2d ed.</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2807.xml"><hi rend="italic">Geological observations</hi> 2d ed.</ref> (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-12561.xml">letter to Adolf Ernst, 4 April 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Venezuela entered the Universal Postal Union on 1 January 1880 (Universal Postal Union, http://www.upu.int/en/the-upu/member-countries/americas/venezuela.html (accessed 22 October 2018)). The postal union was set up in 1874; the charges for letters and printed matter were covered in articles 3 and 4 of the treaty (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8777.xml"><hi rend="italic">Treaty on postal union</hi></ref>, pp. 4–5).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>