<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-350F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">To Eugène Robert   28 March 1838</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">22114</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-350F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-350F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-350F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt> 
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11749.xml">Robert 1840</ref>, pp. 443–4</bibl>
                
                <bibl type="printedSource">LL 3: 237</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                    <date when="1838-03-28">28 Mar 1838</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_9564.xml">Robert, Eugène</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc><abstract>
                <p>Discusses the geology of volcanic islands.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-05-13" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2022-05-24" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
            <change when="2022-10-20" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2022-05-26" status="copyedited">Copy-edited <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2022-08-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
            <change when="2022-08-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
            <change when="2022-12-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
            <change when="2022-08-11" status="OnlineEditionOnly"/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>Londres,</placeName>
                        <date>28 mars 1838.</date>
                        <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>J’ai reçu, depuis quelques jours, votre réponse très-obligeante, et je me permets de vous dire, en témoignage de ma sincère reconnaissance:<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                        <p>Que la question de l’inclinaison des nappes basaltiques vers l’intérieur des terres, ainsi que vous l’avez remarqué en Islande, me semble être clairement établie.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Je suis très-flatté de ce que vous souhaitez connaître les faits qui m’ont porté à admettre la possibilité de ce que vous aviez avancé, relativement à un phénomène des plus remarquables. Les seuls motifs qui m’ont empêché de vous donner des détails dans ma première lettre, viennent de ce que mes observations sont d’une nature bien imparfaite; je ne vous les présente donc qu’avez doute, dans le cas où elles pourraient vous intéresser.</p>
                        <p>A Saint-Yago (île du cap Vert), près de Porto-Praya et sur la côte, il existe une couche de calcaire blanchâtre contenant des espèces récentes de coquilles, qui repose sur des masses irrégulières de rochers, et se trouve recouverte par une ancienne lave sous-marine. Ce dépôt s’étend quelques milles le long de la côte, avec un singulier degré de régularité, jusqu’â la hauteur d’environ quarante-cinq pieds au dessus du niveau de la mer.</p>
                        <p>En suivant cette couche ver l’extrémité d’un promontoire, je m’aperçus qu’elle plongeait brusquement sous les eaux de la mer, mais qu’elle s’élevait de nouveau de l’autre côté du même promontoire, et qu’à partir de ce point on pouvait la voir s’étendre en suivant le rivage dans une étendue de quelques milles, sa position étant presque parfaitement horizontale. Ce promontoire est formé par les restes d’un ancien volcan qui a été en activité depuis l’écoulement du grand courant de lave sous-marine composant la surface du sol environnant. Ici donc, nous avons la preuve qu’après l’élévation en masse de cette partie de l’île, un semblable amas volcanique récent s’était accumulé de manière à forcer les couches sur lesquelles il reposait, à s’incliner de chaque côté ver le promontoire, ou, en d’autres termes, que cet amas n’avait pas primitivement la même hauteur relativement à la surface du sol avoisinant. En liant ce fait à quelques autres d’un ordre semblable, mais moins évident, je conçus que cette disposition observée à l’égard d’une seule colline volcanique, pourrait bien aussi se rencontrer dans une île entière.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                        <p>Certaines considérations théoriques, appliquées à la structure de quelques autres îles volcaniques que j’avais examinées pendant le voyage autour du monde que je viens de faire, m’avaient excité à porter particulièrement mon attention sur ce sujet. Ayant alors entendu M. Lyell parler de vos remarquables observations faites en Islande, je n’ai pu résister au désir de vous adresser des questions auxquelles vous avez répondu si obligeamment. J’aurai donc l’honneur, en usant de votre permission, de faire mention dans mon prochain ouvrage sur les îles volcaniques, de vos observations très-importantes sur la structure de l’Islande.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Signé</hi> DARWIN.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                
                
                
            </div>
           
            
           
            
           
            <div type="translation">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>London,</placeName>
                        <date>28 March 1838.</date>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>A few days ago, I received your very obliging response, and I take the liberty of expressing my sincere gratitude:<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                        <p>The question of the inclination of basalt layers towards the interior of the land, as you have observed in Iceland, seems to me to be clearly established.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am very honoured that you want to know the facts that brought me to accept the possibility of what you had advanced, concerning one of the most remarkable phenomenons. The only reasons that prevented me from giving you details in my first letter were that my observations are very imperfect; so I only present them to you with uncertainty, in case they could be of interest to you.</p>
                        <p>At Saint-Jago (Cape Verde Island), near Porto Praya and on the coast, there is a layer of whitish limestone, containing recent species of shells, that rests on irregular masses of rocks, and is covered by an ancient underwater lava. This deposit extends some miles along the coast, with a singular degree of regularity, up to a height of around forty-five feet above sea level.</p>
                        <p>Following this layer towards the tip of a promintory, I saw that it plunged abruptly under the seawater, but rose again on the other side of the same promontory, and from this point could be seen extending along the coastline for a stretch of a few miles, its position almost perfectly horizontal. This promontory is formed by the remains of an ancient volcano that had been active since the flow of a great undersea current of lava, making up the surrounding surface of the ground. Here then, we have the proof that after the mass uplift of this part of the island, a similar recent volcanic mass had accumulated so as to force the strata on which it lay to tilt on each side towards the promontory, or, in other words, that this accumulation had not originally had the same height relative to the surface of the neighbouring ground. By connecting this fact to several other similar but less evident ones, I realised that this arrangement, viewed with regard to a single volcanic hill, could arise just as well in a whole island.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                        <p>Certain theoretical considerations, applied to the structure of a few other volcanic islands that I had examined during the voyage around the world that I just made, had stimulated me to pay particular attention to this subject. Having the heard Mr Lyell speak of your remarkable observations made in Iceland, I could not resist the urge to ask you the questions to which you have so kindly responded. I shall therefore have the honour, with your permission, of mentioning in my next work on volcanic islands your very important observations on the structure of Iceland.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Signed</hi> DARWIN.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
           
            
           
            
           
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter from Robert has not been found.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">Robert later published these observations, mentioning CD’s  support, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11749.xml">Robert 1840</ref>, pp. 103–4.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3">For CD’s observations at St Jago, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3575.xml">Herbert 2005</ref>, pp. 141–58, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11750.xml">Pearson and Nicholas 2007</ref>, pp. 239–53.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4">Three weeks before writing this letter, CD had given a paper at the Geological Society of London arguing that the forces that produced volcanoes were also responsible for mountain uplift (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8002.xml">‘Volcanic phenomena and the formation of mountain chains’</ref>).  CD later cited Robert's letter as important support for his views about uplift: ‘It appears, from information communicated to me in the most obliging manner by M. E. Robert, that the circumferential parts of Iceland, which are composed of ancient basaltic strata alternating with tuff, dip inland, thus forming a gigantic saucer. M. Robert found that this was the case, with a few and quite local exceptions, for a space of coast several hundred miles in length’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>, p. 95). </note>
            </div>
      
        
      
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>