<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13140">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To C. E. Norton   30 April 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8194</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13140 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13140.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13140.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp encl 1p</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Houghton Library, Harvard University (Charles Eliot Norton Papers, MS Am 1088.14: 1598)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_180.xml">Harvard Houghton</repository>
                    <collection>Charles Eliot Norton Papers</collection>
                    <idno>MS Am 1088.14: 1598</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-30">30 Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3560.xml">Norton, C. E.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends some anecdotal material about Benjamin Franklin, whom his father knew while studying medicine in Paris.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1234">Darwin, R. W.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Franklin, Benjamin</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Paris</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-19" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-24" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi> | (<hi rend="print">Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi>)</placeName>
                    <date>April 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1881.</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Norton</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have thought that you might possibly like to hear the following details about Franklin, whom all Americans justly reference.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> My father while very young studied medicine in Paris, &amp; he often saw Franklin who was very kind to him, either on account of his father (Zoonomia Darwin) or on his own account.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> My father always spoke of Franklin with the greatest reverence &amp; even affection. In looking over some few memoranda, in my father’s hand-writing I found one, of which I enclose a copy. It is, however, of more interest with respect to Louis XVI than to Franklin himself.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>I remember my father saying, that one or two young men, nephews I think, were with Franklin at this time, &amp; they were what would now be called rather flashy young men &amp; they seemed to be ashamed of Franklin for the simplicity of his appearances &amp; manners.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> They often treated him with gross disrespect, which never seemed to ruffle Franklin in the least. On one occasions my father was quite shocked at their behaviour; but when they left the room, Franklin said to my father with a smile “poor young men they do not know what they are saying or how they are acting”.—or words to this effect— Pray forgive me if you do not care at all for these trifling anecdotes.—</p>
                    <p>Sara was here lately &amp; was as delightful as usual. Nursing a husband tenderly seems good for her health, for she looked somewhat better &amp; stronger. If my unfortunate son were to have a third concussion on the brain, I think that he would cure his wife.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Believe me my dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Norton, Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
                    <p>Poor old Carlyles Remembrances has caused more talk here than any book which has been published for many years—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="enclosure" xml:id="encl.1">
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p rend="centre">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Franklin (written by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. R. W. Darwin | Nov. 1. 1803).</p> 
                    <p>In the spring and summer of the year 1785 I used to dine occasionally at the house of that great man at Passy near Paris.— On one of those days it was remarked that an edict the King had published in the morning respecting some regulation of Provisions showed much humanity in his disposition, a gentleman present said that probably the King had neither heard of the scarcity nor of the edict. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> F “It is I fear too common in all absolute governments that the <hi rend="underline">monarch</hi> is the last person who hears either of the oppressions or benefits dispensed in their names. That however is not the case in the present instance, for to my own personal knowledge the humane regulation in question proceeded from the King himself”— After a pause he added “Perhaps no sovereign born to reign, ever felt so much for other men or had more of the milk of human nature than Louis XVI”</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 (<hi rend="italic">Railway … S.E.R.</hi>)] <hi rend="italic">parentheses added</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.6 I … one,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.3 be … of] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘despise’ </note>                
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure</hi>:</note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.1 D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Franklin … XVI” 8.11] <hi rend="italic">in the hand of an amanuensis</hi> </note>
            <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.1 (written … 1803).] <hi rend="italic">added in CD’s hand; square brackets in ms</hi></note>
                </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5700.xml">Benjamin Franklin</ref>, natural philosopher, writer, and stateman, was held up as an exemplary American for his autodidactism, work ethic, and constant quest to improve himself in ways designed to counteract his failings; he was also instrumental in drafting the United States Declaration of Independence (<hi rend="italic">ANB</hi>). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Franklin was the United States minister plenipotentiary in France from 1776 to July 1785. CD’s father was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin</ref>, and his grandfather was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>, whom Franklin had last visited in Lichfield in 1772 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10674.xml">Uglow 2002</ref>, p. 238). <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia; or, the laws of organic life</hi> was published after Franklin’s death (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9122.xml">Louis XVI</ref> was king of France from 1774 to 1793, when he was executed by guillotine during the French Revolution.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Franklin was accompanied to France by his grandsons <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9197.xml">William Temple Franklin</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9196.xml">Benjamin Franklin Bache</ref>. At a time when powdered wigs were de rigeur in French society, Franklin, who had a scalp irritation, rarely wore a wig and dressed plainly. (<hi rend="italic">ANB</hi>.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1240.xml">Sara Darwin</ref>, who was Norton’s sister-in-law, was nursing <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">William Erasmus Darwin</ref>, whose fall from a horse had brought on a recurrence of the concussion symptoms he had suffered following another riding accident in 1876 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13141F.xml">letter from W. E. Darwin, [13 March 1881]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Norton had been a close friend and admirer of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_832.xml">Thomas Carlyle</ref>, who died in February 1881. The publication of Carlyle’s <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11235.xml">Carlyle 1881</ref>) just a few weeks after his death by his literary executor and biographer <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1764.xml">James Anthony Froude</ref> resulted in a bitter disagreement between Froude and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9233.xml">Mary Carlyle Carlyle</ref>, Carlyle’s niece and heir, concerning the ethics of publishing material that revealed Carlyle’s failings, especially his treatment of his wife (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi> s.v. Carlyle, Thomas (1795–1881)).  In a <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to George Howard Darwin on 23 March 1881</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> wrote: ‘We are reading Carlyle’s Remeniscenses—which lower my opinion of him very much. He shews such low &amp; disagreeable &amp; cynical feelings at every turn’ (DAR 210.3: 6). In 1887, Norton, who, with the help of M. C. Carlyle, wished to restore Carlyle’s reputation by supplanting Froude’s poorly edited version of <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>, published an edition that was more faithful to Carlyle’s manuscript and also omitted ‘some trifling passages referring to private persons, calculated to give pain’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11397.xml">Carlyle 1887</ref>, 1: vi–vii; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11398.xml">I. Campbell 2006</ref>).</note>
            
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>