<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8387">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. A. Renshaw   15 June 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14519</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8387 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8387.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8387.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 121</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 121</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3980.xml">Renshaw, Benjamin Adolphus</persName>
                <placeName>Charing Cross Hotel</placeName>
                <date when="1872-06-15">15 June 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports a monkey-like child in Teneriffe.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">monkey</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Teneriffe</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>London. Charing + Hotel.</placeName>
                    <date>15. June. 1872.</date>
                    <salute>Sir:</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My only excuse for troubling you with these lines is the hope &amp; belief that the subject of them may be of interest to you, as it has certainly been to myself.</p>
<p>In the island of Teneriffe, from which I have just returned, there lives near the “Villa de la Orotava”, at a place called “Agua Mansa”, the offspring of a man &amp; woman, so much resembling a monkey, that she is called “La Machanga del Agua Mansa”.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> She is now 14 years old &amp; is the pet child of her parents, tho’ her brothers &amp; sisters are fine &amp; unmistakeable specimens of the human species. The head of the machanga is small &amp; her body is thickly covered with hair. Her mode of scratching herself with upturned hands, of throwing things over her shoulder; her passion for climbing trees, &amp; her ways &amp; habits generally resemble those of a monkey. Her hands &amp; feet are more like the human hand &amp; foot, only the fingers &amp; toes are unusually long. She is very shy, but is easily allured by the sight &amp; smell of food; she speaks only in inarticulate sounds, &amp; is at times quite savage. She has been baptized &amp; confirmed according to the rites of the Roman Catholic Church. I do not remember whether the parish priest told me that she had also made her confession: but I do not see how she could easily have managed <hi rend="underline">that.</hi></p>
<p>On the occasion of her confirmation the Bishop, who then saw her for the first time, was very much startled at the sight of her, &amp; enquired whether she was a fit subject for the sacrament. I am aware that the circumstances of her birth will need, (&amp; I presume that previously to baptism they were subjected by the ecclesiastical authorities to,) the strictest examination. Although I had been in the island already six months, &amp; was living not very far from Orotava I did not come to know of her existence till towards the end of my stay; &amp; that quite accidentally, while speaking one day with the “Beneficiado”, or priest of the place, about your late work on the “Descent of Man”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I was also surprised to find that most foreigners &amp; some even of the natives had never heard of her. I suppose she will be victimised one of these days by some enterprizing Barnum, &amp; I have no doubt he will make a good thing of it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Whatever be the ultimate explanation of the phenomenon, I am convinced of its <hi rend="underline">existence.</hi></p>
<p>I am extremely sorry that, in the first place, I was unable to <hi rend="underline">see</hi> the creature myself, &amp; that consequently I can only speak from hearsay, though on the most undoubted authority &amp; testimony; &amp; that, in the second place, being no naturalist, I did not know what were the chief points to enquire into. I was infinitely more desirous of seeing this monkey, than of making the ascent of the Peak;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> but, after having made all my arrangements, I was prevented at the last moment from making the journey by various difficulties, chiefly delicate health &amp; the unfit state of the roads at that season. If the subject is of any interest to you, I shall be most happy to give, or gather through my relatives &amp; friends on the island any further or more precise information which you should desire. I am going to write by the steamer of the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. from Liverpool, &amp; shall endeavour to get a complete description from three separate &amp; independent sources; from the parish priest, from the gentleman on whose estate she lives, &amp; from an intelligent Swiss tutor, all of whom have seen the machanga &amp; spoke to me of her. I had the idea whilst on the island of getting photographs taken of her, but gave it up as impracticable in those confines of civilization— But as D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carpenter,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> of the London University, to whom also I have written on this matter, suggests that some good photographs, on a sufficiently large scale, &amp; giving the profile as well as other views of the head &amp; face, would be especially valuable, I will do my best to get them. I am in hopes of returning to the island myself for winter after next. My address is:—“Care of Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Brown, Shipley, &amp; C<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. London”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I shall be in London till about the 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. of this month, &amp; in England for a week or so longer after that date. The above is my permanent address should you care to write me a line.</p>
<p>I am, Sir, | Yours obed<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi>. | Benjamin A. Renshaw. M.A. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To | Charles Darwin Esq.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">La Orotava is a settlement in a valley on the north-west coast of the island of Tenerife; Aguamansa is in the mountains to the north. <hi rend="italic">Machanga</hi>: a Spanish dialect term, principally in use in Latin America, for the female of a type of South American monkey (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7463.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stephens 1989</ref>); for the relationship between Canary Spanish and Latin-American Spanish, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4815.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lipski 1994</ref>, pp. 55–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had discussed degrees and patterns of hairiness in humans and other primates in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>, concluding that the differences were a result of sexual selection with occasional instances of reversion (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 375–81).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5993.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phineas Taylor Barnum</ref>, a circus owner, was famous for his lucrative touring shows featuring unusual-looking people (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ANB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Pico de Teide, Tenerife.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Benjamin Carpenter</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The merchants Brown, Shipley, and Company had London offices at Founders’ Court, Lothbury (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1872).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>