<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11758">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Raphael Meldola   25 November 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">2674</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11758 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11758.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11758.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 132</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 132</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3289.xml">Meldola, Raphael</persName>
                <placeName>Atlas Works, Hackney</placeName>
                <date when="1878-11-25">25 Nov 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for preface. When RM’s translation is complete, would like CD to expand it slightly to refer to overlap between Weismann’s observations and CD’s theories.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Studien</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Weismann, A. F. L. 1882</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Offices, | 50, Old Broad Street. | E.C. | Atlas Works, | Hackney Wick, | London, N.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. <hi rend="italic">18</hi>78</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am extremely obliged to you for your preface which I received this morning.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> May I be permitted to offer a suggestion?— When the work is completed (i.e. the translation) I shall have made myself perfectly acquainted with all the details of Weismann’s investigations &amp; the exact value (evolutional) of his arguments &amp; I shall then be in a position to point out to you the portions of your “Origin” &amp; other works which have touched upon the same grounds in the abstract as Weismann’s investigations in the concrete form.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In this manner it will be possible to dovetail (so to speak) Weismann’s observations with your generalizations &amp; so make the book upon which I am engaged a direct outcome of these generalizations. This I am very anxious to do &amp; you will perhaps be so kind as to permit me (when my task is completed) to hand you such a list of references, so that a little expansion of your prefatory notice may be made therefrom. I promise to do this without giving you the least trouble &amp; will wait till you have leisure time to consider the matter. In other words—I am anxious to engraft Weismann’s observations <hi rend="underline">thoroughly</hi> upon your Descent Theory. At my fastest possible rate of working however I should not be ready for a great many months to offer you anything for consideration so that you need take no further trouble in the matter for the present.</p>
<p>I am obliged for your kind consideration in mentioning another publisher to me— should there be any difficulty with my own publishers I will go to the firm you suggest.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I take the liberty of enclosing for your inspection (samples not the slightest value) specimens on wool of the colours ‘evolved’ from coal-tar by chemical processes. I hope their “non-æsthetic” qualities will not excite the horror of Miss Darwin. The green on silk is a new colouring matter which I have just discovered.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>When you last permitted me the honour of an interview with you<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I brought away with me a lively recollection of your appreciation of humour— you will therefore see the <hi rend="underline">teleological</hi> bearing of this story:—</p>
<p>An American gentleman was shown a huge mass of meteoric iron— “Do you mean to tell me” said he “that that chunk fell on to this earth?”— “undoubtedly” replied the exhibitor. “Well” (after reflection) “God is good—but <hi rend="underline">careless</hi>!”</p>
<p>Yours sincerely, | R. Meldola.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
 
 
 <div type="footnotes">
<note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11757.xml">letter to Raphael Meldola, 25 November [1878]</ref> and n. 2. CD had contributed a short prefatory note for a proposed English translation of essays by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Weismann</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f2">In the introduction to his translation of Weismann’s evolutionary essays, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the theory of descent</hi>, Meldola noted that the principle of ‘degeneration’ as an element in descent theory proposed in Weismann’s essay ‘The transformation of the Mexican axolotl into <hi rend="italic">Amblystoma</hi>’ had been prefigured in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10041.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1882</ref>, p. xii). Meldola added two further notes referring to CD’s work (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10041.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1882</ref>, 1: 274–5, and  2: 583).</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11757.xml">letter to Raphael Meldola, 25 November [1878]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f4">In addition to ‘viridine’, an alkaline-green dye, Meldola had recently developed a blue dye, later known as ‘Meldola’s blue’, from naphthalene, a product of carbolic oil which was derived from coal tar (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>;  <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10397.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Meldola 1882</ref>). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11493.xml">letter from Raphael Meldola, 3 May 1878</ref>. Elizabeth Darwin and her parents were visiting <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Litchfield</ref> in London (see n. 5, below).</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f5">The date of Meldola’s visit is not known, but he had been invited to lunch with the Darwins while they were visiting London; they had arrived on 19 November (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-11748.xml">letter to Raphael Meldola, 19 November [1878]</ref> and n. 1).</note>
</div>       
           
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>