<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-324">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Emma Wedgwood and Louisa Holland to F. E. E. Wedgwood   [21 and 24 November 1836]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20310</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-324 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-324.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-324.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
           <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">26 NO 26 | 1836</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Emma Darwin</hi>: 273</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 523 (summary only)</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">V&amp;A / Wedgwood Collection (MS WM 233)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_521.xml">V&amp;A / Wedgwood Collection</repository>
                    <idno>(MS WM 233)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Wedgwood, Emma</persName>
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_9538.xml">Holland, Louisa</persName>
                <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                <date when="1836-11-21">[21 and 24 Nov 1836]</date>
                <date when="1836-11-24"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5010.xml" resp="high">Wedgwood, F. E. E.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Tells of the pleasure that CD’s visit gave the family.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Wedgwood family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-10-25" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
                <change when="2016-11-25">Not published in vol 1 so coding removed; recoded for consideration in vol. 30 supplement</change>
        <change when="2021-06-22" status="sup-footnoted">Supplement footnotes by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2021-08-09" status="sup-reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-27" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                    <date>Monday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Fanny</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>I am in some hopes that we may have a letter from you today &amp; I hope it may bring us word that you are returned to Clapham for there is no saying how long you may be kept there. Ellen &amp; Caroline are with us now, they were very anxious about her for several days but now they think it may go on for another fortnight. It was really too goodnatured of you offering to be with Marianne &amp; I am a little vexed with her for letting you come which I think she ought not to have done.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Do mind &amp; take care of yourself &amp; above all keep out of the way of being frightened &amp; never mind if you happen to be out of the way at the critical time as she cannot want you then.</p> 
                    <p>We enjoyed Charles’s visit uncommonly we had been very handsome in inviting all the outliers of the family to meet him &amp; the last morning the chaise from Tern hill did not come and we persuaded them to stay &amp; had just made ourselves comfortable &amp; planned a walk when the chaise arrived, however we got them to let us send it off though Caroline felt it to be rather naughty &amp; we had a very nice snug day of them to ourselves.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Charles talked away most pleasantly all the time we plied him with questions without any mercy. Harry &amp; Frank<ref target="#foot.f4"/> made the most of him &amp; enjoyed him thoroughly. Caroline looks so happy &amp; proud of him it is delightful to see her. We had her a whole month &amp; I never enjoyed a visit of hers so much she was so very nice &amp; settled herself more at home here than usual. Uncle Allen &amp; my Aunts<ref target="#foot.f5"/> came on Friday. It was a pleasant surprize seeing Fanny as your letter was the only hint we had heard on the subject.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Holland and Louisa<ref target="#foot.f7"/> are amused with the Tollets &amp; like them, but poor Ellen is very poorly today &amp; I fully believe she is going to have the chicken pox as Caroline has lately had it so we shall not be so brilliant this evening I am afraid.</p>
                    <p>I had a very tidy visit at Betley Court of one day last week. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Butt &amp; Cath. Edwards &amp; the Tollets were there so it was not dull at all, but I am not fond of Catherine &amp; I dont approve of her mother.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>I have heard such a melancholy account from Frances of poor Maria Acland who was taken ill soon after she got to Kingscote &amp; they had great difficulty in persuading her to move to Glocester.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Frances only is with her &amp; I can fancy nothing more melancholy for her as Maria’s spirits are extremely depressed &amp; she constantly thinks herself dying &amp; though the D<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> tell Frances that it is entirely a nervous feeling she finds it very difficult to help being alarmed she mentions her lying for an hour quite white &amp; cold but not faint. I must say in excuse for Mrs Acland &amp; the sisters that the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> desires she may have nobody else with her &amp; made some difficulty in allowing Frances to stay &amp; she has sisters within her reach at Bristol.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Mamma<ref target="#foot.f11"/> is quite uncommonly well &amp; talks a great deal to Uncle Allen. I am very glad it happens that she is so well for all their sakes.</p>
                    <p>Charles was quite angry with Charlotte’s<ref target="#foot.f12"/> picture. He studied it many times to see if he could find any likeness &amp; said, “I hope to fate she is not like that picture.” I suppose he has rather a poetical idea of her for the picture is certainly very like. Eliz.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> desires her best love to you &amp; thanks for yr letter. She wants you very much to go home &amp; let things take their course. It will be very bad for you &amp; with Miss Vaughan &amp; Georgina she can’t want you.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Mamma wants Hensleigh to look at a handsome edition of Shakespear with prints by way of a wedding present to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Tom,<ref target="#foot.f15"/> or if there is any other book he can think of. I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not make the prints a sine qua non as they are really not the least improvement</p>
                    <p>Thursday. Poor Ellens malady turns out to be the chicken pox so she is confined to her appartment. I fully expect to have it but it does not much signify as it is very trifling. I shall direct this to Clapham as I dare say you are gone back. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wicksted is foraging for recruits for the Newcastle ball but as her own sisters in law will not go, duty does not call me.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Jos<ref target="#foot.f17"/> is in a bustle so I can write no more. I heard of you at the Aldersons from Uncle Baugh.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
                    <p>How wonderfully Marianne keeps up her spirits | Yours affectly | Em W</p>
                    <p rend="left">My dear Fanny</p>
                    <p>I hope Hensleigh has not set me down as very ungrateful and ungracious, for taking no manner of notice of his prompt and capital execution of my <hi rend="underline">boa</hi> commission. I thought it a remarkably nice one, very pretty looking and so excessively soft feeling and light. Will you thank him much for his trouble and kindness; the price I thought wonderfully cheap. Emma says that if I pay her she will manage the transmitting the sum to Hensleigh, so I hope it may reach him safely in the course of time. We have had a very pleasant week with the Darwins at Shrewsbury whom we left on Monday last, we were much pleased with <hi rend="italic">the lion</hi>, Charles, who has excited the curiosity of the whole county apparently for during our stay there he was constantly employed in <hi rend="italic">[</hi>rotating<hi rend="italic">]</hi> levees of lords and all the great people round. I hope to hear that you are relieved from your anxious post which you have so good naturedly undertaken. Believe me cousin to remain with love to Hensleigh | Yours affec<hi rend="superscript">ately</hi> | Louisa Holland</p>
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
             
            
        </div>       
        
        
 <div type="footnotes">
     <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the postmark; the Monday before 26 November 1836 was 21 November; Thursday was 24 November. A summary extract of this letter was published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 1 with the headline, ‘From Emma Wedgwood to F. M. Wedgwood, [21 November 1836]’.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4767.xml">Ellen Harriet Tollet</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1208.xml">Caroline Darwin</ref>, and Ellen’s sister, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4771.xml">Marianne Clive</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD arrived at Maer from London on 12 November and left on 16 November (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 1, Appendix I). For another description of his visit, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 1, <ref target="DCP-LETT-322.xml">letter from S. E. (Elizabeth) Wedgwood to Hensleigh Wedgwood, [16] November [1836]</ref>; see also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="DCP-LETT-327.xml">letter to W. D. Fox, 15 December [1836]</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5017.xml">Henry Allen Wedgwood</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5015.xml">Francis Wedgwood</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9088.xml">John Hensleigh Allen Sr</ref> and possibly one or more of his sisters. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5038.xml">Sarah Wedgwood</ref>, Emma’s paternal aunt, was also present (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="DCP-LETT-322.xml">letter from S. E. (Elizabeth) Wedgwood to Hensleigh Wedgwood, [16] November [1836]</ref>).</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f6">Probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5012.xml">Frances Mosley Wedgwood</ref> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 1, <ref target="DCP-LETT-322.xml">letter from S. E. (Elizabeth) Wedgwood to Hensleigh Wedgwood, [16] November [1836]</ref>).</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9537.xml">Anna</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9538.xml">Louisa Holland</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f8">Betley Court is about eight miles from Maer; the Tollets lived at nearby Betley Hall. The other guests were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9529.xml">Thomas Butt</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9530.xml">Catherine Butt</ref>, and her daughter, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9531.xml">Catherine James Edwards</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9532.xml">Maria Acland</ref> (1802–44), and possibly her sister <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9533.xml">Frances Acland</ref>. Kingscote, Gloucestershire, was the home of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5024.xml">John Wedgwood</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f10">Mrs Acland: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9535.xml">Maria Acland</ref> (1781–1856).  One sister, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2142.xml">Ellen Harrison</ref>, was living at Bristol.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5009.xml">Elizabeth Wedgwood</ref> (1764–1846).</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2810.xml">Charlotte Langton</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5039.xml">Elizabeth Wedgwood (1793–1880)</ref> was Emma’s sister.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4770.xml">Georgina Tollet</ref> was Marianne Clive’s sister; Miss Vaughan has not been identified.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f15">See this volume, Supplement, letter <ref target="DCP-LETT-315.xml">from Emma Wedgwood to F. E. E. Wedgwood, [24 October 1836]</ref> and n. 6. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5019.xml">Hensleigh Wedgwood</ref>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4999.xml">Anne Maria Wedgwood</ref> (wife of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5043.xml">Thomas Josiah Wedgwood</ref>).</note>
         <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9536.xml">Mary Charlotte Meysey Wicksted</ref>; her sisters-in-law were the Misses Tollet.</note>
         <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5027.xml">Josiah Wedgwood III</ref>.</note>
     <note xml:id="foot.f18"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_66.xml">Edward Hall Alderson</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_67.xml">Georgina Alderson</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_93.xml">Lancelot Baugh Allen</ref>.</note>
  
 </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>