<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10921">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Hermann Müller   2 April 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7924</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10921 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10921.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10921.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 111: A88</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>111: A88</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Müller, H. L. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Lippstadt</placeName>
                <date when="1877-04-02">2 Apr 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Is pleased that CD agrees with HM’s suggestions and criticisms of CD’s work. Will undertake experiments with <hi rend="italic">Viola tricolor</hi> seeds to see if they produce both large- and small-flowered plants.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lippstadt,</placeName>
                    <date>April 2, 1877.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Your agreement to my suggestions and criticisms on your work is a great pleasure to me, and I am very much obliged to you for your advices regarding the experiments to be made with Viola tricolor and the other plants with two kinds of flowers. Four years ago I began such experiments, but unforeseen difficulties frustrated them.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Rhinanthus and Euphrasia being parasites during their youth, I did not succeed in getting seedlings from them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The small-flowered Viola tricolor commonly is self-fertilised before opening its flowers. Supposing that pollen from a distinct stock would be prepotent, I crossed many of its flowers; but my experiments were interrupted before being finished by my absence during the vacancies.</p>
<p>Induced by your letter I will collect as soon as possible and sow a large number of seeds of the small flowered V. tricolor in order to discover whether both forms appear amongst the seedlings. I will also, with greater perseverance, repeat the cross and self fertilisation of the large and small flowered form of Viola tricolor and perhaps of Lysimachia vulgaris and Calamintha alpina.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>My brother lately in the highlands (Campos) of South Brazil has discovered a white flowered Viola species with subterraneous cleistogameous flowers. He says in his last letter to me, that he has in view to collect seeds of both kinds of flowers in order to experiment on them.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>My brothers paper on the neuration of the wings of the two sexes of Lepidoptera has not yet been printed. I will send it to you as soon as I have received it.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>In the next numbers of Kosmos two essays of mine will appear, in which I have attempted to explain some pecularities of entomophilous flowers by what you have statet on the effects of cross and self-fertilisation.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>With the highest respect | yours very sincerely | H. Müller</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 My brother … on them. 3.4] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil and red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Neither Müller’s letter nor CD’s reply have been found. Müller had received copies of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, Appendix III) and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref> (this volume, Appendix IV); his suggestions probably related to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, which he had received in December 1876 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10702.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Müller, 6 December 1876</ref>). In his book <hi rend="italic">Befruchtung der Blumen durch Insekten</hi> (Fertilisation of flowers through insect agency; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>, p. 145), Müller had described insect visitors to the large open flowers of <hi rend="italic">Viola tricolor</hi>. He discussed his continuing observations of insects that visited <hi rend="italic">V. tricolor</hi> and the self-fertilising form of the species in letters of 19 May 1873 and 10 June 1873 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Rhinanthus</hi> or rattle is a genus of hemiparasitic plants, that is, it draws some nutrition from the roots of grasses, but also photosynthesises. All species of <hi rend="italic">Euphrasia</hi> (the genus of eyebright) are also hemiparasitic on grasses.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Lysimachia vulgaris</hi> is garden loosestrife; <hi rend="italic">Calamintha alpina</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Clinopodium alpinum</hi>, alpine calamint.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD reported <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> observation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 318. Some of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to Hermann are reproduced in <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller. Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (Möller ed. 1915–21), but the letter mentioned is not included.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> paper ‘Beobachtungen an brasilianischen Schmetterlingen’ (Observations on Brazilian butterflies; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1877a) appeared in three parts in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> between September and December 1877. The first section of the first part, ‘Die Flügeladern der Schmetterlingspuppen’ (Wing neuration of butterfly pupae) appeared in the September issue.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller’s</ref> papers ‘Darwin’s Werk “Ueber die Wirkungen der Kreuzung und Selbstbefruchtung im Pflanzenreich” und seine Bedeutung für unsere Verständniß der Blumenwelt’ (Darwin’s work ‘On the effects of cross and self fertilisation in the plant kingdom’ and its meaning for our understanding of the world of flowers; H. Müller 1877a) and ‘Ueber den Ursprung der Blumen’ (On the origin of flowers; H. Müller 1877b) appeared in the April and May issues of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>