<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11254">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Samuel Butler to Francis Darwin   25 November 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14115</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11254 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11254.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11254.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160: 393</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 393</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Butler, Samuel (b)</persName>
                <placeName>London, Clifford’s Inn, 15</placeName>
                <date when="1877-11-25">25 Nov 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>SB’s book [<hi rend="italic">Life and habit</hi> (1878)] will be bound shortly. He will send two copies, one of which can be given to CD. To SB’s surprise it has turned out to be an attack on CD’s views and a defence of Lamarck; describes how he was brought to the opinions expressed in it.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Evolution, old and new</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2786">Lamarck, J. B. P. A. M. de</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Butler, Samuel (b) 1879</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">exclamations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">use and disuse, acquired characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-29" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2016-08-22" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-21" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-21" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name>. Corrections entered by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name>.</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01689_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01689_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
        <surface n="393:1r" xml:id="i1689">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01689.jpg" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01689_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01689.dzi" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="393:1v" xml:id="i1690">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01690.jpg" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01690_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01690.dzi" width="5366px" height="7122px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="393:2r" xml:id="i1691">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01691.jpg" width="5285px" height="7064px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01691_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5285px" height="7064px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01691.dzi" width="5285px" height="7064px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="393:2v" xml:id="i1692">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01692.jpg" width="5285px" height="7064px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01692_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5285px" height="7064px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01692.dzi" width="5285px" height="7064px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>15, Clifford’s Inn | Fleet Street E. C</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 25. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am going down home this week, but expect that before I return my book will be out; it has been vexatiously delayed by printers— but shd leave the binders Thursday or Friday and I have left instructions that two copies should be at once sent you— one of which, if you think fit after reading it you will perhaps be kind enough to give to your father.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I confess that I do not like the thought of either his seeing it or of your doing so, for it has resolved itself into a down right attack upon your father’s view of evolution and a defence of what I conceive to be Lamarck’s, and this is what I neither anticipated nor wished but what I was simply driven into.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I should like if you will pardon me just to state how and why I did not say more to you on this head when I saw you last.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Two or three days before I saw you a man had insisted on my reading Mivart’s book, and sent me a copy—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I read it and when I saw you had got through about a quarter of it. I at once felt that something was wanted to give an aim to variations, and if you remember said that I felt this— I then got your father’s last edition of the Origin which I had not looked at for some years having lent my own copy to some one who had not returned it— I read the answers to Mivart, some of which were convincing, but others did not seem to me to be so.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Then I read on and came to the chapter on instinct—and on p. 206 was horrified to read “It would be a serious error &amp;c … ”<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Now this cut at the very root of what I was doing and I felt as though I had better burn my M.S at once— I finished the chapter—and was I need not say 〈    〉 more sure than before that I must have blundered—the conclusion on page 233 “I am surprised &amp;c” knocked me out of time I can assure you.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> This was the first I had ever heard of the doctrine of inherited habit— which I had conceived was the new feature of my own book—and now to find that it was a stale old theory of the exploded Lamarck and was demonstrably impossible when my book was three parts done was, I can assure you, no small blow.</p>
<p>On thinking it over however I was again met with the weight of the evidence in favour of structure and habit being mainly due to memory, and accordingly gathered what I could from encyclopædias of what Lamarck had said—also I read as much about bees and ants as I could lay my hands on and in a little time saw my way again. I had no time to read Lamarck, but shall do so at once and, I think, translate him now—unless I find he has been translated already—but let that pass. Then reading your father more closely—and, I may say, more sceptically—the full antagonism between him and Lamarck came for the first time before me, and I saw plainly that there was no possibility of compromise between the two views. Then I fell to analysing your father’s answers to miscellaneous objections more closely and was met, and this time brought up by, the passage on p. 171 “In the earlier editions &amp;c” on which I have been very severe in my own book<ref target="#foot.f8"/>—but simply from the necessities of my own position, for either your father or Lamarck (and hence I) am on a very mistaken track—and the matter must be fought out according to the rules of the game—then—I went through the earlier part of my book and cut out all support of “natural selection” &amp; made it square in with a teleological view—for such I take it Lamarck’s is, and only different from Paley’s in so far as the design with Paley is from without, and with Lamarck from within<ref target="#foot.f9"/>—and feeling that I was in for a penny and might as well be in for a pound I wrote about your father’s work exactly as I should have done about any one else’s bearing in mind his immense services and his age as compared with my own— In one passage only have I been disrespectful— that is when I say that “domestic productions” may mean anything <hi rend="underline">from a baby to an apple dumpling</hi><ref target="#foot.f10"/>—but I could not resist it—and can only say that it was “not I that did it, but sin that waketh in me”—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> In the other passages I have been exceedingly I hardly like to say “severe” but this is the word I should have used if I were your father’s equal in age and knowledge—but I have always frankly admitted, and in such way as to leave no sense of arriére pensée,<ref target="#foot.f12"/> the inestimable boon which he has conferred upon us by teaching us to believe in evolution, though maintaining that he has led us to believe in it on grounds which I for my own part cannot accept. What I imagine I have added to Lamarck, (though I make no shadow of doubt that if it is true either Lamarck will be found to have said it, or else that some one else will have done so—still I don’t know where to find it) is that I have pointed out the bonâ fide character of the continued personality between successive generations, and the bonâ fide character of the memory on the part of the offspring, of its past existences in the persons of its forefathers, and have connected this with the vanishing tendency of consciousness and the phenomena of the abeyance and recurrence of memory.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> With these additions (if they are additions) I cannot see that Lamarck’s system is wrong. As for “natural selection” frankly to me it now seems a rope of sand as in any way accounting for the “<hi rend="underline">origin</hi> of species.” Of course I am strengthened in my opinion by seeing that it reduces to a common source the sterility of hybrids, the sterility of many wild animals under domestication—all <hi rend="underline">variation</hi> (as being only a <hi rend="underline">phase</hi> of sterility itself—or rather the only alternative left to a creature under greatly changed conditions if the changes are not great enough to induce sterility), the phenomena of growth—&amp; metagenesis—the phenomena of old age, and a lot more which I see at present too uncertainly to venture to commit myself on paper concerning them—</p>
<p>I was obliged to leave the pangenesis chapter out, as I was anxious to keep my book as short as possible and it grew very rapidly upon me towards the end—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Moreover what you told me about the review in Nature determined me to “hurry up.”<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>Well— I hope you will forgive the inordinate length of this letter</p>
<p>If you remember a few days after seeing you I wrote that I was afraid I should have to differ from your father not a little only but seriously &amp; fundamentally— I had finished Mivart’s book between your visit and my letter— as I went on I felt that I could hardly again write and say “I am differing <hi rend="underline">more</hi> seriously and <hi rend="underline">more</hi> fundamentally”—in fact there was nothing for it but to go ahead— the only thing would be to explain to you that when I saw you I had not yet begun to write the last 5 chapters of my book and had only <hi rend="underline">just</hi> begun to see that I might have to fall foul of “natural selection”. Also I should like to assure you, and your father through you—that I have been, and am, a good deal exercised in mind about the whole matter.</p>
<p>Nothing would surprise me less than to see something sprung upon me in reviews and answers which cuts the ground completely from under me—and of course I neither expect nor give quarter in a philosophical argument. We want to get on to the right side, and neither your father nor I take it myself care two straws <hi rend="underline">how we get on to the right side</hi> so long as we get there—nor do we want half refutations nor beatings about the bush. we want to come to an understanding as to what is true and what false as soon as possible, &amp; we know well that we score more for retracting after having been deeply committed than for keeping on to our original course when a new light has come upon us—so you must not be surprised if I am myself among the first to turn upon new book and send it, as I shall most assuredly do if I find, as I probably shall find, that it is naught.</p>
<p>Please excuse this erasure.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Its purpose was to say how sorry I was that your father should have been at school under my grandfather in as much as I myself should dislike an attack from a son or grandson of Kennedy’s when I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not care two pence about it from any one else.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>Believe me y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> very truly | S. Butler.</p>
<p>I have written this in copying ink, &amp; from a copy because I am sure I shall never again be at the pains of writing the steps by which my book came to be what is, but am not sorry to have a record of them.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Life and habit</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>) was published on 4 December 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jones 1919</ref>, 1: 261). No copy survives in the Darwin Libraries at Down or CUL. For Francis’s reply to this letter, and for his response to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jones 1919</ref>, 1: 260–1, 263–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Butler was interested in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2786.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jean Baptiste de Lamarck’s</ref> theory of the inheritance of acquired characteristics or habits. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6491.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raby 1990</ref>, pp. 161–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Francis had lunched with Butler on 26 September 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jones 1919</ref>, 1: 256–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart’s</ref> book <hi rend="italic">On the genesis of species</hi> (Mivart 1871) included an extended critique of CD’s theory of natural selection. The friend who recommended that Butler read it has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> (1876)</ref> was a corrected reprint of the sixth edition of 1872, which included a new chapter responding to Mivart’s criticisms (chapter 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The chapter on instinct was chapter 8. The full quotation reads, <p rend="blockquote">But it would be a serious error to suppose that the greater number of instincts have been acquired by habit in one generation, and then transmitted by inheritance to succeeding generations. It can be clearly shown that the most wonderful instincts with which we are acquainted, namely those of the hive-bee and of many ants, could not possibly have been acquired by habit.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had discussed ants in which two sterile castes existed in the same nest, being widely different from each other and from their parents, concluding, <p rend="blockquote">The case … proves that with animals, as with plants, any amount of modification may be effected by the accumulation of numerous, slight, spontaneous variations, which are in any way profitable, without exercise or habit having been brought into play. For peculiar habits confined to the workers or sterile females, however long they might be followed, could not possibly affect the males and fertile females, which alone leave descendants. I am surprised that no one has hitherto advanced this demonstrative case of neuter insects, against the well-known doctrine of inherited habit, as advanced by Lamarck.</p> CD had also mentioned Lamarck and the effects of use and disuse, or habit, in his Historical sketch at the beginning of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> from the third edition onwards (pp. xiii–xiv in the 1876 edition).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">‘In the earlier editions of this work I under-rated, as it now seems probable, the frequency and importance of modifications due to spontaneous variability. But it is impossible to attribute to this cause the innumerable structures which are so well adapted to the habits of life of each species.’ In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>, pp. 258–61, Butler concluded that this passage was ‘as nearly meaningless’ as it could be. By ‘spontaneous variability’, CD meant special cases such as bud-variations: for example, a nectarine that appeared on the stock of a peach tree.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3647.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Paley</ref>, in his <hi rend="italic">Natural theology</hi>, put forward an argument for the existence of God from the apparent evidence of beneficent design in the natural world (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paley 1802</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>, p. 255: <p rend="blockquote">Mr. Darwin tells us, in the preface to his last edition of the “Origin of species,” that Lamarck was partly led to his conclusions by the analogy of domestic productions. It is rather hard to say what these words imply; they may mean anything from a baby to an apple dumpling, but if they imply that Lamarck drew his inspirations from the gradual development of the mechanical inventions of man, and from the progress of man’s ideas, I would say that of all sources this would seem to be the safest and most fertile from which to draw.</p> CD used ‘domestic productions’ in the sense of domesticated animals and cultivated plants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Rom. 7:17: ‘Now then it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Arrière pensée</hi>: mental reservation or concealed aim (French).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Butler 1878</ref>, Butler traced the origin of characteristics in animals and plants to memories that had been acquired over many generations and had become unconscious, gradually taking the form of instincts, reflexes, and organic structures. For more on Butler’s concept of unconscious memory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9616.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Beer 2007</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Chapter 27 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, ‘Provisional hypothesis of pangenesis’, outlined CD’s ideas regarding heredity; CD suggested that minute particles (gemmules) circulated in the bodily fluids and were capable of generating new cells, remaining dormant until required. He thought his hypothesis could explain both sexual and asexual reproduction, as well as reversion and the regrowth of body parts.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester</ref> had published an article in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 13 June 1876, on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel’s</ref> theory of perigenesis (Lankester 1876; Haeckel had substituted a wave theory of hereditary transmission for the particulate theory, pangenesis, put forward by CD). Haeckel was inspired partly by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5896.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ewald Hering’s</ref> ‘Über das Gedächtnis als eine allgemeine Function des organisirten Materie’ (On memory as a general function of organised matter; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9615.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Hering 1870</ref>). Lankester summarised as follows (Lankester 1876, p. 237): <p rend="blockquote">[Hering] points out that since all transmission of ‘qualities’ from cell to cell in the growth and repair of one and the same organ, or from parent to offspring, is a transmission of vibrations or affectations of material particles, whether these qualities manifest themselves as form, or as a facility for entering upon a given series of vibrations, we may speak of all such phenomena as ‘memory,’ whether it be the conscious memory exhibited by the nerve-cells of the brain or the unconscious memory we call habit, or the inherited memory we call instinct; or whether again it be the reproduction of parental form and minute structure. From the earliest existence of protoplasm to the present day, the memory of living matter is continuous.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Before this sentence, four lines of text have been scribbled out.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">CD had attended Shrewsbury School under the headmastership of Samuel Butler (1774–1839), Butler’s grandfather. When Butler himself attended the school, the headmaster was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Benjamin Hall Kennedy</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>