<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7969">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Guiseppe Carboni<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   25 September 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16380</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7969 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7969.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7969.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 46</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 46</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_825.xml">Carboni, Giuseppe</persName>
                <placeName>Bologna</placeName>
                <date when="1871-09-25">25 Sept 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks CD for autograph and photograph.</p> 
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> destroys philosophical foundations of religion.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#religious_beliefs">Religious Beliefs</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bologna</placeName>
                    <date>li 25 Settembre 1871</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Londra</seg>
                    <salute>Onorevole Sig<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Carlo Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Commosso di sua tanta cortesia non posso far a meno di scrivere anche una volta per esprimerle di cuore i miei più sinceri ringraziamenti e dell’Autografo e della sua fotografia—inaspettata—testé ricevuta:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> dono che tanto mi è stato gradito che qualunque cosa mi dicessi in proposito non arriverei mai a significare il piacere e contentezza che la sua pregiatissima lettera mi ha cagionato.</p>
<p>Io sono giovane,—(come vedrà dalla fotografia che mi son preso la libertà di qui accludere, non in cambio alla sua perchè certamente non sono da paragonare a lei; ma solo perchè abbia l’immagine di un Italiano scevro la qualunque superstizione e che ama la scienza più di se stesso)<ref target="#foot.f3"/>—e se vivo son sicuro di vedere accettate, da tutto il mondo Scientifico, le teorie espresse cosi chiaramente nella famosa sua opera—Sull’Origine della Specie &amp;c—che tanto ha recato fastidio ai sostenitori della creazione divina, vedendo scapitare di assai le loro false dottrine filosofiche;—dottrine che ormai sono certe di dover soccombere sotto il peso dell’esperienze e dei fatti che la scienza tuttodi viene acquistando.</p>
<p>Non mi dilungo più oltre per non riescire di 〈    〉 importuno, sebbene lo sia già stato abbastanza, 〈    〉 so che Ella vorrà scusarmi di questa eccessiva con〈  〉 che mi son preso, la prego di volere accettare l〈  〉 ne della più viva riconoscenza e ringraziandor〈  〉 〈  〉vamente lo riverisco con particolare stima e mi creda | Suo devo: umble servitore | Giuseppe Carboni</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bologna</placeName>
                    <date>25 September 1871</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">London</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. Charles Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Touched by your great kindness, the least I can do is to write once more to express from the heart my most sincere thanks both for the Autograph and for your photograph—unexpected—just received:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> a gift which is so much appreciated by me that whatever I may say about it will never succeed in showing the pleasure and contentment that your most esteemed letter has caused me.</p>
<p>I am a young man,—(as you will see from the photograph that I have taken the liberty of enclosing, not in exchange for your own because I am certainly not to be compared with you; but only it gives the image of an Italian who is free of all superstition and who loves science more than his very self)<ref target="#foot.f3"/>—and if I live I am sure to see the theories expressed so clearly in your famous work—On the Origin of Species etc—accepted by the whole Scientific world. That work has brought so much trouble to the supporters of divine creation, seeing the loss of so many of their false philosophical doctrines;—doctrines which are now sure to buckle under the weight of the experiments and facts that all of science is in process of collecting.</p>
<p>I shall not expatiate further so as not to manage to 〈    〉 obtrusive, even though it has already been enough, 〈    〉 know that you would excuse me this excessive 〈    〉 that I have taken, I beg you to agree to accept the 〈    〉 of the strongest appreciation and gratitude 〈    〉 I shall hold it in special respect and esteem and believe me | Your obliged humble servant | Giuseppe Carboni</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 598–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">No letter to Carboni has been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7942.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Giuseppe Carboni, 13 September 1871</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The picture of Carboni has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>