<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13170F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   23 [May 1881]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21538</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13170F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13170F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13170F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 66</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 66</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Strasbourg</placeName>
                <date when="1881-05-23">23 [May 1881]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Would like some of his notes. Has been looking at roots of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>, cucurbits, larch, and orchids. Is content that mother should teach Bernard whatever religion she likes.</p> 
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-07" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-22" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-30" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>Monday | (23?)</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am very glad that the corrections were good—it really isnt much work and it is a change from microscoping all day—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Also many thanks for your letter   I am v glad poor little Ubbadub is jolly.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I think I should like <hi rend="underline">some</hi> of my notes, as I shall want to refer I think undoubtedly—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> My notes were all classified and pinched in bundles but I am afraid I took the pinchers off— The only ones I should want are marked with a big big D in red or blue pencil, (which means I have made a diagram) &amp; I think these are all together &amp; if so I should like to have them, they wouldn’t be a very big bundle— But dont worry about them</p>
<p>I have been going on at roots Linum, Cucurbita, &amp; Larch &amp; Orchid; Maize I only had a long look at in a prep<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> of D<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Bary’s— I never thoroughly understood a root before chiefly because in our English Sachs he didn’t know about the different types and thought that a maize &amp; a sunflower were the same type.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> There is a beautiful drawing of a maize root which is really perfectly right but which Sachs thought was wrong after he had published it because it wouldn’t go with the sunflower type which owing to Reinke was believed to be the universal type.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> This story is rather muddled however.</p>
<p>I didn’t telegraph about the notes because I couldn’t explain in a telegraph—</p>
<p>I went a long expedition in the Schwarzwald yesterday with Wortmann, &amp; two other “praktikanten” Fisch and Bisgen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Bisgen has got Drosera to germinate and is going to feed &amp; starve plants from their youth up—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> They only germinate almost in water
    <figure rend="inline width20">
        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13170F.jpg"/>
    </figure> 
only on the sides of the lump of peat near the water—<hi rend="underline">a a</hi></p>
<p>Yours affec | F. D.</p>
<p>Please tell mother I am quite content that she should teach Ubbadub what religion she likes<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>The man who wrote a dissert<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> about the Cucurbita peg is going to claim priorität in the Bot Zeitung. D<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Bary is much amused at him &amp; says he has discovered that he made a discovery<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I suppose certainly no printed proof came from the Linnean   I expect about 2 pages more<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The month and year are established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13169.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 20 May 1881</ref>. The Monday following 20 May 1881 was 23 May.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13169.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 20 May 1881</ref>; CD and Francis had begun correcting proof-sheets for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>. Francis was working in the laboratory of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref> in Straßburg (Strasbourg).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Ubbadub was a nickname for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml">Bernard Darwin</ref>, Francis’s son.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The notes have not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Linum</hi> is the genus of flax; <hi rend="italic">Cucurbita</hi> is the genus of gourds. The genus of larch is <hi rend="italic">Larix</hi>; the family of orchids is Orchidaceae. Maize is <hi rend="italic">Zea mays</hi>; the common sunflower is <hi rend="italic">Helianthus annuus</hi>. ‘English Sachs’ is a reference to the English translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml">Julius Sachs</ref>’s textbook of botany (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6836.xml">Sachs 1875</ref>); in it (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 140), Sachs had cited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7538.xml">Johannes Reinke</ref>’s work ‘Untersuchungen über Wachsthumsgeschichte und Morphologie der Phanerogamen-Wurzel’ (Investigations on the development and morphology of the phanerogam root; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11411.xml">Reinke 1871</ref>). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Sachs’s illustration of a root of maize at early stages of development is in Sachs 1875, p. 143, fig. 113; in it, the development of the first secondary (adventitious) root is shown in fig. 113, III. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11411.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Reinke 1871</ref>, p. 43, Reinke stated that root development was essentially the same in both monocotyledons (maize) and dicotyledons (sunflower).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Schwarzwald</hi>: the Black Forest; <hi rend="italic">Praktikant</hi>: apprentice (German). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9180.xml">Julius Wortmann</ref> was De Bary’s assistant. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9330.xml">Moritz Büsgen</ref> was a doctoral student of De Bary’s. Fisch may have been <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9331.xml">Carl Fisch</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Francis had published results of his experiments on feeding <hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> (common or round-leaved sundew) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9536.xml">F. Darwin 1878</ref>. The plants used by Francis were already mature at the start of his experiments (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The Darwin and Wedgwood families were Unitarians; for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Emma Darwin</ref>’s views on religion, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4341.xml">Keynes 2001</ref>, pp. 49–54.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD discussed the peg or heel that develops from a germinating seed in plants of the Cucurbitaceae (gourd) family in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, pp. 102–4. He had recently received a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4814.xml">Friedrich August Tscherning</ref>’s dissertation on germination in the Cucurbitaceae; Tscherning wrote to <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung</hi> to claim priority for his observation of the peg in his dissertation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11332.xml">Tscherning 1872</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13147.xml">letter from F. A. Tscherning, 6 May 1881</ref> and nn. 1 and 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The proof-sheets were for Francis’s article ‘On the power possessed by leaves of placing themselves at right angles to the direction of incident light’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10623.xml">F. Darwin 1880a</ref>), which was published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>), June 1881. The sheets had arrived at Down on 22 May 1881 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13170.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 22–3 May 1881</ref>).</note>  
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>