<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5080A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To William Lonsdale   6 May [1864]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20371</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5080A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5080A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5080A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Murch 1893, pp. 436–7</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Murch, Jerome 1893: 436–7</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1864-05-06">6 May [1864]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2989.xml">Lonsdale, William</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks WL for his MS on coral and suggests that it be sent to the Geological Society for printing or preserving in the archives.</p>
            <p>Comments on his and WL’s bad health and recalls WL’s past kindness to him.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Geological Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Bromley, | Kent;</placeName>
                    <date>May 6th. </date>
                    <salute>My Dear Lonsdale,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I received your letter with as much surprise as from one dead;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> for it so happened that 3 or 4 nights ago I was thinking about you and I saw you as plainly as in the old days in your little room at the Geolog. Soc.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I was thinking how I could learn any news of you. I am sorry at the poor accoun/〉 I was thinking how I could learn any news of you. I am sorry at the poor account that you give, and I know how long and how much you havet that you give, and I know how long and how much you have suffered.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I had quite forgotten about the coral, but I now remember its appearance. Your MS. is arrived and I am fairly astounded at the labour you have bestowed on the subject. It seems a very great pity that such labour should be wasted. Had I not better send the specimen and MS. to the Geolog. Soc. to be printed or kept in the archives?<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It might be of extreme use to any one working on the subject.</p>
<p>I have myself been ill for the last 9 months, but am slowly recovering and hope still to do a little work in Nat. History.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Believe me, my dear Lonsdale, I shall ever remember your uniform kindness to me in old long past days, and our many pleasant conversations.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I remain yours | Very sincerely, | Charles Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to CD’s long illness (see n. 6, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The letter from Lonsdale has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Lonsdale had been curator and librarian, then assistant secretary and librarian, of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref> from 1829 to 1842 (<hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>). He had described CD’s fossil coral specimens from Tasmania, collected during the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (see <hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi>, pp. 161–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lonsdale had resigned his post at the Geological Society in 1842 because of poor health (<hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>). Upon his resignation, CD had contributed to a subscription fund to assist Lonsdale in his work on fossil corals (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-648.xml" resp="#automat">letter to A. S. Horner, [4 October 1842]</ref> and n. 4, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, [5 and 7 October 1842]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The specimen and manuscript have not been found; however, in a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10608.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Peter Martin Duncan of 19 September 1876</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi> no. 10608), CD wrote: ‘On turning out a pile of rubbish in one of my rooms I found a parcel with a fossil coral &amp; a long M.S account (beautifully written) by Lonsdale. I believe that this arrived during one of my long illnesses, anyhow it was completely forgotten’. CD said that he would send the specimen and manuscript to Duncan, who was then president of the Geological Society.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had been seriously ill for the last five months of 1863 and the first four months of 1864; his symptoms including persistent vomiting (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vols. 11 and 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had been introduced to Lonsdale by Adam Sedgwick before his departure on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-129.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Adam Sedgwick, 18 September 1831</ref>); he later remarked on the ‘most cordial reception’ given him by Lonsdale (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. S. Henslow, [30–1 October 1836]</ref>). CD had considered Lonsdale as a possible editor of his 1844 species sketch, in the event of his death (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-761.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Emma Darwin, 5 July 1844</ref>, n. 5).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>