<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11177">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From L. A. Errera<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 October 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16803</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11177 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11177.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11177.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French) &amp; ADraftS 2pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 163: 28</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>163: 28</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                        <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                        <idno>524</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1524.xml">Errera, L. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Brussels</placeName>
                <date when="1877-10-10">10 Oct 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD has made clear that in <hi rend="italic">Cross and self-fertilisation</hi> he had not intended to suggest that <hi rend="italic">autogamie</hi> (fertilisation of a flower by its own pollen) is superior to <hi rend="italic">gitonogamie</hi> (fertilisation of a flower by one on the same plant).</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cross and self-fertilisation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-08-25" status="editorResponseCompleted"><name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">6<hi rend="superscript">A</hi>, Rue Royale | Bruxelles</hi></placeName>
                    <date>10 Oct. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Je ne puis assez vous témoigner ma gratitude pour la bonté et l’empressement que vous avez mis à me répondre et pour les paroles bienveillantes contenues dans votre lettre.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> J’avais déjà résolu d’expérimenter plus tard sur les “inconspicuous flowers” et votre conseil me fait un devoir de mettre à exécution mon projet, aussitôt que mes autres études m’en laisseront le temps.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Vous voulez bien me faire observer que vous n’avez pas dit que l’autogamie fût, en règle générale, supérieure à la gitonogamie. Toutefois il m’a paru que telle était la signification des passages que j’ai cités, extraits de votre beau livre “The effects of Cross &amp; Self-fertilisation”, (pp. VII, 61, 352, 386, etc);— vous y émettez l’avis que l’autogamie est “apparently in some respects beneficial, independently of the assured production of seeds”—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ces avantages, l’autogamie ne peut—semble-t-il—les montrer qu’en donnant des produits supérieurs à ceux d’une forme d’allogamie: et comme elle est certes, en général, inférieure à la xénogamie, elle ne peut accuser cette supériorité que vis-à-vis des plantes gitonogamiques.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> S’il n’en est pas ainsi, je ne parviens malheureusement pas bien à comprendre la nature des avantages de l’autogamie; puis qu’il est évident que ces avantages ne peuvent apparaître que par comparaison avec un autre mode de fécondation.</p>
<p>Quoiqu’il en soit, j’ai cru bien faire, à la suite de votre lettre, en soulignant dans notre manuscrit les mots “if this be really the case” pour bien indiquer que vous-même ne croyez pas la question suffisamment résolue.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Vous voudrez bien m’excuser d’avoir formulé les quelques remarques que je viens de me permettre et recevoir, avec mes remercîments réitérés, l’expression de mon plus profond respect. | Léo Errera</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">6<hi rend="superscript">A</hi>, Rue Royale | Brussels</hi></placeName>
                    <date>10 Oct. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I cannot adequately express to you my gratitude for the generosity and promptness with which you have answered me and for the kind words in your letter.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I had already resolved to experiment later on “inconspicuous flowers” and your advice convinces me to put my plan into action, as soon as my other studies allow me time.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>You quite rightly pointed out that you have not said that autogamy would, as a general rule, be superior to geitonogamy. Even so it seemed to me that was the meaning of the passages that I cited, extracts from your fine book “The effects of Cross &amp; Self-fertilisation”, (pp. VII, 61, 352, 386, etc);— you expressed the opinion that autogamy is “apparently in some respects beneficial, independently of the assured production of seeds”—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> These advantages, autogamy cannot—it seems—demonstrate except by giving superior products to those of some form of allogamy: and since it is certainly, in general, inferior to xenogamy, it can only show this superiority in comparison to geitonogamic plants.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> If this is not the case, unfortunately I cannot easily understand the advantages of autogamy; since it is evident that these advantages could not appear other than by comparison with another manner of fertilisation.</p>
<p>However this may be, I believed I did well, following your letter, to underline in our manuscript the words “if this be really the case” to emphasise that you yourself do not believe the question is adequately resolved.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Please forgive me for having taken the liberty of making these comments and accept, with my repeated thanks, the assurance of my very deep respect. | Léo Errera</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to L. A. Errera, 4 October 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to L. A. Errera, 4 October 1877</ref> and n. 5. Errera was a doctoral student at the Free University in Brussels.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD used this phrase in a chapter summary that appeared in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. vii and 312. On p. 61, he mentioned that self-fertilisation was more advantageous than crossing unless the cross brought with it some decided or preponderant advantage; on p. 352, he gave experimental results showing the superior weight of seeds from self-fertilised plants; and on p. 386, he noted that some species had increased their capacity for self-fertilisation.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Errera had explained these terms in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11160.xml">letter of 30 September 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to L. A. Errera, 4 October 1877</ref>. CD had commented on part of a study on heterostyled plants that Errera had carried out with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustave Gevaert</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>