<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4026">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Julius von Haast   5 March 1863</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7247</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4026 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4026.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4026.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 1–2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2039.xml">Haast, J. F. J. von</persName>
                <placeName>Lake Wanaka N.Z.</placeName>
                <date when="1863-03-05">5 Mar 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends copy of his December letter [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">3851</hi>], which he fears is lost.</p> 
            <p>Has been in the Southern Alps and has discovered a wonderful pass.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">3851</term>
                <term type="lista" ref="#">znr?</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Southern Alps</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lake Wanaka [New Zealand]</placeName>
                    <date>5 March 1863</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Fearing that the parcels of letters which I sent from Lake Ohau and which contained also my letter to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker with yours enclosed, has been lost, I enclose to you a copy of my last letter.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Coming just back from a most interesting journey across the Southern Alps to the West coast, I can only communicate to you, that I discovered a most wonderful pass, a break running N &amp; S across the Alps being only 1600 to 1650<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> above the sea level, which is the more remarkable as on both sides mountains of 10,000<hi rend="superscript">’</hi> are covered with extensive glaciers.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It was a very interesting although arduous task, large rivers &amp; dense N.Z. forest all the way, and I shall do me the pleasure to send you as soon as I return to Christchurch a more detailed report in print which I wrote here in the field and which will give you an idea of the country traversed.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> How I lounge to come back to Christchurch, &amp; study your work on the Orchideæ.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Believe me my dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin | very sincerely yours | Julius Haast.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>(Copy)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Lake Ohau. N.Z. December 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1862. Dear Sir</p>
<p>Our common friend D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. D. Hooker tells me he did me the honour to send you my last letter &amp; extracts and that you were interested in them, yet at the same time communicates to me that you wish for a specimen of our native rat &amp; frog.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I had the pleasure to send you a month ago two productions of my pen (addressed to the British Museum) for the perusal of which I hope you will find a spare moment.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> You will observe that I took the liberty to call one of our Alpine giants after you as a feeble tribute from the Southern hemisphere to the author of ‘Origin of species’.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I am very sorry that I have no specimen of the native rat, it being almost extinct, but I shall do my best to procure one for you; The frog exists only in one or two small creeks at Coromandel in the northern island, and I shall write instantly to one of my Auckland friends, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ch<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Petschler to procure one, and to send it directly to you.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> There are some more highly interesting animals in N.Z. quite unknown to science, as for instance a small quadruped in the rivers forming this lake, &amp; as no doubt I shall be able to procure some, I shall do myself the honour to send them to you for examination &amp; description.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker tells me that you ask him if I had your ‘Origin of Species’, if ever in my life I could be induced to tell an untruth, it would be here the case, because I should consider it the highest compliment to receive a work like yours from the hand of the Author, and on returning to Ch. Church, I shall present my copy to our embryo of a library, so that I can then fairly say, I do not possess it.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>You will see in my address as Presi<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>. of the Phil. Inst<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>. of Canterbury, that I tried to explain in few words to the members &amp; public at large, the great object of your work, so as to preserve them against the prejudices of bigoted people.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> It will perhaps interest you when I tell you, that the ‘Origin of Species’ was my travelling companion during my last journey, in the N.Z. Alps, taking always a book with me, the careful study of which, the long evenings &amp; rainy days in a tent afford the best opportunity, and I need scarcely say that very often I forgot hunger &amp; fatigue, cold &amp; storm in its perusal, &amp; sometimes I was only roused from its study by the falling of an avalanche, or the howling of the storm.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> If you wish me to make any observations on the subject of natural history, I shall be most happy to fulfil your desires. You will allow me to give you one instance which came under my knowlege, how animals in order to preserve their offspring, adapt themselves to circumstances: the ‘Casarca Variegata’, the ‘Paradise duck’ of the setlers, builds its nest along the bank of rivers, on the ground, but several instances have been observed at the Arowenui bush between Lyttelton and Timaru on the east coast of this island, that these webfooted birds when disturbed from their nests, have built new ones on the top of high trees, bringing afterwards their young ones on their backs down to the water. This occurrance has been observed by many respectable people so that there is not the least doubt about its truthfulness, &amp; have not the deductions from such a change in the habit of an animal a very high bearing on the confirmation of your theories? Any parcel for me if entrusted to the care of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. J. Marshman our Provin<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. Agent, 16 Charing Cross London, will reach me safely.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Having hurt my right hand slightly, by a fall with a horse, you will excuse my employing one of my travelling companions to write this. Hoping that you will find time to send me a few lines,</p>
<p>Believe me my dear Sir | very sincerely yours | Julius Haast <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Ch<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> | ect FRS | London.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Change in Habits in nest in Duck. | New Zealand Vertebrata.’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure</hi></note>
                <note>1.1 Our … species’. 1.7] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>2.1 I am very sorry] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket, ink</hi></note>
                <note>2.3 I shall write … desires. 3.11] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See enclosure and n. 5, below. Haast enclosed this letter and its enclosure with a letter to Joseph Dalton Hooker of 5 March 1863 that arrived in mid-June 1863 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 19 June 1863</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Following the discovery of the rich Dunstan gold-fields in Otago province in August 1862, Haast, who was provincial geologist in the neighbouring Canterbury province, began an expedition through the Southern Alps of New Zealand’s Middle Island (now South Island), with the aim of examining the rocks along the boundary line of the two provinces at the nearest point to the Otago gold-fields. In January 1863, Haast discovered a pass above Lake Wanaka (the ‘Haast pass’), which allowed him to traverse the Southern Alps and descend to the west coast. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, pp. 273–301.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Haast’s provisional report to the superintendent of the province was dated 3 March 1863; it was sent ahead of him to Christchurch and was printed in the Christchurch <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>, 1 April 1863, pp. 1–2, and 2 April 1863, pp. 2–3. Haast returned to Christchurch on 12 May 1863, and probably dispatched a copy of these newspaper reports in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4160.xml">letter to CD of 13 May 1863</ref>. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, p. 289.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> was published in May 1862. Hooker had told Haast about the impact of the book in a letter of 18 September 1862 (Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand, MS.37.96).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haast initially wrote this letter on 9 December 1862, evidently enclosing it with a letter to Hooker of 10 December 1862. Hooker received Haast’s letter in mid-April 1863, but either he lost Haast’s letter to CD, or Haast failed to enclose it as promised (see letters from J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4111.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">20 April 1863</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4133.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[30 April 1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4122.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 23 April [1863]</ref>). For reasons of clarity, the copy of Haast’s letter has been reproduced here, in addition to being reproduced in its proper chronological position (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3851.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Julius von Haast, 9 December 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See the enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3731.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 20 September 1862</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10). See also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 21 [September 1862]</ref> and nn. 6 and 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">J. F. J. von Haast 1862a and 1862b (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Julius von Haast, 22 January 1863</ref>). There are annotated copies of these publications in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">J. F. J. von Haast 1862b, p. 127. Mount Darwin is at the northern end of the Malte Brun Range, in the Southern Alps of New Zealand. Haast explained his practice of naming mountains in a letter to William Jackson Hooker of 9 June 1862: ‘When beginning with the survey of the Southern Alps of New Zealand, hitherto entirely unknown, I proposed myself to create a kind of Pantheon or Walhalla for my illustrious contemporaries amongst those never-trodden peaks and glaciers’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, p. 213).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Petschler</ref> was a merchant at Vulcan Lane, Auckland, New Zealand (<hi rend="italic">Chapman’s New Zealand Almanac</hi> 1860, 1862).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. F. J. von Haast 1861</ref>, p. 135, Haast stated: ‘The native rat (Mus rattus) is the only known indigenous land quadruped’. However, in J. F. J. von Haast 1862a, p. 6, Haast discussed the possible existence of two further indigenous quadrupeds. One was a badger- or otter-like quadruped, ‘called by the natives Kaureke’, which he believed probably still existed in areas around the lakes and rivers of the Southern Alps. The second was a smaller, nocturnal quadruped, traces of which Haast had found ‘in the river bed of the Hopkins, the stream which forms Lake Ohou [Ohau]’. <hi rend="italic">Mus rattus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Rattus rattus</hi>, the black rat.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Haast refers to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3781.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philosophical Institute of Canterbury</ref>, which he founded in the summer of 1862 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, pp. 220–30).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In J. F. J. von Haast 1862a, p. 7, Haast presented his discussion of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> as a ‘tribute to its illustrious author’, stating that this was ‘the great work of the age’ in natural history. While asserting that CD’s theories were not altogether new, Haast claimed that CD’s ‘great merit’ was that he had not only dealt with the subject in a ‘true philosophical spirit’ but had also collected ‘a great mass of facts, which throw new light on this inexhaustible source of inquiry’. After briefly summarising CD’s theory, Haast indicated some points of significance raised in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> for the study of the geology and palaeontology of New Zealand. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Julius von Haast, 22 January 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">As provincial geologist for the province of Canterbury, Haast had spent the period from January to May 1862 in the Southern Alps of New Zealand, carrying out the regular work of the geological survey, together with a search for gold-bearing deposits (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. F. von Haast 1948</ref>, pp. 199–219).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">John Marshman was agent to the Canterbury Emigration Office, 16 Charing Cross, London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1863).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>