<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13202">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Anthony Rich   13 June 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14533</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13202 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13202.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13202.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 149</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 149</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3990.xml">Rich, Anthony</persName>
                <placeName>Worthing</placeName>
                <date when="1881-06-13">13 June 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>The Huxleys have visited; CD may come soon.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1240">Huxleys</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">inviting</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-02-28" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-03" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-05-29" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00645_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00645_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="149:1r" xml:id="i645">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00645.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00645_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00645.dzi" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:1v" xml:id="i646">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00646.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00646_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00646.dzi" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:2r" xml:id="i647">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00647.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00647_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00647.dzi" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:2v" xml:id="i648">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00648.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00648_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00648.dzi" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:3r" xml:id="i649">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00649.jpg" width="3299px" height="5474px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00649_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3299px" height="5474px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00649.dzi" width="3299px" height="5474px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:3v" xml:id="i650">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00650.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00650_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00650.dzi" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:4r" xml:id="i651">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00651.jpg" width="3299px" height="5474px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00651_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3299px" height="5474px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00651.dzi" width="3299px" height="5474px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="149:4v" xml:id="i652">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00652.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00652_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00652.dzi" width="3340px" height="5468px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Chappell Croft, | Heene, Worthing.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Monday June 13— 81.</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Last Saturday morning the Post brought me your wellcome and friendly and pleasant letter; on the afternoon of the same day the Railway brought me for a visit M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Huxley, whom I may characterise in similar terms.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> They went back to London this morning, much to my regret; for I found them both extremely agreeable, as you will doubtless have discovered long ago. I only hope that they may have found their time pass here as pleasantly as I did. On the whole I thought him looking rather less vigorous than when I first saw him some two or three years back, as indeed people who come from the midst of London work in the London season are entitled to do.—</p>
                    <p>Now that we are on the subject of visits I may add that I shall look forward with the greatest pleasure to the accomplishment of the intention you express to spend a few days in the autumn at the Heene Hotel, which will afford me the opportunity of another cordial greeting with you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is not, I should say, a cause for wonder that you find yourself less able for a good walk than you used to do. The early warmth of this season before you left home must have told upon you as they have done upon all people who are not young or robust; and the constant rain of which you complain, the normal condition I have found of the Lake district, can scarcely be puffed off, even by hotel keepers, as a good constitutional tonic. I have found myself to be greatly enervated by it—the heat I mean—and that, added to the natural depression of encreasing years, seems to deteriorate my vital energies more than the winter cold by a good deal. I forget now the exact situation and surroundings of Patterdale; but if it is hilly like much of the Cumberland country no doubt it will put an extra strain upon your powers of locomotion, and lead you to suppose that the length of the walk has been diminished while you forget that the exertion spent upon it may have been doubled or trebled. I find <hi rend="underline">now</hi> that a very slight rise in the ground upon which I walk, in my own garden for instance, requires an effort and produces quite an unusual feeling of fatigue. I hope that the park of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Marshall is tolerably level: He is the grandson, or son, I suppose of the gentleman who figures amongst the Dramatis Personae of T. Carlyle’s Reminiscence; and who came off with a slight sprinkling only of the “Sage’s” (!) sub-acid mixture.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Oddly enough the precise sentiment which you express in reference to the mention of your brother Erasmus passed through my mind in reading it.— here is the man who has got through the fire without being scorched, but not without a <hi rend="underline">soupçon</hi> of the <hi rend="underline">agro-dolce</hi> flavour with which the Italians dress their wild boar.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But I attributed that to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Carlyle perhaps; for it suggested a tone in which some women, especially those who figure as socially clever ones, are apt to indulge about their male friends who make exertions out of kindness or politeness in their behalf, with the object of magnifying their own importance and influence over those who put themselves to trouble for the purpose of serving them.— You got a gentle dig in the ribs for your share; and much you will care about that! For myself I do not see logic or common sense in giving out an opinion, either good or bad, upon a book which in the same breath the critic proclaims that he never “could read and never has read”. How does he know that he couldn’t read it, if he never tried?—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The last book of any note that I have read is Trevelyan’s Early Life of C. J. Fox.— very interesting, very amusing, and very well written.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I tried Wallace’s Island Life, which I dare say has considerable merit; but I could not get through it.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Col<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. Gordon’s Central Africa is ordered from the Library, to be received a few days perhaps before the Greek Kalends.— —<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I was truly sorry to hear that William Darwin had met with an accident—the second one you said.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I did not know that he had had a first. If he comes to you please to salute him cordially on my part. And his brother George—my friend as you say—though I collect from your words that he cannot boast of being thoroughly reinstated in good sound health; yet I trust that he may have received some permanent benefit from his residence in Madeira.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> That island appears to have become a place almost of popular resort; for I have seen in the Papers constant announcements of “fashionable” arrivals there during the months lately passed. I do not wonder at your being pleased and proud on the compliments which he has received from the Astromer R. for Ireland.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> It is only by men of first rate standing and advanced knowledge that work such as his can be appreciated; or from whom praise is worth the having— When you see him pray give him my congratulations, and best wishes, and earnest hope that his health will soon become as strong as his genius—</p>
<p>As for myself I really cannot rake up a single scrap of intelligence to impart; for I live here so entirely to myself, that I literally know nothing that is going on beyond what every one knows as well as myself—public events as detailed in public Journals. I have heard more of my own voice during the last two days while H. and his wife were with me, than I have during the two preceding months perhaps; and I am not sure that this habit of listening only to myself (which I can’t help though) and never having to hear the opinions of others, does not lead to a sort of self sufficient belief that others of course think in the same way—and then one often says and writes, quite unintentionally, what is not so agreeable to them. I hope that I do not ever “tread upon your toes” in this way.</p>
<p>Now please to present my very best Compliments to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Darwin, whom I shall hope to see with you at Heene, if fortune favours me in the intention you entertain; and believe me to be. | Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin | Very sincerely yours | Anthony Rich</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Thomas Henry</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2478.xml">Henrietta Anne Huxley</ref>. Rich had added a codicil to his will bequeathing his house to Huxley (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13074.xml">letter from T. H. Huxley, 6 March 1881</ref> and n. 1). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The Darwins went to Heene, Worthing, on 8 September 1881 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). They stayed at the West Worthing Hotel (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13296.xml">letter from Anthony Rich, 25 August 1881</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The Darwins were visiting the Lake District, staying at Patterdale, from 3 June to 4 July (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3174.xml">Victor Marshall</ref>’s Monk Coniston estate was familiar to CD from a previous visit to the Lake District in 1879; Marshall had visited CD on 8 June 1881 and probably offered the Darwins access to his estate for walks (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13197.xml">letter to G. H. Darwin, 8 June [1881]</ref>). Marshall was the son of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8476.xml">James Garth Marshall</ref>, who was briefly mentioned in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_832.xml">Thomas Carlyle</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11235.xml">Carlyle 1881</ref>, 2: 219–20).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Erasmus Alvey Darwin</ref> was CD’s brother. <hi rend="italic">Agro-dolce</hi>: sour-sweet (Italian); a condiment made with vinegar and sugar or honey, to which herbs, spices, and other ingredients are added.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his reminiscences, Carlyle mentioned E. A. Darwin (‘one of the sincerest, naturally truest, and most modest of men’, and CD (‘the famed Darwin on species of these days’), and commented, alluding to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, ‘Wonderful to me, as indicating the capricious stupidity of mankind; never could read a page of it, or waste the least thought on it’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11235.xml">Carlyle 1881</ref>, 2: 208). Erasmus had been a good friend of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_831.xml">Jane Baillie Welsh Carlyle</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6892.xml">George Otto Trevelyan</ref>’s  <hi rend="italic">The early history of Charles James Fox</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11436.xml">Trevelyan [1880]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Island life</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8124.xml">Wallace 1880a</ref>) had been highly praised by CD (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12791.xml">letter to A. R. Wallace, 3 November 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Colonel Gordon in Central Africa</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11437.xml">Hill ed. 1881</ref>) was published in the second half of May 1881 (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Circular</hi>, 1 June 1881, p. 442). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1918.xml">Charles George Gordon</ref> was a British army officer. Calends was the first day of the month in the Roman calendar, but did not feature in the Greek calendar; the ‘Greek calends’, therefore, refers to a time that will never arrive. Rich had probably expected that the  book would be so popular, it would be some time before he received a copy, most likely from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3439.xml">Mudie’s Select Library</ref>, a large subscription library.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">William Erasmus Darwin</ref> had been kicked off his horse, hitting his head, in March 1881; he had also suffered a serious fall in 1876 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13141F.xml">letter from W. E. Darwin, [13 March 1881]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">George Howard Darwin</ref> joined the Darwins at Patterdale on 15 June 1881, while William arrived on 18 June (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). George had travelled to Madeira in early February 1881 for a convalescent stay and arrived back in England at the end of March (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-13036.xml">letter to W. E. Darwin, 4 February [1881]</ref>; <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Emma Darwin to G. H. Darwin, 23 March 1881</ref> (DAR 210.3: 6); <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)). George had visited Rich in 1879 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11824.xml">letter to W. E. Darwin, 10 January [1879]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_262.xml">Robert Stawell Ball</ref> had written to George, praising his work on tidal evolution (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13197.xml">letter to G. H. Darwin, 8 June [1881]</ref> and n. 2). </note>   
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>