<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-30">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Caroline Darwin   8 April [1826]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1808</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-30 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-30.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-30.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Copy</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>154: 29</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1826-04-08">8 Apr [1826]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1208.xml">Darwin, C. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD is studying the Bible, likes the gospels best.</p>
            <p>Glad he stayed for T. C. Hope’s lectures on electricity.</p>
            <p>Is running short of funds.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, miscellaneous</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2374">Hope, T. C.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#darwin_and_belief">Darwin’s Religious Beliefs</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Edinburgh]</placeName>
                    <date>April 8th</date>
                    <salute>My dear Caroline</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I dare say I shall not be able to finish this letter, but I cannot help writing to thank you for your very nice and kind letter. It makes me feel how very ungrateful I have been to you for all the kindness and trouble you took for me when I was a child. Indeed I often cannot help wondering at my own blind Ungratefulness. I have tried to follow your advice about the Bible, what part of the Bible do you like best? I like the Gospels. Do you know which of them is generally reckoned the best? Do write to me again soon, for you do not know how I like receiving such letters as yours. The weather has been very pleasant for these few last days, but nevertheless I long to return very much. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hope has been giving some very good Lectures on Electricity &amp;c. and I am very glad I stayed for them. The Classes are beginning to thin. I think I shall stay about nine days or a fortnight longer. But as my money will not last out for the latter period I should be much obliged if my Father would send up a £5 or £10 pound bill. I should also be much obliged if it could be sent up <hi rend="doubleUnderline">directly</hi>: as you will not receive this letter for three days, and I get the answer in another three.</p>
<p>I hope Eras. has got his books safely, let me know in the next letter, as I mean to go as far as Glasgow by the canals and from thence on “terra firma” to Shrewsbury, but sending my books per sea. How shockingly untidy this letter is, but I think you have a sympathy for untidiness, not that I mean to say that yours are half as bad as this.</p>
<p>I will send my next and last John Bull to Shrewsbury for your edification. I hope you received the last and studied it well. I said in the beginning of this very tidy epistle that I never should be able to finish it, which is now verified.</p>
<p>Love to all. Do not show this. | Your affect., Dear Caroline | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>Nota Benè. I do not so very much care about the money, as what I have will last for nine days: not long after which I hope to be in Shrewsbury. Anyhow let somebody write soon that there may be no mistake, as I will if I receive the money. Direct as formerly to <hi rend="underline">Mrs. Mackays, 11 Lothian St.</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">3.3 never should] <hi rend="italic">the copy reads</hi> ‘should never’, <hi rend="italic">with superscript numbers</hi> ‘2’ <hi rend="italic">and</hi> ‘1’ <hi rend="italic">to indicate that the words should be reversed in order.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Since it is not clear whether the indications are CD’s or the copyist’s,</hi> <hi rend="italic">they have not been retained in the text.</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The copy is dated 1828, but the letter is clearly an answer to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-28.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Caroline Darwin, [22 March 1826]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>