<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11738">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. H. Darwin   7 November 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7592</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11738 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11738.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11738.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp encl 16pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 210.2: 71, The Royal Society (RR/8/91)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>210.2: 71</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier><repository key="../repo/repo_364.xml">Royal Society</repository>
                    <collection>Royal Society</collection>
                    <idno>RR/8/91</idno></msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">Darwin, G. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Trinity College, Cambridge</placeName>
                <date when="1878-11-07">7 Nov 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Encloses William Thomson’s report on GHD’s paper. Some of it was written in Rayleigh’s hand.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4597">Strutt, J. W.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4737">Thomson, William</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-07-01" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-14" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-21" status="editorResponseCompleted">Responded <name sameAs="#ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-19" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-19" status="copyedited">Copyedited by <name xml:id="sjevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2017-10-25" status="transcribed">Enclosure transcribed by <name sameAs="#ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2017-10-26" status="initialProofCompleted">Enclosure proofread by <name sameAs="#elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2017-10-27" status="secondProofCompleted">Enclosure second proofread by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00391_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00391_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        <surface n="71:1r" xml:id="i391">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00391.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00391_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00391.dzi" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="71:1v" xml:id="i392">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00392.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00392_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00392.dzi" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="71:2r" xml:id="i393">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00393.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00393_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00393.dzi" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="71:2v" xml:id="i394">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00394.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00394_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00394.dzi" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="71:3r" xml:id="i395">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00395.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00395_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00395.dzi" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="71:3v" xml:id="i396">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00396.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00396_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00210-00002-000-00396.dzi" width="3155px" height="5305px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Trin Coll Camb.</placeName>
                    <date>Nov 7. 78</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I enclose Sir W. T.’s report on my paper which you might care to see. You will easily be able to skip the technical parts. I found my M.S scrawled about in his untidy hand, but I came to a sheet of paper in ink &amp; I felt as if I knew the hand, but only thought that he wrote very differently with a pen. An hour or two after it suddenly flashed across me that it was Rayleigh’s writing, so I spotted the other referees in that way.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I’ve had another long letter from Sir W. about lunar gravity &amp; he proposes my going down to Glasgow to see an instrument wh. he is going to have made. He does’nt think that it would be possible to do it in a town &amp; I expect I shall have to build a shed somewhere at Down.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I fancy I shall have to get money out of the R.S fund<ref target="#foot.f3"/> as I suppose it will be expensive. Sir W. also quite agrees about the obliquity of the Ecliptic, &amp; what I say about it.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I have been examining into the sea-tidal observations and I really do think they show a primâ facie case for the viscous yielding of the earth. These are observations during 12 different years at various stations &amp; the tides at 8 out of the 12 are too early, which w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. show viscosity &amp; out of the 4 where they are too late two are at a station where they say the observations are not accurate enough to judge safely with regard to the particular tide I care about.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I received D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Carret’s pamphlet both from himself &amp; you, &amp; I don’t think his ideas will work at all—tho’ he must be a cleverish man to get so deep.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Evans had an old idea of the crust of the Earth moving over the inside &amp; I think I can show it to be impossible—at least from the causes which he refers to.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I’ve really got nothing on Earth to write about except math<hi rend="superscript">cs</hi>. &amp; so that must be my excuse for so much axles.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Is’nt Frank going to pay a visit here— &amp; Jim?<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I’ve had no dissipations lately &amp; am glad of it for I’ve been a little down hill again.</p>
<p>Please return Sir W. T.—</p>
<p>Your affec son | G H Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                    <div type="enclosure" subtype="letter" xml:id="encl.1">
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>I have read with much interest M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. George Darwin’s paper “on the bodily tides of viscous and semi-elastic spheroids and on the ocean tides on a yielding nucleus” and I am of opinion that it is suitable for publication in the Transactions. The question raised is undoubtedly a very important one— If what is denoted by A (p 28) have some value intermediate between 3 or 4 hours and 24 or 48h the semi diurnal tides would be nearly the same as if the earth were perfectly elastic and the fortnightly tide and other “long period tides” would be nearly zero (as if the solid mass had scarcely any tidal effective rigidity.) It is just possible that this may be the actual state of the case, and that thus it may be explained how the lunar fortnightly tide is so small as it is. Careful analysis of a large number of tide curves from self-registering tide gauges in different parts of the world made within the last ten years by the Tidal committee of the British Association and more lately have failed to actually <hi rend="underline">prove</hi> any sensible tide of this denomination; but they have not proved that it is sensibly smaller than the equilibrium value. In this uncertainty it is well to be prepared with theory to account for whatever result may be brought out by more extended observation and more complete analysis of the results. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin in p 62 refers to the determination from observation, of the <hi rend="underline">times</hi> of maximum and minimum of the lunar fortnightly—as capable of giving very important information. The determination of the <hi rend="underline">amount</hi> was all that I had pointed out as needed because on the perfectly rigid, or perfectly elastic theory the times must be the equilibrium times; &amp; the amounts would show the value of the tidal effective rigidity. Hence we have renewed and augmented interest in prosecuting the analysis of tidal observations—</p>
                        <p>The rate at which viscosity, or breaking down elasticity, in one or other of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin’s theories, estimated somewhat as I estimated the effect of the tidal friction of the semi diurnal lunar tide in reducing the angular velocity of the earth’s rotation, will be interesting in connection with the question raised by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin. Will it not give so rapid a diminution of the obliquity as to give an argument conclusive against, or rendering very improbable, the supposition of any so great influence of imperfect elasticity as to be discoverable in deviations of the lunar fortn<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. tide from what it would be were the elasticity perfect?</p>
                        <p>If Cap. Clarks results quoted in §797 of Thomson &amp; Tait’s N. P. are valid they would seem absolutely conclusive against any breaking down of resistance to change of shape for deviations of the second order of harmonics (elliptic spheroid deviation from fluid equilibrium)<ref target="#foot.f10"/>  The difference of 6378 feet between the greatest and least diameters of the equatorial diameters of the sea level could not possibly I think be explained by greater &amp; less densities in a rigid crust buoyed on liquid, &amp; not resisting such stresses as would give two or three feet of difference of diameter in elliptic deformations such as those of the tide generating influence. I have written on p 57 a pencil remark on a notion which seems to have occurred to many who have thought of the subject, but which I think is fallacious.</p>
                        <p>Still, though I see much reason for believing the supposition of sensible effects of either viscosity or breaking down elasticity to be improbable, (&amp; indeed M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin himself expresses a similar opinion on his last two pages, (including however apparently, a supposition of improbability of <hi rend="underline">elastic</hi> yielding, in which I cannot agree) there can be no doubt of the importance of the questions raised and of the validity &amp; fertility of the mode of discussion contained in his paper</p>
                        <p>William Thomson</p>
                        <p>P.S. I have also written notes in pencil on pp 42, &amp; 48—</p>
                    </div>
                </div>       
            
            

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
             
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">George Darwin was working on a series of connected papers modelling the effects of lunar gravity on the earth, and investigating the implications for its structure and behaviour (G. H. Darwin 1878b, 1878d, and 1878e). The referees’ reports by William Thomson and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4597.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John William Strutt</ref>, third Baron Rayleigh, concerned George’s paper ‘On the bodily tides of viscous and semi-elastic spheroids, and on the ocean tides upon a yielding nucleus’ (G. H. Darwin 1878b). The paper had been read at a meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref> on 23 May 1878, and was being prepared for publication in the society’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi>.  The referees’ copy of George’s paper was returned to Thomson on 13 December (MSS 421, Register of Papers 1853–1885, Archive, The Royal Society); it has not been found.  The published paper included a remark by Rayleigh (G. H. Darwin 1878b, p. 27 n.).  See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11663.xml">letter to G. H. Darwin, 17 [August 1878]</ref> and n. 3, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11729.xml">letter to G. H. Darwin, 29 October [1878]</ref>. For George’s later account of the development of his ideas, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1818.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. H. Darwin 1907–16</ref>, 2: v–viii; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kushner 1993</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Thomson’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11733F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 2 November 1878</ref> proposing Down as a possible location for an instrument to measure lunar gravity is in Glasgow University Library (Kelvin papers D6). Thomson described the instrument as a weight supported by a vertical spring.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The government grant and donation fund of the Royal Society.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The obliquity of the ecliptic is the angle of the earth’s equator to the plane of its orbit around the sun. In his letter, Thomson wrote that on ‘the question of tidal viscosity on the obliquity of the ecliptic’, which the two men had discussed at a recent meeting, he now saw it perfectly and was glad to find George’s result confirmed (D6, Kelvin papers, Glasgow University Library). The subject is not discussed in the main body of G. H. Darwin 1878b, but is worked out at length in G. H. Darwin 1878d, which had been received by the Royal Society on 22 July 1878 but had not yet been read.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">An appendix ‘On the observed height and phase of the fortnightly oceanic tide’ was added on 7 November 1878 to G. H. Darwin 1878b (pp. 31–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11733F.xml">letter to G. H. Darwin, 2 November [1878]</ref> and n. 2.  CD had sent George a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9057.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jules Carret’s</ref> pamphlet on polar displacement (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10141.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carret 1878</ref>). Adopting a theory of the composition of the earth suggested by John Evans (see n. 7 below), Carret argued that long-term polar displacement had been caused by unequal movement between the earth’s crust and nucleus.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In an attempt to explain the evidence that the climate in some parts of the world had varied between tropical and arctic, Evans had postulated a model of the earth with a thin rigid crust over a molten layer, possibly with a solid core. He suggested that changes in the thickness of parts of the crust through upheaval, denudation, or the accumulation of large bodies of ice, would, through the action of centrifugal force, lead to a change in ‘the relative positions of the solid crust and the fluid nucleus, and in consequence to a change in the axis of rotation, so far as the former is concerned’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Evans 1866</ref>, p. 48).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">‘Axles’ was evidently a family word for ‘shoptalk’ (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 27, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12128F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin to Emma Darwin, 30 June 1879</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, [2 August 1879]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">No record has been found of a visit at this time to Cambridge by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> or by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref>, whose nickname was Jim.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In section 797 of their <hi rend="italic">Treatise of natural philosophy</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7742.xml">Thomson and Tait 1867</ref>, pp. 646–9), Thomson and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4652.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter Guthrie Tait</ref> summarised the conclusions reached by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_943.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Ross Clarke</ref>, a captain in the Royal Engineers, about the shape of the earth.</note>
        </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>