<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3318F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J.-B. P. Guépin<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   14 November 1861</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21183</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3318F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3318F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3318F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Archives Départmentales de Maine-et-Loire (24 J 1, pièce no. 32)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_287.xml">Archives Maine-et-Loire</repository>
                    <collection>Guépin</collection>
                    <idno>24 J 1, pièce no. 32</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1861-11-14">14 Nov 1861</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2011.xml">Guépin, J. B. P.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has read about JPG’s article on the fertilisation of orchids in <hi rend="italic">Annales de la Societé Linnéenne d’Angers</hi> [1853], but has been unable to secure a copy. Seeks information about the role of bees in distributing pollen masses and about the varieties of orchids in Angers.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Annales de la Societe Linneenne d’Angers</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Guepin, J. B. P. 1853</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down.</hi> | <hi rend="print">Bromley.</hi> | <hi rend="print">Kent. S.E.</hi> England</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 14 1861</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’éspère que vous excuserez la liberté que je prends à vous addresser cette lettre. J’ai lu un avis sur un papier dans les Annales de la Societé Linn: d’Angers, sur la fertilisation des Orchides, dont vous ètes l’auteur.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> J’ai en vain essayé d’en obtenir un exemplaire à Londres, ce que je désire beaucoup, comme je suis occupé dans ce moment à préparer pour la publication un ouvrage sur ce sujet.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Auriez vous la bonté de m’informer si vous avez pu indiquer l’éspèce des Orchides desquels les Abeilles avaient deplacé le pollen? Y avait il un, deux, ou plus de “pollen masses” collé sur une abeille? J’ai vu ces masses de pollen en grand nombre sur la trompe des Lepidoptères mais non pas sur les abeilles.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Si par hazard vous possediez plusieurs specimens d’abeille avec le pollen attaché et que vous pourriez m’en épargner un, vous me rendriez un grand service. Si je pouvais éxaminer une de ces abeilles (que vous pourriez m’envoyer dans une lettre, enfermée dans une plume) je crois pouvoir déterminer de quelle éspèce d’orchide sont les “pollen masses”. Surtout si vous pouviez m’informer quelles sont les éspèces d’orchides les plus fréquentes dans le voisinage d’Angers.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je suis avec beaucoup de respect et vous priant d’excuser cette liberté votre très humble serviteur | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 England] *added in CD’s hand </note>
                </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down.</hi> | <hi rend="print">Bromley.</hi> | <hi rend="print">Kent. S.E.</hi> England</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 14 1861</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope you will forgive the liberty I am taking in writing to you. I read a notice of a paper in the Annales de la Societe Linn: d’ Angers, regarding the fertilisation of Orchids, of which you are the author.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have unsuccessfully tried to obtain a copy in London, something I am very keen to do, as I am at present preparing a book for publication on this subject.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Would you be so kind as to let me know whether you have been able to show from which species of Orchids these Bees had been gathering nectar? Were there one, two, or more ‘pollen masses’ stuck to a bee? I have seen these pollen masses in great numbers on the proboscis of lepidoptera but not on bees.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>If by chance you had in your possession several specimens of bees with the pollen attached and you were able to spare one of them, you would be doing me a great service. If I could study one of these bees (which you could send me in a letter, wrapped in a feather), I think I would be able to identify the species of orchid from which the ‘pollen masses’ come. Especially if you were able to enlighten me as to which are the most common species of orchids in the Angers area.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I am with much respect and begging you to forgive this liberty your very humble servant | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol.13, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the original French, see pp. 449–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref> had sent CD a list of references in French and German relating to orchids. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3184.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Guépin 1853</ref> was described on this list as dealing with ‘fecundation of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi>’ (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3039.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Daniel Oliver, [before 8 November 1861]</ref> (redated to [before 3 November 1881]), and this volume, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4329.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 3 November [1861]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD refers to <hi rend="italic">Orchids.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_521.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick Bond</ref> is cited in <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi>, pp. 35–6, as having sent CD a large number of moths and butterflies with orchid pollinia attached to their proboscises. Virtually all the pollinia came from a single species, <hi rend="italic">Orchis pyramidalis.</hi> See also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 17 June [1860]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Guépin compiled a flora of the area of Maine and Loire (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3183.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Guépin 1830–54</ref>). Guépin had died in 1858, so the letter was never answered.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>