<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11586">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Francis Darwin   2 July [1878]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19784</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11586 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11586.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11586.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">AL incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="AL">inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 211: 32</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>211: 32</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-07-02">2 July [1878]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Suggests FD call on Carl Semper.</p> 
<p>Inquires about <hi rend="italic">Porlieria</hi>: Do the leaves shut to check evaporation? Does it appear silver under water?</p> 
            <p>Explains how he thinks the pulvinus acts; wishes FD would investigate the point.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Porlieria</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4291">Semper, C. G.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>July 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear F.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Murie has written to me &amp; you, asking me if you were away to look over your revise, which I have done &amp; found nothing to correct &amp; no criticism to make to you, except that one or two sentences might have been clearer.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The whole strikes me as excellent &amp; conclusive.— The revise is marked “25 copies”: had you not better get more?—</p>
                    <p>I have sent cheque to a repeated bill from Griffin for 2.10.10— A thermometer has come from Kew, for which I have also paid,— I think 1.11.0.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> There is a “<hi rend="underline">certificate</hi>” with the thermometer.—</p>
                    <p>I will now go through your letter, but first will say that Bernard seems quite well, though temper not quite so placid as formerly. He has just started very happy &amp; eager in “boobo” with Miss Darcy &amp; Bessy to the Station.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>I think you certainly had better call on Semper; you can say that I asked you to do so to give my very kind remembrances. You know that he has lately returned from America—has travelled much in Philippines &amp; Malay Arch.—has worked on same subjects as Balfour—is a first-rate man, &amp; I liked him, but he is said to have bad temper &amp; to think that everyone is depreciating him.— He dedicated a magnificent essay to me on eyes of a Mollusc,— Onchidium.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>I have written to Kew about Porliera: do the leaves look like silver under water? Can they shut up to check evaporation; something of this kind occurs (Duval-Jouve) with certain grasses: you could try (if you could get permission) by enclosing small branch in well wetted bottle with wet sponge.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>I am glad to hear that Sachs tries “fools experiments”.</p>
                    <p>Do what you think fit about the 10£ Telescope, &amp; any other instrument; only do not waste money, as you know your honoured father hates this.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>I go on maundering about the pulvinus, cushion or gland whichever you call it, &amp; from what I have seen roughly in the petioles of the Cotyledons of oxalis, I conclude that a pulvinus <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be developed from ordinary cells, which secrete water into the inter-cellular spaces on the concave side of a bending organ; &amp; that a pulvinus is developed only when the bending has to be continued for a period after growth has ceased or nearly ceased.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>The cotyledon of Oats bending towards light would, I think, do for observation, &amp; I much wish that you w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. try either there or here whether by cutting thin sections about <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>10</mn></mfrac></math></formula>th. of inch above the soil of 2 or 3 cots:, you could measure under high power the diameter of the cells, &amp; observe whether their diameter is the same all round. If you can ascertain their average diameter, then cut sections on the most bent part, at same height above soil as before, &amp; see if cells on concave side of the stem where bent through heliotropism (or apogeotropism) are smaller than those on convex side.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I cannot remember whether such observations have been made, but I think that they are worth making. If there is no such action, as I imagine how the deuce can a pulvinus be developed in all sorts of Families?</p>
                    <p>I am trying a slight modification of your dodge; &amp; putting night-light under large bell-glass, standing on little wooden bricks to let some air come in, &amp; I have succeeded in keepin jar of water for many hours between 75° &amp; 80° F:<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>I have thanked Murie &amp; returned revise.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.1 if … away] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.1 your] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.2 found] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘find’</note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.3 The whole] <hi rend="italic">interl above del</hi> ‘It’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.2 very … eager] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.6 Mollusc,—] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘nudibranch’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.1 do] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘have’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n8">5.2 (Duval-Jouve)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n9">5.4 wet] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘sp’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n10">8.5 period] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n11">9.5 their] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n12">9.6 &amp; … side] <hi rend="italic">excised from MS</hi>; <hi rend="italic">added by FD</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n13">9.9 there is] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n14">9.9 how] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘takes place’ </note>
            </div>

            
            
           
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11575.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [29 June] 1878</ref> (see n. 5, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Murie</ref> was assistant secretary of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>; he sent proofs of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin’s</ref> revised version of a paper on the nutrition of <hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> (common or round-leaved sundew) that he had presented at a meeting of the society in January (F. Darwin 1878a). Murie’s letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s Account books–cash account (Down House MS) records a payment of £2 10<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 10<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. to Griffin for ‘Chemical Apparatus’; J. J. Griffin &amp; Sons were London scientific-instrument suppliers and publishers in London. There is no record of a payment for the thermometer.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Mary Catherine Georgiana D’Arcy had arrived at Down House on 1 July 1878. She and Elizabeth Darwin left Down for London on 2 July; Elizabeth was going to stay with her sister, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Litchfield</ref>. (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242).) <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bernard Darwin</ref> was 22 months old; he called a vehicle of any sort a ‘boo boo’ (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 June [1878]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Francis had asked whether he should call on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4291.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Gottfried Semper</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11575.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [29 June] 1878</ref>). Semper had dedicated his book on the visual organs of the vertebrate eye type on the backs of sea slugs to CD (Semper 1877b). In July 1877, before Semper departed for America, he sent CD a copy (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C. G. Semper, 13 July 1877</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Onchidium</hi> is a genus of air-breathing marine slugs (pulmonate gastropods) in the family Onchidiidae. Semper had explored the Philippines from 1858 to 1865; he contributed two volumes of a ten-volume work on the fauna of the Philippine archipelago (Semper <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. 1868–1916, vols. 1 and 3). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_258.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Maitland Balfour</ref> was lecturer on animal morphology at <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had asked <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> whether he could borrow a plant of <hi rend="italic">Porlieria hygrometrica</hi> from Kew (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-11581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 1 July 1878</ref>). Francis had described the plant as almost always being asleep (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-12131F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [22 June 1878]</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1436.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Duval-Jouve</ref> had discovered the cellular mechanism by which certain grasses rolled up or folded their leaf-blades inwards to prevent moisture loss (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10421.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duval-Jouve 1875</ref>, pp. 326–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs’s</ref> ‘fool’s experiment’ and the purchase of a micro-telescope had been mentioned in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12131F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [22 June 1878]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD described ‘a so-called joint, cushion or pulvinus’ as consisting of an aggregate of small cells that had ceased to increase in size from a very early age (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 2). In plants with leaves attached to the stem by a petiole or leaf-stalk, the pulvinus is located at the base of the leaf-stalk. CD was investigating when the organ emerged, and whether there was a pulvinus in cotyledons. He later discussed the emergence of pulvini and variations in cell length in <hi rend="italic">Oxalis corniculata</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, pp. 119–21.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For CD’s understanding of the nature of the cotyledon in grasses, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 62. Grass leaves do not have a stalk but are sessile, and their pulvini are located in the leaf-sheath, the portion of the leaf that encircles the shoot or stem. Apogeotropism: the tendency of leaves and other parts of plants to turn away from the earth and bend in opposition to gravity (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD was probably trying to determine the conditions under which radicles turned towards or away from water; he wished to understand the differences in the experimental results obtained by Julius von Sachs and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8188.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Theophil Ciesielski</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11538.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, [13–26 May 1878]</ref>). The letter in which Francis described his ‘dodge’ has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD’s letter to Murie has not been found. See n. 2, above.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>