<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11534">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Friedrich Ludwig   29 May 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20151</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11534 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11534.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11534.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 417</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 146: 137 </bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>146: 137</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-05-29">29 May 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3036.xml">Ludwig, Friedrich</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks FL for the <hi rend="italic">Plantago</hi> specimens. FL’s view of the stages by which the plant has become gynodioecious seems very probable.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Plantago</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monoecious or dioecious plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham, Kent (&amp;c).</placeName>
                    <date>May 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1878.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I thank you sincerely for the trouble which you have taken in sending me so long &amp; interesting a letter, together with the specimens.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Gradations are always very valuable, &amp; you have been remarkably successful in discovering the stages by which the <hi rend="underline">Plantago</hi> has become gyno-diœcious— Your view of its origin from being proterogynous, seems to me very probable especially as the females are generally the later flowering plants.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> If you can prove the reverse case with <hi rend="underline">Thymus</hi> your view will manifestly be rendered still more probable— I have never felt satisfied with H. Müller’s view, though he is so careful &amp; admirable an observer.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It is more than 17 years since I attended to <hi rend="underline">Plantago</hi>; &amp; when nothing had been published on the subject, &amp; in consequence I omitted to attend to several points,—&amp; now after so long an interval, I cannot pretend to say to which of your forms, the English one belongs; I well remember that the anther of the females contained a good deal pollen, though not one sound grain.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Once again thanking you for your kindness, I remain with much respect— Dear Sir | Yours faithfully. | Ch. Darwin.</p>
                    <p>P.S. | Delpino<ref target="#foot.f5"/> is Professor of Botany in Genoa Italy; I have always found him a most obliging correspondent.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Ludwig’s letter to CD has not been found, but in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9500.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. ix, CD wrote: <quote>I have received an additional account of <hi rend="italic">Plantago lanceolata</hi> being gyno-diœcious in England; and Dr. F. Ludwig of Greiz has sent me a description of no less than five forms of this plant which graduate into one another; the intermediate forms being comparatively rare, whilst the hermaphrodite form is the commonest.</quote> <hi rend="italic">Plantago lanceolata</hi> is ribwort plantain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Ludwig later published a paper, ‘Ueber  die Blütenformen von <hi rend="italic">Plantago lanceolata</hi> L., und die Erscheinung der Gynodiöcie’ (On the flower forms of <hi rend="italic">Plantago lanceolata</hi> L., and the appearance of gynodioecy; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig 1879</ref>), in which he discussed the stages in the development of gynodioecy, or the existence of both hermaphrodite and female flowers. Proterogynous (now protogynous) flowers are hermaphrodite flowers in which the female sexual parts (carpels) mature before the male ones (stamens).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Ludwig noted that another gynodioecious species, <hi rend="italic">Thymus serpyllum</hi> (Breckland thyme), differed from <hi rend="italic">Plantago lanceolata</hi> in the ratio of hermaphrodite to female flowers during its flowering period. In <hi rend="italic">T. serpyllum</hi>, whose hermaphrodite flowers are protandrous (i.e. stamens mature before carpels), female flowers predominated early in the flowering period, while hermaphrodite flowers became more frequent later. The opposite was the case in <hi rend="italic">P. lanceolata</hi>. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig 1879</ref>, p. 448.) <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller</ref> had suggested that since insects tended to visit more conspicuous flowers first (where they were dusted with pollen), less conspicuous flowers of the same species, which were visited only later, might have gradually lost functional stamens and been converted to females (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>, pp. 319, 326; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 304).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s notes on dichogamy and dimorphism in <hi rend="italic">Plantago lanceolata</hi>, dated 28 April 1863, are in DAR 109: A27–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref>.</note>
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>