<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2131">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Laurence Edmondston   2 August [1857]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9303</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2131 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2131.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2131.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">10pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>De Beer (1959): 31</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 6: 440</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">L. D. Edmondston (private collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_125.xml">Edmondston, L. D.</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1857-08-02">2 Aug [1857]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1457.xml">Edmondston, Laurence</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for rabbit.</p>
            <p>Are there dun-coloured ponies in Shetlands? Are they striped?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ponies, dun-coloured</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbit</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shetlands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Aug 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I am very much obliged for your letter of the 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>, &amp; for your information on the wild Pigeons, which is of much value to me.— I enclose the stamps for the Rabbit, for which I heartily thank you, as it will prove interesting in comparison with some other insular individuals.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You are so kind as to offer to take the great trouble of sending me some young Rock Pigeons: if I could have had them ten years ago, they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have been worth their weight in gold to me, but now, I think, I could have hardly any chance of breeding them for a sufficient number of generations to make it worth while to have them; though this does not make it the less kind of your offering to send them.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>About a month ago I wished extremely to ask you a question but I refrained solely because I thought I had already trespassed to a <hi rend="underline">quite</hi> unreasonable degree on your kindness; but as you offer with so much goodnature to assist me further, I will ask my question, as I do not think it can cost very much trouble, &amp; it is a point on which I have vainly sought for information.</p>
<p>In most parts of N. Europe, small horses or ponys are common (Eel-backs) of a Dun or Mouse-colour. Do such occur in the Shetlands? These duns generally, (perhaps <hi rend="underline">always</hi> (?)) have a black stripe along the spine, &amp; sometimes, (as I have seen) transverse dark Zebra-like marks on the legs, &amp; I have been assured on perfect authority a transverse shoulder stripe like that of the Ass. Now any information on ponys of this colour w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be of <hi rend="underline">extreme</hi> interest to me, as it is a most widely geographically extended &amp; ancient breed.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Is the spinal stripe universal with the duns? Have you <hi rend="underline">ever</hi> seen the shoulder asinine stripe? are the transverse leg marks common? But <hi rend="underline">especially</hi> I want to know whether these marks when they occur are plainer on the very young foal before the first hair is shed. And more than all I want to know whether the Dun or Mouse colour ever appears when neither parent is dun, and <hi rend="underline">as far as known</hi>, no ancestor has been of this colour; though this must always be very doubtful.</p>
<p>Is the Dun (with spinal stripe &amp; occasional other stripes) a very hereditary colour, ie will <hi rend="underline">one</hi> parent of this colour generally transmit it, when two horses of different colours, one being dun, are crossed? When duns &amp; other colours are crossed what colour results? I have written to Norway to beg for information;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; if you can give me any (&amp; coming from you, I know it will be reliable) it will in truth be of extreme use to me. Something analogous occurs in cream- &amp; roan &amp; chesnut horses; though in the two latter colours I have heard (&amp; seen) only the spinal stripe. I do not know whether these colours ever appear in the Shetland herds.</p>
<p>I can trust only to your great kindness, so often shown to me, to forgive this long note, &amp; I beg to remain, with hearty thanks, My dear Sir | Your’s sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>Anything about the stripes on Chesnuts interests me almost as much as in Duns.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.3 offer] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘so’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.4 it is] ‘it’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.1 (Eel-backs)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.4 dark] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.7 geographically] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.1 stripe] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">4.1 with the duns] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">4.3 when they occur] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">4.5 and] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘but’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">4.6 has been] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">5.2 it,] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">5.3 one] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘are’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">5.3 When duns … results?] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">5.6 Something] ‘S’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">5.7 colours] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is given by CD’s request for information on dun-coloured horses (see letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [before 13 June 1857]) and by the reference to the rabbit sent by Edmondston (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Edmondston’s letter has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2079.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Laurence Edmondston, 19 April [1857]</ref>, in which CD asked Edmondston to provide him with a specimen of the feral rabbit of the Shetland Islands.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had already received two dead rock pigeons from Edmondston in April (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2079.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Laurence Edmondston, 19 April [1857]</ref>), the measurements of which he later used in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 134 n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD discussed the dun-coloured ponies, but without mentioning any from the Shetlands, in his species book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 329–32). He believed that they, like the occasional reversion of breeds of domestic pigeons to the coloration and markings of <hi rend="italic">Columba livia</hi>, might illustrate the ‘Laws of variation’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The letter has not been found, but a note in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 58 n. 31 indicates that CD had written to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1142.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Rice Crowe</ref>, British consul-general in Norway, who provided him with information on this from several university professors. Crowe had previously corresponded with CD (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 5). In his species book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 329), CD stated that dun-coloured ponies were found ‘commonly (as informed by a friend) in Norway’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>