<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10152">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From F. J. Morphy   6 September 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">18058</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10152 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10152.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10152.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 243</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 243</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3404.xml">Morphy, F. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Buenos Aires</placeName>
                <date when="1875-09-06">6 Sept 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Reports a hybrid ram and sow, the <hi rend="italic">cuino</hi> of Mexico, which is very common and fertile.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cuino</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ram</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sow</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Mexico</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Gran Ferro Carril del Sud</hi><ref target="#foot.f1"/> | <hi rend="print">Oficina del Administrador General</hi> | <hi rend="print">Buenos Ayres</hi></placeName>
                    <date>6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="print">18</hi>75.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Charles Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>. M.A.; F.R.S. &amp;c.</seg>
                    <salute>Sir:</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Having read your works entitled “The descent of Man” and “Origin of Species”, and observing that in them you make no mention of a cross-breed, which exists in Mexico, between the Ram and the Sow, although you allude several times to the crosses between different animals, it seems to me probable that you may not have heard of this cross,—which is known by the name of “Cuino”—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but even if you have, no harm can happen from mentioning the subject to you.</p>
<p>Having lived over twenty years in Mexico, the fact of the cross I have mentioned is well known to me, and I have never regarded it as extraordinary, but since I have left that country, and have been in other parts, I find that not only is the existence of it ignored, but that people find a difficulty in believing such a cross possible.</p>
<p>The Cuino is the offspring of a ram and a sow, I have never heard of a boar crossing with an ewe. The ram and sow are penned up together for some time before they will have intercourse. The sow is generally chosen from a sort called “Concha”, but I believe, solely on account of its being finer than the other breeds in Mexico. The Cuino resembles very much the pig in its outward appearance,—only its nose is flatter, and it is easier to fatten, and is consequently bred for the lard rather than for the meat. It is not sterile; most of the cuinos being descended from other cuinos, and not from the parent-stock.</p>
<p>Should you wish to enquire into the case, you had better do so through someone who has friends in the country in Mexico; for persons living in the City, might probably know nothing about the animal.</p>
<p>In your “Origin of Species” you mention a cross between the hare and the rabbit,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but it seems to me, that the species of the ram and the sow, are still more distinct, yet these not only produce offspring, but the offspring are highly fertile when crossed with the mother species, or with each other.</p>
<p>I am, Sir, | Yours faithfully | F. J. Morphy</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">On the Gran Ferrocarril del Sud (Buenos Aires Great Southern Railway), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rögind 1937</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In 1902, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Bernhard Tegetmeier</ref> exhibited the skull of a supposed sheep–pig hybrid, a cuino, from Mexico, where it was domesticated; he concluded that it was a pig (<hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London</hi> (1902, vol. 1): 102).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 240.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>