<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9810">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From F. J. Cohn<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   9 January 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16450</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9810 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9810.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9810.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 199</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 199</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_999.xml">Cohn, F. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Breslau</placeName>
                <date when="1875-01-09">9 Jan 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for his letter of 1 Jan 1875. Will send a paper on the genus <hi rend="italic">Volvox</hi> ["Die Entwicklungsgeschichte der Gattung Volvox", <hi rend="italic">Cohn Beitr. Biol. Pflanz.</hi> 1 (1875) Heft 3: 99–115].</p>  
<p>Informs CD of his discoveries of the "house"-building capacity of <hi rend="italic">Difflugia</hi>, one of the lowest forms of organism.</p>  
<p>Sends CD his writing on <hi rend="italic">Aldrovanda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Utricularia</hi>, which he is welcome to use in his forthcoming book [<hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi>].</p>  
<p>Has observed a <hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> fertilised without insect aid.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="date" ref="#">1875.01.01</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Difflugia</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insect</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Aldrovanda</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Dionaea</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Utricularia</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nesting and other home-making or web-making behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-10-13" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes">n.9</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00803_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00803_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="199:1r" xml:id="i803">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00803.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00803_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00803.dzi" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="199:1v" xml:id="i804">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00804.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00804_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00804.dzi" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="199:2r" xml:id="i805">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00805.jpg" width="3854px" height="6465px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00805_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3854px" height="6465px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00805.dzi" width="3854px" height="6465px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="199:2v" xml:id="i806">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00806.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00806_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00806.dzi" width="3854px" height="6415px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Schweidnitzer Stadtgraben Nro. 26.</hi> | Breslau</placeName>
                    <date>9 Januar 1875</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Nicht ohne Beschämung erhalte ich Ihren so liebenswürdigen Brief vom ersten Tage dieses Jahres;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> wenn nach altem Glauben der Segen des Weisen Heil bringt, so müssen die freundlichen Wünsche, welche Sie mir entgegengebracht, mir ein glückliches Jahr verkünden. Von ganzem Herzen erwidere ich Ihre Glückwünsche; möge auch in dem neu begonnenen, wie noch vielen folgenden Jahren, Ihnen vergönnt sein, für die Menschheit <hi rend="underline">neue Thatsachen</hi>, <hi rend="underline">neue Gedanken</hi> zu finden, und sich des Erfolges Ihrer Geistesarbeit, und der Verehrung Ihrer Zeitgenossen in ungetrübter Frische zu erfreuen.</p>
<p>Ich bin in diesen Tagen viel beschäftigt gewesen mit den Vorbereitungen zu dem 50 jährigen Jubiläum meines Lehrers und Freundes Prof. Goeppert, der sich, wie kein andrer Naturforscher in unserem Kreise, die Liebe seiner Mitbürger durch seine wahrhaft humane Thätigkeit als akademischer Lehrer zu erwerben gewußt hat.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Eine große Menge von wissenschaftlichen und anderen Festgaben sind für dieses Fest von hiesigen und auswärtigen Freunden vorbereitet worden, ich selbst schicke Ihnen in den nächsten Tagen eine von mir verfaßte Festschrift, über “<hi rend="underline">die Entwicklungsgeschichte der Gattung Volvox</hi>” welche die höchst merkwürdige Organisation und Fortpflanzung dieses mikroskopischen “Zellen staates” schildert, und über die untersten Stufen des Lebens manches Licht verbreitet.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Bei dieser Gelegenheit möchte ich Sie darauf aufmerksam machen, daß bei einem überaus einfachen lebenden Wesen, das kaum höher organisirt ist als <hi rend="underline">Bathybius</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> der <hi rend="underline">Bautrieb</hi>, die Fähigkeit sich ein Haus aus fremden Stoffen zu bauen, sehr entwickelt ist. Ich meine die Gattung <hi rend="underline">Difflugia</hi>, eine im süßen Wasser verbreitete, artenreiche Gruppe aus der Familie der Rhizopoden, deren Plasmakoerper aber nicht nackt ist, wie bei den <hi rend="underline">Amoeben</hi>, noch durch <hi rend="underline">Secretion</hi> sich ein hornartiges oder kalkiges Gehäuse baut, wie <hi rend="underline">Arcella</hi><ref target="#foot.f6"/> und die <hi rend="underline">Foraminiferen</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> sondern durch Zusammenkleben von Sandkörnchen, Diatomeenschalen und andren im Wasser vorkommenden Körperchen sich eine Hülle baut, ähnlich wie die <hi rend="underline">Phryganeenlarven</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Räthselhaft ist eine solche Thätigkeit auf der niedersten Stufe der Organisation</p>
<p>Meine Abhandlung über <hi rend="underline">Aldrovanda</hi> und <hi rend="underline">Utricularia</hi>, obwohl längst gedruckt, ist doch noch immer nicht ausgegeben, weil dieselbe in einem Bande aufgenommen ist, zu welchem ich den Schlußaufsatz (über Bacterien) noch nicht habe vollenden können;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> inzwischen übersende ich Ihnen einen Abdruck der Tafel; es wird mich freuen, wenn Sie von derselben für Ihre Schrift Gebrauch machen wollen, und ich stelle Ihnen dieselbe zu jeglicher Benutzung mit Vergnügung zur Disposition.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Bei einem Besuch des Botanischen Garten zu Berlin im vorigen Herbst sah ich außerordentlich üppige Exemplare von <hi rend="underline">Darlingtonia</hi> und <hi rend="underline">Dionaea</hi>, welche unter Glasglocken auf <hi rend="underline">Sphagnum</hi> cultivirt waren.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Nach der Versicherung des Gärtners waren hier keine Insecten zu den Pflanzen gelangt, und doch entwickelten sich dieselben kräftiger, als ich sie je gesehen. Wie ist dies zu erklären?</p>
<p>Von der Redaction der “<hi rend="underline">Deutschen Rundschau</hi>”, die eine Art “<hi rend="underline">Revue de deux mondes</hi>” zu werden bestimmt ist, und in welcher auch der von mir vor einiger Zeit Ihnen zugeschickte Aufsatz “<hi rend="underline">Botanische Probleme</hi>” enthalten war, bin ich ersucht worden, einen “<hi rend="underline">Essay</hi>” über Ihr in Aussicht stehendes Buch von <hi rend="underline">Drosera</hi> zu schreiben, und ich bin gern bereit dies zu thun.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Sollte ich daher durch Ihre grosse Freundlichkeit zeitig in den Besitz Ihres Buches gelangen können, so würde ich dadurch in den Stand gesetzt, dem grossen Leserkreis der Deutschen Revue durch einen Bericht über Ihre neuen Forschungen bald eine Freude zu machen.</p>
<p>Mit der Bitte mir Ihr, mich so hoch ehrendes und erfreuendes Wohlwollen zu erhalten, zeichne ich in Verehrung | Dr. Ferdinand Cohn.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘Extremely interesting letter— | Particles of case D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carpenter—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> | Feeding of Dionæa— My experiment on Drosera—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> | —Sheet N Review— | New sp. of Aldrovanda’<ref target="#foot.f15"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Schweidnitzer Stadtgraben Nro. 26.</hi> | Breslau</placeName>
                    <date>9 January 1875</date>
                    <salute>Highly honoured Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is not without embarrassment that I receive your so very kind letter of the first day of the year;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> if according to the old belief the blessing of the wise brings luck, then the kind wishes that you bestowed upon me must herald a happy year for me. I return your good wishes with all my heart; may the year that has just begun, and many more beyond that, grant you the opportunity to discover <hi rend="underline">new facts</hi>, <hi rend="underline">new thoughts</hi> for humanity, and to enjoy with undiminished vigour the fruits of your intellectual endeavours, as well as the veneration of your contemporaries.</p>
<p>These days I have been very busy with the preparations for the golden jubilee of my teacher and friend Prof. Goeppert, who, like no other naturalist in our circle, has won the affection of his fellow citizens through his truly humane conduct as an academic teacher.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> A great number of celebratory gifts, scientific and other, have been prepared for this occasion by friends both local and abroad, and I myself will send you my publication in his honour, on “<hi rend="underline">die Entwicklungsgeschichte der Gattung Volvox</hi>”, within the next few days. It is an account of the most remarkable organisation and reproduction of this microscopic “cell state”, and it sheds considerable light on the lowest orders of life.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> May I also take this opportunity to direct your attention to the fact that in an exceedingly primitive living being, that is scarcely more organised than <hi rend="underline">Bathybius</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> the <hi rend="underline">building instinct</hi>, the capacity to build a shelter for itself from foreign matter, is well developed. I mean the genus <hi rend="underline">Difflugia</hi>, a common freshwater species-rich group of the family of Rhizopoda. Their plasma body is not naked like that of <hi rend="underline">Amoeba</hi>, nor does it form a corneous or calcareous casing by <hi rend="underline">secretion</hi>, like <hi rend="underline">Arcella</hi><ref target="#foot.f6"/> and the <hi rend="underline">Foraminifera</hi>;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> rather, like the <hi rend="underline">larvae of Phryganeidae</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Volvox constructs a casing for itself by gluing together grains of sand, the cell walls of diatoms, and other corpuscles in the water. Such an activity on the lowest level of organisation is mysterious.</p>
<p>Though it has long been printed, my paper on <hi rend="underline">Aldrovanda</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Utricularia</hi> is still awaiting distribution, because it will appear in a volume whose concluding essay (on bacteria) I have not yet been able to finish.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> In the meantime, I am sending you a copy of the table. You are welcome to use it for your publication, and it is a pleasure to put it at your disposal for any use you may find for it.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>During a visit to the botanic gardens of Berlin last autumn, I saw extraordinarily luxuriant specimens of <hi rend="underline">Darlingtonia</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Dionaea</hi>, cultivated under glass bells on <hi rend="underline">Sphagnum</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The gardener assured me that no insects had got to the plants, and yet they developed more vigorously than I have ever seen before. How can this be explained?</p>
<p>I have received a request to write an “<hi rend="underline">Essay</hi>” on your forthcoming book on <hi rend="underline">Drosera</hi> from the editors of <hi rend="underline">Deutsche Rundschau</hi>, which is intended to become something like the <hi rend="underline">Revue des deux mondes</hi>, and which also published my article “<hi rend="underline">Botanische Probleme</hi>” (of which I sent you a copy some time ago), and I am most happy to do this.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> If you would be so very kind as to help me get hold of your book early, this would enable me to soon delight the large readership of the German magazine with a report on your latest researches.</p>
<p>In the hope of your continuing goodwill which I feel so highly honoured by and which gives me such pleasure, I remain in veneration | Dr. Ferdinand Cohn.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 19–21.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9795A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to F. J. Cohn, 1 January 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The celebrations in question were held on 11 January 1875 in Breslau, on the occasion of the fiftieth anniversary of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Robert Goeppert’s</ref> doctorate (Cohn 1875b, p. 93 n.).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">There is a copy of Cohn 1875b (The developmental history of the genus <hi rend="italic">Volvox</hi>) in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. <hi rend="italic">Volvox</hi> is a genus of green algae. Cohn proposed that cytoplasmic bridges in embryonic cells served to channel materials from the somatic cells to the developing embryos.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Bathybius</hi> was a substance found on the seabed that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> originally thought was a primordial organism; he named it <hi rend="italic">Bathybius haeckelii</hi> (T. H. Huxley 1868b; L. Huxley ed. 1900, 2: 295–6; <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 19 August 1875, p. 316). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rice 1983</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Difflugia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Arcella</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Amoeba</hi> were genera in the class Rhizopoda; they are currently classified as genera in the subphylum Lobosa (amoebas) in the kingdom Protozoa. The shell of <hi rend="italic">Arcella</hi> is produced by the organism itself, while the shell of <hi rend="italic">Difflugia</hi> is made of mineral particles collected by the organism from the environment.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Foraminifera are unicellular marine protozoans; they are typically found near the bottom of the sea. See Lipps <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2011.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Phryganeidae is the family of giant casemaker caddisflies. The larvae construct cases of plant pieces fastened together with silk.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Cohn’s paper on the carnivorous plant <hi rend="italic">Aldrovanda</hi> (the waterwheel plant) and <hi rend="italic">Utricularia</hi> (bladderworts; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1490.xml">Cohn 1875a</ref>) appeared in the third part of the first volume of <hi rend="italic">Beiträge der Biologie der Pflanzen</hi>, a journal on plant biology edited by Cohn himself. CD’s proof copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1490.xml">Cohn 1875a</ref> is in DAR 58.2: 35–43. Four papers appeared under the heading ‘Untersuchungen über Bacterien’ (Research on bacteria), three of which were written by Cohn (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8655.xml">Cohn 1872b</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10277.xml">Cohn 1875c</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9396.xml">Cohn 1876b</ref>); Cohn evidently decided to publish his last of these in the second volume of <hi rend="italic">Beiträge der Biologie der Pflanzen</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Cohn probably sent table 1 from Cohn 1875a: it contained drawings of <hi rend="italic">Aldrovanda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Utricularia.</hi> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, p. 323, CD reproduced figure 5, a woodcut of a whorl of leaves of <hi rend="italic">Aldrovanda</hi>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9795A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to F. J. Cohn, 1 January 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Darlingtonia californica</hi>, the California pitcher-plant or cobra lily, and <hi rend="italic">Dionaea muscipula</hi>, the Venus fly trap, are both carnivorous plants. <hi rend="italic">Darlingtonia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> are monospecific genera. <hi rend="italic">Sphagnum</hi> is a genus of mosses noted for their ability to store several times their dry weight in water.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Cohn’s essay on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, which included a lengthy treatment of <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> (sundew), appeared in 1876 (Cohn 1876); there is a lightly annotated copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. No copy of his ‘Botanische Probleme’ (Botanical problems; Cohn 1874) has been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD’s annotations are notes for a reply to Cohn that has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Benjamin Carpenter</ref> had written an article, ‘On the hereditary transmission of acquired psychical habits’ (Carpenter 1873), in which he discussed the ability of some Foraminifera to construct multiform tests or casings using quartz grains of various sizes (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8869.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Carpenter, 21 April [1873]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD intended to write to Cohn about his book <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, in which he discussed <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> (sundew) and <hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> (Venus fly trap) at length. Cohn’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (see Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">CD may have meant to write to Cohn about <hi rend="italic">Aldrovanda vesiculosa</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">australis</hi>, which he mentioned in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, p. 329–30, writing that he was not sure whether it should rank as a variety or a species. He had received a specimen from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref> in October 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Daniel Oliver, 20 October 1874</ref>.)</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>