<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3204A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>   [before 9 July 1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20876</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3204A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3204A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3204A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 280–1 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">J. Hortic. n.s. 1 1861: 280–1</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1861-07-08">[before 9 July 1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2615.xml">Journal of Horticulture</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD thanks correspondents for information relating to the fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi> and of wheat. Suggests further observations and experiments.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Pelargonium</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">wheat</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Journal of Horticulture correspondents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope that you will grant me a little space to thank some of your correspondents and Mr. Beaton for his interesting information how to test the effects of different kinds of pollen on the divisions of the same stigma of a Pelargonium, for my special purpose of ascertaining whether one <hi rend="underline">variety</hi> is prepotent over another.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I fear that the Scarlet Pelargoniums include at least two wild forms, which botanists would rank as distinct <hi rend="underline">species</hi>. If Mr. Beaton is at any time writing on these plants, perhaps he would tell us what he knows about the wild parent of the Horseshoe and other Scarlets.</p>
<p>I am very glad that “P.” sent a list of his Perlargoniums with the central flower regular; for I was not aware how common the case was.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Will “P.” be so obliging as to observe and report whether any of the regular central flowers set seed—that is, if the kinds specified are such as ever produce seed?</p>
<p>With respect to the fertilisation of Wheat: several years ago I examined the flowers day by day, and came to the same conclusion as that which “H.C.K.” expresses so forcibly.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Mr. Beaton apparently does not much venerate botanical authorities,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but he might easily quote a long list of great names to show that Wheat is always fertilised in the bud;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> what has misled so many botanists I cannot imagine. But stranger assertions of the same kind may be met with: for instance, that cruciferous plants are generally fertilised before the flower opens!<ref target="#foot.f7"/> As I am away from home I write without my notes;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> but I remember that the Chinese have the singular belief that certain varieties of Wheat are always fertilised in the night-time. Col. Le Couteur, who attended so carefully to the varieties of Wheat, entertains no doubt that the different varieties, when growing near each other, cross.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> On the other hand, a full account has been published of a large number of varieties, I think 150, which were cultivated close together in some continental garden during several years, and never crossed each other.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> This account has much perplexed me; and I have sometimes been tempted to doubt whether any eye, however accurate, could have distinguished so many varieties, and that, perhaps, after all the varieties did cross. Mr. Beaton might advance this case in support of his belief that Wheat is fertilised in the bud.</p>
<p>As Mr. Beaton alludes to some mistake which he had made, might I venture to suggest to him to punish himself by telling sooner than he intended by what means he can produce from pollen of the same flower placed on the stigmas of the same variety two different sets of seedlings?<ref target="#foot.f11"/> That is a mystery which it is tantalising to wait for.—</p>
<p>Charles Darwin, <hi rend="underline">Down, Bromley, Kent</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the publication of the letter in the 9 July 1861 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>. It was printed under the title ‘Effects of different kinds of pollen’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The reference is to responses to CD’s letter to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, [before 18 June 1861]. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_345.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Donald Beaton</ref>, who wrote a regular column for the journal, had discussed some of the points CD raised in an article entitled ‘Cross-breeding plants’ printed in the 25 June 1861 issue (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 232–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The list of <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi> varieties sent by ‘P.’ appeared under the heading ‘Regular flowers in Pelargoniums’ in the 2 July 1861 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, p. 253.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to the letter from ‘H.C.K.,— <hi rend="italic">Rectory, Hereford</hi>.’ printed under the title ‘When is wheat fertilised?’ in the 2 July 1861 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, p. 257. The writer was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Cooper Key</ref>, rector of Stretton-Sugwas, Herefordshire. He referred the reader to Beaton’s response to CD’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3147.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of [before 14 May 1861]</ref>, which was printed immediately following CD’s letter (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, n.s. 1 (1861): 112–13). Beaton claimed, ‘No kind of Wheat has ever been naturally crossed and never can be’ and stated his belief that the seed was fertilised while the ear was still within its sheath, before the wheat blossomed (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 113). According to ‘H.C.K.’, Beaton’s view was ‘entirely in error’, and he gave his reasons for believing that wheat was fertilised after the ear had risen out of the sheath and the blossoming process had begun.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In a number of his articles over the past year or so, Beaton had made several disparaging references to the incursion of botanical science on practical gardening, warning gardeners in one instance against ‘building up systems of practice on a baseless, so-called-scientific foundation’ (<hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>, 21 February 1860, pp. 311–13).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD studied the literature treating the fertilisation of wheat and other plants and carried on his own investigations in 1856 and 1857. One of the ‘great names’ to which he refers was Jean Louis Auguste Loiseleur Deslongschamps. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6, letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1924.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">13 July [1856]</ref>, and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, 18 June [1857].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The reference has not been traced.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD and his family were staying in Torquay (see ‘Journal’; Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2848.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Le Couteur</ref> was the author of a well-known work on wheat (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Le Couteur 1836</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD referred to this experiment in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 314–15, where he cited the account given in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4852.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Loiseleur Deslongchamps 1842–3</ref>, pp. 45, 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Beaton had first referred to producing seeds of different varieties of geranium by placing the pollen of five different geraniums on the stigma of one flower in an article published in the <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>, 24 July 1860, pp. 253–5. He repeated this claim in his article on ‘Cross-breeding plants’ in the 25 June 1861 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, pp. 232–4, stating that before giving this information, he challenged ‘young gardeners to exercise their wits in trying to account for such a thing or how to do it.’ (p. 234), repeating the challenge the next week (p. 257) and discussing the problem of cross-breeding in the 9 July 1861 issue (pp. 272–3). Beaton responded to CD’s query more fully in an article entitled ‘Fertilisation of wheat’ published in the 23 July 1861 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, pp. 311–13.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>