<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11255F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   [27 November 1877]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">21825</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11255F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11255F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11255F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</hi> (1878): (Proceedings) ii–iii<ref target="#foot.f12"/></bibl>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                    <placeName>Santa Caterina, Brazil</placeName>
                    <date when="1877-11-27">[27 Nov 1877]</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
           <abstract>
               <p>Sends proboscis of a Sphinx-moth that is 22 cms long.</p>
               <p>Discusses eleven species of butterfly which visit <hi rend="italic">Lantana</hi>, a plant which blooms only for three days and whose flowers are yellow on the first day, orange on the second, and purple on the third. Most species only visit the flowers when they are yellow.</p>
                <p>Describes and draws the odiferous organs of a Sphinx-moth.</p>
               <p>Describes a secondary sexual character of several species of <hi rend="italic">Callidryas</hi> and other <hi rend="italic">Pierinæ</hi>: the costal margin of the anterior wing is sharply serrated in the males, while it is smooth in the females.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-07-25" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2016-07-26" status="initialProofCompleted">Initial proofread by <name xml:id="esmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
            <change when="2016-08-24" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2016-08-24" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
            <change when="2016-11-21" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name sameAs="#raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2016-11-21" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name>. Corrections entered by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name>.</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>Santa Caterina, Brazil</placeName>
                        <seg type="supplemental"/>
                        <salute/>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p>My children lately caught on flowers of <hi rend="italic">Calonyction</hi> (sp. ?) a Sphinx-moth, the proboscis of which is 22 centimetres long. As I think that you would be glad to see this curious proboscis I send it to you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> […] During the month of October I have watched for some weeks the butterflies visiting a <hi rend="italic">Lantana</hi> near my house, the flowers of which are yellow the first day, orange the second, purple the third day, and falling off on the morning of the fourth.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Eight out of eleven species of butterflies (<hi rend="italic">Heliconius apseudes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Colænis Dido</hi>, <hi rend="italic">C. Julia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dione Juno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hesperocharis Anguitia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eurema Leuce</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Daptonoura Lycimnia,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Callidryas Cipris</hi>) never touched an orange or purple flower, limiting their visits exclusively to the yellow ones.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Two specimens of <hi rend="italic">Pieris Aripa</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Elodia</hi>?) proceeded in the same way, whilst a third specimen of this <hi rend="italic">Pieris</hi> inserted its proboscis indifferently into yellow or orange flowers.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Three specimens of <hi rend="italic">Danais Erippus</hi> evidently preferred yellow flowers, but sometimes also tried orange flowers, and one of them even once put its proboscis into a purple flower; a fourth specimen of <hi rend="italic">Danais</hi> visited yellow flowers only.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Lastly, I saw three specimens of <hi rend="italic">Hesperidæ</hi>, but as I did not catch them, and as the species most closely resemble each other, I do not know whether they belonged to the same species; two visited exclusively yellow flowers, the third indifferently flowers of any colour—yellow, orange, or purple.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> These observations, of which a full account will be published in the ‘Archivos do Museo Nacional do Rio de Janeiro,’ confirm those by Delpino on <hi rend="italic">Ribes aureum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Caragana arborescens</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> If the flowers lasted but one day the flower-heads would be by far less conspicuous; if they lasted three days without changing colour, butterflies would lose much time in visiting honeyless, already-fertilized flowers. […] Yesterday I caught, for the first time, the male of a Sphinx-moth which exhaled a strong musk-like odour; as you know, this is also the case with the males of the European <hi rend="italic">S. convolvuli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. ligustri</hi>; but nobody has as yet, so far as I know, indicated the odiferous organ. It is formed by two pencils of hairs situated on the ventral side of the base of the abdomen, and when at rest are perfectly hidden by the scales (hairs?).<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                        <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width20">
                            <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_11255F.jpg"/>
                        </figure> 
                        <p>I do not remember whether I have already called your attention to an interesting secondary sexual character observable in several species of <hi rend="italic">Callidryas</hi> and some other <hi rend="italic">Pierinæ</hi>. The costal margin of the anterior wing is sharply serrated in the males, while it is smooth in the females. In <hi rend="italic">Callidryas Philea</hi> some females have the wings smooth, others serrated, but in a far less degree than in the male. This may be a sort of weapon in the battles of the males.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Whether in <hi rend="italic">Papilio Grayi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">P. Cleotas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">P. Coræbus</hi>, and their allies, the serrated margin of the fore wings is limited to the male sex I do not know, not having yet caught females of these rare species.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                            
                
            </div>
                  
                  
                  <div type="footnotes">
                      <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is given in the published source.</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Calonyction</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Ipomoea</hi>; Müller probably observed <hi rend="italic">I. alba</hi> (tropical white morning-glory). The moth species was later identified as <hi rend="italic">Macrosilia cluentius</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Neococytius cluentius</hi>, the cluentius sphinx; see <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 17 January 1878, p. 221). CD sent the letter and enclosures to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3289.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raphael Meldola</ref>, who exhibited the proboscis at a meeting of the Entomological Society of London on 6 February 1878 (see <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</hi> (1878): (Proceedings) iii).</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f3">The species was probably <hi rend="italic">Lantana camara</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11191.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 19 October 1877</ref> and n. 8).</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Heliconius apseudes</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">H. sara</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">apseudes</hi> (Sara longwing); <hi rend="italic">Colaenis dido</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Philaethria dido</hi> (scarce bamboo page or Dido longwing); <hi rend="italic">Colaenis julia</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Dryas iulia</hi> (Julia longwing); <hi rend="italic">Dione juno</hi> is the Juno silverspot or Juno longwing; <hi rend="italic">Hesperocharis anguitia</hi> is the Neemia butterfly; <hi rend="italic">Eurema leuce</hi> is Hall’s sulphur butterfly; <hi rend="italic">Daptonoura lycimnia</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Melete lycimnia</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Callidryas cipris</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Phoebis neocypris</hi> (tailed sulphur). </note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Pieris aripa</hi> is a syonym of <hi rend="italic">Leptophobia aripa</hi> (mountain white). A recognised subspecies is <hi rend="italic">Leptophobia aripa elodia</hi>, but it does not occur in Brazil; the Brazilian subspecies is <hi rend="italic">Leptophobia aripa balidia</hi>.</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Danais erippus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Danaus erippus</hi> (southern monarch)</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f7">Hesperidae (a synonym of Hesperiidae) is the family of skipper butterflies; they are small brown or orange butterflies characterised by rapid, skipping flight.</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f8">See ‘A correlação das flores versicolores e dos insectos pronubos’ (The correlation of varicoloured flowers and their insect pollinators; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1877c). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref> had made similar observations in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10371.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1873</ref>, pp. 176–7 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11191.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 19 October 1877</ref> and n. 7). <hi rend="italic">Ribes aureum</hi> is the golden currant; <hi rend="italic">Caragana arborescens</hi> is the Siberian pea tree.</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Sphinx convolvuli</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Agrius convolvuli</hi> (convolvulus hawk-moth); <hi rend="italic">S. ligustri</hi> is the privet hawk-moth. In <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1878, p. 220, Müller discussed the hair-pencils in <hi rend="italic">Macrosilia antaeus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Cocytius antaeus</hi>, the giant sphinx), noting that the pencils were hidden in abdominal grooves when the moth’s wings were at rest.</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Callidryas philea</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Phoebis philea</hi> (orange-barred sulphur butterfly); the Pierinae (whites) are a subfamily of the family Pieridae (orange-tips, whites, sulphurs). Müller had discussed the role of this species in the fertilisation of flowers of <hi rend="italic">Hedychium</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10572.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Hermann Müller, 7 August 1876</ref> and n. 1). Müller sent a specimen of the wings, which was exhibited by Meldola at a meeting of the Entomological Society of London on 6 February 1878 (see <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</hi> (1878): (Proceedings) iii).   </note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Papilio grayi</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. scamander</hi> (scamander swallowtail); <hi rend="italic">P. cleotas</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. menatius cleotas</hi>; <hi rend="italic">P. coroebus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. menatius coroebus</hi>.</note>
                      <note xml:id="foot.f12">The original letter has not been found. CD communicated it to the Entomological Society of London, and it was read by Meldola at a meeting on 6 February 1878.</note>
            </div>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>