<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1538">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Syms Covington   21 October 1853</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5389</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1538 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1538.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1538.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Ferguson (1971): 12</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 5: 163</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Sydney Mail</hi>, 9 August 1884, p. 254</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">De Beer, Gavin 1959b: 21</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1853-10-21">21 Oct 1853</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1096.xml">Covington, Syms</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on SC’s trip to the gold diggings. CD is most interested in Australia and reads every book about it that he can find. Sends news of former <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> shipmates FitzRoy, Sulivan, Mellersh, and of Fuegia [Basket].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">gold diggings</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley, Kent,</placeName>
                    <date>October 21, 1853.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Covington,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I received your letter dated May 25, “53, at Pambala,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> here at Down on Oct. 11, which I think is very quick. I thank you sincerely for writing, as I had for some time been thinking how you were getting on. From what we see in the papers, most of us in England have got an awful idea of the state of things at the diggings.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Your account of the way the Sunday was kept near the Ovens<ref target="#foot.f3"/> was very pleasant to hear. On the spot you must, of course, judge best, but I should have liked to have heard of your turning up a fine nugget worth some hundred pounds, and that would have repaid you for your long journey, which I traced by your letter on the map. Well, I daresay it was almost worth your while once to have seen the diggings, for it must be a curious spectacle. I should like very much at some future time to hear how you get on, and whether the mining has done you and other residents near Twofold Bay<ref target="#foot.f4"/> good or harm. About half a year ago I had Mr. Septimus Martin, the son of the rector of the adjoining parish,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> dining with me; he has now gone back to Melbourne, and is married. He had formerly been at Twofold Bay, and told me a little about it. I feel a great interest about Australia, and read every book I can get hold of. I lately read a long one by Colonel Mundy.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I really have no news to tell you of myself; we live a most quiet life. I have not yet finished my second volume on the Barnacles, but hope soon to do so, and begin some other subject. I saw a few weeks ago Captain Fitz Roy; perhaps you heard that a year or two ago he had the great misfortune of losing his wife.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I am afraid he lost much money by his government of New Zealand.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I saw also Captain Sulivan,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> who has now half-a-dozen children. Lastly, the only other officer I have heard of, Melleish, has greatly distinguished himself by hard fighting with some Chinese Pirates.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> We are all much afraid of war with Russia, which, pray God, may be prevented.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> You might like to hear that two or three years ago Fuegia<ref target="#foot.f12"/> was heard of by a sealer in the west part of the Straits of Magellan. He<ref target="#foot.f13"/> could still speak some English. With every good wish for yourself and family, pray believe me your faithful friend, | C. DARWIN.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">A mistake in the <hi rend="italic">Sydney Mail</hi> transcription for Pambula (see n.4, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1477.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Syms Covington, 14 March 1852</ref>, CD had asked Covington to tell him how people behaved at the recently discovered Australian goldfields.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The Ovens River goldfield in New South Wales.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Covington had settled at Pambula, on Twofold Bay. In 1854 he became its second postmaster (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2487.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferguson 1971</ref>, p. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3189.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Septimus Martin</ref>, the son of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3186.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph William Martin</ref>, rector of Keston, near Bromley, Kent.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD read the three volumes of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3448.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Godfrey Charles Mundy’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Our antipodes</hi> (1852) between 17 May and 2 July 1853. CD’s comment was ‘Very good.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.4, Appendix IV, 128: 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1648.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Henrietta FitzRoy</ref> died in 1852 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mellersh 1968</ref>, p. 270).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">During his governorship of New Zealand, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> had used his own funds, as he had during the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage, for purposes for which he should have obtained government approval and for which he was not reimbursed (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-730.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 13 January – 12 February 1845</ref>, pp. 124–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bartholomew James Sulivan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Mellersh</ref>, midshipman then mate in the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>, was at this time serving in the East Indies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Turkey declared war on Russia in October 1853. England and France intervened, siding with Turkey, and eventually declared war on Russia in March 1854.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_308.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fuegia Basket</ref>. FitzRoy had given this name to Yokcushlu, the Fuegian girl he had taken to England with three other natives of Tierra del Fuego during the first voyage of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>. During the second voyage she was returned to her homeland with two of her companions, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_779.xml">Orundellico (Jemmy Button)</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5279.xml">Elleparu (York Minster)</ref>, the third, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_504.xml">Boat Memory</ref>, having died in England. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-203.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Caroline Darwin, 30 March – 12 April 1833</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">A mistake in the <hi rend="italic">Sydney Mail</hi> transcription for ‘She’ (see n. 12, above).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>