<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-769">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Adolf von Morlot   9 August [1844]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1061</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-769 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-769.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-769.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Burgerbibliothek Bern, Bern, Switzerland</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_41.xml">Bern</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1844-08-09">9 Aug [1844]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3403.xml">Morlot, Adolph von</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Declines to undertake to have AM’s journal published but recommends possible publishers in England.</p>
            <p>Expresses scepticism about AM’s glacier theory. Emphasises role of floating ice instead. Mentions article by William Hopkins on movement of glaciers.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3463">publishers</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down near Bromley | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Aug 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I should have replied to your last obliging letter, had I not lately been much engaged, before this time. I regret exceedingly to say, that I cannot undertake to see your Journal published: my health during the last three years has been exceedingly weak, so that I am able to work only two or three hours in the 24: these are more than fully occupied &amp; I have materials for several years’ work, which is almost more than I dare undertake. Under these circumstances, I hope you will not think me either unkind or unreasonable in declining to add to my employments, &amp; you must be well aware that everything going through the press costs time &amp; trouble. The only channel of publication in England, that I can see, without great expence to yourself, <hi rend="underline">might possibly</hi> be the Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal; but I cannot here aid you, as I am not acquainted with the Editor.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>We in England are accustomed to believe, that publication is much less expensive with you, than with us: certainly Engraving is. The cheapness of German Books always astonishes me, &amp; I wish scientific authors in England knew, how to follow so good an example. I may just mention to you, that “M. Baillière Bookseller Regent St” is one of the most spirited of scientific publishers, &amp; it might, perhaps, be worth while to send your M.S. to him. Every publisher, however, in England looks at scientific books with a cold eye.— I hope sincerely that you will meet with success in whatever you determine on, though I cannot aid you.</p>
<p>You will think me a great sceptic, when I tell you that your letter has not convinced me. I daresay there may have been Glaciers on the mountains you describe, but my mind will require a long series of proofs to believe that they have come from Scandinavia.— One always puts too much stress on what one self has seen; but I cannot avoid suspecting that N. Wales offers an example of what has happened in many cases; viz, that the Boulders have been transported &amp; rocks scored by floating ice, &amp; that after &amp; during elevation, glaciers have removed all these appearances, <hi rend="underline">except</hi> <hi rend="underline">on the outskirts</hi>, &amp; have left in place their own marks.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I do not believe the respective shares of work of these two agencies, will be clear, until the action of floating ice has been fuller studied in the north &amp; some distinctive effect, <hi rend="underline">if any exist</hi>, pointed out. The <hi rend="underline">piled</hi> boulders, one on another, appears to me likely to be a distinctive character.—</p>
<p>Have you ever examined the bottoms of the pot-holes? I think it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be worth doing, for I found the shape of those, formed by <hi rend="doubleUnderline">eddies</hi> during floods in the Welch brooks, curious: they were formed like the bottom of the inside of a green glass bottle—a form evidently due to the centrifugal action of the revolving sand &amp; pebbles.  [DIAGRAM HERE]</p>
<p>Are you aware that Hopkins has lately published a paper in Cambridge Phil. Trans.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> in which he disputes Forbe’s semi-fluid theory,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; maintains that the movement cannot be compared with that of a viscid fluid:— he attributes all to gravity, with <hi rend="underline">the aid of the lower surface melting</hi>.—</p>
<p>With my best wishes for your success &amp; that your zeal may be rewarded by many discoveries; believe me, Yours sincerely | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.1 replied] ‘i’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘y’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.5 Bookseller] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘of’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.8 on] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.3 my] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.4 one] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘one’s’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.7 &amp; during] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.8 in place] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.9 shares] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘shares’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.9 work] ‘w’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.12 a] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">4.1 bottoms of] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2536.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Jameson</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See CD’s <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_154.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Notes on the effects produced by the ancient glaciers of Caernarvonshire’</ref> (1842), <hi rend="italic">Collected</hi> <hi rend="italic">papers</hi> 1: 163–71. As opposed to CD’s view, Morlot appears to have advanced the theory of erratic boulder transport by a great ice-sheet advancing from Scandinavia.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Hopkins 1849, read 1 May 1843.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James David Forbes</ref> believed that glacial ice flowed in the manner of a viscous fluid, whereas <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref> thought it simply slid downhill in its bed. Forbes’s position (presented in numerous contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal</hi> 1841–5, and summarised in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Forbes 1843</ref>) involved him in a priority dispute with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> as well as in controversies with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Tyndall</ref>, and others. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6756.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rowlinson 1971</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>