<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4880">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Crawfurd to E. A. Darwin   7 August 1863</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16531</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4880 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4880.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4880.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">1p, encl 2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 237, 237/1</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 237</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1109.xml">Crawfurd, John</persName>
                <placeName>Athenaeum Club</placeName>
                <date when="1863-08-07">7 Aug 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Darwin, E. A.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Forwards an enclosure for CD, at Archdeacon John Sinclair’s request [extract from J. Sinclair’s <hi rend="italic">Life and works of Sir John Sinclair</hi> (1837) 2: 83–5], showing how Dr Erasmus Darwin anticipated Justus von Liebig [in recognising the importance of phosphorus-rich manures].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Life and works of Sir John Sinclair</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2922">Liebig, Justus von</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4066">Rolfe, R. M.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Sinclair, John 1837</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">The Athenæum</hi></placeName>
                    <date>August 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1863.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin/</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was requested by Archdeacon Sinclair to send the enclosed to your brother.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It contains a remarkable prophecy of your grandfather which long anticipated the opinion of Libig &amp; well deserves attention.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Will you forward with my kind regards | very sin<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi> yours | J Crawfurd <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Erasmus Darwin Esq</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Nor did the Board confine their efforts to the Collection &amp; diffusion of agricultural Knowledge;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> they endeavoured also to arrange it—to connect husbandry with philosophy or as the Founder of the institution frequently expressed himself “to raise agriculture from the level of an art to the dignity of a science.” They wished its process no longer to be carried on blindly or empirically, but to be formed into a regular system &amp; conducted upon rational &amp; experimental principles. The two branches of science from which the greatest aid might be expected were vegetable physiology &amp; chemistry; the Board therefore endeavoured to prevail on men of eminence in these departments to employ their scientific attainments in arranging &amp; combining theoretically the miscellaneous facts &amp; loose notions of which agricultural knowledge at that time exclusively consisted. Among the most valuable results were Darwin’s Phytologia &amp; Davy’s Lectures on Agricultural Chemistry.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>The Phytologia or Philosophy of Agriculture &amp; Gardening was dedicated by the Author in the most cordial terms of friendship &amp; esteem to Sir John Sinclair as a work “begun at his instigation, &amp; forwarded by his encouragement.” D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin entered warmly into Sir John’s feeling of indignation that husbandry had till then been so much neglected by the learned, &amp; that at a time when many branches of knowledge far inferior in importance had been carefully arranged &amp; digested into sciences agriculture &amp; gardening though of such great utility in producing the nutriment of mankind continued to be only arts. The work comprises three parts of which the first explains the physiology of vegetation; the second describes the economy of vegetation &amp; the third applies the principles thus established to agricultural &amp; horticultural productions. Among the casual discoveries which this ingenious work had the merit of bringing forward was the use of bone dust as a manure. Having mentioned phosphorus as an element under different forms, existing universally in vegetables, &amp; not before sufficiently attended to, the Doctor specifies the different substances from which this essential food of plants may be obtained &amp; which therefore might be advantageously employed as manure; he then proceeds— “and, lastly, the use of recent shells, or bones ground into powder, or of bone ashes may be deduced as they consist almost entirely of phosphorus &amp; calcareous earth.”<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The fertilizing properties of this manure had been previously noticed by Hunter,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> but they were first theoretically explained &amp; brought forward with authority by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin. Perhaps no modern discovery has contributed so powerfully to improve the fertility &amp; increase the produce of the soil, as the use of bone dust.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Nothing but experience would render credible the strong &amp; lasting effects produced by even small quantities of this active Substance.—</p>
<p>Life of Sir John Sinclair Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. | vol II. p. 83–5.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The reference is to John Sinclair, archdeacon of Middlesex and vicar of Kensington. The enclosure was a handwritten extract from a book by Sinclair about the life of his father, John Sinclair (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7215.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Sinclair 1837</ref>, 2: 83–5); it included a tribute to CD’s grandfather, Erasmus Darwin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The enclosure discusses points in Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1793.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">E. Darwin 1800</ref>) that the author thought predated <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Justus von Liebig’s</ref> conclusions regarding agricultural fertiliser. Liebig had noted that fields required the replacement of essential minerals in order to maintain a constant state of fertility (Liebig 1840, p. 182). He recommended bone as a rich source of calcium and magnesium phosphates and further observed that the waste materials of the glue industry represented an untapped source of valuable minerals in a form particularly suitable for agricultural use (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.185). For an analysis of Liebig’s role in the development of agricultural chemistry, particularly in the analysis and development of artificial fertilisers, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_924.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Brock 1997</ref>, pp. 145–82.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to the Board of Agriculture, founded in 1793 at the instigation of John Sinclair Sr, who became its first president (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6804.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">E. J. Russell 1966</ref>, pp. 54, 67).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1793.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">E. Darwin 1800</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1852.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">H. Davy 1813</ref>. For a discussion of Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi>, and his anticipation of later discoveries in agriculture and plant biology, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">King-Hele 1999</ref>, pp. 333–8. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1258.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Humphry Davy’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Elements of agricultural chemistry</hi> is discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6804.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Russell 1966</ref>, pp. 67–76.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The quotation is from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1793.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">E. Darwin 1800</ref>, p. 211.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Sinclair refers to a remark on the use of ash as a fertiliser <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3956.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Hunter 1777</ref>, pp. 382–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his biography of his grandfather, CD quoted this sentence, adding in a note that he was ‘indebted to Dr Dowson’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Erasmus Darwin</hi>, for the reference to the <hi rend="italic">Life and Works of Sir J. Sinclair</hi>’ (<hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, p. 113); the quoted sentence appears in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2132.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Dowson 1861</ref>, p. 56.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>