<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9494">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ferdinand von Mueller   16 June 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10133</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9494 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9494.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9494.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 283</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 283</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3441.xml">Mueller, F. J. H. von</persName>
                <placeName>Melbourne, Victoria</placeName>
                <date when="1874-06-16">16 June 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Wants information from CD for a revision of the supplement of his work on timber trees and other industrial plants [<hi rend="italic">Proc. Zool. &amp; Acclim. Soc. Victoria</hi> 3 (1874): 47–95].</p> 
            <p>Reports the ruin of his department thanks to two papers by Edward Wilson, McKinnon, and Sparrow.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">timber trees</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Proc. Zool. &amp; Acclim. Soc. Victoria</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Mueller, F. J. H. von 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">department</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Melbourne,</placeName>
                    <date>16/6/74.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>When lately issuing a supplement to my “timber-trees” and “other industrial plants”, dear Mr Darwin, I came across the Ribes Magellanicum and remained doubtful, whether it ought to be included in my “additions”.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Will you kindly inform me, whether it is a species deserving cultivation.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I wish to prepare a second supplement, and perhaps you may remember other plants of utilitarian importance yet to be cultivated, without taxing your precious time.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>As I have occasion to write to you I cannot refrain from remarking, that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edw Wilson, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kinnon &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Spowers must not be aware of the <hi rend="underline">ruin</hi> of my Department, mainly due to the cruel and unjust persecution of their two papers after their departure for England.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I cannot think that they would have allowed me thus to be ruined, had they not been misled concerning the changes made in my position.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>All that is left me for working my <hi rend="underline">whole Department</hi> with all its responsible daily multifarious duties is £300, which would not even suffice to rent the buildings required for the service in this <hi rend="underline">expensive</hi> country, only one room (without fire place) and overcrowed with collections being left me! Altho’ I have spent again my <hi rend="underline">whole</hi> <hi rend="underline">modest salary</hi> to carry on some part of the service through this year, I was unable to maintain the field branch, nor the laboratory branch, nor the greater part of the required interchanges, nor the lithographic work. Indeed the Observatory receives 10 times as much for working expenses than my Department, not to speak of buildings provided.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Last week a commencement was made to break even down my laboratory. Imagine D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker as Gov. Botanist of England <hi rend="underline">out of Kew</hi> and performing the duties out of his salary, leaving his family &amp; old age unprovided.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> What a <hi rend="underline">poor triumph</hi> of the proprietors of the Argus, who are well aware that with the scanty means granted noone could have done more for the bot Garden than I did.</p>
<p>Yrs faithfully | Ferd. von Mueller</p>
<p>It is strange, that not one of all the men of science of England has taken the slightest notice of my having left no me〈a〉ns beyond £300 to work the important duties of my Department.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In his ‘Select plants (exclusive of timber trees) readily eligible for Victorian industrial culture’, a paper written for the Zoological and Acclimatisation Society of Victoria, of which he was vice-president, Mueller had included several species of <hi rend="italic">Ribes</hi> (currant; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5645.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mueller 1872</ref>, pp. 369–70). In 1871, Mueller had produced a similar report on timber trees for the society (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5644.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mueller 1871</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Ribes magellanicum</hi> (Magellanic currant) is native to Tierra del Fuego; CD had collected a specimen between 27 and 29 December 1832 while on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (see Porter 1999, pp. 184–5). The first supplement to the lists appeared in 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mueller 1874</ref>), but it did not include <hi rend="italic">Ribes magellanicum</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> notes on plants of Tierra del Fuego, made in January 1833, CD mentioned the ‘black currants tree’, along with some other plants, as ‘the most useful plants in the country’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6355.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. M. Porter 1999</ref>, p. 184).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The second supplement was published in 1875 but <hi rend="italic">Ribes magellanicum</hi> was not added to the list (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5647.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mueller 1875</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Wilson</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6253.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lauchlan Mackinnon</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7360.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Allan Spowers</ref> were proprietors of the <hi rend="italic">Argus</hi>, a Melbourne daily newspaper. Wilson also founded the Acclimatisation Society as an offshoot of the Victorian Zoological Society in 1861, but returned to England in 1864 and eventually settled near Bromley, Kent, where he was acquainted with the Darwins. Wilson’s partners, Mackinnon and Spowers, changed the paper’s stance from a radical to a conservative position (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Aust. dict. biog.</hi></ref>, s.v. Wilson, Edward; Mackinnon, Lauchlan). No other newspaper was owned or operated by the partners; Mueller may have intended to write ‘the persecution by the paper of those two’ with reference to the two senior partners, Wilson and Mackinnon. For the effect the paper had on Mueller’s department, see n. 5, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Mueller’s position as director of the Melbourne Botanic Garden had disappeared in 1873, when the government changed the status of the garden from a distinct department to a subordinate part of Government House and appointed a curator to take charge of it. Mueller’s approach to the garden as a centre for scientific inquiry along with his policy of supplying seeds free of charge had been vigorously opposed by horticulturists and nurserymen. In December 1871, when a Board of Inquiry produced a report highly critical of Mueller, the <hi rend="italic">Argus</hi> published it in full and applauded the board’s conclusions. The paper accused Mueller of attempting to manipulate the press and suggested his antagonists were phantoms of his imagination. When Wilson was still in Australia, the paper had supported Mueller. (For a detailed account of the loss of the directorship, including the role played by the <hi rend="italic">Argus</hi>, see H. Cohn and Maroske 1996.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Mueller had retained his position as government botanist of Victoria and had exclusive use of the Botanical Museum but no funding beyond his personal salary (see H. Cohn and Maroske 1996, pp. 104–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> had been under similar pressure from government over the running of the Royal Botanic Garden at Kew when <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_203.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Acton Smee Ayrton</ref>, commissioner of the Office of Works, attempted to undermine his position by separating botanical and horticultural responsibilities (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 19 and 20; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2137.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Drayton 2000</ref>, pp. 211–20, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endersby 2008</ref>, pp. 282–300).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Hooker had written to Mueller about his situation, advising him to hire a horticulturist to do the ‘ornamental and practical gardening’ (<ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from J. D. Hooker to Ferdinand Mueller, 15 January 1873</ref>; quoted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6394.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Powell 1977</ref>, p. 317), but his advice came too late to be of any use.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>