<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10550">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. R. Wallace   25 June 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1793</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10550 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10550.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10550.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 276</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Marchant (1916) 1: 292;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 16</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Add MS 46434)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <idno>Add MS 46434</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1876-06-25">25 June 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has finished <hi rend="italic">Geographical distribution</hi>; sends his comments.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Wallace, A. R. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-19" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-01-19" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Beckenham</placeName>
                    <date>June 25. 76</date>
                    <salute>My dear Wallace</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been able to read rather more quickly of late and have finished your book.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have not much to say. Your careful account of the temperate parts of S. America interested me much, and all the more from knowing something of the country.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I like also much the general remarks towards the end of the Vol on the land mollusks.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Now for a few criticisms.</p>
<p>P. 122: I am surprised at your saying that “during the whole Tertiary period N. America was Zoologically far more strongly contrasted with S. America than it is now.” But we know hardly anything of the latter except during the Pliocene period; and then the Mastodon, Horse, several great Edentata, &amp;c, &amp;c were common to the N &amp; S. If you are right I erred greatly in my Journal where I insisted on the former close connection between the two.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>P 252 &amp; elsewhere: I agree thoroughly with the general principle that a great area with many competing forms is necessary for much and high developement; but do you not extend this principle too far,—I should say much too far, considering how often several species of the same genus have been developed on very small Islands?</p>
<p>P. 265: You say that the Sittidæ<ref target="#foot.f5"/> extend to Madagascar, but there is no number in the tabular heading.</p>
<p>P 359: Rhinochætus is entered in the tabular heading under No 3 of the <hi rend="underline">Neotropical</hi> sub-regions<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Reviewers think it necessary to find some fault; &amp; if I were to review you, the sole point which I should blame is your not giving very numerous references. These would save whoever follows you, great labour. Occasionally I wished myself to know the authority for certain statements &amp; whether you or somebody else had originated certain subordinate views. Take the case of a man who had collected largely on some Island, for instance S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Helena, &amp; who wished to work out the geographical relations of his collection; he would I think feel very blank at not finding in your work, precise references to all that had been written on S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Helena. I hope you will not think me a confoundedly disagreeable fellow.</p>
<p>I may mention a capital essay which I received a few months ago from Axel Blytt on the distribution of the plants of Scandinavia; showing the high probability of there having been secular periods alternately wet &amp; dry; &amp; of the important part which they have played in distribution.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I wrote to Forel who is always at work on ants, and told him of your views about the dispersal of the blind coleoptera, and asked him to observe.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I spoke to Hooker about your book, and feel sure that he would like nothing better than to consider the distribution of plants in relation to your views; but he seemed to doubt whether he should ever have time.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>And now I have done my jottings, &amp; once again congratulate you on having brought out so grand a work. I have been a little disappointed at the review in Nature<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>my dear Wallace | Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had read Wallace’s <hi rend="italic">Geographical distribution of animals</hi> (Wallace 1876a). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10538.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 17 June 1876</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Wallace discussed ‘South temperate America, or the Chilian sub-region’ (from Tierra del Fuego in the south to Santiago in the north) in Wallace 1876a, 2: 36–51. For CD’s experiences there, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10531.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 5 June 1876</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10535.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 7 June 1876</ref>. In Wallace 1876a, 2: 525, Wallace concluded that air-breathing molluscs could be transported across the sea by attaching themselves to floating logs or being carried on birds’ feet.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 131. CD’s page references at the beginning of paragraphs are to the second volume of Wallace 1876a. The order Edentata has now been split into the orders Xenarthra, Pholidota, and Tubulidentata. The Tertiary period is a former geologic period roughly equivalent to the Paleogene and Neogene periods. The Pliocene is the most recent epoch of the Neogene period; it formerly included the Gelasian stage, which is now included in the Pleistocene epoch.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Sittidae is the family of nuthatches.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Rhynochetos jubatus</hi> is the kagu, a bird of the family Rhynochetidae; it should have been listed in the Australian subregion.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10433.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Axel Blytt, 28 March 1876</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Blytt 1876</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10539.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Auguste Forel, 19 June 1876</ref>. In Wallace 1876a, 1: 212, Wallace suggested that two wingless species of Coleoptera found in Madeira might have been transported in the egg by flying ants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">It is not known when CD spoke to Hooker about Wallace’s book. Hooker believed that the hypothesis of land-bridges was necessary to account for the distribution of plants (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4169.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [24 May 1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Wallace 1876a was reviewed in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 22 June 1876, pp. 165–8, and 29 June 1876, pp. 186–9. The second part of the anonymous review was more positive.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>