<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12131F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [22 June 1878]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21523</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12131F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12131F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12131F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 51</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 51</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="high">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Hotel de Russie, Würzburg</placeName>
                <date when="1878-06-22">[22 June 1878]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes his talk with Julius von Sachs about canary-grass.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Hotel de Russie | Würzburg</placeName>
                    <date>Saturday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have had a talk with Sachs about oat &amp; canary grass   he says the chlorophyll is only beginning to be developed when the seedling appears above ground &amp; that the assimilation is extremely small for the first few days— He evidently thought that assimilation was practically not going on for the first few days. If you want to know more accurately I can easily grow some oats, &amp; it would be good practice in section cutting or perhaps in spectroscoping.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But Sachs seemed very confident about the complete unimportance of assimilation. I have borrowed Cieselski &amp; read him.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Sachs doesn’t consider that there is any puzzle as to how the difference between their results arose. He says the bend up only occurs when the root has previously lost water &amp; &amp; then the cells on the water surface become more turgid &amp; cause the upward bend. I think I only saw a passage about Cieselski in ‘Ablenkung der Wurfeln &amp;’ p 219— I suppose you have seen the place in “Ueber das Wachsthum der Hapt u Nebenw” p 401, where he talks about the fact that the roots must be slightly dry for C’s bend.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have read most of Cieslski &amp; I dont think there is much to trouble about. Sachs doesn’t think much of him, although some of his experiments were good. One fact of his would be interesting if it were true but Sachs says it is “falsch’— If you cut the extreme tip of a root, it goes on growing pretty well though the punctum vegetationis is destroyed. Cieselski says that while this growth continues &amp; before a new punctum veg<hi rend="superscript">is</hi>. is formed that the roots does not care for gravity &amp; will grow in any direction it is placed in<ref target="#foot.f5"/>  This Sachs says is not true.</p>
<p>Cieselski says if you shave a long sloping bit off a root—&amp; place the root horizontally then if the cut surface is downwards the root will bend down geotropically even quicker than usual, but if the cut surface is uppermost, the root will sometimes bend up before it bends down. This looks like bending towards the cut side.</p>
                    <p>I have got a most queer looking sleeper—? hygrometrica: it has pinnate leaves like <hi rend="underline">M. Farnesiana</hi> &amp; Sachs says it always asleep—he doesn’t understand the movements: he thinks it must be suited for some very exceptional climate or position: it has a great deal of wood &amp; very few leaves &amp; all afternoon in shade they were pressed back agains the stems &amp; the leaflets shut—I will observe it.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Sachs declares he believes that one use of sleeping plants shutting up on being irritated is a protection against hail. There was a summer hailstorm here of only 5 or 10 minutes which did many pounds worth of damage by killing plants, &amp; some mimosas were out in it &amp; were quite uninjured   He thinks the flaccidity of the leaf in the irritated state important as making it yield on being struck. He seemed quite inclined to believe in protection from cold. Also in bloom being protection against dryness. He thinks blo〈om〉 must have many functions &amp; said it was a protection against insects.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> He had never noticed the fact that when you wet the lower end of a yew stick water appears above &amp; quite agrees with my idea that it is important, he evidently didint much believe in it till he tried it himself &amp; then was pleased with it</p>
                    <p>I have not got any good Hydrocharis plants so have not begun.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have been cutting to get exactly central ones. I think Sachs thought I wanted to publish something &amp; that was why he gave me the the Hydrocharis to do, I told him that I would rather do something that hadn’t been finished even tho’ it led to nothing so I have started trying to make out what changes in strength &amp; in elasticity go on as a woody stem loses water</p>
<p>At present the experiments are very simple</p> 
<figure rend="floatRight width45"> 
    <graphic url="../images/DCP-LETT-12131F.svg"/>
</figure> 
                    <p rend="left">A stick or grass stalk fixed horizontally at one end &amp; a weight to take off &amp; put on, &amp; I measured the movement with my mercury microm<ref target="#foot.f9"/>   The ultimate object is to know what share the tension of the cell walls (not the hydrostatic turgor) takes in causing the stiffness of a stem. One ought to be a first rate mathematician for such a thing. I shall also do some experiments putting fresh &amp; withered shoots into alcohol &amp; seeing what happens. Sachs has done some experiments, &amp; says they both retain their form very nearly, but he doesn’t know exactly. Sachs told me of a real fools experiment he tried, he thought the green colour of cabbage catterpillars must come from chlorophyll &amp; so he tried feeding them on etiolated leaves—but they would not turn white.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I think it would be a good thing to have a telescope like Vines used, it would do for any careful observations—they are made in Munich &amp; I could order one like Sachs’   they cost about £10.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I should think there are at least 50 thermometers in the laboratory   some beauties divided in <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>10</mn></mfrac></math></formula><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Centigrade. The fittings generally are very simple; he has a great many big cylinders of glass &amp; all sorts of zinc covers &amp; boxes for various things—&amp; splendid lots of cork, also silvered wire for fastening things under water, tho’ brass does as well I should think.</p>
<p>My love to everybody | Yr affec son | Frank Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 I have got … <hi rend="italic">M. Farnesiana</hi> 3.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.13 I … observations— 6.14] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>6.15 at least … Centigrade. 6.16] <hi rend="italic">cross in left margin, pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11570.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 26 June [1878]</ref>. In 1878, the Saturday before 26 June was 22 June.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Francis was investigating whether there was chlorophyll in the cotyledons of canary grass (<hi rend="italic">Phalaris canariensis</hi>) and oats (<hi rend="italic">Avena sativa</hi>). Thin sections examined under a microscope could provide a view of individual cells containing chlorophyll. The spectroscope (invented in the late 1850s by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2711.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Robert Kirchhoff</ref> and Robert Wilhelm Eberhard Bunsen) provided a means of calculating the absorption spectra of a chemical element or compound. In 1871, Kliment Arkadievich Timiryazev had published the first spectral analysis of chlorophyll (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10635.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Timiryazev 1871</ref>), in which he had shown that absorption was restricted to blue and red wavelengths; his analysis could therefore be used to detect the presence of chlorophyll in cells. For contemporary views of what constituted the cotyledon of grasses, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11219.xml">letter from George Henslow, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 20 February 1878]</ref> and n. 3; for CD’s own usage, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 62. Francis was working in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs’s</ref> laboratory in Würzburg, Germany, over the summer (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11540.xml">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 2 June 1878</ref> and n. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had asked Francis to read <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8188.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Theophil Ciesielski’s</ref> observations on the movement of radicles (embryonic roots) when in contact with water (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1871</ref>, p. 33;  see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10454.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1872</ref>, p. 25). See letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11538.xml">[13–26 May 1878]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11559.xml">18 June [1878])</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his paper ‘Ablenkung der Wurzel von ihrer normalen Wachsthumsrichtung durch feuchte Körper’ (Deflection of the root from its normal direction of growth by moisture; Sachs 1872, p. 219), Sachs observed that radicles turned towards water whereas Ciesielski’s experiments showed that roots laid on a horizontal wet surface grew upwards away from the moisture. In ‘Ueber das Wachsthum der Haupt- und Nebenwurzeln’ (On the growth of primary and adventitious roots), Sachs dismissed Ciesielski’s results, claiming they were due to Ciesielski’s having allowed the roots in his experiments to dry out partially during preparation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sachs 1873–4</ref>, p. 401). CD had reported that his experiments on radicles were inconclusive (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11559.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 18 June [1878]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Falsch</hi>: wrong (German). <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1871</ref>, pp. 29–30; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10454.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ciesielski 1872</ref>, pp. 21–2. The <hi rend="italic">punctum vegetationis</hi> is the growing point.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had asked Francis to check sleeping plants in the botanic garden greenhouses at night (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11559.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 18 June [1878]</ref>). Francis later identified the species as <hi rend="italic">Porliera hygrometrica</hi> (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-11575.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, [29 June] 1878</ref>). In taxonomic literature, <hi rend="italic">Porliera</hi> is considered an incorrect subsequent spelling of <hi rend="italic">Porlieria</hi>; the name <hi rend="italic">Porlieria hygrometrica</hi> is unresolved, but is likely to be an error for <hi rend="italic">P. hygrometra</hi>; the name was sometimes applied to specimens later identified as <hi rend="italic">P. chilensis</hi> (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10636.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johnston 1938</ref>, pp. 253–4). <hi rend="italic">Mimosa farnesiana</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Vachellia farnesiana</hi> (sweet acacia).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had begun studying bloom (the waxy or powdery coating on leaves and fruit) in August 1873 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9007.xml">letter to J. D. Hooker, 13 August 1873</ref>). He had resumed investigating the function of bloom on leaves in 1877 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10960.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 14 May 1877</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Hydrocharis</hi> is a genus of aquatic plants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">A mercury micrometer is used to measure very small changes in pressure; a micron is one millionth part of a metre.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Cabbage caterpillars: either caterpillars of the small cabbage white butterfly, <hi rend="italic">Pieris rapae</hi>, which are green, or those of the cabbage moth, <hi rend="italic">Mamestra brassicae</hi>, which vary from green to brown or blackish.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4896.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sydney Howard Vines</ref> had investigated the influence of light on unicellular organisms while working in Sachs’s laboratory; he described the ‘micro-telescope’ he used in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10451.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vines 1878</ref>, p. 135. The instrument had been made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8235.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. A. Steinheil Söhne</ref> of Munich.</note>    
        </div> 
        
     
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>