<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-630">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To H. E. Strickland   31 May [1842]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8269</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-630 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-630.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-630.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Museum of Zoology Archives, University of Cambridge (Strickland Papers)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_79.xml">Cambridge UMZ</repository>
                    <collection>Strickland Papers</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Maer</placeName>
                <date when="1842-05-31">31 May [1842]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4592.xml">Strickland, H. E.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on HES’s Report ["Report of a committee … (on) nomenclature of zoology", <hi rend="italic">Rep. BAAS</hi> 12 (1842): 105–21]. Suggests limit be put to changing names that are only partially erroneous to prevent those who detect the error from coining new names and attaching their own. HES’s rule for "authority for a species" is difficult, though on the whole best. Suggests stating it boldly to prevent appropriation of species names by "tacker[s] of two old names together".</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Rep. BAAS</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Strickland, H. E. 1842</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>May 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Strickland</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much obliged for the Report,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> which I have reread with interest &amp; entire approval: I think it must do good &amp; I am sure it would do great good, if followed.—</p>
<p>At p. 8, it occurs to me, to ask you whether you know of any name “glaringly false”, except geographical names, which when wholly &amp; not merely partially wrong, I fully agree should be changed.— if you know any other cases, had you not better give an example?— if not, had not the limit of change be allowed exclusively to false geographical names?—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> An animal if called “alpinus” &amp; afterwards found to inhabit a low as well as alpine country, ought not, I presume, to have its name changed.— an animal called “albus” &amp; afterwards found to be white only in the female or young state ought not, I presume, to have its name changed.— All authors, if left quite to themselves without <hi rend="underline">rule</hi> or <hi rend="underline">examples,</hi> (as in above cases) will think errors of their <hi rend="underline">own discovery</hi>“glaring” ones, &amp; will think themselves justified in changing the name, coining another &amp; attaching their own name (ex. grat. Swainson or G. R. Gray)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> after it.— I hope you will take this into consideration, &amp; I feel sure, whatever you resolve, after all the attention you have paid to the subject, will have every chance of being right.—</p>
<p>I have been thinking over the rule, respecting the “authority for a species”, (p. 15.)—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> the case does appear most difficult.— I think the plan you suggest, on the whole the best, though no doubt occasionally involving a search for the authority, who couples the terms—but it sends the enquirer <hi rend="underline">direct</hi> to the original description, habitat &amp;c of the species, &amp; this I apprehend is what the enquirer generally wants.— Would it not be advisable to give some such reasons for attaching (Lin) to Tyrannus crinitus; showing that thus an enquirer at once know where to search for original specific description habitat &amp;c &amp;c &amp; secondly that genera being fewer in number than species are always more easily found in systematic works, &amp; therefore that the omission of (Viell) is not very important even in abridged ones, as in Cuvier Règne Animale. I would, also, urge on you to put the rule <hi rend="underline">boldly</hi> that the tacker of two old names together should not attach his name, as the authority; at present it is only left to be inferred that Sw. ought not to follow <hi rend="underline">T. </hi> <hi rend="underline">crinitus.</hi> — Do think of this, I am sure, those confounded authorities are the cause of much confusion in Zoolog. Nomenclature. Excuse this letter written in haste. I daresay it suggests nothing, but what you have already thought of.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>With my sincere wishes, that you may be recompensed for all the trouble you have taken, in hereafter seeing much good result from your labours.</p>
<p>believe me | Very truly yours | C. Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> Maer Hall | Newcastle under Lime</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 do great] ‘d’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘g’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.4 allowed] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘given’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.5 names] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.8 state] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.9 authors] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">over del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.9 (as … cases) 2.10] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.3 authority] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘person’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.6 such] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.8 habitat &amp;c &amp;c] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.9 than species] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">3.9 &amp; therefore … important 3.10] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The corrected draft of Strickland <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1842 was circulated among naturalists for criticism before the final committee recommendation was presented to the British Association. For CD’s comments on the initial draft see his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-619.xml">letter to Strickland, 17 February 1842</ref>, n. 2. The report had been corrected in committee meetings at the Zoological Society on 28 April and at <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Yarrell’s</ref> house on 5 May. CD was present only at the first meeting.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD made comments on this corrected draft: <quote> A. Would it not be advisable to <hi rend="doubleUnderline">state</hi> [‘th’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] <hi rend="doubleUnderline">distinctly</hi>, that the author who tacks the specific name given by one naturalist to the generic name of another, has no <hi rend="doubleUnderline">right whatever</hi> to append his name to [‘the’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] his [<hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘this’] new binomial compound?— Should not a rule be given for the cases, where an author discovers a generic term has been previously used, or that a specific is grossly-geographically false, &amp; gives another name, but does not alter the generic or specific description [<hi rend="italic">above del </hi>‘names’], whose name should be given? [<hi rend="italic">over</hi>‘—’] I trust in Providence it is not requisite that the error-finder should have the same priviledge as the discoverer—or will it be right punishment for *the discoverer [<hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘him’] to lose his right of Christening if he gives a [<hi rend="italic">added</hi>] wrong name? C.D. (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref> Museum of Zoology, Strickland collection, nomenclature papers I, p. 13v.).</quote> See also n. 5, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4632.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Swainson</ref>; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1958.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Robert Gray</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Strickland had raised the awkward case of citing an authority for <hi rend="italic">Tyrannus crinitus</hi>, first described by Linnaeus as <hi rend="italic">Muscicapa crinita</hi>, then assigned to Tyrannus by the French ornithologist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4886.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Jean Pierre Vieillot</ref>, and finally designated as <hi rend="italic">T. crinitus </hi> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4632.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Swainson</ref>. The report concluded that ‘Lin.’ should be cited as the authority in order to indicate the original species description. <hi rend="italic">Tyrannus crinitus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Muscicapa crinita</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Myiarchus crinitus</hi>, the great crested flycatcher.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Section ‘<hi rend="italic">h</hi>’ of the report, headed ‘<hi rend="italic">Generic names derived from </hi> <hi rend="italic">persons</hi>’, reads: ‘Words of this class have been very extensively used in botany, and therefore it would have been well to have excluded them wholly from zoology …’ CD has placed an ‘X’ before ‘and therefore …’ and noted ‘L. Jenyns objects to this clause’. (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref> Museum of Zoology, Strickland collection, nomenclature papers I, p. 10).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>