<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10936">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Otto Zacharias<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   21 April 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11151</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10936 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10936.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10936.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp † (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 184: 6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>184: 6</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5291.xml">Zacharias, Otto</persName>
                <placeName>Geestemünde</placeName>
                <date when="1877-04-21">21 Apr 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends abnormal pig’s foot. Does abnormality occur often?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pig</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Geestemünde</hi>,</placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="print">den</hi> 21. April <hi rend="print">187</hi>7</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In einem beifolgenden Paquet erlaube ich mir, Ihnen die Vorderpfote eines Schweins zuzusenden, an welcher der Daumen in wunderbarer Weise ausgebildet ist. Die andere Pfote habe ich hier behalten, um sie photographiren zu lassen. Sie würden mir einen grossen Dienst erweisen, wenn Sie die Güte hätten und mir mittheilten, ob Ihnen eine derartige (oder aehnliche) Monstrosität schon öfter vorgekommen ist, oder ob der Grad der Daumenausbildung an dieser Pfote ein abnorm grosser ist.</p>
<p>Alle Schweineschlächter, die ich hier gefragt habe, erinnern sich nicht schon jemals eine gleich prononcirte Daumenausbildung gesehen zu haben. Als ich diese Pfoten sah, dachte ich gleich daran, dass es für Sie von Interesse sein müsste, wenn Sie autoptisch davon Kenntniss nehmen. Desshalb habe ich mir erlaubt eine davon Ihnen zu schicken.</p>
<p>Ich ersuche Sie freundlichst, hochgeehrter Herr, mir meine obige Frage gelegentlich beantworten zu wollen, denn begreiflicherweise interessirt es mich sehr, was Sie zu der Monstrosität sagen.</p>
<p>Ich werde dann auch im “Kosmos” eine Notiz darüber bringen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Hochachtungsvoll | Otto Zacharias</p>
<p>P Scr. Das Paquet wird heute Abend (via Hamburg) an Ihre werthe Adresse versandt.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">              
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Answered’<ref target="#foot.f3"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil, circled pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Geestemünde</hi>,</placeName>
                    <date>21. April <hi rend="print">187</hi>7</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In an attached parcel, I take the liberty of sending you the forefoot of a pig, the thumb of which has developed in an astonishing way. The other foot I kept here to have photographed. You would do me a great service if you would be so kind as to let me know whether you have come across the same (or similar) monstrosity often before, or whether the degree of thumb development in this forefoot is a greater abnormality.</p>
<p>All the pig butchers that I questioned here cannot recall ever having seen an equally pronounced thumb development. When I saw these forefeet, I immediately thought that it must be of interest to you to inspect them personally. Therefore I took the liberty of sending one of them to you.</p>
<p>I kindly request, highly esteemed Sir, an answer to the above question at your convenience, for understandably I am very interested in what you have to say about this monstrosity.</p>
<p>I would then also publish a note on this in “Kosmos”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Most respectfully | Otto Zacharias</p>
<p>P.S. The parcel will be sent tonight (via Hamburg) to your honoured address.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">No article on the pig’s foot appeared in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>. CD had briefly discussed abnormalities in the feet of pigs in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Otto Zacharias, 26 April 1877</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>