<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13003">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. E. Litchfield to Leslie Stephen   10 January 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3018</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13003 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13003.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13003.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">15pp &amp; ACC 8pp inc</note>
            <relatedItem type="draft" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 147: 553, DAR 143: 445, DAR 92: B84–7</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Barlow (1958): 212</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The New York Public Library. Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations. The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature (MSS Stephen)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_304.xml">NYPL Berg</repository>
                    <collection>MSS Stephen</collection>
                    </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml">Litchfield, H. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1881-01-10">10 Jan 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4545.xml" resp="high">Stephen, Leslie</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>The Darwin family cannot agree on what CD should do about Butler’s charges [in <hi rend="italic">Unconscious memory</hi>]. CD has commissioned HEL to ask LS’s advice. She sends an account of the affair with background materials.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Unconscious memory</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1202">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2357">Litchfield, H. E.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Butler, Samuel (b) 1880</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative self-criticism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-08-13" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-07" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-12-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Jan 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1881</date>
                    <salute>Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stephen,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>We have been having a great family talk &amp; at last have come to such a hopeless division of opinion that my Father has commissioned me to write &amp; ask you whether you would be so very kind as to consider the following question &amp; give him your judgement as to what he had better do. He hopes you will not mind the trouble, &amp; that the consideration of the points involved will not take much time— but he will be really grateful for the opinion of an outsider &amp; of someone in whose opinion he will have so much confidence as in yours.</p>
                    <p>The question is as to the advisability or necessity of his meeting in any way Butler’s allegation that he has made a false statement in his preface to the Life of Eras. Darwin, which he—Butler—considers does him a great injury.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>We are sending you Butler’s Op. 5 with the pages marked which bear upon the question,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> namely 60– to 79, &amp; also Erasmus Darwin’s life in order that you may see the preface.</p>
                    <p>The only point which some of us think my Father should meet is, the alleged implication in the preface that Krause’s original article in Kosmos was not altered or added to before translation.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> All the accusations as to Krause’s having taken passages from Op 4 without acknowledgement do not concern my Father &amp; we none of us wish that he should enter into any sort of controversy with Butler.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Two or three of my brothers much wish that a fly leaf should be inserted in the unsold copies of the Life of Eras. Darwin stating as an erratum on p. 1, ten lines from the top, that Krause’s article in Kosmos was altered &amp; enlarged before it was sent to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dallas for translation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>My husband &amp; I, on the other hand, are very strong that nothing whatever should be done. My brother Leonard will be the Devil’s Advocate &amp; will send you what he has to say &amp; I will state our views.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>We maintain:</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. that Butler has put himself out of court by the grossness of his attack on my Father. If a man clearly implies that he considers another to be a liar, he cannot expect his complaints to be listened to &amp; met by statements, which are only worth making on the assumption that his opponent is a person of credit.</p>
                    <p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.: That supposing he has any cause of complaint, which we do not grant, my Father’s letter to him of Jan 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. 1880, in which he states that there has been a blunder &amp; that if there should be a second edition this shall be altered, removes all reasonable ground of complaint: Butler has himself made this letter public not only in Op. 5 but also in the Athenæum &amp; in the St James Gazette, so that any one who reads his books will see that this imaginary injury was not intentional.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> If, in last January, it had occurred to my Father to offer to insert a fly leaf with this correction, we should have had no objection, but we do strongly object to any action being taken in consequence of Butler’s last book. We think it is a confession that he has done someone a wrong and this is not the fact. Also his doing anything will open the way to fresh insults.</p>
<p>3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>: We maintain that no injury has been done to Butler— Supposing any careful &amp; unprejudiced reader had read Butler’s Op. 4 &amp; afterwards read the Life of Eras. D. he would see when he came to the last sentence of the book that it applied to Butler, &amp; he would, if he turned to the preface, be puzzled by finding that it was implied that this was the mere translation of Kosmos unaltered, but a very little reflection would, let him see that in the interval which elapsed between Feb &amp; Nov it was likely that Krause had added to &amp; revised his original article—&amp; had in the meantime read Op 4.</p>
<p>It is hardly necessary to remark that it is impossible to discover what advantage it would be to my Father to attack Butler by a spirit of prophecy.</p>
<p>It would I suppose be an infinitesimal disadvantage to Butler to have it supposed that some anonymous person existed, who had already, before Feb 79, given forth similar views to Butlers—but he has never put that forward as his ground of complaint, &amp;, on the contrary, has said that it was clear the sentence was intended for him.</p>
<p>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: The plea for now correcting the statement in the preface is, that its words now mislead as to a matter of fact. But we contend that it is a case where literal accuracy will now give a false impression of what has occurred. The worst that the preface can now do is to cause a misapprehension in a minute point of no consequence to anyone; but the act of meeting Butler’s attack in any way <hi rend="underline">now</hi> will be read, &amp; naturally, as a confession by my father that he has done a wrong; and this is not the fact. We think the whole thing utterly unimportant &amp; that the outside world will think so too. And finally we tell my Father that the good sensible rule is, ‘when you doubt let it alone.’ This he is upon the whole inclined to do. He still holds that the preface is not materially inaccurate—the note as to Butler’s book being wholly detached from the sentence as to Krause, &amp; appended to the list of Authors on page 2—&amp; though he would, if he had thought of it, have put in the fly leaf erratum twelve months ago, he leans to our view that he had best now let the matter alone or at any rate is quite doubtful on the matter.</p>
<p>I hope you will not think us all gone mad on such a small matter.</p>
<p>My Father sends his best remembrances &amp; apologies for thus troubling you. He desires me to say he only asks for your verdict &amp; not for any reasons why you give it.</p>
<p>I am, | yours sincerely | H. E. Litchfield</p>
                    <p>P.S. I may as well add that Krause has written a statement which he is going to send to the Popular Science Review* giving his observations as to Butlers attack upon himself &amp; upon my Father. In this statement he explains as to the inadvertent omission in the preface—</p>
                    <p>*or Nature more probably<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD had asked Henrietta and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2952.xml">Richard Buckley Litchfield</ref> whether he should respond to accusations made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Samuel Butler</ref> in <hi rend="italic">Unconscious memory</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11180.xml">Butler 1880</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12978.xml">letter to H. E. Litchfield, 4 January 1881</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12979.xml">letter from R. B. and H. E. Litchfield, 5 January [1881]</ref>). In the preface to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. iv, CD had stated that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Ernst Krause</ref>’s essay, which comprised the second part of the book, was completed before the publication of Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Evolution, old and new</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml">Butler 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">‘Op. 5’ was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11180.xml">Butler 1880</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Krause’s original essay (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879</ref>) was substantially modified before it was translated into English for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">On Butler’s specific accusations against Krause, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12969.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 2 January 1881</ref> and n. 3. ‘Op. 4’ was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml">Butler 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> had translated Krause 1879 for <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>. On the proposed errata sheet, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13004.xml">letter from Leonard Darwin to Leslie Stephen, [10 January 1881]</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13004.xml">letter from Leonard Darwin to Leslie Stephen, [10 January 1881]</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12396.xml">letter to Samuel Butler, 3 January 1880</ref>. CD’s letter was quoted in full in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11180.xml">Butler 1880</ref>, pp. 72–3; extracts also appeared in Butler’s letters in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 31 January 1880 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12445.xml">letter to H. E. Litchfield, 1 February [1880]</ref>, enclosure 1), and the <hi rend="italic">St James’s Gazette</hi>, 8 December 1880, p. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Krause had suggested publishing his response to Butler in <hi rend="italic">Popular Science Review</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12969.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 2 January 1881</ref>); however, it was eventually published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 27 January 1881, p. 288.</note>
        </div>   
    
       
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>