<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-179">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Catherine Darwin   25 July [– 3 August] 1832</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5015</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-179 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-179.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-179.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">AU 3 〈1832〉</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 85</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 85</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1212.xml">Darwin, E. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Shrewsbury</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1832-07-25" notAfter="1832-08-03">25 July [– 3 Aug] 1832 </date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Tells of the family’s pleasure in reading CD’s first two letters and his journal.</p>
            <p>Comments on Shrewsbury politics, the cholera, and the family. Sedgwick calls often; Catherine thinks he is interested in Susan.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Beagle</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1202">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shrewsbury</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">politics</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Shrewsbury.</placeName>
                    <date>July 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1832.</date>
                    <salute>My dearest Charles</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of June we were delighted to receive your letter from Rio dated 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of April, and on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of July (this month) we received your second letter and Journal dated 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of April, with the interesting account of your expedition into the Brazils. I cannot tell you how interesting and entertaining we find your letters and Journal, and what great joy it gives all the house when we have such happy accounts of you in every way. I run to tell Nancy and some of the other Servants, and the pleasure is universal over the house, as everybody loves you, and thinks of you, my dearest Charles. It is so delightful too to find how wonderfully your Voyage answers, and how excessively you have enjoyed yourself. I do not think any pleasure can be more vivid than your’s must have been. I had no idea before I read your Journal of the extraordinary beauty of the Tropics. If you wish to have <hi rend="underline">my</hi> Criticisms, I must say I think your descriptions most excellent, and gave me most lively pleasure in reading them. I was so interested I could not bear to stop reading it, till I came to the end, which was the case also with Marianne and Caroline, who both admired and liked it exceedingly. Your Journal &amp; Letters were sent on to Marianne, Caroline and myself, at the Sea, where we have been the last three weeks. Susan read the Journal aloud to Papa, who was interested, and liked it very much. They want to see it at Maer, but we do not know whether you would choose that, and must wait till we hear from you, whether we may or not. It shall be kept most carefully for you.— The same Packet contained a note from Capt Beaufort, which I dare say you will be curious about, so I will copy it out. “Capt Beaufort presents his Compliments to Miss Darwin, with the enclosed letter, and perhaps she will pardon the liberty he takes in adding that Capt Fitzroy omits no opportunity of expressing the unqualified satisfaction he feels in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin’s society—and in his last dispatch he says ”D. is equally liked and respected by every person in the Ship“. Admiralty. June 29.”—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Susan wrote to thank Capt Beaufort for his politeness.—</p>
<p>This is the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> letter going to Monte Video, April, May, June, July &amp; August. It is a pity that April was not directed to Rio, but we were obliged to follow your original directions.— We were rather puzzled by your writing by a slip of the pen, I suppose that the Beagle was to sail back to St Salvador on the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of <hi rend="underline">March</hi>, but you must have meant to write <hi rend="underline">May</hi>. It is a very nice scheme your remaining stationary at Botofogo Bay. I can conceive no thing more extraordinary and interesting than to be quietly living in a Brazilian Cottage,— but do not let the Cottage put the Parsonage out of your head, a far better thing, and which we were rejoiced to hear continued to be a vista to your prospects. I hope you will in all probability find Fanny Wedgwood <hi rend="underline">disengaged</hi> and <hi rend="doubleUnderline">sobered</hi> into an excellent Clergman’s Wife by the time you return, a nice little invaluable Wife she would be;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I will not quite promise though that you will find her disengaged, as another Clergman, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Paget Moseley, Brother to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Frank Wedgwood, is said to be paying her very sedulous attention; but he is such a vulgar, fat, horrid man, I do not think it is possible she will have him. I must tell you a little scene that took place between them. They were admiring some Flowers in the Greenhouse, when M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Moseley declared he could show some far prettier flowers, and out of his pocket produced a scrap of paper, on which Fanny had scrawled some little flowers some weeks before. Emma was by, and was near choking with laughing at the man’s odd manner, and Fanny’s amazemen〈t.〉</p>
<p>Professor Sedgwicke has been so continually calling here of late at all the most unexpected times, tha〈t〉 I think the next piece of news you will hear, will be that Susan has turned into M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Sedgwicke.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The last time he called, he was on his road to Cader Idris.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> When we were at the Sea (at Rhyl, in Flintshire, not far from Abergelley, an ugly place) we made the usual little Tour to Bangor and Conway, and also to your old Acquaintance, the Orme’s Head, which Caroline is so delighted with, she quite longs to build a house there.— The Rhyl is a very ugly Sea Coast, and I found it quite a <hi rend="underline">Plas</hi> <hi rend="underline">Edwardes</hi> <ref target="#foot.f5"/> and got heartily sick of it.— We have been reading a Review of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Earle’s Voyages in the South Seas,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lytton Bulwer’s Monthly Review;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> his book is much praised, and I think must be very entertaining.— I am very curious to know how often you get Newspapers, and how much of the Public news you know. The Papers will hardly tell you how much the Cholera has broken out again in London, and spread all over the Country; it is so strange its appearing this second time so much more among the higher classes. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Smith (Lord Forrester’s Sister’s) death was the most frightfully sudden thing; she was at the Opera on Saturday Night, was perfectly well till Luncheon time on Sunday, when she was suddenly seized, and was dead by 12 at night. She suffered agonies; every Physician in London was sent for, but they wasted 2 hours in disputing before they could do any thing.— We are free from it yet in Shrewsbury.— The County Members are canvassing about all Shropshire, for the Reformed Parliament. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pelham and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Whitmore are undisputed for the South of Shropshire, and Sir Rowland Hill, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gore and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Coates for the North of Shropshire, which will be a disputed election. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Coates is the only Whig among them, and he is a very poor one. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Biddulph is to stand a Contested Election for Denbighshire with Lord Kenyon’s Son, which is a very foolish thing, as he is almost certain to lose.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Poor Fanny will not have a very pleasant or easy life I am afraid; the old Mother, M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Biddulph is so odious to her, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Biddulph is such an exacting Husband.— It is too bad of Erasmus not writing to you, he is such an idle creature, and he is so engrossed with Paganini I suppose.— I long to hear from you again, my dearest Charles. You cannot think how it rejoices my heart, when we get a letter from you.</p>
<p>God bless you always &amp; believe me, with every body’s Love, y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> most affect<hi rend="superscript">te</hi>| E. Catherine Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The original letter is in DAR 223.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5013.xml">Frances (Fanny) Wedgwood</ref> ‘died on August 20th, 1832, aged twenty-six, after a few days’ illness from some inflammatory attack’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2338.xml"><hi rend="italic">Emma Darwin</hi></ref> 1: 250).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Although <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml">Henrietta Litchfield</ref> reports (in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2338.xml"><hi rend="italic">Emma Darwin</hi> (1915)</ref> 1: 141 n.) that CD once told her that ‘anything in coat and trousers from eight years to eighty was fair game to Susan’, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1239.xml">Susan</ref> was the only sister who never married.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">A mountain near Barmouth.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Town in North Wales. The ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, Appendix I) records that CD spent three weeks at Plas Edwards in 1819.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1442.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Augustus Earle</ref>, the draughtsman of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>, had lived in New Zealand and travelled in the Pacific in 1827. The work referred to was published in 1832 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2239.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Earle 1832</ref>). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-289.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Caroline Darwin, 27 December 1835</ref> for the reaction of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> and CD to its account of missionary work.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_721.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward George Earle Lytton Bulwer-Lytton</ref> edited the <hi rend="italic">New Monthly</hi>, 1831–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3733.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Cressett Pelham</ref> was a Conservative candidate for Shrewsbury and was defeated; for South Shropshire, the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4860.xml">Earl of Darlington</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_970.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Henry Clive</ref>, both Conservatives, were elected, defeating <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5109.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Whitmore</ref>, also a Conservative; for North Shropshire, Sir <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2297.xml">Rowland Hill</ref> (Conservative) and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Cotes</ref> (Liberal) defeated <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3597.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Ormsby-Gore</ref> (Conservative) (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2074.xml">Hanham 1972</ref>, pp. 283, 275). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_440.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Myddelton Biddulph</ref> stood as a Whig, for reform, and narrowly defeated <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2671.xml">Lloyd Kenyon</ref> (1805–69).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>