<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11378">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Torbitt   26 February 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13714</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11378 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11378.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11378.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 148: 96</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>148: 96</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-02-26">26 Feb 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4777.xml">Torbitt, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Comments on letter on potato experiments JT intends to publish. Will talk with T. H. Farrer concerning JT’s work. Could he undertake work if aided by moderate grant or subscription?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">potato</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1599">Farrer, T. H.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down,</placeName>
                    <date>Feb. 26, 1878.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental"><hi rend="italic">Private</hi></seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Your letter seems a very good one, and you are perfectly at liberty to have it published in any form you may think fit.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>I know little of public affairs, but fear that our governing men are so ignorant of science and so immersed in political squabbles that they will do nothing. It would be a great misfortune if your seeds are wasted. I would suggest your sending a copy of your letter to T. H. Farrer, Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>., Board of Trade, Whitehall, London. He is the head of office, and a friend of mine and scientific. I am going to London to-morrow for change and rest, as I am very poorly (and this must excuse this ill-expressed and ill-written note) and will see Mr. Farrer and talk to him on the subject. Mr. Farrer is brother-in-law of Chancellor of the Exchequer. I fear that there will be great difficulties.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Could you undertake the continuation of the experiments, if aided by a moderate grant of money or a subscription from a few friends of the cause? They are so overworked at the R. Gardens at Kew I do not think the work could there be undertaken.</p>
                    <p>Send a copy to Sir J. Hooker,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> K.C.S.I., Kew Gardens: mark with red or blue passages quoted from me, as this will call his attention to them.</p>
                    <p>If even a moderate stock of a sound variety was once raised I should think a great salesman like the Messrs. Carter would cultivate and dispose of them; and thus they would be best distributed.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> You will understand that I know nothing of your circumstances and one of Mr. Farrer’s first questions probably will be “Does Mr. Torbitt require to be repaid for expences already incurred? or, has he worked solely for patriotic purposes?” Will you kindly answer immediately my several questions:—addressing your letter to me, as on enclosed slip.</p>
<p>Yours very faithfully | Ch. Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
               
            </div>

        </div>
     
     
     <div type="footnotes">
         <note xml:id="foot.f1">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11373.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to CD of 24 February 1878</ref>, Torbitt had enclosed a printed copy of his letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stafford Northcote</ref>, chancellor of the Exchequer, of 23 February 1878. The letter to Northcote contained extracts from CD’s letters to Torbitt; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11373.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Torbitt, 24 February 1878</ref> and n. 6.</note>
         <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref> was permanent secretary of the Board of Trade and had corresponded with CD and published on botanical topics. CD was in London from 27 February to 5 March 1878 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)). Northcote’s wife, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7981.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cecilia Frances Northcote</ref>, was Farrer’s sister.</note>
         <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
         <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2528.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Carter &amp; Company</ref> was a London firm of seedsmen.</note>  
     </div>   
       
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>