<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4232F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Asa Gray to J. D. Hooker<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   6 July 1863</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21114</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4232F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4232F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4232F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 11: 521–3</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Asa Gray correspondence: 328–9)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Asa Gray correspondence: 328–9</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
                <placeName>Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>
                <date when="1863-07-06">6 July 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Includes comments about George Bentham’s anniversary address to the Linnean Society with particular notice of the favourable attention to Darwin, except for Natural Selection, and to AG’s essay in the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>.</p> 
            <p>He defends [W. B.] Carpenter and [Jeffries] Wyman against [Richard] Owen.</p>
            <p>Gossip about scientific honours and other matters.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_839">Carpenter, W. B.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_5268">Wyman, Jeffries</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Bentham, George 1863</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Linnean Society</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">scientific honours</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>
                    <date>July 6, 1863.</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Hooker</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you for a nice letter of June 12, and later, for the draft on your bankers for £72.12 for Parry.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The latter send profound thanks, and is quite set up by his venture on seeds. He ought to be (and is) very thankful to you.</p>
<p>A note from Bentham<ref target="#foot.f3"/> came in your envelope. Let me answer one of his enquiries to you—who will let him know my answer: for I infer that this will not reach him at Kew until after his holiday, so I address to you</p>
<p>He asks whether the Major John Le Conte, Deceased, of Philadelphia, is the Entomologist and F.L.S.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Yes, doubtless, if a Fellow of long standing. His son John L. Le Conte is the more distinguished entomologist:<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but he could have been chosen only a few years ago,—and I suppose you do not now elect Fellows in foreign parts. Whereas the old Major Le Conte was probably chosen about the same time with his contemporary D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bigelow.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Now I am to discourse, partly for Bentham, partly for you, anent Bentham’s Anniversary address.<ref target="#foot.f7"/>—which I like greatly, and yet have some flaws to pick at.— Here—far away from the great centres of scientific activity, we “are nothing if not critical”.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>He rightly blames Huxley for his use of the term <hi rend="underline">Biology</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I take the word to be essentially equivalent to Physiology and a better term. It certainly is not = Nat. History.</p>
<p>Darwin may well be pleased and satisfied at having made such an impression on Bentham. The latter’s conclusion as to “the tide of opinion,” on p. 13, I am pleased to see—;<ref target="#foot.f10"/> both because it is <hi rend="underline">evidently true</hi>, and because I had lately in Amer. Journal. been saying the same.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Natural Selection he does not quite appreciate, I think; but few do.</p>
<p>The caution, in p. 10, is well enough. But few, I imagine, fit to handle such questions, ever take an <hi rend="underline">illustration</hi> for an argument, at least for a proof.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> A comparison is sometimes a capital argument for its purpose.— An analogous case may perfectly rebut an objection, tho’ it establishes nothing for itself.</p>
<p>As to my Essay in Atlantic—which has been made so much of—Bentham seems to misapprend a little its object and the occasion.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> It was not to “remove the prejudices excited by religious views” or to deprecate attack on Darwin in this regard, but to rebut and turn aside attacks which had been made on this ground, and partly by scientific men. To show the futility and unreasonableness of such attacks was only to remand the discussion to its proper court. “His opponents reply that his Natural Theology is not Religion” Bree, I suppose.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> But the same line of argument holds as well. It is easy to show that the very same principles have been admitted in respect to astronomy &amp; geology, and so may just as well be in Natural history.— But all this is of no account. But as a review of Darwin’s Theory on scientific grounds, why did not B. mention my much earlier review, in Silliman’s Journal,—perhaps the better of the two, and addressed to scientific men instead of <hi rend="underline">ad populum</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>I am pleased to see him pitch into Owen for ill-treating Carpenter.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> But, in the <hi rend="underline">Heterogeny</hi> question, the prejudice (in which I share) against spontaneous generation, and too great deference to French Academy, has made him unjust to Wyman,—who is one of the most conscientious and accurate of observers.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> Wyman will now probably publish the results of a lot of experiments, which he did not think were worth while.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> As respects the heat employed to destroy germs, Wyman’s experiments are better than Pasteur’s. The latter subjected them to <hi rend="underline">dry heat</hi> only, and to say 230<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Fahr. But Wyman in the experiments under pressure, <hi rend="underline">boiled</hi> at 250<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> <hi rend="superscript">o</hi> and 307<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> <hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Fahr.. You know how great the difference between the two modes.</p>
<p>I enclose you a brief mem. by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wyman.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> By the way, when you want a new Foreign Member of Linn. Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. you should think of Wyman.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> He is pure gold.</p>
<p>As to canvassing for scientific honors—for which you blame A.DC,<ref target="#foot.f21"/> one may be led into it, and I suspect it is not uncommon on the Continent. Last summer Ruprecht,—whom I know little of, wrote to ask me to furnish him with what I could to enable him to put me in nomination for a vacancy in Acad. Petro<hi rend="italic">[</hi>ff<hi rend="italic">]</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f22"/> I declined to have anything to do or say in the matter, telling him to refer to any botanists he chose. Where upon I supposed the matter was dropped. But, last week, the diploma came to me.</p>
<p>I should have thought that they would have preferred Bentham or yourself. By the way, now that I am writing of myself I have, against my will been put into the chair of Amer. Acad. on the retirement of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bigelow. I could have succeeded in avoiding it had it not been that Agassiz and his small clique set to work with all their might against me,— —the result was a demonstration that made A open his eyes, and has, I hear, mortified him exceedingly.<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p>
<p>Bond is at home again, much pleased with his trip.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> He says that the greatest thing to see, and the most satisfactory, on the other side of the water, is Kew Gardens &amp; museum. We were pleased to see one who had lately seen you all, and brought such pleasant accounts of you and Mrs. Hooker, I should suppose that Mrs. Hooker is as well as possible.<ref target="#foot.f25"/></p>
<p>The sudden death of an aged and very dear Great Aunt of Mrs. Gray’s took us to Connecticut last week, where we remained some while.<ref target="#foot.f26"/> The good soul has bequeathed to my wife property which would amount in ordinary times to about £2000:—a great help to us. I now see my way clearer than ever to shaking off other things before long and taking myself to <hi rend="underline">Fl. N. Amer.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f27"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Flora Australiensis</hi> is a nice vol.<ref target="#foot.f28"/> <hi rend="underline">Mesembryanthemum</hi> was truly collected in California by Fremont<ref target="#foot.f29"/> and by others—I think also by Coulter.<ref target="#foot.f30"/>—said to be common on the coast. I always supposed it must have been introduced by the Spaniards.<ref target="#foot.f31"/></p>
<p>I note what you write of Seemann.<ref target="#foot.f32"/> I never liked the fellow, and always had just as little as possible to do with him, while being civil distantly. I looked upon him as a sort of adventurer.— I shall keep very clear of him.</p>
<p>Ovules bearing pollen is a very curious business. But I do not see what use can be made of the case.</p>
<p>I take issue with you square, and say that the radicle <hi rend="underline">is</hi> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> internode. I support the proposition thus— 1. It is in the place of internode, i.e. below the first node; 2. It grows like an internode whenever (as is usual) it lengthens at all. 3. It produces roots like an internode, i.e. all internodes favorably placed, e.g. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. &amp;c—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Hooker enclosed this letter in a letter to CD of late July, which has not been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [21 July 1863]</ref>, and letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 July [1863]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4254.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">26 [July 1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3697.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Christopher Parry</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2846.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Eatton Le Conte</ref> died on 21 November 1860, at Philadelphia, where he had been resident for ten or twelve years (<hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> 2d ser. 31 (1861): 303, 463); his address was given as New York in the <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">List of the Linnean Society of London</hi></ref> 1863. Bentham was president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2847.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lawrence Le Conte</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The American botanist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_445.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jacob Bigelow</ref> was elected a fellow of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> in 1819; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2846.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Eatton Le Conte</ref> was elected a fellow in 1812 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">List of the Linnean Society of London</hi></ref> 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi>, 2.1.122 (Wells and Taylor eds. 1988).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>. In his anniversary address, delivered to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 7 May 1863, Bentham questioned whether the term ‘Biology’ could be retained in the limited sense in which it had been originally proposed, ‘that of the <hi rend="italic">science of life, i. e.</hi> of the phenomena of life, in contradistinction to the description and classification of living beings’, given that it had recently been used in a more general sense to refer to ‘Zoology and Botany in all their branches’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, p. xii). He continued: ‘if Biology continues to be used by Professor Huxley and other distinguished public lecturers in the most general sense, it will be the one which will be definitively attached to it’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Bentham devoted most of his address to a review of the state of the literature on the origin of species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, pp. xii–xxii). In summing up the literature relating to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, he averred that the tide of opinion among ‘philosophical naturalists’ was ‘setting fast in favour of Mr. Darwin’s hypothesis’, and that few who really considered the subject would now deny that new species had been produced from a common ancestor by natural selection (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, pp. xxi–xxii; Gray evidently refers to the pagination of an offprint). For CD’s reaction to Bentham’s address, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4217.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to George Bentham, 19 June [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Gray probably refers to A. Gray 1863d, which was published in the May 1863 number of the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi>, and in which Gray discussed the ‘general drift of opinion’ on the question of the origin of species (A. Gray 1863d, p. 437).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In his address, Bentham argued that there was a ‘general logical confusion’ in most of the reviews of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, arising ‘from that aptness of illustration and figurative language’ in CD’s book, which, Bentham considered, carried CD’s supporters, and even sometimes CD himself, ‘beyond strict logical bounds’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, p. xviii). Among the figurative terms singled out as requiring ‘the greatest caution in their use’ were the phrases ‘Struggle for Life’ and ‘Natural Selection’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Gray refers to his three-part review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, which appeared in 1860 in the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> (A. Gray 1860b), and was reprinted as a pamphlet on CD’s initiative (A. Gray 1861a; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, Appendix 111). Bentham discussed Gray’s ‘remarkable dissertation’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, p. xvii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The reference is apparently to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_874.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bree 1860</ref>. Although <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Robert Bree</ref> did not discuss Gray’s natural theology in his book, he did argue that a developmental natural theology (like that espoused by Gray) was in conflict with revelation, and that a belief in the natural progressive development of species ‘struck at the root of religion itself’ (pp. 244–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><hi rend="italic">Ad populum</hi>: ‘to the people’. A. Gray 1860c was published in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi>, commonly known as ‘Silliman’s Journal’ after its founder, Benjamin Silliman.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Gray refers to Bentham’s criticism, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, pp. xxvi–xxvii, of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen’s</ref> anonymous review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1265.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carpenter 1862</ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 28 March 1863, pp. 417–19 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, Appendix VII).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">In his address (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, pp. xxv–xxvi), Bentham criticised the work of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jeffries Wyman</ref>, Gray’s colleague at Harvard University, who in 1862 began a series of experiments which paralleled those of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Pasteur</ref>, although with different results (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wyman 1862</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>). Bentham suggested that Pasteur’s results (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6204.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pasteur 1861</ref> and 1862) seemed to refute completely ‘the idea of heterogeny in the production of microscopic animals or plants in organic matter in a state of fermentation’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863</ref>, p. xxv). The Académie des Sciences of Paris had awarded Pasteur the Alhumbert prize for his work on spontaneous generation in 1862 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2447.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Farley 1977</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Wyman subsequently published a further paper detailing experiments relating to spontaneous generation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wyman 1867</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">The enclosure has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Wyman was elected a foreign member of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> in 1869; the number of foreign members was restricted to fifty (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">List of the Linnean Society of London</hi></ref> 1870).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alphonse de Candolle</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4123.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Franz Josef Ruprecht</ref> was director of the botanical museum of the Academy of Sciences of St Petersburg.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">On Gray’s election as president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">American Academy of Arts and Sciences</ref> in 1863, and the opposition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, pp. 319–20.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">The reference is probably to Gray’s colleague at Harvard University, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_522.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Phillips Bond</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frances Harriet Hooker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1960.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jane Loring Gray’s</ref> great aunt, ‘one of the country kin in Connecticut’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, p. 332), has not been further identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">In collaboration with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Torrey</ref>, Gray had first begun work on a planned flora of North America in 1833. A portion of the work was published between 1838 and 1843 (Torrey and Gray 1838–43), but it remained unfinished. Although Gray for many years planned to complete the work, he ultimately abandoned it, beginning to publish instead his <hi rend="italic">Synoptical flora of North America</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3057.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1878–84</ref>), which also remained unfinished (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, pp. 385–93).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28">Gray refers to the first volume of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bentham 1863–78</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f29"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1733.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Charles Frémont</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f30"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1092.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Coulter</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f31">In Torrey and Gray 1838–43, 1: 556, the authors stated that two or more species of <hi rend="italic">Mesembryanthemum</hi> were reported to be naturalised in California, and that one of them was suspected to be native.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f32"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4278.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Berthold Carl Seemann</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>