<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9077F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From S. V. Wood Sr to Charles Lyell   30 September 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21580</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9077F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9077F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9077F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The University of Edinburgh Centre for Research Collections (Gen.117/6422-3)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_124.xml">Edinburgh</repository>
                    <collection>(Gen.117/6422-3)</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5228.xml">Wood, S. V., Sr</persName>
                <placeName>Brentwood, Essex</placeName>
                <date when="1873-09-30">30 Sept 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends proofs of pages on shells with revised species names. Discusses Crag Moll, Sutton and Butley Red Grag, and Scrobicularia beds. Son asks him to thank Lyell for extract from Darwin’s book.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Crag</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Leda limatula</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Sutton</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Brentwood, Essex.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Septr 30. <hi rend="print">18</hi>73.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir Charles</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>With respect to <hi rend="underline">Leda limatula</hi> I send you a proof of p. 114 in which you will see that I do not now regard the shell which I had for some time considered identical with it as the same &amp; that I have reverted to my name of 1840 <hi rend="underline">oblongoides</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Tritonium carinatum</hi> you will find in my synoptical list under the name of <hi rend="underline">Trophon antiquus</hi> var. <hi rend="underline">carinatus</hi> (the name of Tritonium I have rejected as in this were several others generically distinct (see Note Suppl<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> to Crag Moll p. 19) altho’ it is a shell of the Sutton &amp; Butley Red Crag &amp; also a Bridlington one I am not aware of its occurrence in the Chillesford Beds. it is altogether a Northern form.</p>
<p>With respect to the Scrobicularia Beds I do not exclude them from the Red Crag tho’ I have given a separate column for them (see footnote p. 203) they form the uppermost portion of the Red Crag in actual section &amp; their relation to the Fluvio-marine is fully discussed at pages VIII &amp; IX of the Introduction to my Supplement in the Pal<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> Vol for the year 1871<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>My son desires me to thank you for the extract from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwins book &amp; to say that whatever may be the case as to the Ribstone pippin his experiments satisfy him that the general principles enunciated by Mr Darwin in this paragraph are at variance with the true state of the case the rule being that the cultivated apple produces progeny identical with itself the reverse being the exception.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> On the other hand the Oak produces an infinite variety of progeny for altho the acorns of one tree are all alike those of separate Oaks differ greatly   He also bids me mention to you that so far as he can learn from acquaintances who have raised plants from Orange pips the same feeble productive power obtains in their case as in that of the seedling apple</p>
<p>Yours very truly | Searles V. Wood <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Sir Cha<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Lyell Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>P.S. The four shells you mention at p. 168 viz <hi rend="underline">Cardium Groenlandicum</hi> <hi rend="underline">Leda limatula</hi> (taking this as <hi rend="underline">Leda oblongoides</hi>) <hi rend="underline">Tritonium carinatum</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Scalaria Groenlandica</hi> are all species of the Red Crag of Butley.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Wood’s son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7236.xml">Searles Valentine Wood</ref> Jr, had sent Lyell the proof-sheets of the supplement to his father’s work, <hi rend="italic">Crag Mollusca</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8476.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wood 1873</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9059G.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from S. V. Wood Jr to Charles Lyell, 19 September 1873</ref> and n. 1). <hi rend="italic">Leda limatula</hi>, a fossil mollusc, is now <hi rend="italic">Yoldia limatula</hi>; Wood originally identified the species as <hi rend="italic">Nucula oblongoides</hi>, now considered a synonym of the still extant <hi rend="italic">Yoldia myalis</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The <hi rend="italic">Crag Mollusca</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wood 1848–61</ref>) and its supplements were published by the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Palaeontographical Society</ref>. The introduction to the first supplement appeared in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8475.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wood 1871</ref>. The red crag, a shelly sand stained red by iron compounds, is a geological term for the series of marine deposits at the base of the Pleistocene in Suffolk and Essex.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">S. V. Wood Jr had asked Lyell’s secretary, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_710.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arabella Burton Buckley</ref>, to copy passages from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> for him (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9075F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from S. V. Wood Jr to Charles Lyell, 27 September 1873</ref>). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 350, CD had stated that no-one could raise a tree of the same kind from the seed of the Ribstone Pippin, but that well-marked kinds of apple produced crab-like seedlings that bore a resemblance to their parents. For Wood’s view, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9059G.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from S. V. Wood Jr to Charles Lyell, 19 September 1873</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>