<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3282">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Asa Gray   11 October 1861</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6518</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3282 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3282.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3282.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="inc">†</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 109: 82–3, DAR 110 (ser. 2): 117, DAR 111: 83</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>109: A82–A83,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>110: B117,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>111: A83</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
                <placeName>Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>
                <date when="1861-10-11">11 Oct 1861</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Notes several cases of "dioecio-dimorphism" in different genera; feels the discovery of pollen that will act only on the pistil of another flower is most important. Believes CD should next turn his attention to investigating cases of "precocious fertilisation".</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dichogamy, sexual dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1861</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It was through pure forgetfulness at the moment of writing my letter last August, that I did not endeavor to supply to you such instances as I could recollect (for I have no memoranda on the subject) of what D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Torrey and I long ago (in Fl. N. Amer. 2, p. 38, 39) called <hi rend="underline">diœcio-dimorphism</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>In Rubiaceæ I think this dimorphism was first somewhere mentioned by D. Don, but I have no reference.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> We are most familiar with it in <hi rend="underline">Houstonia</hi> (a genus which I have proposed to restore, in which it occurs in all our N. American species, and, as you will see in Wight &amp; Arnott, Prodr. Fl. Pen. Ind. 1. p. 408, in some Indian ones.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In the living plants I have formerly noticed it in <hi rend="underline">H. purpurea</hi>, and it is every year noticed familiarly in our most abundant <hi rend="underline">H. cærulea</hi>. Of this I shall try to send you some tufts—seedlings of this year—which you can blossom in early spring, or in your house in winte〈r.〉 We must run the chance of your getting 〈both〉 subsexes. Wight &amp; Arnott (see p. 439) ob〈served〉 it in <hi rend="underline">Knoxia</hi>. Another familiar case is furnished by our pretty little <hi rend="underline">Mitchella</hi> <hi rend="underline">repens</hi>; this is recorded by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Torrey in Flora of State of New York, 1. p. 315.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> This would be a good plant for you to experiment upon, if I had only thought of marking plants the two sorts.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Diodia Virginica</hi> (and I suppose <hi rend="underline">D. teres</hi>) also shows it.</p>
<p>The dimorphism may perhaps occur in many <hi rend="underline">Rubiaceæ</hi>, but I have reason to think it that the far greater part show no such tendency. And <hi rend="underline">included</hi> or <hi rend="underline">exsert</hi> stamens are pretty good and constant generic characters in much of the order<ref target="#foot.f5"/>   <hi rend="underline">Mitchella</hi> is an interesting instance for you from its relationship (with <hi rend="underline">Nertera</hi>) to <hi rend="underline">Coprosma</hi>, one of the few diœcious genera of Rubiaceæ, and in which the stamens are long-exserted in the male flowers, the styles or stigmas, in the female.</p>
<p>In these and in all genuine cases of the kind, the two sorts of flowers are always borne on different roots.</p>
<p>Upon consideration, I can say nothing of <hi rend="underline">Labiatæ</hi> or <hi rend="underline">Borragineæ</hi> from my own observation. But I believe that D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Torrey can tell us about the latter. 〈I〉 have just written to ask him.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>〈In〉 <hi rend="underline">Labiatæ</hi>, what dimorphism I have observed—and without particular examination—is merely such as in <hi rend="underline">Nepeta Glechoma</hi>, where the stamens of the <hi rend="underline">earlier flowers</hi> appear to abort. I know not whether they do, or whether it is a case of precocious fertilization, such as I will presently call your attention to: but as the flowers are otherwise normal, I suppose it is not a case of this.</p>
<p>A case in point, which will interest you, occurs in <hi rend="underline">Rhamnus</hi>—a genus which has both truly hermaphrodite and polygamo-diœcious species.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Rhamnus lanceolatus</hi>, of our Southern &amp; Middle &amp; Western States, bears, on different trees, two kinds of flowers which differ <hi rend="underline">in the pistil only</hi>;—i.e. as far as appeared to ordinary investigation the <hi rend="underline">stamens</hi> are the same in both; but in one the style is short and included; in the other long and exserted. In the latter the flowers are subsolitary in the axils and fruitful; in the former the flowers are more numerous and clustered, and not so fruitful. Yet they do mature some fruit. Here you have an initial state of dimorphism, <hi rend="underline">apparently</hi> affecting only the female organs. (See Gray, Genera Am. Bor. Illustr 2, p. 180, f. 168.)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Your close observation might likely enough find a difference in the pollen.</p>
<p>Next take certain portions of the genus <hi rend="underline">Plantago</hi>,—upon which, instead of writing details, I refer you to my <hi rend="underline">Manual</hi> p. 269,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> and to my observations in <hi rend="underline">Pacific Rail-Road Surveys</hi>, vol. 4. p. 117,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> or, in the Extra copies of Botanical Report on D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bigelow’s collection, p. (117) 61.)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Hooker possesses both the volume and the separate paper. I only add that, in <hi rend="underline">Plantago Virginica</hi> I have since seen in herbaria, the staminate sort maturing seed, but generally it has gone to <hi rend="underline">dioicism</hi>, while in <hi rend="underline">P. Patagonica</hi> the two sorts are fruitful, perhaps almost equally so. (If you have difficulty in referring to the memoir above-mentioned, I will have the foot-note copied for you.)</p>
<p>Ilex opaca, the analogue of your Holly, I find in dried specimen, that the female flowers have stamens with filaments as long and anthers as large as those of male flowers, but in a flower-bud examined the anthers have <hi rend="underline">no pollen</hi>. The male flowers have no pistil.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Our Hollies (<hi rend="underline">Ilex</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Prinos</hi>) must be more particularly examined, to see whether anthers of any fertile flowers bear pollen. I should say they did, from general impression, and from my description in <hi rend="underline">Manual</hi>, which was condensed from MSS, prepared long ago for Flora of N. America. But we descriptive botanists have not been careful nor exact enough for your purposes.</p>
<p>In our loose observations we never should have noticed, in <hi rend="underline">Primula, Houstonia</hi>, &amp;c—any difference in the <hi rend="underline">pollen</hi> of the two sorts of flowers. I should much like to have you tell me <hi rend="underline">what the difference is</hi>, in the pollen, and I will make observations next spring, upon <hi rend="underline">Houstonia</hi>. The discovery that the <hi rend="underline">pollen</hi> of <hi rend="underline">one</hi> <hi rend="underline">is good for the pistil of the other, but not for the pistil of its</hi> <hi rend="underline">own flower, is most important</hi>.— I should rather expect this, but I want to know more about the <hi rend="underline">fact</hi>—how you made it out, &amp;c &amp;c</p>
<p>You should next turn your attention to a very different sort of dimorphism, which is almost equally common, perhaps,—one which looks to <hi rend="underline">close</hi>- instead of <hi rend="underline">cross</hi> fertilization. I allude to such cases as that occuring in the European <hi rend="underline">Impatiens nolitangere</hi>, where it was discovered by Weddell, &amp; published by Ad<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Jussieu (Malphigiaceæ, p. 85),<ref target="#foot.f12"/> and in our American two species, by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Torrey. See about this, Gray Genera Illustr. 2, p. 132, f. 152, 153.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Here all the fruit in the early part of the season comes from pistils fertilized by their own pollen precociously, in the young bud. But at or after midsummer, many of the conspicuous full-grown flowers are fertile,—their ovary lengthening enough to push out the stigma beyond the connivent scales, so that pollen of the same flower, or of other flowers brought by insects, can get access to it.</p>
<p>Malpighiaceæ, Violaceæ, Leguminosæ, &amp;c—furnish very numerous instances of such precociously-fertilized flowers.— these flowers always far more fertile than others.— And a similar case in <hi rend="underline">Specularia perfoliata</hi> has very long been known.</p>
<p>I did not know of diœcio-dimorphism in <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi>. I have suspected it in <hi rend="underline">Oxalis</hi>, from the differences in relative length of the stamens &amp; styles of some species.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>0.3 My Dear … tendency. 4.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed red and blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.6 in the female.] <hi rend="italic">closing square bracket blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 In these … of this. 7.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed red and blue crayon</hi>; ‘Holly—’ <hi rend="italic">added in margin red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>9.1 <hi rend="italic">Rhamnus lanceolatus</hi>,] <hi rend="italic">opening square bracket red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>12.1 Our Hollies] ‘Holly’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon, circled red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>12.2 I should … purposes. 12.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>13.1 In our … &amp;c 13.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>14.3 I allude … 153. 14.6] ‘Impatiens’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon</hi>; ‘Cleistogamy’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon, circled red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>17.1 I did … species. 17.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed red crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘Other Genera | Houstonia—Diodia Knoxia’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2819.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, [10 July 1860]</ref>. CD had subsequently queried Gray again about his knowledge of dimorphic plants (see especially letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3176.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">5 June [1861]</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 July [1861]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3255.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">16 September [1861]</ref>). The reference is to Torrey and Gray 1838–43.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The botanist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Don</ref> had served as librarian to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> of London from 1822 to 1841 and as professor of botany at King’s College, London from 1836 until his death in 1841. Gray may be referring to a paper by Don that describes Rubiaceae as providing the best example among plants of extensive variation in the sexual organs (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2098.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Don 1837</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Wight and Arnott 1834.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7790.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Torrey 1843</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">This sentence was added at the bottom of the page and keyed to the text with an asterisk. CD cut off this portion of the letter, which was filed separately from the other two portions. It is now in DAR 110 (ser. 2): 117.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The botanist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Torrey</ref> was the United States assayer in New York. He had recently moved to the campus of Columbia College, New York.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3002.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gray 1848–9</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">There is an annotated copy of Gray 1856 in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Torrey 1857</ref>; this work includes many plant descriptions provided by Gray.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_444.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Milton Bigelow</ref> made the botanical collections for the Pacific railroad survey of 1853–4. The greater part of his collection was submitted to Torrey for examination and description (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Torrey 1857</ref>, p. 62). The different sections of the survey report were also printed separately (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4219.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johnston 1943</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The section from ‘Ilex opaca’ to ‘no pistil.’ was written in the margin and keyed to the text with an asterisk.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4994.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Algernon Weddell</ref> was a former pupil of Adrien Henri Laurent de Jussieu. The reference is to Jussieu 1843.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3002.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gray 1848–9</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>