<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10131">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From F. J. Cohn   21 August 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16469</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10131 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10131.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10131.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 200</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 200</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_999.xml">Cohn, F. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Liebwerda (Hejnice)</placeName>
                <date when="1875-08-21">21 Aug 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Acknowledges presentation copy of <hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi>.</p>  
<p>Studying <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> on vacation in Bohemia. Thinks CD has erred in considering "aggregation" to have occurred in the protoplasm. Suggests it is result of exosmosis of vacuole.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Drosera</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Bohemia</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cell theory, cell behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">holidaying</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Pflanzenphysiologisches Institut | der | K. Universität Breslau.</hi> | Liebwerda, Bohemia</placeName>
                    <date>Aug. 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. <hi rend="print">187</hi>5</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Believe me not ungrateful because I did not acknowledge till today the receipt of so precious a gift as your book on Insectivorous plants is valued by me.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I found it impossible to limit myself to a simple expression of thanks; on the contrary I felt obliged to bestow the most sedulous study into a work affording an incredible amount of new facts, and a true model of inductive method which cautiously proceeding step by step, conducts to the most surprising biological revelations. So I took with me your book into this little place at the utmost corner of North-Bohemia on the foot of the Iser-mountains, where I am spending some weeks in quiet seclusion amidst forests and hills;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> soon I happened to gather a supply of living Drosera rotundifolia from the moors of this country which did forward me the opportunity to repeat at least the most striking of your admirable experiments, in as much the total want of scientific apparatus did allow; and a little pocket-microscope, which I happily brought there in my carpet bag, permits me to observe your wonderful discovery of aggregation.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Many years before I had bestowed much time to the observation of Drosera, Mr. Nitschke being a pupil of mine and his principal researches about Drosera being made in my then-private laboratory under my direction for the purpose of an inaugural dissertation.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But your book shows the whole question quite under a new light, and I congratulate you most sincerely to this last but by no means least contribution to the Advancement of science our generation is owing to your genius.</p>
<p>Will you kindly permit me to express candidly a scrupule I was struck with, by perusing your book attentively? By descriving the aggregation in the cells of the tentacles, you always take it granted that the red masses, in incessant changes of form coalescent and again separating, are protoplasma.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> But did you really prove it? To tell the truth, I have some doubts about the protoplasmatic nature of the aggregated masses. My principal reason is their colour. By its general proprieties as well as after the spectroscopic examination of Mr. Sorby the red pigment seems not different from the common <hi rend="underline">erythrophylle</hi> of red leaves, petala, fruits, which is not wanting in the tissues of stems and roots; if red, it shows always an acid reaction: if neutral, it changes in violet; if alcaline, it becomes blue or green; the blue colour is generally called <hi rend="underline">anthocyane</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Perhaps there are different pigments confound under these denominations; but they all agree: they are always dissolved in the <hi rend="underline">watery fluid</hi> which fills out the inner cavity of the cells, and they are <hi rend="underline">insoluble in protoplasma</hi>. Compare for instance the blue hair-cells at the stamens of Tradescantia and you will well distinguish the colourless circulating protoplasma adhering to the inner cell-wall, and the blue watery fluid of the central cavity.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I guess, that in Drosera the true circulating Protoplasma is also colourless, and that the purple substance is <hi rend="underline">not protoplasma</hi>. But how explain the wonderful phenomenon of aggregation discovered by you? To my greatest regret the microscope here in my possession does not suffice to solve the question; perhaps I shall be happier after my return at Breslau. But I dare to indicate an analogy, first described by Naegeli; put red or blue petala in a denser fluid; by exosmosis water quickley exsudates from out the cells, through their membranes; the membranes withdraw it from the colourless protoplasma and the protoplasma from the coloured watery fluid of the cells, in such a degree, that the pigment looses the necessary quantity of water for its dissolution and is reduced in dense and intensively coloured drops, smaller or larger; by adding fresh distilled water, the later enters by endosmosis into the cells, and the coloured drops dissolve in the cell-fluid once more.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Perhaps there is the clue, for explaining the aggregation by the water-absorbing power of the protoplasma.</p>
<p>Please to accept these remarks as a token of the deepest interest I take on your admirable researches and believe me</p>
<p>Truly yours | Ferdinand Cohn</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Cohn’s name is on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (see Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The health resort where Cohn stayed is now known as Lazne Libverda in the Czech Republic and the mountain range is the Jizera mountains (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Most of CD’s experimental work was done with <hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> (common or round-leaved sundew; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, pp. 1–277). He described the aggregation of matter within cells of the tentacles and concluded, from the movement and consistency of the masses, that they consisted of protoplasm (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 40).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7316.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Theodor Nitschke’s</ref> doctoral dissertation was titled <hi rend="italic">Commentatio anatomico-physiologica de Droserae rotundifoliae (L.) irritabilitate</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5884.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nitschke 1858</ref>). Nitschke published articles on the growth of round-leaved sundew, on the sensitivity of its leaves, and on its morphology and anatomy (Nitschke 1860a, 1860b, 1861a, 1861b). CD referred frequently to these papers in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See n. 3, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4469.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Clifton Sorby</ref>, who had invented a spectrum microscope, had studied the nature of pigments in several organic and inorganic substances. CD had learned from Sorby that the red pigment in hairs of <hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> was erythrophyll, a common red pigment found in leaves, fruit, and flowers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, enclosure to <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9638.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 15 September 1874</ref>; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, p. 5 n.). The term erythrophyll is no longer generally used in scientific terminology, but the substance belongs to a family of pigments that vary in appearance depending on the acidity or alkalinity of the environment, and are now known as anthocyanins.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The stamen hairs in <hi rend="italic">Tradescantia</hi> (spiderwort) are usually blue; each hair consists of a single row of connected bead-like cells, in which the blue pigment is located in the central vacuoles, while the clear protoplasm is near the outer cell wall.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Wilhelm von Nägeli</ref> described this process in 1855 (see Nägeli and Cramer 1855–8, part 1, pp. 5–7). CD’s copies of the first and fourth parts of Nägeli and Cramer 1855–8 (the first and second parts were written by Nägeli) are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>