<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1200A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Thompson   29 September 1848</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20498</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1200A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1200A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1200A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc">inc</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 4: 167–8</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): 272–3</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Living Cirripedia (1854): 272–3</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4727.xml">Thompson, William (a)</persName>
                <date when="1848-09-29">29 Sept 1848</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Concerning the measurements of <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi> specimens with respect to growth.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Balanus</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Sept. 29, 1848.—I examined a great number of Balani, in reference to the growth made by them during the present season, and found it to average three lines in diameter, and at most four lines. I saw a few minute specimens, only one line in diameter, showing that the species continued to breed until lately: these latter were probably not more than four weeks old. The young of the present year are plainly distinguished from the older ones, by their pure white colour and fresh appearance. Judging from the size of this year’s specimens, and of the older ones on the same stones, I am of opinion that the term of life of the species is two years. Of the older shells, which I examined and found living in the spring, nine tenths are now dead, the walls only remaining, the opercular valves having been washed away.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Following the extract from Thompson’s letter, CD recorded (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>273): <quote> Mr. Thompson goes on to say, that the individuals which had, on July 3, a basal diameter of from two and a half to three lines, had attained, by the 30th of September, a diameter of four and a half lines, this being here the maximum size of the species.</quote> Earlier, CD quoted additional information supplied by Thompson, perhaps from this or another letter (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>272): <quote> I am informed by Mr. Thompson, that he has seen specimens [of <hi rend="italic">Balanus balanoides</hi>] attached to a spot not covered by water during neap-tides. As a proof of its tenacity of life, Mr. Thompson informs me that he accidentally kept some specimens in a box, in a warm sitting-room, and found them alive seven days afterwards. This same most accurate observer finds, however, that <hi rend="italic">B. balanoides</hi> is very susceptible to brackish water; he says, “that having kept some specimens alive for a week in excellent health, the water being changed once in thirty-six hours, they were one day killed instantly by some water, though brought from the same part of the estuary as usual, having been rendered brackish by much rain having lately fallen.”</quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>