<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2950F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To John Medows Rodwell   15 October [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21323</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2950F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2950F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2950F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 185: 149</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>185: 149</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <date when="1860-10-15">15 Oct [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4051.xml">Rodwell, J. M.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on Rodwell’s discussion of the “struggle for life” with reference to languages and G. H. Lewes’s article in the <hi rend="italic">Cornhill Magazine</hi> (Lewes 1860, pp. 445–7). Comments on Rodwell’s account of horses affected by mildewed pasturage, and asks for more information about his white cat.</p> 
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>15 Marine Parade | Eastbourne</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am truly obliged for your interesting letter.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am very far from being surprised at anyone not accepting my conclusions on the origin of species; as the argument rests almost solely on the view explaining &amp; grouping phenomena, otherwise inexplicable. I have some confidence that I am in the main right; for I find it as yet a universal rule, that those naturalists who go a little way with me, the more they reflect on the subject the further they go.— I am at work on my larger work, but ill-health &amp; other interruptions make my progress very slow.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Your remarks on language seem to me very striking; &amp; the “struggle for life” with words is quite new to me.— I had often thought that a striking resemblance might be traced in the genesis of words &amp; species; but was much too ignorant to attempt it.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It was done to a certain extent some 4 or 5 or 6 months ago in the Cornhill Magazine by Lewes in one of his Zoological papers.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Could you not publish an essay on the subject?</p>
<p>I have been particularly interested by your case of the Horses. I have somewhere read a nearly parallel case. I am sorry to give you trouble; but I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. very much like to know whether the case was published; &amp; if you can give me any further particulars; such as how many Horses were affected; how soon they recovered &amp;c.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Prof. Wyman has sent me an analogous case with respect to pigs in Florida: he was surprised at seeing them all black; &amp; he found that they eat a certain root, which injures &amp; kills the white pigs, but does not hurt the black; &amp; the farmers added, “we help it by <hi rend="underline">selection</hi>, for we kill the young white pigs”.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>It is not white cats, but white cats with <hi rend="underline">blue</hi> eyes, which are deaf,—if one eye is blue the cat is deaf on that one side—if your cat has <hi rend="underline">distinctly</hi> blue eyes &amp; is not deaf, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be particularly obliged for the fact, as it will be the sole exception which I have heard of.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Pray accept my best thanks for your interesting letter &amp; with respect, I beg leave to remain | Dear Sir | yours faithfully &amp; obliged | Charles Darwin | of Down, Bromley, Kent</p>
<p>I shall be here for about 10 days<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.3 almost] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.3 explaining] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘given’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.10 much] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2970.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. M. Rodwell, 31 October 1860</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Rodwell’s letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD was working on the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>, the first part of what was intended as a three-part work explaining in greater detail the operation of natural selection; the other two parts were never published. See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, Appendix II and n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Rodwell made translations from Hebrew, Arabic, Ethiopic, and Coptic; he planned to write a book on the ‘birth, life, and death of words’ (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2976.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. M. Rodwell, 5 November [1860]</ref>), but apparently it was never published. On the application of CD’s theories to language, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_139.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Alter 1999</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2911.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Henry Lewes</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4727.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Lewes 1860</ref>, pp. 445–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Rodwell’s answer was in the portion of his letter of 31 October 1860 (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8) that is now missing; see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2976.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. M. Rodwell, 5 November [1860]</ref>. CD gave Rodwell’s information in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2: 337: <quote type="quote"> The Rev. J. Rodwell informs me that his father turned out about fifteen cart-horses into a field of tares which in parts swarmed with black aphides, and which no doubt were honeydewed, and probably mildewed; the horses, with two exceptions, were chesnuts and bays with white marks on their faces and pasterns, and the white parts alone swelled and became angry scabs. The two bay horses with no white marks entirely escaped all injury. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> had sent CD information from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jeffries Wyman</ref> on the black pigs of Florida, which was later confirmed by Wyman himself (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2743.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 3 April [1860]</ref>, and letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5268.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jeffries Wyman</ref>, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 15] September 1860). The case was given in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed., p. 12, and in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2: 227, 336, where the pigs were incorrectly said to live in Virginia.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD discussed the correlation between blue eyes and deafness in cats in <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, pp. 12 and 144, where he stated that the connection was invariable. In <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed., p. 12, he altered the text to state that cats with blue eyes were ‘generally’ deaf. He discussed the topic again in <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2: 329. In <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> CD mentioned, without citing Rodwell’s case, that he had since heard of a few exceptions to the rule. See also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2970.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. M. Rodwell, 31 October 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The Darwins stayed at Eastbourne from 22 September to 10 November 1860 in the hope that a stay at the seaside would improve <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin’s</ref> health (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 8, Appendix II, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2918.xml" resp="#automat">letter to G. V. Reed, 15 September [1860]</ref>; their stay was prolonged by Henrietta’s attack of sickness on 22 October (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2962.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Innes, 26 October [1860]</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>