<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5583A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   17 July 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20485</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5583A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5583A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5583A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">(German trans)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 130–1</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Möller, Alfred 1915–21 2: 130–1</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Itajahy, Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1867-07-17">17 July 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for sending F. H. G. Hildebrand’s book on fertilisation [<hi rend="italic">Die Geschlechter-Vertheilung bei den Pflanzen</hi> (1867)]</p> 
            <p>and J. D. Hooker’s "Lecture on insular floras".</p> 
<p>Describes work on Rubiaceae, <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi>,</p> 
            <p>and on crossing orchids. Lists crosses made.</p> 
<p>As for CD’s query concerning sexual differences among invertebrates, he gives the case of the local amphipod, <hi rend="italic">Brachyscellus diversilor</hi>. Male differs in shape of antennae and coloration.</p> 
            <p>Also mentions local fish in sea near Sta Catharina which emits melodic tone to attract females.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">amphipod</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Brachyscellus diversilor</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fish</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">invertebrates</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oxalis</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Rubiaceae</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die Geschlechter-Vertheilung bei den Pflanzen</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Sta Catharina</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Hildebrand, F. H. G. 1867</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Hooker, J. D. 1867</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex differences</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex-linked behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Itajahy, Santa Catharina,</placeName>
                    <date>17. Juli 1867.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>.... . Ich muss Sie noch um Verzeihung bitten, dass ich Ihnen nicht früher für Dr. Hildebrand’s Buch über die Befruchtung gedankt habe, welches Sie mir freundlichst zuschickten. Ich habe es mit grossem Interesse gelesen. Ich bekam auch Dr. Hooker’s höchst interessante Schrift “Vorlesung über Insel-Floren”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Die Familie der Rubiaceen scheint sehr reich an dimorphen Pflanzen zu sein; obwohl jetzt im Winter viel weniger Pflanzen blühen, wie zu irgend einer andern Jahreszeit, so bemerkte ich doch schon wieder drei dimorphe Arten: 1) eine zierliche etwa Erica ähnliche Hedyotis, 2) eine zweite Art von Suteria mit braunem Kelch und gelber Krone, von der man sagt, sie sei das Lieblingsfutter des Tapirs, 3) die Manettia bicolor, welche hier sehr häufig ist.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ich kenne zwei andere Arten von Manettia mit rothen Blüthen, von der ich vermuthe, dass sie auch dimorph ist, obwohl alle Pflanzen, die ich bisher beobachtete, langgrifflig waren.</p>
<p>Ich fand hier auch eine weisse trimorphe Oxalis; ich habe verschiedene kurzgrifflige und mittelgrifflige, bisher aber noch keine langgrifflige gesehen; eine einzige Pflanze hatte die Staubfäden der langgriffligen Form in Verbindung mit den Griffeln der mittelgriffligen, so dass die Griffel dieselbe Länge hatten, wie die längeren Staubfäden.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Ehe ich Desterro verliess,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> untersuchte ich die meisten Kapseln, die ich aus Kreuzungsversuchen von Orchideen erhalten hatte; die meisten waren noch unreif.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Beinahe alle Samen waren offenbar gut in den Kapseln von:</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>Cattleya intermedia ♀ und Cattl. elegans<ref target="#foot.f7"/> ♂</p>
<p>Epidendrum vesicatum ♀ und Ep. raniferum ♂</p>
<p>"  "  ♀ und Ep. glumaceum<ref target="#foot.f8"/> ♂</p>
<p>"  raniferum ♀ und Ep. cinnabarium ♂</p>
<p>"  "  ♀ und Brassavola fragans Leon<ref target="#foot.f9"/> ♂!</p>
<p>Cirrhaea saccata (?) ♀ und Cirrhaea dependens (?)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> ♂</p>
<p>Oncidium micropogon ♀ und Gomeza<ref target="#foot.f11"/> sp. ♂</p>
<p>Gomeza sp. ♀ und Oncidium micropogon ♂.</p>
<p>Es waren viel mehr gute Samen als schlechte Samen in den Kapseln von:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior var. Leopoldi ♀ und Laelia purpurata ♂.</p>
<p>"  intermedia ♀ und Cattl. elatior var. Russeliana ♂.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Ungefähr die Hälfte der Samen war offenbar gut in einer Kapsel von:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior ♀ befruchtet mit Cattl. intermedia ♂.</p>
<p>Wenigstens <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>9</mn><mn>10</mn></mfrac></math></formula> der Samen waren schlecht in den Kapseln von:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior ♀ gekreuzt mit Cattl. elegans ♂ und</p>
<p>Oncidium (aus Theresopolis)<ref target="#foot.f13"/> ♀ gekreuzt mit Sigmatostalix ♂.</p>
<p>Eine ausserordentlich kleine Zahl von offenbar guten Samen wurde gefunden in den Kapseln von:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior var. Russeliana ♀ und Epidendron cinnabarinum ♂</p>
<p>Notylia sp. ♀ und Ornithocephalus sp. ♂ (!).<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Alle Samen waren schlecht in den Kapseln von:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior ♀ und Epidendron<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Schomburgkii (?) ♂</p>
<p>Epidendron vesicatum ♀ und Epid. Schomburgkii (?) ♂</p>
<p>"  "  ♀ und Epid. cinnabarinum ♂</p>
<p>Sigmatostalix sp. ♀ und Ornithocephalus sp. ♂.</p> </figure> 
<p>Bei einer selbstbefruchteten Kapsel von Ornithocephalus fand ich, dass sie viel kleiner war und viel mehr schlechte Samen enthielt als eine andere Kapsel, die mit Pollen einer fremden Pflanze befruchtet war.... .</p>
<p>Was Ihre Frage über Geschlechtsverschiedenheiten bei niederen Thieren betrifft, so mag vielleicht eine unserer Amphipoden, Brachyscelus diversicolor F.M.,<ref target="#foot.f16"/> hier zu nennen sein. Das Männchen dieser Art, welche auf einigen unserer grösseren Acalepheen lebt (Rhizostoma cruciatum Less. = Rhacopilus cruciatus und cyanolobatus Agass. und Chrysaora Blossevillei Less. = Lobocrocis Blossevillei Agass.),<ref target="#foot.f17"/> unterscheidet sich nicht nur durch seine Antennen, deren erstes Paar sehr dick und reichlich mit Riechhaaren versehen ist, während das zweite ausserordentlich lang ist (dies zweite Paar fehlt den ♀ und den jungen ♂)—sondern auch durch seine Farbe. Das Weibchen ist gewöhnlich von milchweisser oder mattgelblicher Farbe, das Männchen dunkelröthlich-braun oder schwärzlich. Die Art hat aussergewöhnlich grosse Augen, wie in der That die meisten Hyperina sie haben, und so ist es nicht unwahrscheinlich, dass das Weibchen durch die Farbe des Männchens angezogen wird.</p>
<p>Bei dieser Gelegenheit will ich hinzufügen, dass es im Meere bei Santa Catharina einen Fisch giebt, der sehr melodische Töne hervorbringt, welche auch dazu dienen mögen, das andere Geschlecht anzulocken.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> Die Töne klingen wie entferntes Geläute von Kirchenglocken. Ich habe sie nur an ruhigen Abenden gehört, wenn diese Seemusikanten um einen Felsen dicht bei der Küste schwammen, aber ich sah den Fisch nie.</p>
<p>Um noch einmal auf das Epidendron mit seitlichen fruchtbaren Antheren zurückzukommen, bei dem Pollenschläuche sogar noch vor dem Oeffnen der Blüthe getrieben werden, so scheint die grosse Veränderlichkeit der seitlichen Antheren, welche in einem Falle beobachtet wurde, der Ansicht günstig zu sein, dass sie erst neuerdings erworben wurden in Folge eines zufälligen Rückschlags auf einen längst verlorenen Character.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>Mit der grössten Hochachtung, glauben Sie, dass ich, werther Herr, aufrichtigst der Ihrige bin | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Itajahy, Santa Catharina,</placeName>
                    <date>17. July 1867.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>. . . . I have to apologise for not thanking you earlier for kindly sending me Dr. Hildebrand’s book on fertilisation. I have read it with great interest. I have also received Dr. Hooker’s extremely interesting publication “Lecture on insular floras”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>The family Rubiaceae seems to be very rich in dimorphic plants; although now in winter many fewer plants are flowering than in any other season, I still observed yet another three dimorphic species: 1) a delicate Hedyotis somewhat similar to Erica, 2) a second species of Suteria with brown calyx and yellow corolla, which is said to be the favourite food of tapirs, 3) the Manettia bicolor, which is very common here.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I know another two species of Manietta with red flowers, which I suspect are also dimorphic, although all the plants that I have observed so far were long-styled.</p>
<p>I have also found a trimorphic white Oxalis here; I have seen various short-styled and medium-styled but no long-styled yet; a single plant had the stamens of the long-styled one in conjunction with the styles of the medium-styled ones, so that the style was as long as the longest stamens.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Before leaving Desterro,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I examined most of the capsules that resulted from my crossing experiments with orchids; most had not yet matured.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Almost all seeds were apparently good in the capsules of:</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>Cattleya intermedia ♀ and Cattl. elegans<ref target="#foot.f7"/> ♂</p>
<p>Epidendrum vesicatum ♀ and Ep. raniferum ♂</p>
<p>" " ♀ and Ep. glumaceum<ref target="#foot.f8"/> ♂</p>
<p>" raniferum ♀ and Ep. cinnabarinum ♂</p>
<p>" " ♀ and Brassavola fragans Leon<ref target="#foot.f9"/> ♂!</p>
<p>Cirrhaea saccata (?) ♀ and Cirrhaea dependens (?)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> ♂</p>
<p>Oncidium micropogon ♀ and Gomeza<ref target="#foot.f11"/> sp. ♂</p>
<p>Gomeza sp. ♀ and Oncidium micropogon ♂</p>
<p>There were many more good than bad seeds in the capsules of:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior var. Leopoldi ♀ and Laelia purpurata ♂</p>
<p>" intermedia ♀ and Cattl. elatior var. Russeliana ♂.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Approximately half the seeds were apparently good in the capsule of:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior ♀ fertilised with Cattl. intermedia ♂.</p>
<p>At least <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>9</mn><mn>10</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of the seeds were bad in the capsules of:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior ♀ crossed with Cattl. elegans ♂ and</p>
<p>Oncidium (from Theresopolis)<ref target="#foot.f13"/> ♀ crossed with Sigmatostalix ♂.</p>
<p>An extraordinarily small number of apparently good seeds were found in the capsules of:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior var. Russeliana ♀ and Epidendrum cinnabarinum ♂</p>
<p>Notylia sp. ♀ and Ornithocephalus sp. ♂ (!)<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>All seeds were bad in the capsules of:</p>
<p>Cattleya elatior ♀ and Epidendron<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Schomburgkii (?) ♂</p>
<p>Epidendron vesicatum ♀ and Epid. Schomburgkii (?) ♂</p>
<p>" " ♀ and Epid. cinnabarinum ♂</p>
<p>Sigmatostalix sp. ♀ and Ornithocephalus sp. ♂.</p> </figure> 
<p>I found a self-fertilised capsule of Ornithocephalus was much smaller and contained many more bad seeds than another capsule fertilised with the pollen from a different plant.... .</p>
<p>With regard to your query about sexual differences in lower animals, one ought perhaps to mention one of our amphipods, Brachyscelus diversicolor F.M.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> The male of this species, which lives on some of our larger acalephs (Rhizostoma cruciatum Less. = Rhacopilus cruciatus and cyanolobatus Agass. and Chrysaora Blossevillei Less. = Lobrococis Blossevillei Agass.),<ref target="#foot.f17"/> differs not only in the antennae, the first pair of which is very thick and covered in olfactory hair whereas the second is extraordinarily long (this second pair is absent on the ♀ and young ♂)—but also in colour. The female is usually milky white or dull yellowish, the male is dark reddish-brown or blackish. The species has unusually large eyes, as indeed most Hyperina have, and so it is not unlikely that the female is attracted by the colour of the male.</p>
<p>In this connection I would like to add that there is a fish in the sea by Santa Catharina that produces very melodious sounds that may also serve to attract the opposite sex.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> The sounds are like the ringing of distant church bells. I have only heard them on quiet evenings when these maritime musicians swam by a rock close to the coast, but I never saw the fish.</p>
<p>To come back once more to the Epidendron with fertile lateral anthers, in which the pollen tubes are emitted even before the opening of the flower: it seems that the great diversity of the lateral anthers observed in one case is favourable to the view that they have only been acquired recently as the result of a chance reversion to a long lost character.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>With the greatest respect, believe me, dear Sir, that I am sincerely yours | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, Appendix I. All <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (Möller ed. 1915–21). Möller also found drafts of some Müller letters among <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> papers and included these in their original English form (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 2: 72 n.). Where the original English versions are missing, the published versions, usually appearing in German translation, have been used.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the German of its published source, see p. 322–4. All <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (Möller ed. 1915–21). Möller also found drafts of some Müller letters among <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> papers and included these in their original English form (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 2: 72 n.). Where the original English versions are missing, the published versions, usually appearing in German translation, have been used.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The references are to Hildebrand 1867a and J. D. Hooker 1866a (see letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5458.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">25 March [1867]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5509.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 April [1867]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 131–3, 135, CD reported Müller’s information on heterostyly in <hi rend="italic">Hedyotis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Suteria</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Manettia bicolor.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Suteria</hi> is now subsumed within the genus <hi rend="italic">Psychotria</hi>; <hi rend="italic">M. bicolor</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">M. luteo-rubra.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD mentioned Müller’s observation of a white-flowered trimorphic <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 180.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Müller had lived in Destêrro (now Florianópolis) from 1856, but had just returned to live on the Itajahy (now Itajaí) river near Blumenau, where he bought a new property in September 1867. Müller typically gave his address simply as ‘Itajahy’ until the mid-1870s, when he began to add ‘Blumenau’, but only consistently gave his address as ‘Blumenau’ from 1878 (Möller ed. 1915–21, 3: 94; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">West 2003</ref>, pp. 149–50).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Müller had begun a series of crossing experiments with orchids earlier in the year (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5480.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 April 1867</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Cattleya elegans</hi> is an orchid hybrid, a cross of <hi rend="italic">C. tigrina</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. purpurata</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Epidendrum raniferum</hi> is a synonym of  <hi rend="italic">E. cristatum</hi><hi rend="italic">Epidendrum glumaceum</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Prosthechea glumacea</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3621.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Higgins 1997</ref>, p. 378).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Brassavola fragans</hi> (named by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6149.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lemaire</ref>; Möller mistranscribed ‘Lem’ as ‘Leon’) is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">B. tuberculata.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Cirrhaea dependens</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">C. viridipurpurea.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Gomeza</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Gomesia.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Cattleya elatior</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">C. guttata</hi>; the varieties mentioned by Müller are now <hi rend="italic">C. guttata</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">leopoldii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. guttata</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">russelliana.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Laelia purpurata</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Cattleya purpurata</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Now Queçaba (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">West 2003</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Müller probably found it surprising that a cross between two fairly widely separated genera was possible. In orchids, natural hybrids are usually confined to intergeneric crosses within a subtribe, making a cross at this level rare (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1981</ref>, pp. 147–8). <hi rend="italic">Notylia</hi> is now a member of the orchid tribe Cymbidieae, while <hi rend="italic">Ornithocephalus</hi> belongs to the tribe Maxillariae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">‘Epidendron’: a mistranscription of <hi rend="italic">Epidendrum.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">For CD’s query, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5410.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 22 February [1867]</ref>. The name <hi rend="italic">Brachyscelus diversicolor</hi> was never published by Müller. For a description of all currently recognised species within the genus, see Vinogradov <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. 1996, pp. 488–96. Müller had discussed sexual differences in the antennae of <hi rend="italic">Brachyscelus</hi> in F. Müller 1864, p. 53 (see also Dallas trans. 1869, pp. 78–9; CD annotated this section in his copy; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 609).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><hi rend="italic">Rhacopilus cyanolobatus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rhizostoma cruciata</hi> are both synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Catostylus cruciatus</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4488.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kramp 1961</ref>, p. 370). <hi rend="italic">Chrysaora blossevillei</hi> is now considered to be a doubtful species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4488.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kramp 1961</ref>, p. 324). Two species of <hi rend="italic">Chrysaora</hi> have been recorded in Brazil, <hi rend="italic">C. lactea</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. plocamia</hi> (Migotto <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. 2002, p. 23). It is likely, because of its size, that the species Müller refers to is <hi rend="italic">C. plocamia.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">The fish has not been identified, but of thirty-four possible sound-producing species in the families Batrachoididae and Sciaenidae in Brazil, the Bocon toadfish, <hi rend="italic">Amphichthys cryptocentrus</hi>, is the only reef-associated species known to occur at depths of a metre or less (Joseph Luczkovich, personal communication). CD mentioned musical sounds made by fish in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 23, 331 (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pauly 2004</ref>, pp. 193–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Müller first mentioned this orchid in a letter of 1 June 1866 that has not been found (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5196.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter to Fritz Müller, 23 August 1866</ref>). He gave an account of it in letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4240.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Johann Sigismund Schultze</ref> (2 June 1866) and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller</ref> (1 July 1866; the letters are reproduced in Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 83–4, 86–9. Müller described it as a species of the orchid tribe Epidendreae with three fertile anthers, two in the outer whorl and one in the inner whorl (see Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 87–8). He later published his observations in F. Müller 1868a, 1869, and 1870; CD added a reference to Müller’s work in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 148.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>