<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7148">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. H. Flower   25 March [1870]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20199</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7148 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7148.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7148.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">John Innes Foundation Historical Collections; DAR 270.1: 24</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_203.xml">John Innes Foundation</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>270:1 24</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1870-03-25">25 Mar [1870]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1670.xml">Flower, W. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks WHF for his very good lecture.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Beckenham | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Mar 25</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Flower</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much obliged to you for having sent me yr Lecture, of which I had heard &amp; was anxious to see. It strikes me as in every way very good &amp; very well written. I am sure I feel much obliged to you for the highly honourable manner in which you mention my name.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>The feet of the Koala &amp; Kangoroo is one of the most beautiful cases I ever heard of.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Such facts will do more to convince unbelievers than pages of general reasoning. I am glad you noticed the curiously false argument in the Month about the teeth of the dog &amp; Thylacinus: I had selected this in my M.S. as an excellent instance of analogical resemblance.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have answered, I think satisfactorily, many of the objections advanced in this article; but my whole time w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be wasted if I once began to answer objectors.</p>
<p>With very sincere thanks for the great interest &amp; instruction which you have afforded me Pray believe me | yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin P.S.How curiously inaccurate the author of article in “The Month” is in some respects— He speaks of similarity of teeth of Thylacinus &amp; Canis as being so great as to bespeak community of descent, &amp; what a profound difference in essential nature in incisors &amp; premolars &amp; molars!<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>How odd with the giraffe— but it is not worth writing.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Flower 1870</ref>; see n. 2, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Flower had given the introductory lecture to the course of comparative anatomy at the Royal College of Surgeons on 14 February 1870; it was published in the <hi rend="italic">Medical Times and Gazette</hi> for 19 February (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Flower 1870</ref>). Flower mentioned CD along with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref> as the originators of the theory of the origin of species by means of natural selection (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Flower 1870</ref>, p. 196).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 6th ed.</ref>, p. 382, CD cited Flower for the information that the hind feet of the kangaroo, the koala, and the bandicoot were constructed on the same plan, despite being used for different purposes. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Flower 1870</ref>, pp. 197–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The July 1869 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Month</hi> included the first part of an anonymous article by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Mivart] 1869</ref>) titled ‘Difficulties of the theory of natural selection’. The author argued (p. 49): <quote type="quote"> Nothing can be more remarkable than the identity of structure between certain of the teeth of the large predatory marsupial called the thylacine, or Tasmanian wolf, and those of the common dog. The resemblance is so complete that community of descent is at once most forcibly suggested, and yet on the assumption adopted, the thylacine may be closely related genetically to the kangaroo and its allies, but must be separated from the dog by an abyss. </quote> In the sixth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, published in 1872, CD commented (p. 374): <quote type="quote"> Numerous cases could be given of striking resemblances in quite distinct beings between single parts or organs, which have been adapted for the same functions. A good instance is afforded by the close resemblance of the jaws of the dog and Tasmanian wolf or Thylacinus,—animals which are widely sundered in the natural system. But this resemblance is confined to general appearance, as in the prominence of the canines, and in the cutting shape of the molar teeth. </quote> CD added that Flower had come to the same conclusion (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 375). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Flower 1870</ref>, p. 199.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Thylacinus</hi> is a genus of marsupials which had one extant species in the 19th century, <hi rend="italic">T. cynocephalus</hi>, the Tasmanian wolf or thylacine. The species dentition differed from that of <hi rend="italic">Canis</hi> in many respects (see Jones and Stoddart 1998). It became extinct in the 1930s.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>