<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6812">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   2 July 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5289</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6812 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6812.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6812.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 52</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 52</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1869-07-02">2 July 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on 5th edition of the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> [1869];</p>  
<p>preparation of second edition of <hi rend="italic">Natürliche Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> [1870].</p> 
            <p>The reception of CD’s theory. Mentions support of Pieter Harting and Michael Sars.</p>
            <p>EH’s research on calcareous sponges and plans to publish monograph on them.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sponges, calcareous</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Naturliche Schopfungsgeschichte</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2150">Harting, Pieter</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4185">Sars, Michael</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1870</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>2. Juli 69.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Vor einigen Tagen erhielt ich die fünfte Auflage Ihres “Origin of Species” und danke Ihnen herzlich für diesen neuen Beweis Ihrer Güte.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich freue mich sehr dass Ihre epochemachendes Werk immer noch so zahlreiche neue Abnehmer mit jedem Jahre findet, trotzdem es schon in so vielen tausend Exemplaren und in so zahlreichen Übersetzungen durch die ganze Welt verbreitet ist. Besonders freue ich mich, dass Sie noch die grosse Genugthuung erleben, die ungeheure Wirkung des colossalen Fortschritts, den Ihr Werk in der Biologie hervorgerufen hat, mit eigenen Augen zu sehen, und daraus zu ermessen, wie gross erst sein Ruhm in späterer Zukunft sein wird.</p>
<p>Von meiner “Natürlichen Schöpfungsgeschichte” bereite ich jetzt die II. Auflage vor, welche im nächsten Jahre erscheinen wird.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Die Zahl der Schriften, welche die einzelnen Seiten Ihrer Theorie ausbauen, wächst mit jeder Woche, und ebenso auch die Zahl Ihrer Anhänger. Unter den deutschen Naturforschern der <hi rend="underline">jüngeren</hi> Generation giebt es jetzt keine irgend bedeutenden Gegner mehr. Besonders freut es mich aber, dass auch höchst verdiente ältere Naturforscher sich zur Descendenz-Theorie bekehren, wie z. B. <hi rend="underline">P. Harting</hi> in Utrecht und <hi rend="underline">M. Sars</hi> in Christiania, welche mir Beide in letzter Zeit geschrieben haben, und ihre volle Übereinstimmung ausgedrückt haben.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In einigen Wochen werden Sie meine “Entwickelungsgeschichte der Siphonophoren” erhalten, welche jetzt endlich fertig gedruckt und von 14 Tafeln begleitet ist.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Gegenwärtig arbeite ich seit bald einem Jahre sehr eifrig an den <hi rend="underline">Kalkschwämmen</hi> (Calcispongiae)<ref target="#foot.f6"/> einer höchst interessanten Thiergruppe, welche auch für Ihre Theorie von sehr grosser Bedeutung ist. Die organische “Species” ist hier bei manchen Grantien quasi “<hi rend="underline">in statu nascenti</hi>” zu beobachten. Um die Naturgeschichte dieser Thiere möglichst vollständig zu bearbeiten, werde ich gegen Ende Juli auf einige Wochen nach <hi rend="underline">Norwegen</hi> (Christiania, Bergen, Drontjhem)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> gehen, wo es sehr viel Kalkschwämme zu geben scheint. Ich werde Ihnen eine vorläufige Mittheilung über meine Resultate in einigen Wochen zuschicken. Eine umfassende “<hi rend="underline">Monographie der Kalkschwämme</hi>” denke ich dann im nächsten Jahre zu veröffentlichen.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Um den systematischen Theil derselben recht vollständig zu machen, erbitte ich nun Material von allen Seiten. Sollten Sie oder einer Ihrer Freunde mir Kalkschwämme schicken können (wenn auch nur die <hi rend="underline">ganz gemeinen</hi> Specien der britischen Küsten, Grantia ciliata,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Leucosolenia botryoides etc) so würde ich dafür sehr dankbar sein. Bei <hi rend="underline">der ausserordentlichen Variabilität der Kalkschwämme</hi> kann ich <hi rend="underline">nicht genug Individuen</hi> von verschiedenen Standorten vergleichen. Grade von den britischen Küsten habe ich noch sehr wenig erhalten.—</p>
<p>Hoffentlich befinden Sie und Ihre liebe Familie sich wohl. Mir geht es recht gut. Mein Junge ist jetzt 9 Monate alt und fängt schon an, viel Pithecoides zu verlieren, ja selbst bereits zu philosophieren!<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen | Ihr treu ergebener | Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Calc-sponges | Ask Huxley’<ref target="#foot.f11"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName>Jena</placeName>
        <date>2. July 69.</date>
        <salute>Esteemed dear friend!</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>A few days ago I received the fifth edition of your “Origin of Species” and I thank you cordially for this new evidence of your kindness.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am very glad to see that your epoch-making work is still finding so many new readers every year, even though it is already spread all over the world in so many thousand copies and so many translations. I am especially pleased that you should live to experience the great satisfaction of witnessing with your own eyes the immense effect of the colossal advance which your work has created within biology, and to judge from this just how great its fame will be in the more distant future.</p> 
            <p>I am now preparing the second edition of my “Natürlichen  Schöpfungsgeschichte”, which will appear next year.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The number of works that develop the various aspects of your theory increases by the week, and so it is with the number of your followers. Among German naturalists of the <hi rend="underline">younger</hi> generation there is now no important opponent of your theory. I am especially pleased, however, that even most eminent older naturalists are converting to the theory of descent, such as for example <hi rend="underline">P. Harting</hi> in Utrecht and <hi rend="underline">M. Sars</hi> in Christiania, both of whom have written to me lately and expressed their full agreement.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p> 
        <p>In a few weeks’ time you will receive my “Entwickelungsgeschichte der  Siphonophoren”, which has now finally come out and which is accompanied by fourteen tables.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> At present I have been working diligently for almost a year on the <hi rend="underline">calcareous sponges</hi> (Calcispongiae),<ref target="#foot.f6"/> a most interesting class of animals which is also of very great importance for your theory. The organic “species” can be observed in some Grantia quasi “<hi rend="underline">in statu nascenti</hi>”. In order to compile the most complete natural history possible of these animals, I am going for a few weeks at the end of July to <hi rend="underline">Norway</hi> (Christiania, Bergen, Drontjhem)<ref target="#foot.f7"/>, where calcareous sponges can apparently be found in large numbers. I shall send you my preliminary results in a few weeks. I’m planning to publish a comprehensive “<hi rend="underline">Monograph on calcareous sponges</hi>” next year.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> So that the systematic part of the work will be quite complete, I am now requesting material from all sides. Should you or one of your friends be able to send me calcareous sponges (even if only the <hi rend="underline">very common</hi> species of the British coast, Grantia ciliata,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Leucosolenia botryoides etc), I would be very grateful indeed. Due to <hi rend="underline">the extraordinary variability of calcareous sponges</hi> I can <hi rend="underline">not</hi> compare <hi rend="underline">enough individuals</hi> from different locations. In particular, from the British coast, I have as yet received only very little.—</p> 
        <p>I hope you and your dear family are fine. I am quite well. My boy is now 9 months old and he is already beginning to lose much of the pithecoid, and even to philosophise already!<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p> 
        <p>With the most cordial greetings | Your loyally devoted | Haeckel</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 297–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref> was published in June 1869 (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-6794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from R. F. Cooke, 22 June 1869</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The second edition of Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Natural history of creation</hi> appeared in 1870 (Haeckel 1870a). CD’s annotated copy of Haeckel 1868 (the first edition) is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 358–60). His copy of Haeckel 1870a is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pieter Harting</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Michael Sars</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel refers to his study of the development of siphonophores (Haeckel 1869a). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 355). Siphonophores are hydroids of the order Siphonophorae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The current name for the class of calcareous sponges is Calcarea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Christiania is now Oslo; Haeckel also refers to Trondheim.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Die Kalkschwämme</hi> (Calcareous sponges) was published in 1872 (Haeckel 1872). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 357–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Grantia ciliata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Sycon ciliatum</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Haeckel refers to his son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5819.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walter Haeckel</ref>. In an earlier letter, Haeckel had described his son’s ‘atavistic movements’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6452.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 9 November 1868</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6823.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 9 July [1869]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>