<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11030">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alfred Espinas<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   1 July 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16807</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11030 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11030.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11030.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 163: 34</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>163: 34</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1537.xml">Espinas, A.-V.</persName>
                <placeName>Dijon</placeName>
                <date when="1877-07-01">1 July 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On painful state of CD’s reception in France.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">France</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Dijon,</placeName>
                    <date>1<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> juillet 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur et cher maitre,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Vous avez dit quelque part qu’on peut être convaincu pour des raisons philosophiques de la filiation des espèces;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> si vous n’aviez eu que ces raisons, il est probable que le Darwinisme ne serait pas né. C’est avec des arguments zoologiques et biologiques que le transformisme veut être soutenu— Vous ne trouverez donc pas étonnant qu’un philosophe de profession, dans une thè〈se〉 philosophique, garde sur ce point, une prudente réserve, et se borne à déclarer (p. 361) qu’il croit à l’universalité de la loi d’évolution.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Votre impartialité tiendra compte aussi des conditions de milieu dans lesqelles se meut un français qui desire entrer à l’heure qu’il est dans les facultés de l’Etat. Je n’insiste pas sur ces conditions: elles sont pénibles à dire surtout vis à vis d’un étranger. Je puis affirmer seulement que dans aucune thèse présentée a la faculté des lettres de Paris on n’a encore été aussi loin que je l’ai fait dans le sens de l’évolution.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>J’ajoute que—quelles que soient les modestes objections que je me suis permis d’élever contre quelques unes de vos vues, et bien que je ne sois pas disposé à aliéner mon indépendance d’esprit—cependant je considère votre oeuvre comme la plus importante du siècle avec celles de Comte et de Spencer.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Vous êtes pour moi comme pour la plupart de ceux qui etudient en Europe la psychologie zoologique, un maitre vénéré. <hi rend="underline">Tu pater et rerum inventor</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Mon essai est plein de votre nom; et tel chapitre n’est que le développement d’une page de votre <hi rend="underline">Descent of Man</hi>.</p>
<p>Je n’ai pas voulu vous dire ces choses avant d’avoir obtenu votre jugement. J’ai pris la liberté de vous le demander, parceque trop longtemps retenu en effet dans les études littéraires et metaphysiques, je ne savais vraiment que penser de ma tentative pour parler le langage de la science. Je vous remercie vivement de votre réponse.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Je regrette beaucoup d’avoir, bien involontairement en effet, altèré votre pensée. Je profiterai de vos remarques, je relirai vos écrits, et loin de rester indifférent à vos vues, je croirai toujours avoir progressé dans le mesure où je me serai inspiré de votre méthode.</p>
<p>Croyez-moi, cher Monsieur, votre dévoué, | A. Espinas | co-traducteur avec M. Ribot de la Psychologie de Spencer.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Dijon,</placeName>
                    <date>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> July 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Sir and dear master,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You said somewhere that one can be convinced on philosophical grounds of the descent of species;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> if you did not have any reasons other than these, it is likely that Darwinism would not have existed. It is with zoological and biological arguments that transmutation must be defended— You will not find it surprising that a professional philosopher, in a philosophical thesis, maintains a prudent reserve on this point, and limits himself to declaring (p. 361) that he believes in the universality of the law of evolution.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Your impartiality will also take account of the conditions of the milieu in which a Frenchman moves who wishes to enter at this time into an academic post. I do not insist on these conditions: they are painful to explain, especially to a foreigner. I can only affirm that in no thesis presented to the faculty of literature in Paris has anyone gone as far as I have in the direction of evolution.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I add that—whatever the modest objections that I allowed myself to raise against some of your opinions, and although I am not disposed to relinquish my independence of spirit—still I consider your work, with those of Comte and Spencer,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> the most important of the century. For me, as for most of those who study zoological psychology in Europe, you are a venerated master. <hi rend="underline">Tu pater et rerum inventor</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> My essay is full of your name; and each chapter is nothing but a development of a page of your <hi rend="underline">Descent of man</hi>.</p>
<p>I did not want to say these things before having obtained your judgment. I took the liberty of asking you for it, since, having been detained too long, in fact, in literary and metaphysical studies, I did not rightly know what to think of my attempt to speak the language of science. I thank you warmly for your reply.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I very much regret having altered, quite involuntarily in fact, your thought. I will profit by your remarks, I will reread your writings, and far from being indifferent to your views, I will always believe myself to have progressed insofar as I am inspired by your method.</p>
<p>Believe me, dear Sir, your devoted, | A. Espinas | co-translator with M. Ribot of Spencer’s psychology.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The reference has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Espinas taught philosophy at Dijon. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9524.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Espinas 1877</ref>, p. 361, a copy of which he had sent to CD (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alfred Espinas, [before 1 July 1877]</ref>), he wrote that evolution was the sole fundamental law.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9524.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Espinas 1877</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Des sociétés animales</hi>) was the doctoral thesis Espinas had submitted to the Sorbonne, Paris (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tort 1996</ref>). On the critical reception of CD’s theories in France, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3413.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harvey 2008</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tort 2008</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Auguste Comte</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Tu, pater, es rerum inventor</hi>: You, father, are the uncoverer of truths (Lucretius, <hi rend="italic">De rerum natura</hi> 3: 9. Espinas’s slight misquotation changes the meaning to, ‘You are the father and uncoverer of truths’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See the draft <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alfred Espinas, [before 1 July 1877]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Espinas translated Spencer’s <hi rend="italic">Principles of psychology</hi> with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8009.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Theodule Ribot</ref> (Espinas and Ribot trans. 1874–5).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>