<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-355">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. S. Henslow   18 [May 1837]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5238</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-355 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-355.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-355.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 42</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Darwin and Henslow</hi>: 127;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 283</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 17</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Henslow letters: 35 DAR/1/1/35)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Henslow letters: 35 DAR/1/1/35</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 36</placeName>
                <date when="1837-05-18">18 [May 1837]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml">Henslow, J. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Plans to apply to Government for assistance with publishing <hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Robert Brown has taken an interest in the fossil woods.</p> 
<p>CD is at work on his journal. Has not begun his geology <hi rend="italic">yet</hi>. Has seen much of Lyell.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Zoology</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_671">Brown, Robert (a)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Government</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>36 Gr<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Marlborough Street</placeName>
                    <date>18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Henslow</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was very glad to receive your letter. I wanted much to hear how you were getting on with your manifold labours.— Indeed I do not wonder you head began to ache; it is almost a wonder you have any head left.— Your account of the Gamblingay expedition was cruelly tempting, but I cannot anyhow leave London.— I wanted to pay my good dear people at Shrewsbury a visit of a few days but I found I could not manage it.— At present I am waiting for the signatures of the Duke of Somerset as President of the Linnæan; of L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Derby &amp; Whewell, to a statement of the value of my collection; the instant I get this, I shall apply to goverment, for assistance in engraving &amp; to publish the Zoology on some uniform plan.— It is quite ridiculous the time any operation requires, which depends on many people.— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown has been taking a good deal of interest in my affairs &amp; in a most kind manner. I want therefore to oblige him any way I can.— He was much pleased with the fossil woods &amp; has gone to the expence of having several of them cut &amp; ground.— The clump of trees which were growing vertically are allied to Araucaria, but in some respect resembling yews.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Some of the good wise people, till seeing the wood, thought I had mistaken <hi rend="underline">calcareous concretions</hi> for <hi rend="underline">silicified trees</hi>!— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown is very curious about the fungi from the beech trees in T. del Fuego.— He has some specimens, but is very curious to see mine, but I do not know whether he wants to describe them: as your hands are so full, would you object to send them to me, &amp; allow M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown to do what he likes with them.— If you particularly care about them, of course do not send them, but otherwise I should be glad to oblige M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown.— I have introduced my imperfect account of them in my journal.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> so that I should for my own sake be glad of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown’s inspection <hi rend="underline">soon.</hi> —</p>
<p>I have been working very steadily, but have only got two thirds through the journal part alone.— I find though I remain daily many hours at work the progress is very slow:—it is an awful thing to say to oneself, every fool and every clever man in England, if he chooses, may make as many illnatured remarks as he likes on this unfortunate sentence.</p>
<p>There is a very <hi rend="underline">remote</hi> possibility of my publishing my part before the Captains, in which case it would be out this summer.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> There are about half a dozen plants, of which if I do not know the names of genus or something about them, I must strike out long passages in my journal.— Will you have the kindness to tell me; a week or ten days before you leave Cambridge; so that those questions which are most indispensible to me; perhaps you would not grudge one day in answering.— This is in case I publish before autumn, otherwise when you return will be soon enough for me.— I have not begun my geology <hi rend="underline">yet</hi>!, though indeed I have been far from idle.— I give abstracts in my journal which cost much time.— I am greatly obliged to you, for talking with the Dons about the publication of my geology; the more I see of things the greater difficulty I anticipate on any other method.— Having seen a very great deal of Lyell, who is a most kind friend, I entertain great hopes that my geology will be of service.— I grieve to hear that the London University scheme will not bring you often to London.— But I will pay Cambridge a visit before very long &amp; we will have one more of those goods walks, that I used often to think of at the antipodes, as indeed I now do.—</p>
<p>Eyton is up here and working away famously.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He tells me to say that he has bought Freycinets voyage of L’Uranie,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and that he has 120 folio uncoloured plates and a quarto of letter press with a few pages imperfect at beginning, &amp; he says anyone may have them for three pounds.— I forgot to ask you: if I succeed with government and <hi rend="doubleUnderline">if</hi> afterwards it appears advisable, should you object to publish the botany of the Galapagos in it: as part of the fauna?— I certainly should like, if possible, some part of the botany kept together, where there are materials for any general result.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Dont trouble yourself to answer this letter, for every five minutes must be precious to you.— Pray remember me most kindly to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Henslow. Ever yours most truly | C. Darwin—</p>
<p>Remember me to L. Jenyns.— I daresay he is with you this very day at Gamblingay.— I wish I was: how pleasant a good ramble would be in those nice woods. If you decide to send the fungi, will you send them soon by coach.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 Gamblingay] ‘G’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘ex’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.6 it] <hi rend="italic">over full stop</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.7 of L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>] ‘of’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.8 to] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.15 are] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘were fine’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.16 had] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘was’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">1.17 <hi rend="italic">silicified</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">1.22 introduced my] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘ac’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.5 likes] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘can’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.2 are] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘one’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">3.3 genus] ‘g’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">3.9 which] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">3.15 Cambridge] ‘C’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘c’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">4.2 uncoloured] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">4.3 a quarto of] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi>; ‘of’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">4.6 publish] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">4.7 some] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">So described by Robert Brown. See <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> p. 406, for CD’s description of his extraordinary discovery of the fossilised trees in the Andes at a height of 7,000 feet, and also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-274.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. S. Henslow, 18 April 1835</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks,</hi> pp. 298–9. The fungus was eventually described by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_408.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Miles Joseph Berkeley</ref> in a paper for the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_602.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Berkeley 1845</ref>). The specimens are preserved in the Botany School, Cambridge.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Although CD’s volume of the <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative </hi></ref> was finished and in print by early 1838, publication was delayed until mid-1839, awaiting FitzRoy’s volumes. As Volume III of the <hi rend="italic">Narrative,</hi> it was called <hi rend="italic">Journal and</hi> <hi rend="italic">remarks, 1832–36,</hi> but it was almost immediately published separately under the title <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches into the geology and natural</hi> <hi rend="italic">history of the various countries visited by H.M.S. ‘Beagle’,</hi> etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1570.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Campbell Eyton</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2675.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freycinet 1824–44</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The Galápagos specimens were not described until 1845, after Henslow had turned CD’s botanical collection over to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (see J. D. Hooker 1845). The geographical distribution of the plants is discussed in J. D. Hooker 1846.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>