<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2354">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Egan<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   8 November [1858]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">160</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2354 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2354.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2354.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp &amp; ADraft 1p</note>
            <note type="postmark">NO 9 58</note>
                <relatedItem type="publication">
                    <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 184</bibl>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.160)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>160</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>206: 37</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1858-11-08">8 Nov [1858]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1474.xml">Egan, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Asks about dark stripes on shoulders and legs of Hungarian horses. Are stripes plainer in foal or adult?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">horses, Hungarian</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">maturity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I have just seen an article by you in the Gardeners Chronicle, &amp; I observe that you are a member of an Agricultural Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. <ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am very anxious for information on one point in Natural History, &amp; it has occurred to me that you might perhaps be willing to oblige a stranger, who is an old correspondent of the Chronicle, &amp; a friend of the Editor, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lindley.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But you may not have time or inclination, &amp; if I receive no answer to this, I am sure that I shall have not the least reason to complain, but rather to apologise for the liberty which I take in addressing you.—</p>
<p>My question refers to the colours of Horses, for I am trying to investigate the laws of inheritance of colours.— I have seen it stated in print that the Horses of Hungary, frequently have a dark stripe down the spine &amp; <hi rend="underline">sometimes a stripe on shoulders</hi> (sometimes double) <hi rend="underline">like that on the ass</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline">sometimes cross</hi> <hi rend="underline">stripes on the legs</hi>. I am anxious to know whether this really is the case, &amp; whether such stripes occur frequently either on the shoulders, or on the <hi rend="underline">front</hi> or <hi rend="underline">hind</hi> legs or on <hi rend="underline">both</hi>.</p>
<p>I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. wish to know, by comparison with some object, the colour of any horse with such stripes. But what I most want to know, &amp; which I have in vain endeavoured to find out, is whether such stripes are plainer in the foal or in the full-grown horse. In England such stripes are observed only on dun-coloured horses (By dun I mean dark cream-colour mixed with some brown), but I have not been able to find out what the colours of the parents were; whether the crossing of any other two colours will produce a dun.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>As Hungary is a great horse-breeding country, perhaps you could find out something on these heads, <hi rend="underline">from persons on whom you could</hi> <hi rend="underline">rely</hi>; &amp; if you are willing to oblige me by taking so much trouble, it will be a very great favour &amp; kindness,</p>
<p>&amp; I beg leave to remain, Sir, | Your obliged servant | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 &amp; a] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.4 (sometimes double)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.6 what] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘wheth’</note>
                </div>
<div type="cdnotes">
    <ab><ref target="#foot.f5"/></ab>
    <note><p rend="centre">—Questions about Asses &amp; Horses Stripes.—</p>
        <p rend="centre">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> James Egasy Hotel Queen of England Pesth</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Asses</hi>— Are the legs ever transversely striped in any slight *or considerable [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] degree like those of the [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] zebra? Are the front or hind legs most striped? Is the shoulder-stripe ever double? Does the shoulder (&amp; spinal stripe) ever wholly disappear.? Are the asses ever marbled or mottled *with any colours [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] like a grey-horse? If any such cases occur, please state whether frequently—&amp; especially describe general colour of animal, &amp; whether large or small. <hi rend="italic">Mules</hi>. Same queries. <hi rend="italic">Horses</hi>. Are the legs, front or hind, or both, ever transversely striped? Does a shoulder stripe, though probably faint, ever occur.? Such [<hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘It’] stripes would probably be observed only in Duns (ie dark cream-colour mixed with brown) or Mouse-duns, or [<hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘in’ <hi rend="italic">and after del</hi> ‘or’] cream-coloured or [<hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘&amp;"] perhaps in chesnuts. If such sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> occur, please give particulars, of size &amp; colour of horse or pony. *Any horse with leg or shoulder stripe would probably have the spinal stripe [<hi rend="italic">added</hi>] It would be particularly interesting for me to hear, though probably impossible to be ascertained, whether any coloured horse, having any such stripes., was a breed always or generally so characterised, or an accidental individual.— It is possible that foals might have such marks &amp; not the mature animals.—</p></note>
</div>
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD addressed this letter and the one of 25 November [1858] to ‘James Egasy’, the name on the notice printed in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> (see n. 2, below). It appears, however, that the name was given incorrectly. A note on the letter of 25 November reads: ‘This lettre, of this great man, was written to my dear father <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1474.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Egan</ref>.’ It has not been possible to identify Egan, but the National Library of Hungary lists an author by this name.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Under the section ‘Home Correspondence’ in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’</hi> <hi rend="italic">Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 6 November 1858, pp. 813–14, there is a letter signed ‘James Egasy, member of the Agricultural and Gardening Societies for Hungaria, Hotel Queen of England, Pesth, Oct. 18.’ The letter gives information about horticulture in Hungary and announces the foundation of a gardening society on 13 November 1858.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his letter (see n. 2, above), Egan stated that he had been a reader of the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> ‘for a long time’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. C. Eyton, 4 October [1858]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The note is in DAR 206 (Letters) and served as the basis of questions sent to other correspondents: it is marked, ‘Questions (to China) about Asses &amp; Horses Stripes’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>