<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10172">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From N. A. Severtsov   25 September [1875]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10715</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10172 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10172.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10172.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 143</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 143</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4301.xml">Severtsov, N. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1875-09-25">25 Sept [1875]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends CD the 2d part of his travels into the Tien-shan mountains [<hi rend="italic">Erforschung des Thian-Schan Gebirgs-Systems</hi> (1875)].</p>  
<p>Has written a paper on the ranges and systematics of wild sheep and on modifications probably resulting from competition with domestic sheep, which he wishes to translate into English and would like to see appended to <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses sexual selection in thrushes; it apparently modifies one species into another.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sheep, domestic</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sheep, wild</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">thrushes</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erforschung des Thain-Schan Gebirgs-Systems</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Tien-shan mountains</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Severtsov, N. A. 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have the honour to send you the second part of my travel into the inner part of the Tian-shan mountains; I think you have already received the first part, which I left to Mr. Dresser, Tenderden street 6, for sending this book to you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It contains general observations about the nature, the geological and orographical formation and the nomade inhabitants of these very little known innermost asiatic mountains, and some zoological observations, which may be perhaps of some interest for you. If you would allow me to translate in english a monographical study about the relations between systematic affinities and geographical range of the wild sheep, and the probable influence of struggle for life with the domesticated sheep on some modifications of zoological characters of the different wild species—and if you find this paper worthy to be added as an appendix to a new edition of your “domesticated animals and cultivated plants”— (This book I have read only in a russian translation, not english, and therefore translate again the russian title of it.) that will be an honour of which I dreamed for two years, since that paper is published in russian.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> And now I have a fear that such a suggestion is an indiscreet one. I fear also that this very first attempt of investigating a quite untouched question, and a difficult one will prove weak enough—but its subject is one of high interest and a beginning must be done—may abler men continue—and therefore the protection of your high authority to my essay may be useful for provoking new investigations.</p>
<p>I have also left to Mr. Dresser, for showing you, a sery of central asiatic thrushes, to which he promised to add some instructive chinese specimens from Mr. Swinhoe.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> This sery is to illustrate the modification of Turdus mystacinus into Turd. atrogularis, by sexual selection: the males having originally a spotted throat (T. mystacinus), this growing gradually blacker, to complete black   Now the black throated males are the most numerous, their number increasing with each generation; the females in inverse proportion, mostly maintaining the original spotted throat of both sexes—but some females already black throated like the males, though not so completely.</p>
<p>By this hereditary extension of male characters to both sexes this change will appearingly come to a close: the stages of modifications being so.</p>
<p>1. Both sexes alike, spotted throat; Turd. mystacinus; males then changing;</p>
<p>2. A great sexual difference; male alone black throated; females then changing</p>
<p>3. Both sexes alike again, and both changed in the same way from 1), both black throated.</p>
<p>Now is a transition stage between 2 and 3, and very few males of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> stage, perhaps atavistic; and one specimen somewhat intermediate between Turd. mystacinus and the european T. musicus.</p>
<p>The specimens of Mr. Swinhoe illustrate the origin of Turd. fuscatus and T. Naumanni from the same old type.</p>
<p>A paper of me about this will appear in Mr Dresser’s birds of Europe, with a few separate prints, the first of which for your.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I have the honour, Sir, of being with utmost respect | most truly yours | N. Severtzow</p>
<p><lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Berlin, 25 September.</p>
<p>If you honour me with an answer, please send if so: 6, Tenterden-str., Hanover square—to Mr. H. E. Dresser for N. Severtzov.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8912.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sewerzow 1875</ref> (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7651.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Eeles Dresser</ref> visited Down with Severtsov on 13 September 1875 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13836F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. E. Dresser, [10 September 1875]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10156.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. H. Darwin, 13 September [1875]</ref>). There are copies of both parts of Severtsov’s travels in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8912.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sewerzow 1875</ref>; the text is in German). The pages have not been cut and there is a note on both parts, ‘not read’. The Tien Shan mountains are in China and Kyrgyzstan. Tenterden Street is in Mayfair, London.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The Russian translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> was V. O. Kovalevsky trans. 1868–9. The second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> was already at an advanced stage (see CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)), although it was not published until the second half of February 1876 (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ circular</hi> 1876). Severtsov’s monograph on sheep is <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Severtsov 1873</ref>; it was not referred to in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 2d ed.</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4642.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Swinhoe</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8913.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dresser 1871–96</ref>, 2: 85–6; no copy has been found in the Darwin Libraries at CUL or Down. In his description of <hi rend="italic">Turdus atrigularis</hi>, the black-throated thrush (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8913.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dresser 1871–96</ref>, 2: 85–6), Dresser discussed Severtsov’s separation of <hi rend="italic">T. mystacinus</hi> from <hi rend="italic">T. atrigularis</hi> as a distinct species, but remained doubtful of Severtsov’s conclusion. He pointed to the high degree of individual variation among Siberian thrushes as the chief reason for the ongoing confusion in determining species. <hi rend="italic">Turdus musicus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">T. iliacus</hi> (the redwing). The name <hi rend="italic">T. fuscatus</hi> had been used by different authors for different species.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>