<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12461">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To G. J. Romanes   5 February 1880</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">571</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12461 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12461.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12461.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="28">28</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 147: 372</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 51</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.571)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>571</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1880-02-05">5 Feb 1880</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On GJR’s work on mental evolution in animals. Emphasises "love" among animals.</p>
            <p>Comments on stimulation of plants.</p>
            <p>On pleasure and pain.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-02" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-12-06" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2019-01-07" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-05-23" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2019-05-23" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington.S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Feb 5. 80</date>
                    <salute>My dear Romanes</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>As I feared, I cannot be of the least use to you. I couldn’t venture to say anything about babies without reading my expression book, &amp; paper on infants; or about animals without reading the Descent of man &amp; referring to my notes; &amp; it is a great wrench to my mind to change from one subject to another.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I will however hazard one or two remarks. Firstly I should have thought that the word ‘love’ (not sexual passion) as shown very low in scale to offspring &amp; apparently to comrades, ought to have come in more prominently in your table than appears to be the case.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Secondly if you give any instance of the appreciation of different stimulants by plants, there is a much better case than that given by you. Namely that of the glands of Drosera which can be touched roughly 2 or 3 times &amp; do not transmit any effect, but do so if pressed by a weight of <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>78,000</mn></mfrac></math></formula> grain (Insectiv Plants 263). On the other hand the filament of Dionæa may be quietly loaded with a much greater weight with no effect, while a touch by a hair causes the lobes to close instantly.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> This has always seemed to me a marvellous fact.</p>
<p>Thirdly I have been accustomed to look at the coming in of the sense of pleasure &amp; pain as one of the most important steps in the development of mind; &amp; I should think ought to be prominent in your table.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The sort of progress which I have imagined is that a stimulus produced some effect at the point affected; &amp; that the effect radiated at first in all directions, &amp; then that certain definite advantageous, lines of transmission were acquired, inducing definite reaction in certain lines. Such transmission afterwards became associated in some unknown way with pleasure or pain. These sensations led at first to all sorts of violent action such as the wriggling of a worm, which was of some use. All the organs of sense would be at the same time excited. Afterwards definite lines of action would be found to be the most useful &amp; would be practiced. But it is of no use my giving you my crude notions</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>The diagram is returned as <hi rend="underline">may</hi> wish to show it some one else</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Romanes’s letter, to which this letter is the second response, has not been found, but Romanes evidently asked CD to comment on a diagram showing the evolution of emotions and intellect in the animal world; the diagram was later published in <hi rend="italic">Mental evolution in animals</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10553.xml">G. J. Romanes 1883</ref>, facing the title page). For CD’s initial response, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12454.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 3 February 1880</ref> and n. 1. There is a section in the published diagram in G. J. Romanes 1883 that correlates the development of instincts and intellect in different groups of animals with the age at which these faculties develop in a human infant up to the age of 15 months. CD had discussed these topics in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8641.xml">‘Biographical sketch of an infant’</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In the published diagram, under the heading ‘Products of emotional development’, Romanes included ‘parental affection’ and ‘social feelings’ at the same level as ‘sexual selection’; the term ‘sexual passion’ does not appear on the chart.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Romanes did not include any mention of plants in the diagram. CD had noted that the glands of <hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> (common or round-leaved sundew) did not bend, even when touched with considerable force, if touched momentarily, but bent to the slightest prolonged pressure, while a filament of <hi rend="italic">Dionaea muscipula</hi> (Venus fly trap) was highly sensitive to momentary touch but less so to prolonged pressure (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, pp. 289–90). Romanes discussed the different types of sensitivity displayed by these plants in G. J. Romanes 1883, pp. 49–51.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Romanes included a category ‘pleasure and pains’ as a relatively early acquisition under the heading ‘Products of intellectual development’ in his published diagram.</note>
        </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>