<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1073">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Bernhard Studer<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   21 March [1847]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1104</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1073 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1073.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1073.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Burgerbibliothek Bern, Bern, Switzerland</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_41.xml">Bern</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1847-03-21">21 Mar [1847]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4602.xml">Studer, Bernhard</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends copy of <hi rend="italic">South America</hi>.</p>  
<p>Will consult BS’s article in the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>.</p>  
<p>Recommends article by Daniel Sharpe ["On slaty cleavage", <hi rend="italic">J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</hi> 3 (1847): 74–105].</p>  
<p>Cites his description of thin laminae in volcanic rocks in <hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi>. Suggests similar process may have affected metamorphic schists.</p>  
<p>Thanks him for offer of his book [<hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der physikalischen Geographie und Geologie</hi> (1844–7)]. Since he reads German poorly, BS should send book only if short and inexpensive.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">laminae</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">metamorphic schists</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">slaty cleavage</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Bulletin unspecified</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Lehrbuch der physikalischen Geographie und Geologie</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">South America</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Volcanic islands</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Sharpe, Daniel 1847</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Studer, Bernhard 1844–1847</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">volcanoes and earthquakes</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>March 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Permit me to thank you for your extremely kind letter: I have no doubt my small volume on S. America will reach you soon, as I directed my publishers to send it, at the same time that I addressed you: I fear you will find little in it that will interest you, except perhaps the short discussion on cleavage &amp; foliation.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Had I known that you were so well acquainted with English, I should have taken the liberty of writing to you at rather greater length respecting your interesting views on the structure of the Alpine metamorphic schists;—but so far from knowing that you had done me the very great honour of making others acquainted with my volume on Coral Reefs,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I did not suppose that you would ever have heard my name.— I am glad to hear of your paper in the Bulletin<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; will take an early opportunity of consulting. I beg to call your attention to a paper in the last number of the Journal of our Geolog. Soc., by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D. Sharpe, on cleavage, which strikes me as very important.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It is a difficult paper, I find, to understand, but the leading idea appears capital,—namely the proof from the distortion of known fossil-shells, that there has been regular &amp; great displacement along the planes of cleavage.— In a small volume on Volcanic Islands published by me about two years ago, I have described in detail some curious laminated volcanic rocks, composed of crystals of feldspar, quartz &amp; diopside &amp; oxide of iron, in <hi rend="underline">parallel</hi> &amp; excessively thin layers,—so as to resemble some gneisses.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> these layers, no doubt, have been produced by the flowing movement of the lava, just before consolidation, in the same manner as the blue &amp; white layers are produced in a glacier, according to Prof. Forbes.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I am greatly tempted to extend this view to the foliation of the metamorphic schists, not that I suppose that these ever flowed as lava, but that they have been stretched in uniform planes, by widely-extended elevatory movements. The planes of “tearing” or “of lesser &amp; greater tension” determining the planes of crystallization &amp; separation of the constituent minerals. The parallelism in <hi rend="underline">direction</hi> or strike, though not in dip of the principal axes of elevation with the strike of the planes cleavage in almost every country points towards this conclusion. And now we know from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sharpe that there has been actual movement along the planes of cleavage in clay-slate;— Whatever explanation is applicable to cleavage, I 〈am〉 satisfied, in accordance with your statements, mu〈st〉 include the foliation of the metamorphic schists.—</p>
<p>But I ought to apologise for troubling you with so long a letter; &amp; I can only plead the kindness of your note as my excuse.— I beg to thank you cordially for your offer of your work “sur la physique du globe”;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I do read German but most imperfectly &amp; with much difficulty &amp; without making any progress towards facility (a remark made by many Englishmen who seldom can boast of a turn for languages), &amp; therefore, if you will permit me speak quite frankly, I should be extremely much pleased to receive it, if it is not a very large &amp; expensive work; for in this latter case, it would, I grieve to say, be almost thrown away on me.</p>
<p>Pray believe me, dear Sir, with much respect, your faithful &amp; obliged servant | C. Darwin</p>
<p>My address in London, for parcels is 7. Park St<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. | Grosvenor Square</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.7 views on] ‘o’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.6 or strike, though not in dip] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.6 strike of the 2.7] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The recipient is identified by the cover which is addressed to ‘Professor B. Studer | Berne | Switzerland’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See CD’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1054.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Bernhard Studer, 20 January [1847]</ref>, for an earlier discussion of this subject. See also <hi rend="italic">South</hi> <hi rend="italic">America</hi>, pp. 162–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Studer 1844–7</ref>, 1: 197–206, includes a number of CD’s conclusions in a description of coral reef formation.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Studer 1847a. This contains a more detailed discussion of the subject of Studer 1847b, namely, that the Alpine gneiss stratification at Mettenberg could not have been sedimentary. See letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4311.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Sharpe</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1052.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[19 January 1847]</ref>, and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4602.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bernhard Studer</ref>, 20 January [1847].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Sharpe 1847, read 2 December 1846.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>, pp. 65–72. The analogy between glaciers and lava flow is on p. 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2593.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. D. Forbes 1842</ref>, pp. 350–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Studer 1844–7</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>