<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11483">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. S. Wilson   24 April 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13829</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11483 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11483.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11483.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 419</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 148: 364</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>148: 364</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-04-24">24 Apr 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5176.xml">Wilson, A. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends specimens of Russian wheat variety <hi rend="italic">kubanka</hi>, which after sowing for two years degenerates into a different variety, <hi rend="italic">saxonka</hi>. Suggests that ASW conduct experiments.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">wheat, kubanka</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">wheat, saxonka</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Russia</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">degeneration</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reversion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">years</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down</placeName>
                    <date>April 24. 1878</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I send you herewith some specimens which may perhaps interest you, as you have so carefully studied the vars. of wheat. Any how they are of no use to me as I have neither knowledge or time sufficient. They were sent me by the Governor of the Province of Samara in Russia, at the request of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Asher (son of the great Berlin publisher) who farmed for some years in the province.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The specimens marked <hi rend="underline">Kubanka</hi> is a very valuable kind, but which keeps true only when cultivated in fresh Steppe-land in Samara, and in Saratoff.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> After two years it degenerates into the var. <hi rend="underline">Saxonica</hi> or its synonym <hi rend="underline">Ghirca</hi>. The latter alone is imported into this country. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Asher says that it is universally known, and he has himself witnessed the fact, that if grain of the Kubanka is sown in the same steppe-land for more than two years it changes into Saxonica. He has seen a field with parts still Kubanka and the remainder Saxonica. On this account the government in letting steppe-land contract that after two years wheat must not be sown until an interval of eight years. The ears of the two kinds appear different as you will see, but the chief difference is in the quality of the grains. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Asher has witnessed sales of equal weights of Kubanka and Saxonica grain, and the price of the former was to that of the latter as 7 to 4. The peasants say that the change commences in the terminal grain of the ear. The most remarkable point as D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Asher positively asserts is that there are no intermediate varieties; but that a grain produces a plant yielding either true Kubanka or true Saxonica. He thinks that it would be interesting to sow here both kinds in good and bad wheat soil and observe the result. Should you think it worth while to make any such trial, and should you require further information, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Asher whose address I enclose, will be happy to give any in his power.</p>
                    <p>I hope that I have not troubled you uselessly and remain, my dear Sir | Yours faithfully | Ch. Darwin.</p>
                    <p>P.S.— | I received Rimpau safely.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_164.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georg Michael Asher</ref> was the son of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8242.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolf Asher</ref>; he lived in Samara and Saratov in Russia for a period in the 1870s. G. M. Asher had sent CD the wheat specimens in February, after receiving them from Mikhail Nikolaevich Galkin-Vraskoi, the governor of Saratov province (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-11357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. M. Asher, 14 February 1878</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD obtained this and the following information about Russian wheat from Asher’s <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to John Murray, 1 November 1877</ref>, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11228.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. M. Asher, 7 November 1877</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Wilson had borrowed CD’s copies of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4009.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wilhelm Rimpau’s</ref> papers on the varying degrees of self-sterility in different varieties of wheat and rye (Rimpau 1877a and 1877b; <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11372.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. S. Wilson, 23 February 1878</ref> and n. 7).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>