<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6428">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. P. M. Weale   23 October 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7938</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6428 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6428.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6428.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 46.1: 93a–94a</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>46.1: 93a–94a</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4989.xml">Weale, J. P. M.</persName>
                <placeName>Bedford, Cape of Good Hope</placeName>
                <date when="1868-10-23">23 Oct 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Describes <hi rend="italic">Lappago aleina</hi>, a species of South African grass,</p> 
            <p>and reports his observations on locusts and their feeding habits.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">locusts</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">grass</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Lappago aleina</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">South Africa</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">habit</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00193_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00193_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="93ar">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00193.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00193_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00193.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="93av">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00194.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00194_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00194.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="93br">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00195.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00195_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00195.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="93bv">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00196.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00196_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00196.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i5" n="94r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00197.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00197_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00197.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i6" n="94v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00198.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00198_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00198.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i7" n="94ar">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00199.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00199_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00199.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i8" n="94av">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00200.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00200_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00046-00001-000-00200.dzi" width="3823px" height="6348px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bedford | Cape of Good Hope</placeName>
                    <date>23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. October 1868</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been waiting sometime with the hope of having something of interest to communicate to you, but am sorry to say that I have little to add to former communications.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Your last letter somehow or another went to Natal, &amp; therefore did not come to hand till very late.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I was very much interested by what you wrote to me about the locust dung having grass seeds in it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The particular grass, to which I referred was “<hi rend="underline">Lappago aliena</hi> Spr.” Its glumes are covered with minute hooked hairs, by which it adheres to the wool of sheep, &amp; has become a very great nuisance to sheep farmers, by whom it is known here as the “carrot seed”, to which it has a sort of analogical resemblance.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>It generally springs up after rain, &amp; is very sweet &amp; much liked by the sheep as a pasture. Old farmers say that formerly it did not grow in the grass country, but was confined to the Karroo. I cannot however affirm this as correct, &amp; I was suspicious about the authority for the following reason.</p>
<p>Cape wool was formerly noted for its bad get up, &amp; it is still in bad repute, but about two years ago the London brokers complained very much about the appearance of the ‘Carrot seed’ in the staple, &amp; the attention of the farmers was directed to it. As a rule farmers only observe plants which in some way affect their pockets, &amp; it was then that I was told that this seed had only been noticed since the last influx of locusts. One thing is quite certain that Karroo grasses of late, as also many Karroo shrubs such as ‘Chrysocoma tenuifolia’ have spread into the sweet grass country, &amp; many sweet grasses into the sour grass country on the coast.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Last year, while riding from this to Kaffraria I particularly noticed the manner in which this grass had in places sprung up amongst the sour grasses, as also another kind—I think a ‘Festuca’—but am not certain—along the road sides throughout Kaffraria, although but seldom found in the sour grass itself.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> This last species is the principal pasture for sheep on which they thrive better than any other kind, &amp; is the characteristic grass of the sweet grass country.</p>
<p>I have been able to watch the locusts very carefully as we have this last year had the largest swarms, which have been known for a long time</p>
<p>When the old ones came down last March, it was astonishing to see the destruction they caused throughout all the sweet grass country. Although large flights passed over this village very few remained here, as the pasturage just in the vicinity is rank, coarse &amp; sour, but at about 12 miles from here they committed great havoc on a farm belonging to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fuller, one of the principal sheep farmers near here.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>They appeared on the wing at about 9 am, &amp; never left the farm but were constantly arriving till sundown. Both the ground &amp; the air was dense with them. After the fine rains the whole farm was a waving field of grass in the morning studded here &amp; there with the “Acacia horrida”, &amp; the pasturage intermixed with a few Karroo bushes, such as Chrysocoma, Melolobium, Pentzia &amp;c<ref target="#foot.f8"/>   On the rises are little valleys rather densely covered with bushes of different kind, &amp; there the grass was up to ones middle. The next day almost every patch of sweet grass had been cleared out, &amp; large spaces of bare ground had taken the place of a luxuriant meadow.</p>
<p>The locusts are I think without exception more cunning than any kind of insect, excepting “Hemiptera”. If the wind be not blowing at the time you may ride through a large swarm, as dense as a a heavy snow storm, &amp; yet hardly one will touch you.</p>
<p>If, when they have just risen on the wing, a strong wind springs up they will travel a very long distance without stopping, but if once settled to feed they are exceedingly difficult to move, &amp; care very little about smoke or fire. Towards night, when settled, they present a most singular appearance, &amp; are a characteristic of a very weird landscape. One evening I observed them with the setting sun shining full over the plain. Every shrub &amp; bush was covered with them, &amp; immense heaps were congregated wherever they could get shelter.</p>
<p>The silvery light on their wings, &amp; the reddish earthy tint of their bodies had a most singular aspect, as if all the trees were covered with a half smothered living fire, &amp; I regretted that I was unable to sketch the scene. I tried to photograph a swarm which settled here in the village but the plate turned out a failure owing to the constant motion. I send you a copy of it such as it is.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>The old ones invariably fly towards the sea, but never except in very strong winds, venture as far. The young on the contrary, as soon as hatched, seem instinctively to begin hopping inland. At the present time the whole country is alive with these young pests. It is curious to notice the predilection the locusts have for certain kinds of food. Where they can secure plenty of sweet grass, they seldom touch the crops, but when the former is scarce they clear a crop in a very short time.</p>
<p>In eating both the grass &amp; the corn they climb up the stalks &amp; devour the grain or bite it off so that it falls to the ground. I have seen whole crops of wheat &amp; oats thus destroyed. Leguminous plants they generally avoid, &amp; I have seen a garden in which the peas &amp; beans were untouched although every other vegetable had been destroyed.</p>
<p>I have been told though I have never myself observed it that in a narrow valley, where they had cleared everything else they even attacked the foliage of the Blue Gum, notwithstanding its strong &amp; peculiar odour &amp; taste.</p>
<p>Since I last wrote I noticed a curious instance of irritability of stamens, in “Schizanthus purpureus” which I noticed whilst growing in my friend M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. MacOwans Garden at Grahamstown.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> We were talking on the subject, when I said “Let us try this plant, it looks a likely subject,” &amp; were much interested by the result. As I was there only a day I was unable to give the subject a closer examination.</p>
<p>Near King Williamstown I observed in last February a great many striped mules belonging to the Commissariat, one especially its legs were regularly barred from the hoof up to the haunches &amp; the stripes inside the leg were as distinct almost as a zebra’s only of a different colour.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>“Queries about Expression”<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>1. A Kafir girl on hearing the price of an article, raised her eyebrows, &amp; at the same time whistled, just as a European might.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>4. The hand placed over the mouth in a contemplative manner, the head bent &amp; eyes deflected down.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>I had an opportunity of writing to Herr Mauch, when he was at D’Urban, Natal prior of his departure for the interior, &amp; sent him a copy of your questions asking him particularly to make observations on the subject on interior natives, thinking that they would be of great value to you.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> He has promised to give his close attention to the subject. I also sent a copy to the Natal Natural History Society through M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Sanderson, the well known botanical collector.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>I am very busy drawing &amp; dissecting all the orchids I can lay my hands on, &amp; any rare plants, by which means I hope we may someday be able to continue the Thesaurus, which D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Harvey’s death has closed.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>I must thank you very much for your photograph which I esteem very much, &amp; enclose you mine as requested. I have not yet seen your new work but hope shortly to receive it, &amp; look forward to it with great interest.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>Meanwhile Believe me, my dear Sir | faithfully Yours | J. P Mansel Weale</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.2 Lappago aliena] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>10.1 If, … the ground. 13.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>13.2 I have seen … destroyed. 13.5] ‘Locusts’ <hi rend="italic">added and circled ink</hi></note>
                <note>13.3 Leguminous plants] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>14.1 I have been … interest 22.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>17.1 “Queries … down. 19.2] ‘S. Africa | 22’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The most recent extant letter from Weale is that of [10 December 1867] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The most recent extant letter to Weale is that of 23 January [1868].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">A small packet of locust dung was enclosed with the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5581.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter from Weale of 7 July 1867</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15). In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5714.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Weale of 9 December [1867]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>), CD reported that he had found seeds in the dung. CD had sown the seeds and sent the grasses to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> for identification; for Hooker’s replies, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [20 May 1868]</ref>, n. 3, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6254.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 22 June 1868</ref>. CD reported on his experiment in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, p. 439.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">It had been suggested to Weale that locusts might disseminate ‘certain obnoxious grasses’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. P. M. Weale, 7 July 1867</ref>, where the phrase is mistranscribed as ‘certain obnoxious masses’). A modern synonym for <hi rend="italic">Lappago aliena</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Tragus racemosus</hi>, the large carrot-seed grass (G. E. G. Russell <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1990, pp. 337–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Chrysocoma tenuifolia</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">C. ciliata</hi>, or bitterbush, is indigenous to the more arid Karoo (or Karroo) and is still considered an invasive plant in the south-eastern grasslands of South Africa; <hi rend="italic">Tragus racemosus</hi>, unpalatable to livestock, has also invaded overgrazed grasslands (Huntley ed. 1989, pp. 113–14, 215). The Great Karoo lay inland, to the west of Bedford.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Tragus racemosus</hi> is often found on disturbed ground such as roadsides. There are eight indigenous species of <hi rend="italic">Festuca</hi> in South Africa, as well as an introduced species that thrives on disturbed ground. See G. E. G. Russell <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1990, pp. 168–71, 337. ‘Kaffraria’ initially comprised south-eastern territories colonised by the Portuguese and British, but by the mid nineteenth century indicated a more limited area that had come to be inhabited by the Xhosa people (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The brown locust (<hi rend="italic">Locustana pardalina</hi>) swarmed Cape Colony from 1862 to 1876, coming from the Karoo, further inland (Fuller ed. 1907, p. 54; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2468.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Faure 1932</ref>). Mr Fuller has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Two <hi rend="italic">Melobium</hi> species and six <hi rend="italic">Pentzia</hi> species indigenous to the Karoo still persist in South African grasslands that are used for grazing (see Wells <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1986, pp. 352, 403–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The photograph has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Schizanthus purpureus</hi> has not been identified. <hi rend="italic">Schizanthus</hi> is a genus native to Chile. On the significance of ‘irritability of stamens’, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Henslow, 6 November 1865</ref> and n. 7. Weale refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6263.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter MacOwan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD recorded similar observations by others in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 42. Weale had not yet received his copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (see n. 18, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">For CD’s printed list of queries about expression, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix V.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD cited Weale for this observation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 286. The term ‘Kafir’ was used to refer to the Xhosa people of south-eastern Africa.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD cited Weale for this observation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 230.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">There is no record of correspondence between CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6299.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Gottlieb Mauch</ref>; CD did not cite him in <hi rend="italic">Expression.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Weale probably refers to the Natal Agricultural and Horticultural Society, of which John Sanderson was president (Gunn and Codd 1981).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Weale refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Harvey’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Capensis: or, illustrations of the South African flora</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3421.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harvey 1859–63</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Weale refers to <hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi> Weale’s photograph has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>