<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6366">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. B. Meyer<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   15 September 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10024</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6366 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6366.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6366.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German) damaged †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 165</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 165</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3306.xml">Meyer, A. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1868-09-15">15 Sept 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends essay by Karl Bettelheim.</p>
            <p>Describes preparations for scientific journey.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_424">Bettelheim, Karl</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin Kanonierstrasse 30 Part. links</placeName>
                    <date>15 Sept 1868</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Im Auftrage meines Freundes D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Karl Bettelheim in Wien erlaube ich mir Ihnen diesen kleinen Aufsatz “über bewegliche Körperchen im Blute” zu überreichen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Derselbe dürfte nicht ohne Interesse von Ihnen gelesen werden, wenn wir uns auch nicht zu irgendwe〈lchen〉 weitergehenden Folgerungen daraus verleiten lassen wollen.</p>
<p>Hochverehrter Herr! Es ist die Absicht des Untergezeichneten sich nach Beendigung seiner vorbereitenden Studien dazu, für mehre Jahre in die Tropen zu begeben und zwar will er nach Java, 〈    〉 die Inseln des ostindischen 〈Archi〉pels, Australien—Ame〈rika〉 bereisen. Seine Studien haben sich auf medicinischen Gebieten—er ist Arzt—hauptsächlich drum Physiologie—und jetzt auf allgemein naturwissenschaftlichen, besonders Zoologie—bewegt, jedoch beabsichtigt er nicht fortzugehen ehe er nicht auch in Botanik u Geologie gewisse Kenntnisse erreicht hat, um möglichst umfassende Beobachtungen und Sammlungen machen zu können.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Seine Vorbereitungen werden ihn mindestens noch ein Jahr in Europa aufhalten u er möchte hierdurch bei Ihnen anfragen ob es ihm gestattet wäre ehe er fortgeht sich Ihnen vorstellen zu dürfen, um von Ihnen noch durch jene 〈  〉lichen Punkte bereichert zu werden, die Ihrem umfassenden 〈G〉eiste zu Gebote stehen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Er schätzt sich glücklich in einer Zeit zu leben in der die organischen morphologischen Naturwissenschaften einen so ungeheuren Impuls erhalten haben und bittet die Hochachtung entgegen zu nehmen, die er Ihrem Geiste und Ihrer Arbeit zollt.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Adolf Meyer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin Kanonierstrasse 30 ground floor left</placeName>
                    <date>15 Sept 1868</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On behalf of my friend, Dr. Karl Bettelheim in Vienna, allow me to present you with this little essay “On mobile corpuscles in the blood”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It should not be without interest to you, although we should not let ourselves be misled to any further conclusions from it.</p>
<p>Most esteemed Sir! It is the intention of the undersigned, after completion of his preliminary studies on the topic, to visit the tropics for some years, and indeed he will travel to Java, 〈    〉 the islands of the East Indian Archipelago, Australia—America. His studies have focused on medicine—he is a doctor—mainly on physiology—and now more generally on natural science, especially zoology; however, he does not intend to depart before having acquired some knowledge of botany and geology as well, in order to make the most comprehensive observations and collections possible.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> His preparations will keep him in Europe for at least another year, and thus he would like to inquire whether he might be permitted to you on those 〈    〉 points that are encompassed by your comprehensive genius.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>He counts himself lucky to live at a time when the organic morphological natural sciences have received such an immense impulse and asks you to accept the expression of his high regard for your genius and your work.</p>
<p>Dr Adolf Meyer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see part II: 744.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Bettelheim’s article, ‘Ueber bewegliche Körperchen im Blute’ was on the front page of a weekly newspaper for physicians, <hi rend="italic">Wiener medizinische Presse</hi>, 29 March 1868. An annotated clipping, on which CD wrote ‘Pangenesis’, is in the Darwin Archive–CUL (DAR 193: 31).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Meyer spent at least three years (1870 to 1873) travelling and collecting in the Celebes, visiting New Guinea and the Philippine Islands. Before his travels, Meyer studied medicine and natural history in Berlin. See <hi rend="italic">Auk</hi> 28: 519.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">There is no record of a visit by Meyer to Down House. Meyer and CD did correspond further (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6990.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter from A. B. Meyer, 16 November 1869)</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>