<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6846">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Louis Rérolle   30 July 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10508</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6846 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6846.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6846.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 131</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 131</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3901.xml">Rérolle, Louis</persName>
                <placeName>Lyons</placeName>
                <date when="1869-07-30">30 July 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Progressing with translation of new footnotes for <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi>. Asks for help with a few words.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Orchids</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">French</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1584">Rerolle, Louis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lyons,</placeName>
                    <date>the 30 July 69</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Since the last letter I had the honour to write you, after having received the footnotes you sent me, I went on translating your Orchis book.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Now, the two first chapters are entirely ready and copied out, together with the appended notes, I shall immediately despatch them to the publisher, who has agreed with me to print them before he has received the others.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have, besides, looked at some Orchid-flowers that you describe in other chapters, of which I have finished some passages; so that I still hope that the whole will be ended in November next, and owing to the printing being already begun, the publication will take place in february 1870.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I generally take care to have my French version as near your English text as possible, making only the slight modifications which are required by the peculiar idiom of our language, and in all cases, endeavouring to express as strictly as possible your idea. Allow me to ask you some explanations for a few points of detail.</p>
<p>In the case of the Epipactis palustris, you give to the terminal portion of the labellum the epithet of <hi rend="underline">distal</hi>, which I cannot understand.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In your notes, you speak of little insects which you call <hi rend="underline">thrips</hi>; though I suppose it is what we name in French <hi rend="underline">pucerons</hi>, as I am not sure of it, I shall ask you to send me the Latin or French name.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I suppose it is needless to repeat some epithets like these “<hi rend="underline">pouch-formed</hi> rostellum, <hi rend="underline">saddle-formed</hi> disc, <hi rend="underline">boat-formed</hi> disc, etc.” which you frequently repeat; in French, we have not so many compound adjectives as in English, and we are obliged to say “le rostellum en forme de poche, le disque en forme de selle, etc”, which being repeated makes the phrases languid.</p>
<p>I hesitated in translating the word <hi rend="underline">Bank</hi>. For instance, in the list given in the p. 40 of your work, when you say “six plants from a much exposed bank” do you mean a green bank, a grassy mound, a river bank, or simply a locality?</p>
<p>Would you be desirous, Sir, to look over one or several chapters of my translation before printing, I would soon send you the M.S.</p>
<p>Allow me, Sir, to assure you of the deep respect with which I have the honour to remain | Your very obedient servant | L. Rérolle</p>
<p>P.S. Would you be so kind as to answer me, I pray you to direct your letter to the address: quai Joinville, 9, Lyon.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Rérolle refers to his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6741.xml">10 May 1869</ref> and to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The publisher of Rérolle’s translation (Rérolle trans. 1870) was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3970.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles-Ferdinand Reinwald</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The translation appeared in June 1870 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7234.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Louis Rérolle, 15 June 1870</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 94–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">‘Thrips’ is both the common name given to any member of the insect family Thripidae and one of the genus names within that family. CD probably used the term in the former sense. ‘Pucerons’: aphids.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>