<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5443">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Vladimir Onufrievich Kovalevsky   15 March 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17767</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5443 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5443.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5443.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 71</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 71</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2751.xml">Kovalevsky, V. O.</persName>
                <placeName>St Petersburg</placeName>
                <date when="1867-03-15">15 Mar 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for permission to translate <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> into Russian. The translation will be guided by his brother Alexander, a follower of Darwin,</p> 
            <p>whose articles on the affinity of ascidians and vertebrates he forwards.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ascidians</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">Russian</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2749">Kovalevsky, A. O.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>S Petersbourg</placeName>
                    <date>3/15 March 1867<ref target="#foot.f1"/></date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Truebner transmitted me the answer you had the kindness to make on my offer to be the Editor of a Russian translation of your new work, authorised by you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Even if it is not a work for general reading, still, even in our country your name enjoys such a general and well deserved fame, that everything written by you is sure to awaken the liveliest interest, at least in the best part of our reading public. At all events I shall be very proud to be the editor of a Russian translation authorised by you, and you should make me quite happy if you thought fit to write two lines as an Introduction or Preface to my edition.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I must aknowledge you that I am, besides being an editor, also a little naturalist now and still more so <hi rend="underline">in spe</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> so that you will make me doubly happy by authorising me to be the Russian editor of your new work and adressing a few lines to this translation.— You can be quite sure that the translation of the work will be made most carefully, as I shall make it myself under the guidance of my brother who is lecturer of Zoology in the University of S Petersburg, but now temporarily absent on an excursion to Triest.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I take the boldness to send you some of his Memoirs, perhaps some of his studies and it may be a little wild conceptions about the affinity of the Ascidian and vertebrate types by their history of developement shall, however lightly, interst you, whose most true and steady follower he professes to be.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>In finishing my letter, I shall beg your pardon for my bad English, and pray you, if you shall have a moment time, to inform me directly, or trough M. Truebner is there any hope that the first part of the work will be finisched this year, will it be illustrated and what approximative dimensions (in pr. sheets)<ref target="#foot.f7"/> it will have.—</p>
<p>Leaving the pecuniary arrangement entyrely to you, and if you will have the kindness to adress your resolution to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Truebner, I shall wait with the utmost impatience of a naturalist and of your admirer, for the first printed sheets of your work which you had the kindness to promise to send me as soon as you receive them from the printer</p>
<p>I am | Sir | Your most true and impatient admirer | W. Kowalewsky</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">My adress</hi>. | <hi rend="underline">S Petersbourg</hi>. | coin de la Petite Morskaja | A Gowchovaja m Mitkoff. N 19.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Kovalevsky gives both the Julian (3 March) and Gregorian (15 March) calendar dates.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4787.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nicholas Trübner’s</ref> publishing firm had approached CD with an offer from Kovalevsky to translate <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5421.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Trübner &amp; Co, 26 February 1867</ref>). CD’s reply to Trübner has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">No preface was added to the Russian edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (V. O. Kovalevsky trans. 1868–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘In spe’: hopefully, in the future (Latin).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Onufrievich Kovalevsky</ref> was curator of the zoological cabinet and privat-dozent at St Petersburg University (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>). Trieste, now an Italian city, situated on the gulf of Trieste at the head of the Adriatic sea, was capital of Küstenland province, Austria, in 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Kovalevsky sent seven papers by his brother on the anatomy and embryology of marine invertebrates, all written in German (A. O. Kovalevsky 1865a and 1865b, 1866a–d, and Ovsjannikov and Kovalevsky 1866; CD’s copies of these papers are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL). In one paper, on the embryology of simple ascidians (A. O. Kovalevsky 1866b), Kovalevsky noted similarities between the larval stages of ascidians and amphioxus, suggesting an ancestral link between invertebrates and vertebrates. CD’s copy of the paper is heavily annotated.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Pr. sheets: i.e. proof-sheets.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>