<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1514">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To T. H. Huxley   11 April [1853]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3207</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1514 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1514.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1514.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy; ALS incomplete<ref target="#foot.f11"/></note>
            <note type="physdesc">C 3pp ALS 2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 150</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 145: 150Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 13)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>145: 150</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 13</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1853-04-11">11 Apr [1853]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Offers to send Ascidia specimens of <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage. Describes some of them.</p>  
<p>Hopes THH will review his book [<hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi>, vol. 1] which has been published for a year with no notice taken of it except briefly by Dana.</p>  
<p>Discusses <hi rend="italic">Limulus</hi>-like larva. "I have become a man of one idea.– cirripedes morning &amp; night."</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Ascidia</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cirripedes</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Limulus</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Living Cirripedia</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1190">Dana, J. D.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">larvae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">Beagle</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Farnborough, Kent.</placeName>
                    <date>April 11,</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I heard you say that you were at work at the Ascidiæ.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have some 12–15 specimens in Spirits; I hope in fairish condition. It is very likely that you may have more than you want, but should you like my specimens they are completely at your service. It will give me some trouble to get them out of several large bottles, but it would give me <hi rend="underline">real pleasure</hi> should you wish to have and examine them, but please do not say you should like them for mere form-sake. The colours are noted in some instances.</p>
<p>I procured a compound Ascidian (Boltenia?) at the Falklands<ref target="#foot.f3"/> (now I believe preserved in spirits) like a strawberry on a long foot-stalk; in this there were ova in all states which seemed to pass as they became mature out of what I considered the ovarium, into two gut-formed bags in each individual; and here they could be traced passing into larva, first with a long tail, (having transverse septa) coiled round the head or body, and then free, and causing the larva to be locomotive. In the same compound individual all the eggs and larvæ were in the same state; and when most matured, the animals were so shrunk, that the whole seemed formed of the gut-formed bags with the larvæ. In another genus (now dried) from T. del Fuego, there were also tailed larvæ.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> My descriptions were only such as an ignorant school-boy might make. Doubtless you have Müller’s “Uber die Larven … Echinodermen, <hi rend="underline">Viertel</hi> Abhand:, 1852,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Müller sent me a copy which is really wasted on me, and would be at the service of <hi rend="underline">anyone</hi> who would value it.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>You spoke as if you had had an intention to review my Cirripedia: it is very indelicate in me to say so, but it would give me <hi rend="underline">great</hi> pleasure to see my work reviewed by any one so capable as you of praising anything which might deserve praise, and criticising the errors which no doubt it contains. My chief reason for wishing it, is, otherwise I do not believe any foreigner will ever hear of its existence. It has been published a year, and no notice has been taken of it by any zoologist,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> except briefly by Dana.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Upon my honour I never did such a thing before as suggest (not that I have exactly suggested this time) a review to any human being. But having done so, I may mention that in my own opinion, the Limulus-like larva in 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> stage;—the mouthless pupa;—especially the method of cement with its modifications;—the senses;—&amp; homologies &amp; sexual peculiarities,—are the most curious points,—but I daresay I <hi rend="underline">greatly</hi> exaggerate their curiosity, for I have become a man of one idea,—cirripedes morning &amp; night.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I am <hi rend="doubleUnderline">perfectly</hi> aware that with every wish on your part it may <hi rend="underline">easily</hi> happen, that you could not spare time for <hi rend="underline">old</hi> work,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> you having so much valuable <hi rend="underline">new</hi> work.</p>
<p>Forgive the length &amp; egotistical character of this note, &amp; believe me | very truly your’s | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">3.11&amp; sexual peculiarities,— 3.12] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year of this letter is established by the reference to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref> having been published a year previously (see n. 7, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Huxley was cataloguing the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> collection of Ascidia. He had reported on some of his findings to the British Association for the Advancement of Science in 1852 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3994.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1852</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Described in CD’s zoological diary from the voyage of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> (DAR 30.2: 167–72), where it is called ‘Synoicum’. The specimens were collected on 2 April 1833 on East Falkland Island.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Described as ‘Holothuria’ in the zoological diary (DAR 30.2: 173).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Müller 1852</ref>, issued separately with a title-page indicating it to be the fourth part of Johannes Peter Müller’s <hi rend="italic">Über die Larven und die Metamorphose der Echinodermen.</hi> Huxley had reviewed Müller’s previous papers on echinoderms (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1442.xml" resp="#automat">letter to T. H. Huxley, 17 July [1851]</ref>, n. 1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">An unannotated reprint of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Müller 1852</ref> is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2621.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Fossil Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref> had been announced in the <hi rend="italic">Annales des Sciences Naturelles (Zoologie)</hi> 3d ser. 15 (1851): 175, but later volumes were not noticed, even though <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854)</ref> was dedicated to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3335.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Milne-Edwards</ref>, editor of the journal. The restricted circulation of Ray and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Palaeontographical Society</ref> publications on the Continent, particularly in Germany, in part explains why the monograph went unnoticed. Only in 1856 was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref> reviewed by Julius Viktor Carus in his survey of zoological literature for the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift fü</hi>r wissenschaftliche Zoologie, edited by Karl Theodor Ernst von Siebold and Rudolph Albert von Koelliker (7, supp. (1856): 75–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana’s</ref> review had appeared in July 1852 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1492.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Dana, 25 November [1852]</ref>, n. 6). A generally favourable anonymous notice had also appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, no. 1304, 23 October 1852, pp. 1138–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Huxley did not review <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, but in one of his ‘Lectures on general natural history’, a series published in the <hi rend="italic">Medical Times and Gazette</hi>, he praised Darwin’s monograph as ‘one of the most beautiful and complete anatomical and zoological monographs which has appeared in our time, and is the more remarkable as proceeding from a philosopher highly distinguished in quite different branches of science, and not an anatomist <hi rend="italic">ex professo</hi>’ (T. H. Huxley 1857, p. 238 n.). He mentioned the points suggested by CD, but did not wholly agree with CD’s interpretations. He took, for instance, a slightly different view of the homologies of the cirripedes, believing the carapace must consist of thoracic segments in addition to the three cephalic segments CD recognised. Huxley agreed with CD that the gut-formed glands, the cement glands and ducts, and the peduncular ovarian tubes were modified parts of a single organ system, but he believed the ovarian tubes and not the gut-formed glands were the true ovaria. He also doubted CD’s identification of two glands as acoustic and olfactory organs.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Huxley had turned in 1853 to work on the cephalous molluscs, greatly different from the ascidians and medusae on which he had previously concentrated. His numerous other publishing and editorial activities at this time are listed in L. Huxley ed. 1900, 1: 107.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The text, up to ‘briefly by Dana.’ (paragraph 3, line 7), is taken from a copy in DAR 145. The rest of the letter is transcribed from all that is preserved of the original in the archives of Imperial College of Science, Technology and Medicine.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>