<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11363">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Gaston de Saporta   16 February 1878<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10619</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11363 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11363.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11363.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 35</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 35</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4181.xml">Saporta, L. C. J. G. de</persName>
                <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                <date when="1878-02-16">16 Feb 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the difficulty of reconstructing angiosperm phylogeny.</p>
            <p>Discovery of polar fossil plants helps explain migrations.</p>
            <p>Hooker has identification of GdeS’s Permian fossil.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">angiosperm</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">polar plants</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Permian</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2357">Hooker, J. D.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                    <date>le 16 Fevr. | 1878</date>
                    <salute>Très cher Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>en même temps que je vous adresse par la poste un exemplaire d’une conférence sur les anciens climats, que j’ai donné au Hâvre au commencement de Septembre dernier, je veux vous remercier de votre utile intervention auprès de M. Hooker pour arriver à la détermination de mon Dicheuneuron permiers— Je crois que M. Hooker est dans le vrai et qui’il s’agit réellement d’une fougère plus ou moins alliée au <hi rend="underline">Ceratopteris</hi>, genre aujourd’hui anomal et isolé dans la nature et qui doit avoir eu des représentants dans la flore ancienne—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Vous verrez si vous voulez bien parcourir mon conférence l’etat actuel de la question relative à l’origine et à la marche du règne végétal avec les difficultés à surmonter pour arriver à une solution pleine et entière— Les découvertes des plants polaires ont fait faire un très grand pas en expliquant par des émigrations venues de l’extrême nord l’origine de plusieurs types tertiaires la plupart encore vivante—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Je crois également que s’il ne s’agissait que de déclarer erronée et détruite <hi rend="underline">l’opinion</hi> <hi rend="underline">professée</hi> jusqu’ici sur <hi rend="underline">l’espèce</hi> par les représentants des écoles de Linné et de Cuvier, tout serait maintenant résolu, nos espèces actuelles, surtout les européenes ayant leur représentant direct dans les flores des âges précédents—vous verrez figurés tous les antécédents de notre hêtre avec un cortège de formes antérieures dans les nôtres sont évidemment sorties.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> à ce point de vue donc la filiation des espèces végétales par d’autres plus anciènnes me parait démontrée; mais comme par le moyen de ces sortes de filiation, dèsqu’elles sont un peu complètes, on remonte <hi rend="underline">très haut</hi> et au delà du tertiare, et que, d’autre part, il n’y a pas traces de Dicotyledons avant le milieu de la Craie nulle part, sauf un seul exemple dans le craie inférieure du Groënland et que dans la plus ancienne flore de Dicotylédones, les types définissables les premiers paraissent dès lors revêtus de leurs caractères différentiels et fixés dans leurs principaux traits— cette absence de formes primordiales opérant un passage vers les souches-mères d’où la classe entière a du émerger, me parait constituer, non seulement en cequi concerne les Dicotylédones, mais pour tout le règne végétal, un problème du plus obscurs—</p>
                    <p>La difficulté est d’autant plus grande et d’autant moins facile à saisir, qu’il n’en est pas de même pour les mammifères chez lesquels on peut observer presque tout les passages et les enchainements menant d’une type à un autre et d’un groupe imparfait à un autre groupe définitif, comme des Marsupiaux aux Pachydermes et de ceux-ci aux Ruminants dans une direction, aux Equidées dans une autre— Les premiers vertébrés étant cartilagineux font aisement présenter la filiation de cette classe par une classe d’animaux moins inférieure.—</p>
                    <p>Dans le règne végétal, il n’en est pas ainsi et bien que les Angiospermes presentent des traces irrécusables de métamorphoses qui ont dû modifier graduellement leurs organes—nous ne trouvons jamais aucune trace des phases successives que les organismes ont du nécessairement traverser avant d’arriver au point où ils se trouvent arrivés maintenant et où ils étaient deja arrivés, alors quels premières Dicotyledones se montrent à nous—</p>
                    <p>Il faut donc supposer ou une région mère non encore découverte où la classe aurait pu élaborer peu à peu ses caractères, pour en sortir dejà parvenue à un état avancé et à peuprès difinitif pour beaucoup de types; ou bien croir à la possibilité, sous l’empire de <hi rend="underline">circonstances extérieures très décisives</hi>, peut-être sous l’influence de la différenciation premiere des climats, à une évolution rapide de nature à faire franchir rapidement à toute une classe de végetaux la distance qui sépare les premières ébauches d’une organisation arrétée et définitive, destinée à ne plus se préter qu’à des variations secondaires—</p>
                    <p>Si je prends les Dicotylédones je vois en effet que les variations produites depuis le commencement du tertiare n’ont été que depuis détails et seulement dans les groupes comme les Araliacées et qui ne forment en realité qu’un genre unique— Les parties se sont légérement modifiées, c’est à dire que les particularités relatives aux nombres des pieces florales, des loges du fruit on pu et dû varier, tout le plan de structure restant le même— un gland découvert à Gelinden extrême base du tertiaire et combiné avec des feuilles de chênes de la même localité, m’a prouvé que le genre <hi rend="underline">quercus</hi> existait des lors avec l’ébauche au moins des sections qu’il comprend et à côte de lui le genre Castanea trop reconnaisable à ses feuilles pour induire en erreur— Cependant si l’on examine l’appareil frutificateur des Quercinées, l’involucre parait bien réellement répresenter un axe garni de bractées qui ne sont elles-même que des feuilles transformées, axe qui a du subir une longue suite de modification avant de revêtir l’aspect qui le distingue maintenant—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> mes idées sur la fleur impliquent une longue succession de changements d’où la classe des Dicotyledones serait sortie; mais leur apparition subite vers le base du cénomanien— renverse tous les calculs et nous place face à face d’un inconnu dont les termes nous échappent. Je livre ce point à vos méditations, non sans ajouter qu’il met de même des autres parties du règne végetal et au particulier des Gymnospermes— je termine en vous remerciant et vous serrant la main votre bien devoué C<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> de Saporta</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                    <date>16 Febr. | 1878</date>
                    <salute>Dearest Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>At the same time as I send you by post a copy of a lecture on ancient climates, which I gave at le Hâvre at the beginning of last September, I wish to thank you for your useful intercession earlier with Mr Hooker to arrive at the determination of my Permian Dicheuneuron— I believe that Mr Hooker is in the right and that it really is a fern more or less connected to <hi rend="underline">Ceratopteris</hi>, a genus today anomalous and isolated in nature and that must have had representations in the ancient flora—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>You will see, if you kindly look over my lecture, the current state of the question as regards the origin and the progress of the vegetable kingdom with the difficulties to be overcome in order to arrive at a full and complete solution— The discoveries of polar plants have gone a long way to explain, by migrations from the extreme north, the origin of several Tertiary types, the majority of which are still extant—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p> I also believe that if it were simply a case of pronouncing erroneous and defunct <hi rend="underline">the view</hi> <hi rend="underline">taught</hi> up to now on <hi rend="underline">species</hi> by the representatives of the schools of Linnaeus and of Cuvier, all would now be resolved, our current species, especially the European ones having their direct antecedants in the flora of preceding ages—you will see represented all the ancestors of our beech, with its attendant preceding forms from which our own evidently emerged.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> from this point of view then, the derivation of plant species from others more ancient seems to me proven; but since by means of these sorts of filiation, as soon as they are pretty much comprehensive, one goes back <hi rend="underline">very far</hi> and beyond the Tertiary, and as, on the other hand, there are no traces  of Dicotyledons before the middle of the Cretaceous anywhere, except for a single example in the lower Cretaceous of Greenland, and as in the most ancient flora of the Dicotyledons, the first definable types appear from then on having assumed their differential characteristics and become fixed in their principle traits— this absence of primordial forms effecting a transition to parent strains from which the whole class must have emerged, seems to me to constitute, not only as regards Dicotyledons, but for all the vegetable kingdom, a problem even more obscure—</p>
                    <p>The difficulty is all the greater and all the less easy to grasp, in that it is not the same for mammals among whom one can observe almost all the transitions and sequences leading from one type to another and from one imperfect group to another definitive group, like Marsupials to Pachyderms, and from the latter to Ruminants in one direction and <hi rend="underline">Equidae</hi> in another— The first vertebrates being cartilaginous make it easy to show the derivation from this class of a class of animals less inferior.</p>
            <p>In the vegetable kingdom, it is not like this and even though the Angiosperms present undeniable traces of the metamorphoses that must have gradually modified their organs—we never find any trace of the successive phases that the organisms must have had to pass through before getting to the point where they now find themselves, and which they had already reached at the time the first Dicotyledons were revealed to us—</p>
                    <p>One must, then, imagine either a source region not yet discovered, where the class could have developed its characteristics gradually, in order to emerge having already reached an advanced and  nearly final state for many types; or indeed believe in the possibility, under the influence of <hi rend="underline">very decisive external circumstances</hi>, perhaps under the influence of the first differentiation of climates, in a rapid evolution of nature by a whole class of plants swiftly crossing the distance that separates the first signs from a fixed and definitive organisation, destined no longer to lend itself to any but secondary variations—</p>
                    <p>If I take Dicotyledons, I see indeed that the variations produced since the beginning of the Tertiary have been only in details, and only in groups like the Araliaceae and those which in reality form only one unique genus— The parts were slightly modified, that is to say that the characteristics relative to the numbers of floral parts, the locules of fruit could and must have varied, the whole plan of the structure remaining the same— a gland discovered at Gelinden, extreme bottom of the Tertiary, and combined with oak leaves of the same locality, proved to me that the genus <hi rend="underline">quercus</hi> existed since then with the outline at least of the sections it contains, and next to it the genus Castanea, too recognisable in its leaves to mislead— Accordingly if one examines the fructifying apparatus of the Quercineae, the involucre seems truly enough represented, an axis covered with bracts that are themselves only transformed leaves, an axis that had to undergo a long series of modification before assuming the aspect that now distinguishes it—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> my ideas on the flower imply a long succession of changes from which the class of Dicotyledons would have come; but their sudden appearance about the bottom of the Cenomanian—overturns all the calculations and brings us face to face with an unknown whose limits elude us. I offer this point to your meditations, not without adding that it applies also to other parts of the vegetable kingdom, and in particular Gymnosperms— I end by thanking you and shaking your hand, your most devoted, C<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> de Saporta</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
         
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Saporta gave his lecture ‘Les anciens climats de l’Europe et le développement de la végétation’ (Ancient climates of Europe and the development of vegetation; Saporta 1878) at a conference on ancient climates that he had organised as part of the Congress of the French Association for the Advancement of Sciences at Le Hâvre in August 1877. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker’s</ref> identification of Saporta’s fossil tracing was sent in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11347.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Gaston de Saporta, 4 February [1878]</ref>. For Saporta’s earlier ideas about the fossil, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Gaston de Saporta, 16 December 1877</ref> and n. 26.  In Saporta 1878, pp. 871–2, Saporta discussed the identification of the leaf, found in Permian deposits in the Urals, referring to it as <hi rend="italic">Dichoneuron hookeri</hi>; he also discussed and illustrated it in <hi rend="italic">L’évolution du règne végétal</hi> (Saporta and Marion 1885, 1: 231). Later researchers suggested it was a form of <hi rend="italic">Psygmophyllum</hi> sp. (see, for example,  <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10382.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zalessky 1937</ref>, p. 61). <hi rend="italic">Ceratopteris</hi> is a genus of aquatic homosporous ferns.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Saporta 1878 discussed the sudden appearance of many angiosperms in the Upper Cretaceous.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">On the sexual taxonomic system of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2942.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl von Linné</ref> contrasted with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georges Cuvier’s</ref> system of embranchments, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5338.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mayr 1982</ref>, pp. 182–4. Saporta 1878 traces a phylogenetically based taxonomy in which all the ancestors of the modern beech are represented.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Araliaceae is the ginseng and ivy family. Gelinden is a village in north-east Belgium. <hi rend="italic">Quercus</hi> is the genus of oaks; <hi rend="italic">Castanea</hi> is the genus of chestnuts. The former family Quercineae included oaks, chestnuts, <hi rend="italic">Castanopsis</hi>, and beeches, all of which are now in the family Fagaceae.</note>
        </div>         
             
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>