<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. A. Darwin   8 December 1822</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6003</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 4</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 4</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml">Darwin, E. A.</persName>
                <placeName>[Cambridge]</placeName>
                <date when="1822-12-08">8 Dec 1822</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Suggestions for laboratory equipment. Will buy some mineral specimens. Describes experiments he has seen.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">laboratory</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Cambridge]</placeName>
                    <salute>Dear Bobby.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I should not have written till I had received an answer about my going to fetch the girls, only I received a message, to acknowledge immediately the receipt of the drafts.—</p>
<p>You give me a very good account of the Lab:, it is quite wonderful how perverse the glass house people are, for I particularly told them to make the test tubes round at the bottom &amp; they must need’s grind them flat. If the cow is not utterly consumed the next milking, it would be a very good thing to buy as many of the large green, stoppered, bottles, as possible, &amp; have them all filled with distilled water, &amp; then I shall not be obliged to <hi rend="underline">persuade</hi> you quite so often to run down to Blunt for some water.</p>
<p>Professor Cummings shewed us some of the most beautiful crystall’s you can imagine, in fact they were artificial diamonds. The way he made them was, by putting a few drops of Sulphuret of Carbon at the bottom of a well stopped bottle, &amp; the liquid, being the most volatile of any, crystallized against the sides of the vessel. They were far more brilliant than any diamonds I ever saw, but if air was admitted they melted away.—</p>
<p>I shall not bring you any minerals down this time as they would stand a very good chance of being knocked about, rather more than their constitution can bear.— I will bring you some wavellite,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> &amp; uranite &amp; likewise a petrifaction from a well near here, as I have bought them already.—</p>
<p>What I shall buy in London will be principally stop cocks, &amp; jars with stop cocks, for that is what we are principally deficient in, &amp; we shall then be able to get over the ground rather quicker in our gas experiments.— The lab will look very insignificant after all the grand things I see here.— I hope you practise making gases, and have learnt to manage the argand Lamp,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> quite beautifully.— In lecture the other day, 3 or 4 men got perfectly tipsy with the nitrous oxide or laughing gas, (that one made from nitrate of ammonia) and made themselves utterly ridiculous. they all recovered in about a minute—one man said he felt just as if he could fly, &amp; when he was drinking the gas, he began to jump, &amp; twiddle his fingers, &amp; make a kind of half laughing &amp; screaming noise, &amp; y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Professor gave a good tug, before he would let the bladder be taken out of his mouth.—</p>
<p>Tell Susan<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I will bring the book down. I have nothing more to say of news or nonsense. | I remain yours affectionately | E. Darwin. *S 2</p>
<p rend="left">Dec. 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1822.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Hydrous phosphate of aluminium, named after Dr <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4987.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Wavel</ref>, its discoverer.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">A lamp invented <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 1782 by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_146.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Aimé Argand</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1239.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Susan Elizabeth Darwin</ref>, CD’s sister.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>