<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-218">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Robert FitzRoy   4 October 1833</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5127</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-218 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-218.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-218.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">9pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 120</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 120</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml">FitzRoy, Robert</persName>
                <placeName>HMS Beagle, Montevideo</placeName>
                <date when="1833-10-04">4 Oct 1833</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Urges CD to return to the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> early in November. Conrad Martens arrives to succeed Augustus Earle as artist for the expedition.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">Beagle</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Beagle. Monte Video</placeName>
                    <date>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1833</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Two hours since, I received your epistle, dated 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. and most punctually and immediately am I about to answer your queries. (mirabile!!)</p>
<p>But firstly of the first—my good Philos why have you told me nothing of your hairbreadth scapes &amp; moving accidents How many times did you flee from the Indians? How many precipices did you fall over? How many bogs did you fall into?— How often were you carried away by the floods? and how many times were you kilt?— that you were not kilt <hi rend="underline">dead</hi> I have visible evidence in your handwriting,—as well as in a columnar paragraph in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Love’s unamiable paper. You did not tell me whether you received the blank papers safely—you informal homo—how am I to feel certain that I have not signed what may blast my <hi rend="underline">immaculate</hi> reputation? Harris<ref target="#foot.f1"/> carried the Packet which contained them and promised to deliver them faithfully. How Sancho by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hood’s assistance,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> contrived so to mismanage as to reach B<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Ayres some days after Harris—Quien sabe? In it were 5 “Skimpy” lines, as Capt Beaufort would call them &amp; a promise of better behaviour. Since the date of that note the Beagle has been two days at Maldonado—one day here and about a week between this &amp; Cape Corrientes.— Not having any Stone pounders on board—nor any qualified person (the <hi rend="underline">Mate</hi> being absent)—I could not think of landing,—so <hi rend="underline">you</hi> have yet a <hi rend="underline">chance</hi>,—“de verus” (it <hi rend="underline">blew</hi> strong &amp; prevented landing.) I believe you have heard from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Parry and are aware of his loss.— If you have not heard from him—your <hi rend="underline">ally</hi> (!! of bone stealing fame) will have informed you. Shocking as it was to him, and his family, but to him, most particularly,—I am in hopes that better times will be found by our good friend Parry,—in consequence of his being a single man.— Warm hearted and friendly as she was—and friendly to the utmost extent of her means—she had her share of woman’s weakness and woman’s failings. Robert Parry is gone to England in the “Mary Worrall”, Merchant man,—to be placed at a school,— the young daughters are going to B<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Ayres—also to school— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. P. intends to give up his house and turn “bachelor, in lodgings”,— —a <hi rend="underline">wise</hi> resolve, though painful indeed to the Father of a family,—think what a change in a domestic circle.</p>
<p>If M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. P. has written as he intended you have heard of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Martens<ref target="#foot.f3"/> —Earle’s Successor,—a <hi rend="underline">stone pounding artist</hi> —who exclaims <hi rend="underline">in his sleep</hi>“<hi rend="underline">think</hi> of <hi rend="underline">me</hi> standing upon a pinnacle of the Andes—or sketching a Fuegian Glacier!!!” By my faith in Bumpology, I am sure you will like him, and like him <hi rend="underline">much</hi> —he is—or I am wofully mistaken—a “rara avis in navibus,— Carlo que Simillima Darwin”.— Don’t be jealous now for I only put in the last bit to make the line scan— you know very well your degree is “rarissima” and that <hi rend="underline">your</hi> line runs thus— Est avis in navibus Carlos rarissima Darwin.— but you will think I am cracked so seriatim he is a gentlemanlike, well informed man.— his landscapes are <hi rend="underline">really</hi> good (compared with London men) though perhaps in <hi rend="underline">figures</hi> he cannot equal Earle— He is very industrious— and gentlemanlike in his <hi rend="underline">habits</hi>,—(not a <hi rend="underline">small</hi> recommendation).</p>
<p>Wickham gets on famously—really the “Lighter” will not merit <hi rend="underline">trifling</hi> considerations— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Kent of the Pylades is at Gorriti—belonging to our Squad. We have plenty of men,—and <hi rend="underline">good</hi> ones; and all is prospering— —</p>
<p>“<hi rend="underline">Well, but the conjunctions—the conjunctions</hi>” I hear you saying—“<hi rend="underline">you</hi> <hi rend="underline">have got to the end of a sheet of paper without telling me one thing that I</hi> <hi rend="underline">wanted to know</hi>”.—</p>
<p>—This is the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of October,—“<hi rend="underline">so the date of your letter tells me</hi>”— —well— hum— —if—hum—but—we must consider—then—hum—tomorrow will be the sixth— “<hi rend="underline">Prodigious</hi>”!! Do you know what I mean—“<hi rend="underline">to be sure</hi>” so—and so &amp; so—&amp; hum hum hum &amp; off goes the head!!—</p>
<p>I never will write another letter after tea—that green beverage makes one tipsy—besides it is such a luxury feeling that your epistle is not to go across the wide atlantick—and has only to cross the muddy Plata. It is so awful writing to a person thousands of miles off—when your conscience reproaches you with having been extremely negligent and tells you that six or eight or (oh—how awful) twelve months’ “<hi rend="underline">History</hi>” is due to your expectant and irate correspondent.</p>
<p>Still <hi rend="underline">you</hi> get no <hi rend="underline">answer</hi> — “<hi rend="underline">what is the Beagle going to do—will you</hi> <hi rend="underline">tell me, or not</hi>?”—</p>
<p>Philos—be not irate—have patience and I will tell thee all.</p>
<p>Tomorrow we shall sail, for Maldonado—there we shall remain until the middle of this month;—thence we shall return to Monte Video—to remain quietly, <hi rend="underline">if</hi> <hi rend="underline">possible</hi>, until the end of the month.— I will try all I can to get away from the River Plate the first week in November but there is much to do—and I shall not be surprised if we are detained even until the middle of November.— However—weather is of such consequence, that every long day gained will tell heavily—and I hope &amp; will try hard to be off <hi rend="underline">Early</hi> in November—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> therefore do not delay your arrival <hi rend="underline">here</hi> later than the <hi rend="underline">first few</hi> days of November, at the <hi rend="underline">farthest</hi>.</p>
<p>You say nothing about the “Journal of the expedition up the Rio Negro”—nor have you sent me the map of the province of Buenos Ayres— I pray you to <hi rend="underline">do</hi> <hi rend="underline">the latter</hi> —right speedily—and enquire about the <hi rend="underline">former</hi> —from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gore as well as the other man whose name I forget (Seņor—Don—or Colonel Something, or somebody.)—but in writing to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gore I mentioned it—so he will know it.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I wish to compare the map with our charts—previous to sending them away—in order to “connive” a little; as your <hi rend="underline">friend</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bathurst says.</p>
<p>Roberts<ref target="#foot.f6"/> (of the Liebre) passed our bows <hi rend="underline">this morning</hi> on board of the “<hi rend="underline">Paz</hi>” bound to Rio Negro with a cargo of <hi rend="underline">tobacco</hi>. he did not honor us with a visit—nor did he ask for Chico—respecting the former, he was somewhat rude, and as to the latter rather wise I think.—</p>
<p>Adios Philos—Ever very faithfully yours. Rob<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. FitzRoy</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2137.xml">James Harris</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2347.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Samuel Hood</ref>, British Consul-General in Montevideo (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> 2: 293–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Conrad Martens</ref>, who replaced <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1442.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Augustus Earle</ref> as draughtsman. Earle’s poor health had forced him to leave the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> in August.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The actual date was 6 December 1833. The delay was caused by the need to complete the charts of the surveys made by the <hi rend="italic">Liebre</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Paz</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_468.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">‘Beagle’ diary</hi></ref>, pp. 191, 200).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1925.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Yorke Gore</ref>, Chargé d’Affaires in Buenos Aires.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Mr Roberts was the pilot on board the <hi rend="italic">Liebre</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> 2: 110).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>