<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5376">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   22 January 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14797</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5376 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5376.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5376.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 117, DAR 111: A91</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 117 (fragile),</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>111: 91</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1867-01-22">22 Jan 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Position as Curator allows no time for experiment.</p>
            <p>Describes plans for vast new layout of Calcutta Botanic Garden according to natural orders.</p>
            <p>Himalayan and Scottish plants are doing well.</p>
            <p>Hopes to experiment on temperate plants in tropics, to test CD’s views of migration during glacial periods.</p>
            <p>Sends observations on acclimatisation of English cultivated plants.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Leersia</hi> CD sent are growing and fertile.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Leersia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">temperate plants</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">glacial periods</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">curator of Calcutta Botanic Garden</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Calcutta Botanic Garden</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Himalaya</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Scotland</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">tropics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">naturalisation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Royal Botanic Gardens | Calcutta</placeName>
                    <date>22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 1867.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I cant longer defer writing a note to you—though I have yet failed to accomplish the purpose of my delay. This you can only guess at just now. I shall explain in a future letter, and in the meantime, I would have you believe me though silent, in heart ever grateful to you my chiefest benefactor.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>My duties as Curator of the Botanic Gardens have been and yet are engrossing my time so completely, that I have been quite unable to engage in the experimental illustrations of many subjects which lie very near my heart.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You may be surprised at the press of duties incumbent to my appointment considering that our Gardens have been so long established. This is natural, but when you know, that we are raising a new Garden out of the wholesale devastations of the Cyclone of 1864, and this on a scientific basis, which had never been previously attempted here, you can conceive of the labour— reclaiming much actual jungle land, planning and planting systematically a tropical garden 250 acres in extent. We have now however got the outlines of all the Natural Orders fixed, and the planting of many of them in so far as we can at present represent them, done,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> so that my duties are turning daily lighter, and will soon permit of my directing some little portion of my time to former scientific recreations.</p>
<p>In talking of our Garden you will I doubt not be interested in hearing, that we have now planned out on a rather extensive scale the basis of a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">temperate</hi> <hi rend="underline">herbaceous</hi> garden. So far as my observations go, this promises to be most pregnant with interesting results: plants from an elevation of 7 &amp; 8000 ft in the Himalayahs are luxuriating in our hands; and <hi rend="underline">many</hi> <hi rend="underline">many</hi> common <hi rend="doubleUnderline">British</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">plants</hi> of which I have had seeds this season from the North of Scotland are proving quite at home. This experiment is interesting me greatly; and excitingly interesting is the hope that further experience may yield us something in the way of illustrating your views on the origin of species by variation.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It has already however shown me that our domesticated plants, are not as some would have us believe, the alone possessors of the power of habitating most diverse climes. Again it seems to show us, that there must not necessarily have been a great lowering of the temperature of the globe to account for the occurrence of temperate species of plants on tropical mountains. In so far as temperature is concerned, from the wide flexibility of constitution, which many temperate plants possess, I believe that under existing physicial arrangements, along continuous meridional tracts of land migrations of those species into tropical climes might occasionally be effected. I say occasionally for it is evident, that plants though flourishing in diverse climes under cultivation could rarely compete successfully with the respective indigens in their exodus from the temperate to the tropic zone; while there is further the absence of any directive force occasioning such migrations, which is so well explained by your views of a simultaneous glacial epoch in both hemispheres and a concomitant cooling of the tropical zone.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I have hopes after a few years careful observation of the various temperate plants I am now introducing to accumulate an interesting body facts on acclimatation. This subject seems yet to excite some little discussion at home; perhaps a brief note on a few experiments may interest you— Thus the Common Sweet Pea (Lathyrus odoratus) from English grown seeds germinates freely here, producing strong rigid plants, a reduced developement of leaf and tendril, with thick prominently winged stems, rarely ever producing a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">single</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">flower</hi> <hi rend="underline">no</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">seed</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Again English seeds grown in the vicinity of Darjeeling are abundantly productive of flowers and seeds, affording material for successful cultivation in the plains of India. Seedlings raised from these acclimatized up-country seeds, are readily distinguished from the direct products of English saved seed, when grown in the plains, of their lax, and naturally scandent habit, and their flowering and seeding profusely… It is worthy of note also as indicating a stage in the process of acclimatation that a small quantity of French grown Sweet Peas which I had yielded plants, markedly distinct from the English seedlings (and naturally so) <hi rend="underline">blossomed</hi> sparingly, but all proved infertile.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I am curious to see how a number of other Legumes introduced from various parts of Europe during last season will behave.... Another point worthy of notice is the tendency of many of those highly cultivated productions of the florist to vary under cultivation here. Thus the double flowering Balsam from English seed, are as <hi rend="underline">fine</hi> for the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">first</hi> season as any I ever saw at home— in the second generation there is a decided falling off. While in the third scarcely a double flower is to be seen. This is also the case with other double flowering florists flowers, and so with many single varieties of the same. Petunias and Antirrhinums for example are splendid for the first season, while in the second and third they are <hi rend="italic">[</hi>surely<hi rend="italic">]</hi> wortheless for the flower garden. Indian florists are in general so disheartened with these very natural results that in place of making attempts to raise varieties from their retroverted stock, suitable to the climate and the adornment of their garden, trust almost entirely to direct imports of English grown seed. I am experimenting a little with this view.</p>
<p>By the way I am growing successfully <hi rend="underline">Leersia</hi> <hi rend="underline">oryzoides</hi> from the seeds you were good enough to send me.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> It has not however as yet protruded a single flower, all are <hi rend="underline">enclosed</hi> <hi rend="underline">within</hi> the <hi rend="underline">culms</hi> and <hi rend="doubleUnderline">quite</hi> <hi rend="underline">fertile</hi>. I had great hopes of cultivation here inducing variation on that point, but have been as yet disappointed. Succeeding generations, however may yet afford it<ref target="#foot.f9"/> .... . Curiously enough some of our Indian Violas, like the European, produce also perfect and imperfect flowers. <hi rend="underline">V.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Roxburghiana</hi>, for example, produces <hi rend="underline">perfect</hi> <hi rend="underline">flowers</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">only</hi> in the cold season— these I may remark are quite fertile—during the hot, though chiefly in the rainy season an abundance of closed-fertile flowers are produced.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Excuse my desultory notes, as I am as yet only able to indicate points of promise.</p>
<p>Yours most respectfully | John Scott</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I cant … recreations. 2.13] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.7 and this … labour— 2.8] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 In talking] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.4 plants … home. 3.6] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 I have … infertile 4.15] <hi rend="italic">crossed red crayon</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">Acclimatisation</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.15 sparingly,] ‘but all proved infertile’ <hi rend="italic">added below, ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.15 but all … view. 4.29] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.26 attempts … seed. 4.28 <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 By … disappointed. 5.4] ‘<hi rend="italic">Leersia</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.6 <hi rend="italic">V. Roxburghiana</hi> … produced. 5.9] ‘<hi rend="italic">Viola</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘J. Scott’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">Keep</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of last page</hi>: ‘Jan 1. 1867’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The last extant letter from John Scott is that of 21 July 1865 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13). Scott alludes to the money that CD gave him for his passage to India, where he went to seek employment.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Scott became curator at the Royal Botanic Garden, Calcutta, in late May 1865 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4876.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 July 1865</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13). He had conducted experimental work while foreman of the propagating department of the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh, and had corresponded extensively about the work with CD since 1862 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 10–13).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For information on the Royal Botanic Garden, Calcutta, and the destructive cyclone of 1864, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1102.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burkill [1965]</ref>, pp. 21, 66, 103, 133; the garden was on the banks of a tidal river, the Hooghly, and suffered inundations of seawater during the cyclone. The Calcutta garden covered more than 300 acres (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5071.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McCracken 1997</ref>, p. 111). The garden had earlier been planted partly along the lines of a horticultural nursery, and partly according to the Linnaean system (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1102.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burkill [1965]</ref>); Scott was arranging the beds according to the natural orders (families) promoted by Robert Brown (1773–1858) and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Wild plants and seeds were brought down from higher elevations by the garden’s collectors, and cultivated plants and seeds from plantations in Sikkim; they were then planted at sea level in the botanic garden at Calcutta (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1102.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burkill [1965]</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5071.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McCracken 1997</ref>). CD had written on acclimatisation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 139–43.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Scott alludes to CD’s discussions in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 365–82, of plant dispersal during the glacial period.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD included Scott’s information on <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus odoratus</hi> in India in a section on acclimatisation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 311.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD noted Scott’s information on the French sweetpeas in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 311.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Scott asked CD for seed of <hi rend="italic">Leersia oryzoides</hi> in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4876.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 21 July 1865</ref> so that he, like CD, could investigate self-fertilisation in closed flowers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13). For CD’s interest in the plant and his acquisition of specimens, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12. CD’s observations had been published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>, pp. 191–2 n. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 131).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Scott evidently never succeeded in cultivating <hi rend="italic">L. oryzoides</hi> in India with flowers that opened; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 335.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD cited Scott’s observations of <hi rend="italic">Viola roxburghiana</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">V. patrinii</hi>) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 320.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>