<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12060">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   23 May 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5458A</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12060 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12060.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12060.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B28</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B28</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-05-23">23 May 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Samuel Butler seems not even to have read works of Erasmus Darwin. Quotes only passages quoted by other authors. Thorough account now more necessary than ever.</p>
            <p>CD’s preliminary notice should be incorporated in German edition completely unchanged, though some annotation is needed to explain matters unfamiliar to German readers.</p> 
<p>Would like to have article by CD for <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Kosmos</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_774">Butler, Samuel (b)</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">German readers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-17" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-18" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-20" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-30" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by Alison Pearn. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2018-08-30" status="copyedited">Copyedited by Samantha Evans. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00174_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00174_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <surface n="B:28r" xml:id="i174">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00174.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00174_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00174.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:28v" xml:id="i175">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00175.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00175_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00175.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 23.5.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Nachdem ich das Buch des Herrn S. Butler, welches Sie die Güte hatten, mir senden zu lassen, nunmehr gelesen habe, freue ich mich doppelt, dass Sie dasselbe nicht als Hinderniss betrachten.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Herr Butler hat sich in der That nach seiner gewöhnlichen Art, die Sache sehr leicht gemacht, und wie mir scheint, nicht einmal die Mühe genommen, die Werke von Dr. Erasmus Darwin selbst zu lesen. Er citirt nur, was Dr. Dowson und Fräulein Seward citirt haben, und ist auf den “Tempel der Natur” ebensowenig wie auf den botanischen Garten näher eingegangen, trotzdem der letztere so reich an fruchtbaren Gedanken war, und der erstere doch als die reifste Darstellung seines Sÿstems nothwendig berücksichtigt werden musste.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Fast scheint es mir daher, dass eine gründliche Darstellung nach Erscheinen des Butler’schen Buches nothwendiger geworden ist, als sie vorher war.</p>
                    <p>Was die deutsche Ausgabe anbelangt, so denke ich Ihre Praeliminar Notice <hi rend="underline">unbedingt unverändert</hi> dem Buche voranzustellen, denn dieselbe wird naturgemäss für den deutschen Leser den Mittelpunkt des Interesses bilden.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Vielleicht wird es geeignet sein, über einzelne Persönlichkeiten und Dinge, die Sie bei dem englischen Leser als bekannt voraussetzen dürfen, meinerseits in Anmerkungen, die an den Schluss des Bändchens zu stellen sein würden, einige Ausführungen hinzuzufügen; so über die Personen, an welche seine Briefe gerichtet waren, u.s.w.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Über den letzteren Punkt werde ich natürlich einen bestimmten Entschluss erst durch die Ansicht Ihrer Druckbogen gewinnen. Für die Uebersetzung der poëtischen Citate in’s Deutsche habe ich einen in solchen Arbeiten sehr geschickten Freund gewonnen, und ich dachte deshalb diese Citate noch etwas zu vermehren, durch die bezeichnenden Stellen über die französische Revolution, die Philanthropie und vielleicht auch durch Mittheilung einiger Gelegenheitsgedichte, wie desjenigen an Dr. Boulton in Betreff der Theevase u.s.w.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>Butler’s “Life and habit” ist, wie ich nun selbst gesehen habe, durch Dr. Hermann Mueller im “Kosmos” viel zu günstig beurtheilt worden.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Es ist eine auf manche Fälle vielleicht anwendbare Idee, die aber in ihrer Tragweite überschätzt wird, wenn man in ihr die Lösung aller Räthsel sucht, und ich habe mich schon gewundert, keine Opposition aus dem Kreise der deutschen Leser u Mitarbeiter des Kosmos darüber vernommen zu haben. Ich würde allerdings sehr glücklich darüber sein, wenn Sie über solche oder ähnliche Differenzpunkte Ihre Ansichten für unsere Zeitschrift einmal niederschreiben wollten, oder uns eine Notiz über den Stand Ihrer jetzigen Experimente zukommen lassen wollten, aber ich will Sie ganz gewiss auch <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi> bitten, aus blossem Wohlwollen, eine Arbeit zu beginnen, die Ihnen vielleicht nicht sÿmpathisch wäre. Nur das möchte ich betonen, dass unsre Leser, mit den höchst vereinzelten Ausnahmen etlicher Gegner, die das Journal nur aus Politik lesen, alle Ihre begeisterten Verehrer sind, für die irgend eine kleine Notiz oder Zuschrift von Ihnen ein freudiges Ereigniss wäre.</p>
                    <p>Verzeihen Sie, hochverehrter Herr, wenn in diesen Zeilen unversehens der Redacteur des Kosmos durchgeblickt hat | Ihrem treulich ergebensten | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
          
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>23.5.79.</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Now after having read the book by Mr S. Butler, which you had the kindness to send me, I am doubly glad that you do not regard it as an obstacle.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Indeed, Mr Butler made things easy for himself in his usual manner, and, as it seems to me, has not even taken the trouble to read for himself the works of Dr Erasmus Darwin. He merely quotes what Dr Dowson and Miss Seward have quoted, and goes into just as little detail on the “Temple of Nature” as on the Botanic Garden, even though the latter was so rich in fertile ideas and the former absolutely deserved consideration as the most mature presentation of his system.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> So it almost seems to me that a thorough account has become more necessary following the appearance of Butler’s book, than it was before.</p>
                    <p>As concerns the German edition, I intend to preface the book with your preliminary notice <hi rend="underline">absolutely unaltered</hi>, for naturally it will be of central interest to the German reader.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> For particular persons and matters that you can assume the English reader to be familiar with, it will perhaps be appropriate on my part to add a number of remarks in notes that would be appended at the end of the volume; for example, concerning the persons his letters were addressed to, etc.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> With respect to this last point I will of course be able to arrive at a decision only upon seeing your proof-sheets. For the translation of the poetic quotations into German I have found a friend who is very skillful in this kind of thing, and it therefore occurred to me to increase the number of these quotations somewhat, by adding significant passages on the French Revolution, philanthropy and perhaps also by including a number of occasional poems, such as the one to Dr Boulton regarding the tea vase etc.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>As I have now seen for myself, Butler’s “Life and Habit” was judged much too favourably by Dr Hermann Müller in “Kosmos”.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Perhaps the idea can be applied to a certain number of instances, but its implications are being overestimated when one sees in it the solution of all problems, and I have been surprised not to hear any objections from the circle of the German readers of &amp; contributors to Kosmos about this. It would certainly make me very happy if you were to write down your views on this or related issues for our journal some time, or if you were to let us have a note on the latest state of your current experiments, but I certainly do <hi rend="underline">not</hi> want to ask you to embark on a labour that you might dislike just to please us. I would just like to emphasise however, that our readers, with the very rare exception of some opponents who read the journal merely for political reasons, all admire you enthusiastically and for them some brief note or communication on your part would be a happy occurence.</p>
<p>Forgive me, highly esteemed Sir, if in these lines the editor of Kosmos peeped through unexpectedly | Yours truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
                        
            
              
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had arranged to have a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Samuel Butler’s</ref> book <hi rend="italic">Evolution, old and new</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml">S. Butler 1879</ref>) sent to Krause (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-12051.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 13 May 1879</ref>). <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">S. Butler 1879</ref> included a discussion of the evolutionary theories of CD’s grandfather <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>. Krause and CD were working on a joint publication on Erasmus (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>). Although CD had only glanced at Butler’s book, he informed Krause it would not deter him from publication (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12052.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 14 May 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Krause refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8551.xml">John Dowson</ref>  and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2132.xml">Dowson 1861</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>. The <hi rend="italic">Temple of nature</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1794.xml">E. Darwin 1803</ref>) and the <hi rend="italic">Botanic garden</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>) were two of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>’s principal works. For Butler’s treatment of the life and views of Erasmus Darwin, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">S. Butler 1879</ref>, pp. 173–234.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s ‘Preliminary notice’ for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> was unchanged in the German translation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Krause 1880</ref>, CD’s own notes remained within the text of his ‘Preliminary notice’, but notes added by Krause were numbered and appeared at the end of the book.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Krause 1880</ref>, p. vi, Krause thanked <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8707.xml">Johann H. Becker</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8706.xml">Karl Kösting</ref> for translating the poetry in the volume. Among several additional quotations of poetry by Erasmus Darwin, Krause included the first verse of Erasmus’s short poem ‘Directions for a tea vase’, addressed to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8434.xml">Matthew Boulton</ref>, in English and German translation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 185–6). The poem had appeared posthumously in the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, June 1802, p. 543. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Hermann Müller</ref> had published an essay review of Butler’s book <hi rend="italic">Life and Habit</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9614.xml">S. Butler 1878</ref>) in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10923.xml">H. Müller 1879c</ref>). Müller’s review was generally favourable; he did not view Butler’s theory as opposed to natural selection, rather he concluded that it was an important complement to CD’s theory (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 38). Krause had become sole editor of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> in April 1879.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>