<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3147">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi><ref target="#foot.f1"/>   [before 14 May 1861]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20101</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3147 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3147.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3147.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 39</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 124</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi>, n.s. 1 (1861): 112 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">J. Hortic. n.s. 1 1861: 112</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1861-05-13">[before 14 May 1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2615.xml">Journal of Horticulture</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Asks D. Beaton whether varieties of the same species of Compositae frequently cross by insect agency or other means. Do the raisers of hollyhocks have to keep each variety separate for raising seed?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Compositae</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_345">Beaton, Donald</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Bromley, Kent</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Will Mr. Beaton, who has made such a multitude of most interesting observations on the propagation of plants, have the kindness to state whether varieties of the same species of Composite plants frequently cross each other by insect agency or other means?<ref target="#foot.f3"/> For instance, will any of the Cinerarias, if kept apart from other varieties, breed true? but if standing near other varieties, will they generally, or almost certainly, produce a much greater diversity of coloured seedlings?</p>
<p>I saw an allusion by Mr. Beaton to this subject in <hi rend="underline">The Cottage Gardener</hi> of last year with respect to Zinnias;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and from this allusion I infer that Zinnia sports much when kept separate.</p>
<p>As I am begging for information on the natural crossing of plants, I will likewise venture to inquire whether the great raisers of Hollyhocks find it necessary to keep each variety far separate from the others for raising seed. The late famous horticulturist, the Hon. and Rev. W. Herbert, when I visited him at Spofforth many years ago, remarked that he was much surprised (considering the structure of the flower and the relative periods of maturity of the pollen and stigma) how true some sorts of Hollyhocks bred, even when growing close to other varieties.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have found this to be the case with some of the varieties, and cannot understand how it is possible. Mr. Beaton might, if he pleased, write an article, very valuable to physiological botanists and of some practical utility, on the natural crossing of varieties.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> He might indicate in which genera crossing most commonly occurred, and in which it seldom or never occurred. For instance, I have observed Sweet Peas during several years and believe that they never cross;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and it is not easy to make an artificial cross, though I succeeded at last, but got no good in a horticultural point of view.—</p>
<p>Charles Darwin, <hi rend="underline">Down, Bromley, Kent.</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Beginning with the issue of 2 April 1861, the <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi> changed its name to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman. A journal of horticulture, rural and domestic economy, botany and natural history</hi>. CD’s copies of the journal,—issues from October 1855 through March 1856 and from January 1860 to February 1866,—are in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter was published in the issue of 14 May 1861.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The letter, printed under the heading: ‘Phenomena in the cross-breeding of plants’, was prefaced by the following editorial comment: ‘Having received the following letter from Mr. Darwin we forwarded it to Mr. Beaton, and now publish it with his reply.’ The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_345.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Donald Beaton</ref>, a Scottish practical gardener with an interest in hybridisation who contributed regularly to the journal. The editors of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi> were George W. Johnson and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2328.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Hogg</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi>, 10 April 1860, p. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had corresponded with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Herbert</ref>, a great authority on plant hybridisation, about the crossing of plants (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 2). CD visited Herbert, after his appointment as dean of Manchester, on 15 September 1845 (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., vol. 3, ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD’s letter was followed by a long response from Beaton, which addressed several of the points raised by CD (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture, Cottage Gardener, and Country Gentleman</hi> n.s. 1 (1861): 112–13). CD, however, did not find Beaton’s information helpful (see letters to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, [17 May 1861], and to J. D. Hooker, 14 May [1861]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had for many years been investigating mechanisms of crossing in the Leguminosae in connection with his view that all organic beings must occasionally cross-fertilise. He found that <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus odoratus</hi>, the sweetpea, challenged this general rule. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, chap. 3, especially pp. 68–71, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2005.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">30 November [1856]</ref>, and to W. D. Fox, 22 February [1857].</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>