<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13500">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francisco de Arruda Furtado<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>    21 November 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20304</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13500 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13500.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13500.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt><relatedItem type="publication"><bibl><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11431.xml">Constância ed. (2002)</ref>: 117–18</bibl></relatedItem></notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Directors’ Correspondence 181/39)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <collection>Directors’ Correspondence</collection>
                    <idno>181/39</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_160.xml">Arruda Furtado, Francisco de</persName>
                <placeName>Ile St Michel Azores</placeName>
                <date when="1881-11-21">21 Nov 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>The statues on which the egg-cases were found were perfectly clean and had never been painted.</p>
            <p>Reports on fossilised leaf-prints he has found on the island. Found no seeds or land shells at the site.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">shells, land</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Ile St Michel</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">eggs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">land shells</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-28" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread against original by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-11" status="secondProofCompleted">Proofread against original by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2020-09-28" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-17" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-04" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-30" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Final proofread by <name sameAs="#raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Ile St. Michel (Açores)</placeName>
                    <date>21 Nov. 1881</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Je me hâte de vous remercier la bienveillance avec laquelle vous avez accueilli ma petite découverte, et je suis très heureux d’apprendre que vous lui accordez une certaine valeur, en la jugeant digne d’être publiée.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Maintenant je dois vous faire une histoire plus complète du fait. Les statuettes où l’insecte a déposé ses trois boites d’œufs étaient placées dans l’armoire vitrée d’une salle à manger. Elles ont été fabriquées à Paris avec une sorte de craie verdâtre et, faisant l’ornamentation de l’armoire il y a bon nombre d’années, on ne les a jamais enduit d’aucune peinture. Du reste, je suis parfaitement sûr que les œufs ont été déposés par l’insecte dans les 8 jours avant la découverte que j’en ai faite; avant ce temps là les statuettes étaient parfaitement netoyées quand on les a essuyé de la poussière.</p>
                    <p>Prochainement je me ferais l’honneur de communiquer a Sir J. Hooker<ref target="#foot.f3"/> les documents d’un fait important de botanique açoréenne. Il s’agit de nombreux exemplaires de belles empreintes de feuilles de Hedera, Persea et (Viburnum?) trouvées, dans un tuf, à Mosteiros sur la pointe N. O. de St. Michel.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Je n’ai point trouvé aucun autre vestige fossile. J’avais l’espoir d’y trouver quelques graines ou quelques coquilles terr.; mais mes recherches ont été infructueuses. Le tuf et les couches supérieures, livrant passage à l’eau, l’humidité a tout pourri. Je ferais accompagner les empreintes d’un profil géologique du site, illustré de spécimens des différentes couches. Peut être ce sont là des effets de l’éruption de 7 cidades.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Je prends la liberté de vous adresser un exemplaire de ces empreintes et quelques graines apportées sur nos plages par le gulf stream, de celles dont je vous ai parlé dans une précédente lettre.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Une de ces graines à été jadis la tabatière d’un pêcheur.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Peut-être cette application est-elle particulière aux açoreennes; ils ne s’en servent que pour le tabac en poudre sèche, et, quand il veulent en prendre une prise, ils secouent la graine sur le dos de la portion metacarpienne du pouce (point commode où il n’y l’odeur de poisson!) et ils y appliquent avidement la narine.</p>
<p>Daignez agréer, Monsieur, la nouvelle assurance de mon humble et éternelle reconnaissance | Arruda Furtado.</p> 
                    <p>P.S. | Voici, Monsieur, un petit croquis du profil à empreintes:—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width65">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13500_french.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                    
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 Prochainement] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.10 ces empreintes et quelques graines 3.11] <hi rend="italic">bar blue crayon between</hi> ‘empreintes’ <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> ‘et’</note>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
                       
            
            
              
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>São Miguel island (Azores)</placeName>
                    <date>21 Nov. 1881</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charles Darwin</seg>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>I hasten to thank you for the kindness with which you have received my little discovery, and I am very happy to learn that you attribute some value to it, in judging it worthy of being published.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Now I must tell you a more complete history of the matter. The statuettes where the insect deposited its three cases of eggs had been placed in a glass cabinet in the dining room. They were made in Paris with a sort of greenish chalk and, forming the decoration of the cupboard for a good number of years, were never coated with any paint. Morever, I am absolutely sure that the eggs were deposited by the insect in the 8 days before the discovery that I made; before that time the statuettes were perfectly cleaned when we wiped them of dust.</p>
                    <p>Shortly I will have the honour to communicate to Sir J. Hooker<ref target="#foot.f3"/> documents on an important fact of Azorean botany. It concerns numerous examples of good impressions of leaves of Hedera, Persea and (Viburnum?) found in tuff at Mosteiros on the N.E. point of São Miguel.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have found no other fossil remains at all. I had hoped to find some seeds or terr. shells; but my searches have been unfruitful. The tuff and the higher strata allowing water to pass through, the moisture has decomposed everything. I will supplement the impressions with a geological profile of the site, illustrated with specimens from different strata. Perhaps these are the effects of the eruption of 7 Cidades.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I take the liberty of sending you a specimen of these impressions and some seeds brought to our beaches by the gulf stream, about which I spoke to you in a previous letter.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> One of these seeds was once the snuffbox of a fisherman.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Perhaps this use is unique to Azoreans; they use them only for powdered tobacco, and, when they wish to take a dose, they shake a grain on the back of the metacarpal part of the thumb (a convenient point where there is no smell of fish!) and they apply it eagerly to the nostril.</p>
<p>Please accept, Sir, renewed assurance of my humble and everlasting gratitude | Arruda Furtado.</p> 
                    <p>P.S. | Here, Sir, a little sketch of the topographic profile:—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width65">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_13500_english.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                </div>             
            </div>
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13444.xml">letter to Francisco de Arruda Furtado, 31 October 1881</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">On Arruda Furtado’s correspondence with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11360.xml">Góis Marques and Menezes de Sequeira 2015</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Hedera</hi> is a genus of ivy; <hi rend="italic">Persea</hi> is a genus of evergreen trees in the laurel family (Lauraceae); <hi rend="italic">Viburnum</hi> is a genus in the family Adoxaceae. Tuff is a type of rock made of volcanic ash.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">7 cidades</hi>: 7 cities (Portuguese). Sete Cidades Massif is a volcanic complex in the western part of the island of São Miguel; the most recent eruption was in the fifteenth century (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11514.xml">R. B. Moore 1990</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13258.xml">letter from Francisco de Arruda Furtado, 29 July 1881</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The letter is accompanied by a note in an unknown hand that reads: ‘1 Snuff box of seed of <hi rend="italic">Entada scandens</hi>   In the Museum are similar snuff boxes made from these seeds from Ceylon and from the Niger. There are also seeds thrown up at the Azores by the Gulf Stream | 2 The small seed is <hi rend="italic">Caesalpinia Bonducella</hi>.’ <hi rend="italic">Caesalpinia bonducella</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Guilandina bonduc</hi>, the grey nicker or nicker bean. <hi rend="italic">Entada scandens</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">E. gigas</hi>, known in the Azores as ‘fava de colom’; the seeds are dispersed by ocean currents and the plant is found from Central and South America to West and Central Africa, and India.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Pico Mafra is on the island of São Miguel in the Azores. Pozzolan is a class of siliceous minerals. Scoria is highly vesicular, dark volcanic rock.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>