<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10910">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Gazette</hi>   22 March 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13848A</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10910 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10910.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10910.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 2</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 2 April 1877, pp. 324–5</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Agric. Gaz. 1877.04.02: 324–5</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1877-03-22">22 Mar 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_44.xml">Agricultural Gazette</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Evidence for inheritance of constitutional diseases like scrofula so good that it seems rash to breed tainted animal.</p> 
<p>Experiments given in <hi rend="italic">Cross and self-fertilisation</hi> show that evil of inbreeding follows from near relations possessing closely similar constitution.</p> 
            <p>Size and vigour increased by breeding plants and animals from ancestors that lived some generations under different conditions of life.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cross and self-fertilisation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">generations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">in-breeding</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Down.]</placeName>
                    <salute>D<hi rend="smallCaps">ear</hi> S<hi rend="smallCaps">ir</hi>,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You ask my opinion as to whether the employment of a bull supposed to be scrofulous is consistent with the ultimate interest of the breeder.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> As a general rule I should defer to the judgment of any one who had experience on such a point, supposing that he was not biassed by interest or prejudice. But in this particular instance we have such good evidence of the inheritance of constitutional diseases, such as scrofula, consumption, &amp;c., that it seems to me very rash to breed from an animal thus tainted. In all probability a large majority of the offspring from a scrofulous bull, paired with a perfectly sound cow, would be to all appearance sound, but it can hardly be doubted that the evil would be latent in many of them, and ready to break out in subsequent generations.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I will venture to add a few remarks on the general question of close interbreeding. Sexual reproduction is so essentially the same in plants and animals, that I think we may fairly apply conclusions drawn from the one kingdom to the other. From a long series of experiments on plants, given in my book <hi rend="underline">On the Effects of Cross and Self-Fertilisation</hi>, the conclusion seems clear that there is no mysterious evil in the mere fact of the nearest relations breeding together; but that evil follows (independently of inherited disease or weakness) from the circumstance of near relations generally possessing a closely similar constitution. However little we may be able to explain the cause, the facts detailed by me show that the male and female sexual elements must be differentiated to a certain degree, in order to unite properly, and to give birth to a vigorous progeny.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Such differentiation of the sexual elements follows from the parents and their ancestors having lived during some generations under different conditions of life.</p>
<p>The closest interbreeding does not seem to induce variability or a departure from the typical form of the race or family, but it causes loss of size, of constitutional vigour in resisting unfavourable influences, and often of fertility. On the other hand, a cross between plants of the same sub-variety, which have been grown during some generations under different conditions, increases to an extraordinary degree the size and vigour of the offspring.</p>
<p>Some kinds of plants bear self-fertilisation much better than others; nevertheless it has been proved that these profit greatly by a cross with a fresh stock. So it appears to be with animals, for Shorthorn cattle—perhaps all cattle—can withstand close interbreeding with very little injury; but if they could be crossed with a distinct stock without any loss of their excellent qualities, it would be a most surprising fact if the offspring did not also profit in a very high degree in constitutional vigour. If, therefore, any one chose to risk breeding from an animal which suffered from some inheritable disease or weakness, he would act wisely to look out, not merely for a perfectly sound animal of the other sex, but for one belonging to another strain which had been bred during several generations at a distant place, under as different conditions of soil, climate, &amp;c., as possible, for in this case he might hope that the offspring, by having gained in constitutional vigour would be enabled to throw off the taint in their blood.—</p>
                    <p>C<hi rend="smallCaps">harles</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">arwin</hi>,</p> 
<p><hi rend="underline">March</hi> 22.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3416.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Chalmers Morton</ref>, the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Gazette</hi>, had asked CD to respond to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Holt Beever’s</ref> unsigned comments on scrofula and inbreeding; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10905.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. C. Morton, 19 March 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For CD’s views on the reappearance of latent characteristics, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 51–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For CD’s conclusions regarding the advantages of crossing, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 443.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>