<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-147">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. S. Henslow    15 [November 1831]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5215</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-147 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-147.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-147.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">NO 15 1831</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 20</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Darwin and Henslow</hi>: 47;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 214</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 179</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Henslow letters: 10 DAR/1/1/10)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Henslow letters: 10 DAR/1/1/10</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Devonport</placeName>
                <date when="1831-11-15">15 [Nov 1831]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml">Henslow, J. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sailing date fixed for end of month. <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> is beautiful. Details of instructions and route. Hopes voyage will not exceed four years. Quarters very confined. Considers Jenyns did wisely in not coming. If CD were longer out of college and some years older he never could have endured it.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">Beagle</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Devonport</placeName>
                    <date>15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Henslow</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The orders are come down from the Admiralty &amp; every thing is finally settled.— We positively sail the last day of this month &amp; I think before that time the Vessel will be ready.— She looks most beautiful, even a landsman must admire her. <hi rend="underline">we</hi> all think her the most perfect vessel ever turned out of the Dock yard.— one thing is certain no vessel has been fitted out so expensively &amp; with so much care.— Everything that can be made so is of Mahogany, &amp; nothing can exceed the neatness &amp; beauty of all the accomodations.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The instructions<ref target="#foot.f2"/> are very general &amp; leave a great deal to the Captains discretion &amp; judgement, thus paying a substantial, as well as many verbal compliments to him.— I will now give you an outline of the plans. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. to Madeira or Canary (perhaps only the latter) Cape Verd, Fernando Noronha, Rio de Janeiro, Monte Video, then set to work at Patagonia Terra del, Falkland Islands, so as to consume about year &amp; half. After this is completed to work our way Northward on W coast of S America, as far as Captain chooses, leaving time to take a good stretch across Pacific ocean—(taking some new course) New S. Wales, Van Diemens land.— Some of E Indian Island, Cape of good hope, So home.— I grieve to say time is unlimited, but yet I hope we shall not exceed the 4 years.— No vessel ever left England with such a set of Chronometers,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> viz 24, all very good ones.— In short everything is well, &amp; I have only now to pray for the sickness to moderate its fierceness, &amp; I shall do very well.— Yet I should not call it one of the very best opportunities for Nat Hist. that has ever occurred.— The absolute want of room is an evil, that nothing can surmount.— I think L Jenyns did very wisely in not coming:, that is, judging from my own feelings, for I am sure if I had left College some few years, or been those years older, I <hi rend="underline">never</hi> could have endured it.— The officers (excepting the Captain) are like the freshest freshmen— that is in their manners: in every thing else widely different.— Remember me most kindly to him, &amp; tell him if ever he dreams in the night of Palm trees he may in the morning comfort himself with the assurance that the voyage would not have suited him.— I am much obliged for your advice, de Mathematicis. I suspect when I am struggling with a triangle I shall often wish myself in your room, &amp; as for those wicked sulky surds, I do not know what I shall do without you to conjure them.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> My time passes away very pleasantly. I know one or two pleasant people, foremost of whom is M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Thunder &amp; Lightning Harris, whom I daresay you have heard of. My chief employment is to go on board the Beagle &amp; try to look as much like a sailor as ever I can.— I have no evidence of having taken in man, woman or child.— I am going to ask you to do one more commission &amp; I trust it will be the last. When I was in Cambridge, I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ash, asking to send my college account to my Father after having subtracted about 30£ for my furniture This he has forgotten to do, &amp; my Father has paid the bill, &amp; I want to have the Furniture money transmitted to my Father. Perhaps you would be kind enough to speak to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ash. I have cost my Father so much money.— I am quite ashamed of myself.—</p>
<p>I will write once again before sailing &amp; perhaps you will write to me before then. Remember me to Prof Sedgwick &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Peacock.</p>
<p>Believe me Yours affectionately | Chas. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.13 W] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘E’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.40 Perhaps] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘though’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.6 ‘Everything’; 1.6 ‘made so’; 1.16 ‘So’; 1.17 ‘hope’; 1.20 ‘it’; 1.27 ‘may’; 1.31 ‘know’; 1.33 ‘whom’; 1.34 ‘heard’; 1.35 ‘sailor’; 1.37 ‘last.’; 1.37 ‘When’; 1.40 ‘money’; 2.1 ‘perhaps’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The modifications ordered by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref> are described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> 2: 17–18. For discussion of the reconstruction of the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> as equipped for surveying work, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Darling 1978</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7545.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. A. Sulivan 1979</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7408.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stanbury 1979</ref>; for a history of her active service, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7733.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomson 1975</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The Admiralty instructions, in a memorandum by Captain Beaufort, are reproduced in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> 2: 24–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The chronometers (twenty-two, not twenty-four as CD says) and the measurements taken with them on the voyage are described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> Appendix, pp. 325–31. To superintend and repair the instruments, FitzRoy engaged, on a private basis, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4537.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George James Stebbing</ref>, son of a mathematical instrument maker at Portsmouth (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> 2: 19 and Appendix, p. 327).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his reminiscences of the Barmouth reading tour of 1828, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Maurice Herbert</ref> wrote to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref>: ‘He had, I imagine, no natural turn for mathematics, for he gave up his mathematical reading before he had mastered the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. part of Algebra, having had a special quarrel with Surds and the Binomial Theorem’ (DAR 112 (ser. 2): 62).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>