<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10439">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Mary Treat   3 April 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10992</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10439 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10439.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10439.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 178</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 178</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4796.xml">Treat, Mary</persName>
                <placeName>Green Cove Spring, Fla.</placeName>
                <date when="1876-04-03">3 Apr 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Encloses <hi rend="italic">Pinguicula</hi> specimens.</p> 
            <p>Believes she has found a new species of water-lily.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Pinguicula</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">water-lily</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Green Cove Spring, Florida,</placeName>
                    <date>Apr. 3, 1876.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. Darwin—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I came to Florida in November last, and have been working on the carnivorous plants here. With this letter I send you pressed specimens of the Pinguiculas which I have worked with. I shall soon publish my observations, and will send them to you in print.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I sent you Harper’s Magazine for February containing my article entitled “Is the Valve of the Utricularia sensitive”?<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I think I have found two distinct species of Utricularia since I came here, one growing in a warm sulphur spring in beautifully clear water, this species has no antennae, but it is not at all like our <hi rend="underline">U. purpurea</hi>, which you have noticed in the article I sent you.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>But my <hi rend="underline">greatest find</hi> has been a new water lily. It is really astonishing how it could have escaped the botanists. What have they been doing to let me come down here and find this beautiful lily? I enclose specimen of leaf. There are acres of it in extent growing in the bays and coves of the St. John’s river.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It is one of the most beautiful plants I ever beheld, and when I first saw it my heart fairly stood still. It cannot be a <hi rend="underline">variety</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Nymphaea</hi>, but a <hi rend="underline">distinct species</hi>. The character of the plant is unlike our Nymphæa, and it produces large double yellow flowers. I have sent the plant to Dr. Gray,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and asked him to give me directions to send it to Dr. Hooker.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I sent it to Dr. Gray a week ago, but it takes so long for letters and packages to go from one end of the Union to the other, that I grow impatient and write to you before hearing from him. If you are in communication with Dr. Hooker, please tell him about this water lily. I have transplanted it, and know that it will stand pretty rough treatment. It sends out runners, and even the little plants on the ends of the runners grow readily.</p>
<p>I have just met one of your countrymen and his charming wife—Mr. and Mrs. White<ref target="#foot.f7"/> who are traveling in this country. Mr. White is a member of Parliament and has traveled with Dr. Hooker. Mrs. W. is a good botanist, and is drawing and painting our Flora. I accompanied her in a row boat to this bed of water lilies, and she is to paint it for me.</p>
<p>Dr. Gray thinks that I have also found a distinct species of <hi rend="underline">Amaryllis</hi>, it blooms some two months earlier than our <hi rend="underline">A. atamasco</hi>, and the leaves are much longer and broader. It commenced blooming early in January and the leaves and flower-scapes are now dying down, and the bulbs are ripe, whereas our <hi rend="underline">A. atamasco</hi> is now in full flower.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I remain here until about the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May, when I shall return to to Vineland, N. Jersey. | Most sincerely yours, | Mary Treat,</p>
<p>P.S. As soon as I can press good specimens of the entire plant of the water lily—flowers roots &amp; runners, I will send to you &amp; Dr. Hooker if you desire—</p>
<p>P.S. You will not get a very good idea of the beauty of the leaf of the water lily from the pressed specimens, when fresh, it is very glossy, and finely blotched with red. I enclose some of the larger leaves in the package with the Pinguiculas.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>M.T.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.4 I ... sensitive”? 1.5] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The specimens have not been found. Treat recorded her observations of carnivorous plants in Florida in <hi rend="italic">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</hi> (Treat 1876b); see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9025.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Treat 1885</ref>, chapter 10. <hi rend="italic">Pinguicula</hi> is the genus of butterworts.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">An annotated copy of Treat’s article (Treat 1876a) is in DAR 226.2: 160–2. <hi rend="italic">Utricularia</hi> is the genus of bladderworts.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The ‘distinct species’ have not been identified. Treat described <hi rend="italic">Utricularia purpurea</hi> as different from all other species she had examined and as having no antennae in Treat 1876a, p. 384. This species was not discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Treat named the water lily <hi rend="italic">Nymphaea lutea</hi> but later noted it was the same as <hi rend="italic">N. flava</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">N. mexicana</hi>). It had been depicted (with an American swan) in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John James Audubon’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Birds of America</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_251.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Audubon 1840–4</ref>, 6: facing 226) but was unknown to botanists (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Treat 1877</ref> for Treat’s account of her discovery and her description of the plant). The leaf has not been found. St Johns River runs almost the entire length of eastern Florida; Treat traced the plant from Green Cove Spring thirty-five miles south to Jacksonville (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 366).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7771.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James White</ref> (MP for Brighton from 1860 until 1874), and his wife Mary.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Gray concluded that this was a new form of <hi rend="italic">Amaryllis atamasco</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Zephyranthes atamasco</hi>, the rain lily); see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Treat 1877</ref>, pp. 367–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The leaves have not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>