<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5292A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   1 December 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20481</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5292A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5292A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5292A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">(German trans)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 99–102.</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Möller, Alfred 1915–21 2: 99–102</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Desterro, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1866-12-01">1 Dec 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Gives observations on orchid ovules ripening long after blooming.</p> 
<p>Infertility with own pollen sometimes does and sometimes does not indicate dimorphism; gives observations on <hi rend="italic">Ximenia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eschscholtzia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oncidium flexuosum</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Describes some striking seeds eaten by birds,</p>
            <p>and some new dimorphic species.</p> 
<p>Variation in <hi rend="italic">Thillia</hi>.</p>  
<p>Confirms CD’s suspicion that the lancet-fish [<hi rend="italic">Amphioxus</hi>] lives in competition with invertebrates: it shares its habitat with a similar-looking <hi rend="italic">Ophelia</hi>, which is quite unlike other annelids, just as the lancet-fish is unlike other fishes.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Amphioxus</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">annelids</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">invertebrates</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">lancet-fish</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Ophelia</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Thillia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Eschscholtzia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oncidium flexuosum</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchid</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Ximenia</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">maturity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">stations, niches</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">struggle for existence</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>1. December 1866.</date>
                    <salute>Verehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Vor einer Woche erhielt ich Ihren freundlichen Brief vom 25. Septb. und danke Ihnen herzlich;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> er ist sehr werthvoll und äusserst interessant für mich, da er sich mit Gegenständen beschäftigt, die gerade jetzt meine Aufmerksamkeit lebhaft fesseln.</p>
<p>Schon Dr. Hildebrand hat, wie ich durch Ihren Brief zu meiner Freude erfahre, beobachtet, dass die Ovula mancher Orchideen zur Blüthezeit nicht reif sind.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Dies scheint ganz allgemein bei Epidendren und Vandeen vorzukommen; wenigstens habe ich noch keine Art von diesen Familien kennen gelernt, welche ihre Ovula zu dieser Zeit ganz fertig hätte. Bei meinem Epidendrum triandrum, wie es heissen mag,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> sind selbst jetzt—ungefähr 6 Monate nach der Blüthe—die Ovula noch nicht ganz reif. Das Säulchen solcher Orchideen pflegt nach dem Welken der Blüthe stark zu schwellen; die Pollenschläuche dringen bald in den Griffel ein und bilden sechs Fäden, die an seinen Wänden entlang laufen; diese Fäden kann man mit grosser Leichtigkeit von einander trennen. Bei Leptotes bicolor waren in einer Blume zwei Monate, nachdem sie mit ihren eigenen Pollinien befruchtet war, diese Fäden sehr dick und schneeweiss mit einem seidenartigen Glanze. Der Pollen scheint in vielen Fällen lange Zeit frisch zu bleiben, während er bei anderen Arten trocken und schwärzlich wird, bald nachdem die Schläuche in den Griffel eingedrungen sind. So ist es z. B. der Fall bei einem kleinen sich selbst befruchtenden Epidendrum (verwandt mit E. caespitosum). Die Caudiculi bleiben unverändert und Pollenschläuche werden nicht gebildet, weder bei dieser, noch, soweit ich weiss, bei irgend einer anderen Art von Epidendren. Wenn die Befruchtung durch Insecten-Thätigkeit bewirkt wird, so pflegen die Caudiculi gewöhnlich an dem Insectenkörper festgeheftet zu bleiben, an dem sie durch die klebrige Substanz des Rostellum angeklebt sind.</p>
<p>Was Pflanzen betrifft, die mit ihrem eigenen Pollen unfruchtbar sind, so vermuthe ich stark, dass manche von ihnen in der That wirklich dem Wesen nach dimorph sind.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Es stehen z. B. ein paar Büsche einer Ximenia nicht weit von meinem Hause und einige andere Büsche etwa eine Meile entfernt. Diese verschiedenen Büsche haben im Laufe von 10 Jahren nur zwei Früchte hervorgebracht. Unter der Annahme, dass die verschiedenen Pflanzen an jeder der beiden Oertlichkeiten zu derselben, in ihrer Function verschiedenen, obwohl in der Form nicht zu unterscheidenden Gruppe gehören, würde sich diese Unfruchtbarkeit leicht erklären. In anderen Fällen ist sicher kein Dimorphismus vorhanden, wie ich mich jetzt überzeugt habe, sondern (wie bei Dr. Hildebrand’s Fall von Corydalis cava)<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Unfruchtbarkeit mit dem eigenen, Fruchtbarkeit aber mit dem Pollen irgend einer andern Pflanze derselben Art. Dies fand ich z. B. bei vier Pflanzen von Eschscholtzia in meinem Garten, an denen ich einige Versuche machte. Diese vollkommene Unfruchtbarkeit mit eigenem Pollen würde kaum unbemerkt geblieben sein können, wenn sie bei allen Individuen einer so häufigen Gartenpflanze existirte; vielleicht mag sie bei meinen Pflanzen auf die Kultur unter abweichenden klimatischen Verhältnissen zurückzuführen sein.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Die Verschiedenheit der beiden Pollen wird an sonnigen Tagen 4–5 Stunden, nachdem der Pollen auf die Narbe gebracht ist, sichtbar, da alsdann der Pollen einer fremden Pflanze bewirkt, dass die Narbe sich aufrichtet, während der eigene Pollen keine Bewegung hervorruft.</p>
<p>Oncidium flexuosum ist auch ganz unfruchtbar mit eigenem Pollen und fruchtbar mit dem Pollen irgend einer andern Pflanze derselben Art.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Ich habe mehr als 100 Blumen befruchtet und unveränderlich dasselbe Ergebniss erhalten. Während der ersten drei Tage, nachdem man die Pollinien auf die Narben gebracht hat, ist kein Unterschied zwischen den eigenen und denen von einer anderen Pflanze. Die Narbenkammer hat so zu sagen zwei Thüren, welche in der nicht befruchteten Blüthe weit offen stehen. Im Lauf des ersten Tages wird die innere Thür, im Lauf des zweiten Tages die äussere, welche von den beiden seitlichen unfruchtbaren Staubfäden gebildet ist, geschlossen. Bald beginnen die Pollinien sich aufzulösen oder sich zuerst in Gruppen von vier und dann in einzelne Körner zu sondern, und diese einzelnen Körner senden Schläuche aus, von denen einige am Ende des dritten Tages schon von erheblicher Länge sind; das Säulchen erscheint leicht geschwollen. Im Lauf des vierten Tages erscheint bei den Blüthen, welche mit eigenem Pollen befruchtet sind, eine mattbräunliche Linie, welche die Pollinien von der Narbe trennt, und diese Linie nimmt schnell an Breite zu und wird dunkler, so dass am Ende dieses Tages oder etwas später das ganze Pollinium und die Oberfläche der Narbenkammer dunkelbraun geworden ist. Die Pollenkörner und Schläuche sind verschrumpft. Diese mit eigenem Pollen befruchteten Blumen welken etwas schneller als die mit dem Pollen einer andern Pflanze befruchteten. Die Fruchtknoten der letzteren beginnen bald zu schwellen und die rudimentären Fransen der Placenta wachsen schnell, obwohl 23 Tage nach der Befruchtung die Ovula noch weit von der Reife entfernt sind; die Pollenschläuche haben sich zu dieser Zeit bis über mehr als die Hälfte der Griffelsäule verlängert.</p>
<p>Ich dachte zuerst, dass das Schliessen der Thüren von der Narbenkammer und das Austreiben von Pollenschläuchen als Zeichen der beginnenden Befruchtung der Blumen angesehen werden könnte, fand aber später, dass—auch wenn man die Pollinien einer so weit verschiedenen Art, wie z. B. Epidendrum fragrans auf die Narbe von Oncidium flexuosum bringt—die Narbenkammer sich schliesst, die Pollinien sich auflösen und Pollenschläuche hervortreiben.</p>
<p>Ein altes Pollinium, welches ich 9 oder 10 Monate früher von einer anderen Art von Oncidium genommen hatte, löste sich nicht auf, sondern war, nachdem es 4 Tage lang in der Narbenkammer von Oncidium flexuosum gelegen hatte, schwarz geworden.</p>
<p>Ich bin jetzt in der Lage, Ihnen zwei neue Beispiele von Pflanzen zu geben, welche auffällige Samen haben und an den Klappen der Frucht festsitzen bleiben. Eines ist ein kleiner Baum, der zu den Meliaceen gehört, wahrscheinlich eine Guarea; die Pflanze hat acht ziegelrothe Samen, welche an den Klappen der Frucht befestigt bleiben (sie sind zu gross, um sie in einem Briefe zu senden); das Andere ist ein grosser Baum aus der Gattung Talauma (Magnoliacee).<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Ich erinnere mich noch meines Erstaunens, als ich vor etwa 12 Jahren seine zahlreichen leuchtend gefärbten Samen an einer grossen Ananas ähnlichen Frucht baumeln sah. In dem Falle von Paullinia mag wohl der fleischige Arillus Vögel veranlassen, die Samen zu verschlucken; bei den Mimoseen und bei Rhynchosia ist keine fleischige Hülle vorhanden, aber die Samen sind ungewöhnlich hart, und da Hühnervögel häufig kleine Steine verschlucken, um die Zerkleinerung ihres Futters zu beförden, so habe ich mir gedacht, dass diese harten auffälligen Samen wohl zu demselben Zwecke von unsern Jacús (Penelope) oder andern Vögeln verschluckt werden möchten. Endlicher sagt von Talauma, dass die Samen eine “testa subossea” hätten.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Die Samen von Guarea haben weder eine fleischige Hülle noch sind sie sehr hart.</p>
<p>Unsere strauchartige Oxalis ist wirklich dimorph; ich habe jetzt die mittelgrifflige Form auch gefunden.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Diesmal kann ich nur zwei Arten zu der Liste der dimorphen Pflanzen hinzufügen:</p>
<p>1) Ein Lipostoma mit blauen Blüthen;<ref target="#foot.f12"/> es wächst in kleinen Gräben zusammen mit der merkwürdigen moosähnlichen Mayaca; die Antheren der kurzgriffligen Form sind länger, die Pollenkörner grösser. Ich glaube, dass man unter den Rubiaceen noch manche dimorphen Pflanzen finden wird; denn in Endlicher’s Gattungsbeschreibungen lese ich häufig: “stamina inclusa, stigma exsertum” oder “stamina exserta, stigma inclusum”.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>2) Eine Statice, welche an der Küste wächst, aber auch feuchte Stellen liebt.</p>
<p>Nun zu der Veränderlichkeit des Kelches bei Hillia, auf die ich in meinem letzten Briefe hingewiesen habe.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Die Gattung Hillia, welche man auf den ersten Anblick nach der Form der Blumenkrone, der Samenkapsel und der Samen eher für eine Apocynee als für eine Rubiacee halten möchte, soll nach Endlicher einen “limbus calycis biquadripartitus” haben.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Nun kann man bei unserer Art an derselben Pflanze Calyces finden mit einem ganz verkümmerten Limbus, andere mit zwei, mit vier oder sogar sechs Laciniae. Die Länge der zwei Paare von Blättern, die unmittelbar unter dem Fruchtknoten stehen, ist ebenso veränderlich wie die Zahl der Laciniae des Kelches. Ich mass sie bei 19 Blumen. Bei 11 von diesen Blumen hatte der Kelch einen verkümmerten Limbus, bei sechs zwei Laciniae; in einer Blüthe waren vier Laciniae vorhanden, von denen zwei 6 mm und zwei kaum 1 mm lang waren, und in einer Blume endlich hatte der Kelch sechs Laciniae von 4 mm Länge. Die Länge des obersten Blätterpaares schwankte von 3 bis zu 50 mm, die der Stipulae von ganz verkümmerter Ausbildung bis 15 mm, das nächste Blätterpaar hatte 5 bis 118 mm, die Stipulae verkümmert und bis zu 32 mm. Die Krone hatte immer 6 Laciniae.</p>
<p>Sie hatten ganz recht mit der Vermuthung, dass in dem Falle des Lancettfischchens der Kampf ums Dasein mit Gliedern der wirbellosen Klassen stattfinden werde.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Hier wenigstens ist sein einziger Begleiter und Nebenbuhler in dem unfruchtbaren Sande, in welchem es lebt, eine Ophelia, welche dem Lancettfisch im allgemeinen Aeussern und in der Bewegung so ähnlich ist, dass ich, als ich sie zuerst sah, eine neue rothblütige Art von Amphioxus entdeckt zu haben glaubte.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> Die Ophelia sieht in der That den meisten andern Anneliden so wenig ähnlich, wie der Lancettfisch anderen Fischen. Unser Lancettfisch scheint von der europäischen Form specifisch nicht verschieden zu sein; wenigstens konnte weder Johannes Müller, der von Kröyer gesammelte Exemplare untersuchte, noch Max Schultze, dem ich einige gesandt hatte, irgend welchen Unterschied von dem Lancettfisch aus Neapel auffinden.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>Indem ich Ihnen ein glückliches neues Jahr wünsche, bin ich, werther Herr, mit aufrichtiger Hochachtung treulichst der Ihrige. | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>1. December 1866.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>A week ago I received your kind letter of 25 Sept for which I thank you very much.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is very valuable and extremely interesting for me since it deals with objects that currently fascinate me.</p>
<p>Dr. Hildebrand has already observed, as I am pleased to learn from your letter, that the ovula of many orchids are not ripe at the time of flowering.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> This seems to be common among the Epidendreae and the Vandeae; at least I have not yet encountered one species in these families in which the ovula were ready at this time. In my Epidendrum triandrum, as it may be called,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> the ovula are not even quite ready now, approximately six months after flowering. The little column of such orchids usually swells up a lot after the flower has withered; soon the pollen tubes penetrate the style and form six threads that run along its walls. The threads are very easily separated from one another. In a flower of Leptotes bicolor these threads were very thick and snow white with a silky sheen two months after it had been fertilised with its own pollinia. The pollen seems in many cases to remain fresh for a long time whereas in other species it dries up and turns black soon after the penetration of the tubes into the style. For instance, this is the case with a small self-fertilising Epidendrum (related to E. caespitosum). The caudiculi remain unchanged and pollen tubes are not formed, either in this species or, as far as I know, in any other species of Epidendreae. When the fertilisation is effected by insect activity the caudiculi usually remain on the insect body by means of the sticky substance of the rostellum.</p>
<p>In plants that are infertile with their own pollen, I strongly suspect that many of them are really, in essence, dimorphic.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> For example, there are a couple of bushes of a Ximenia not far from my house and several more about a mile away. These various bushes have only produced two fruits in the course of 10 years. Assuming that the various plants in each of the two locations, different in their function but indistinguishable in form, belong to the same group, it would be easy to explain this infertility. In other cases, as I have now convinced myself, there is certainly no dimorphism, rather infertility with own pollen but fertility with that of another plant of the same species, as in Dr. Hildebrand’s case of Corydalis cava.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I found this, for example, in four plants of Eschscholtzia in my garden on which I have made some experiments. This complete infertility with own pollen could hardly have remained unnoticed, had it existed in all individuals of such a common garden plant. Perhaps in the case of my plants it can be attributed to their cultivation in divergent climatic conditions.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The difference between the two pollens becomes visible on sunny days 4 to 5 hours after the pollen has been put on the stigma, for the pollen from a foreign plant causes the stigma to stand up erect whereas its own pollen does not give rise to any movement.</p>
<p>Oncidium flexuosum is also completely infertile with its own pollen and fertile with the pollen of any other plant of the same species.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have fertilised more than 100 flowers and without fail always had the same result. There is no difference between own pollen and that from another plant during the first three days after having brought the pollinia on to the stigma. The stigmatic chamber has two doors, so to speak, which are widely open in the unfertilised flower. In the course of the first day the inner door will be closed; in the course of the second, the outer, which is formed from the two lateral, infertile filaments, will be closed. Soon the pollinia begin to disintegrate or at first to separate into groups of four and then into single grains; and these single grains emit tubes, some of which by the end of the third day are of considerable length. The little column appears slightly swollen. During the fourth day, in flowers fertilised with their own pollen, a pale brownish line appears that separates the pollinia from the stigma and this line quickly gets wider and darker so that at the end of this day, or soon after, the entire pollinium and the surface of the stigmatic chamber have become dark brown. The pollen-grains and tubes have shrivelled. These flowers fertilised with their own pollen wither somewhat faster than those fertilised with pollen from another plant. The ovaries of the latter soon begin to swell up and the fringe of the placenta grows quickly, although the ovula are still far from ripeness 23 days after fertilisation. The pollen tubes have by this time lengthened by up to more than half the length of the stylar column.</p>
<p>At first I thought that the closing of the doors to the stigmatic chamber and the emission of the pollen tubes could be seen as a sign of the beginning fertilisation of the flowers, but later I found that—even when the pollinia of such a widely differing species as Epidendrum fragrans are brought onto the stigma of Oncidium flexuosum—the stigmatic chamber closes, the pollinia dissolve and the pollen tubes begin to grow.</p>
<p>An old pollinium that I had taken from a different species of Oncidium 9 or 10 months earlier did not dissolve but turned black after it had lain in the stigmatic chamber of Oncidium flexuosum for 4 days.</p>
<p>I am now in a position to give you two new examples of plants that have conspicuous seeds stuck to the valve of the fruit. One is a small tree of the Meliaceae, probably a Guarea. The plant has eight brick-red seeds stuck to the valve of the fruit (they are too big to be sent in a letter). The other is a big tree of the genus Talauma (Magnoliaceae).<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I still remember my surprise about 12 years ago when I saw its numerous brightly coloured seeds dangling on a large pineapple-like fruit. In the case of Paullinia the fleshy arillus may prompt birds to swallow the seeds. With Mimosa and Rhynchosia there is no fleshy hull but the seeds are exceptionally hard and since gallinaceous birds often swallow small stones in order to promote the breaking up of their food, I imagined that these hard and conspicuous seeds could well serve the same purpose when swallowed by our Jacús (Penelope) or other birds. Endlicher says of Talauma that the seeds have a “testa subossea”.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> The seeds of Guarea neither have a fleshy hull nor are they very hard.</p>
<p>Our bush-like Oxalis really is dimorphic; I have now also found the mid-styled form.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> This time I can only add two species to the list of dimorphic plants:</p>
<p>1) A Lipostoma with blue flowers;<ref target="#foot.f12"/> it grows in small ditches with the strange, moss-like Mayaca. The anthers of the short-styled kind are longer, the pollen-grains bigger. I think that one can still find many dimorphic plants among the Rubiaceae because in his descriptions of genera Endlicher often writes: “stamina inclusa, stigma exsertum” or “stamina exserta, stigma inclusum”.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>2) A Statice which grows on the coast but also likes humid spots.</p>
<p>Now on to the variability of the length of the calyx in Hillia, which I referred to in my last letter.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> The genus Hillia, which at first glance might be taken for an Apocynaceae rather than a Rubiaceae on account of the shape of its corolla, seed capsule and seeds, ought to have a “limbus calycis biquadripartitus” according to Endlicher.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Now, in our species of this plant one finds calyces with a completely rudimentary limbus, others with two, four, or even six laciniae. The length of the two pairs of leaves that are directly under the ovary is just as variable as the number of laciniae of the calyx. I measured it in 19 flowers. In 11 of these flowers the calyx had a withered limbus, in 6 of them there were 2 laciniae; in one flower four laciniae were found of which two were 6 mm long and two barely 1 mm, and finally in one flower the calyx had six laciniae 4 mm long. The length of the upper pair of leaves ranged from 3 to 50 mm, that of the stipules from completely rudimentary to 15 mm. The next pair of leaves were from 5 to 118 mm, the stipules from rudimentary to 32 mm. The corolla always had 6 laciniae.</p>
<p>Your conjecture that in the case of the lancelet the struggle for survival takes place in competition with members of the invertebrate classes was thoroughly justified.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Here at least, its only companion and rival in the infertile sand that it inhabits is an Ophelia which in general appearance and movement resembles the lancelet so closely that at first I thought I had discovered a new red-blooded Amphioxus species.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> The Ophelia indeed resembles the other Annelida as little as the lancelet resembles other fish. Our lancelet does not seem to differ specifically from the European type; at least neither Johannes Müller, who examined samples collected by Kröyer, nor Max Schultze, whom I had sent some, could find any difference from the Neapolitan lancelet.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>In wishing you a happy new year, I remain, honoured Sir, sincerely yours. | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For an account of the reconstruction of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5004A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 13 February 1866</ref>, n. 1. For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.14, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For an account of the reconstruction of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5004A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 13 February 1866</ref>, n. 1. For a transcription of this letter from its published German source, see pp. 405–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 25 September [1866]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had mentioned <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Hildebrand’s</ref> observations on the development of the ovules in some orchid species (Hildebrand 1865c) in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5216.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Müller of 25 September [1866]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Epidendrum triandrum</hi> is a  synonym of <hi rend="italic">Prosthechea cochleata</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">triandra</hi>, a variety that does not occur in Brazil. It seems likely that Müller used the name here simply to refer to a three-anthered, self-pollinating form of <hi rend="italic">Epidendrum</hi> (Robert Dressler, personal communication). CD added Müller’s information on the immature state of the ovules at the time of flowering in orchids of the tribes Epidendreae and Vandeae to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 173.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Müller refers to the concept of ‘functional dimorphism’ that CD introduced in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref>, p. 82 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 104; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 2 August 1866</ref> and n. 9). CD clarified his use of the phrase ‘dimorphic in function’ as referring to plants that could be ‘divided into two equal bodies functionally but not structurally different’ in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5216.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Müller of 25 September [1866]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to Hildebrand 1866d (see also the expanded German version of the paper, Hildebrand 1866–7b). CD had corresponded with Hildebrand on the pollination mechanism of <hi rend="italic">Corydalis cava</hi>, and had communicated Hildebrand’s paper to the International Horticultural Exhibition (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5092.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Friedrich Hildebrand, 16 May [1866]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Müller refers to <hi rend="italic">Eschscholzia californica</hi>, a plant not native to Brazil (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 2 August 1866</ref>). His suspicion that self-sterility in this plant might be related to the climate in which it was grown was later confirmed by CD. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. 331–3, CD described changes in the degree of self-sterility in plants raised from seeds of <hi rend="italic">E. californica</hi> sent to him by Müller and also gave the results of reciprocal experiments made by Müller on plants raised from seeds sent by CD.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD discussed Müller’s observations of <hi rend="italic">Oncidium flexuosum</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 134–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Müller had described plants with brightly coloured seeds attached to the valve of the fruit in his letters of 2 August 1866 and 1 and 3 October 1866.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Müller refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1508.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stephan Ladislaus Endlicher’s</ref> generic diagnosis of <hi rend="italic">Talauma</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endlicher 1836–42</ref>, 1: 837). ‘Testa subossea’: somewhat bony seed-coat.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Müller probably meant to write ‘trimorphic’, or <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref> may have incorrectly transcribed or translated the word. (Like all of Müller’s letters to CD, the letter was written in English and later translated into German for Möller ed. 1915–21. The original letter has not been found.) Müller had earlier told CD he thought the species was probably trimorphic, but had only found specimens of the long-styled and short-styled forms (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5264.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, [2 November 1866]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Lipostoma</hi> is now placed in synonymy with <hi rend="italic">Coccocypselum.</hi> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 134, CD described flower specimens of <hi rend="italic">Lipostoma</hi> sent to him by Müller.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Müller refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endlicher 1836–42</ref>. ‘Stamina inclusa, stigma exsertum’: stamens not projecting, stigma exserted. ‘Stamina exserta, stigma inclusum’: stamens exserted, stigma not projecting.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5264.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, [2 November 1866]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">‘Limbus calycis biquadripartitus’: lobe of the calyx biquadripartite (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endlicher 1836–42</ref>, 1: 556). For a recent revision of the genus <hi rend="italic">Hillia</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Taylor 1994</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 143–4, CD had remarked that the lancelet (<hi rend="italic">Branchiostoma lanceolatum</hi>, formerly <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus lanceolatus</hi>) would not compete with other fish, but more probably with invertebrates. CD added Müller’s information to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, p. 146. The lancelet was initially classed as a primitive fish but has now been moved to its own subphylum, Cephalochordata.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><hi rend="italic">Ophelia</hi> is a genus of the class Polychaeta (marine worms). For more on the similarity between some forms of Opheliidae and <hi rend="italic">Branchiostoma</hi>, see Rouse and Pleijel 2001, pp. 53–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Johannes Peter Müller reported that he received a specimen of <hi rend="italic">Branchiostoma</hi> collected in Brazil by Henrik Nikolaj Krĺ yer (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5706.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. P. Müller 1844</ref>, p. 8 n. 3). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4240.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Johann Sigismund Schultze</ref> had written a paper on young specimens of lancelet (Schultze 1851).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>