<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6691">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Richard Spruce   1 April 1869<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10784A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6691 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6691.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6691.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Spruce 1908, 2: 385</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Spruce, Richard 1908 2: 385</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1869-04-01">1 Apr 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4507.xml">Spruce, Richard</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>RS’s facts are remarkable. A year or two ago CD would not have believed ants could produce an inherited effect, but he has "lately come to believe rather more in inherited mutations". However, CD is not satisfied that the sacs are inherited and urges RS to produce any other evidence he might have.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The facts which you state are extraordinary, and quite new to me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> If you can prove that the effects produced by ants are really inherited, it would be a most remarkable fact, and would open up quite a new field of inquiry. You ask for my opinion; if you had asked a year or two ago I should have said that I could not believe that the visits of the ants could produce an inherited effect; but I have lately come to believe rather more in inherited mutilations. I have advanced in opposition to such a belief, galls not being inherited. After reading your paper I admit, Firstly, from the presence of sacs in plants of so many families, and their absence in certain species, that they must be due to some extraneous cause acting in tropical South America. Secondly, I admit that the cause must be the ants, either acting mechanically or, as may perhaps be suspected from the order to which they belong, from some secretion. Thirdly, I admit, from the generality of the sacs in certain species, and from your not having observed ants in certain cases (though may not the ants have paid previous visits?), that the sacs are probably inherited. But I cannot feel satisfied on this head. Have any of these plants produced their sacs in European hot-houses? Or have you observed the commencement of the sacs in young and unfolded leaves which could not <hi rend="underline">possibly</hi> have been visited by the ants? If you have any such evidence, I would venture strongly to advise you to produce it …</p>
<p>I may add that you are not quite correct (towards the close of your paper) in supposing that I believe that insects directly modify the structure of flowers. I only believe that spontaneous variations adapted to the structure of certain insects flourish and are preserved.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is provided by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref>, the editor of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7395.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spruce 1908</ref>, from which this transcription of part of CD’s letter is taken.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6690.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Richard Spruce, [before 1 April 1869]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Spruce had written, ‘The inimitable researches of Mr. Darwin have rendered it (to my mind) almost certain that many of the deviations from symmetry in the form and direction of the parts of a flower have been brought about by the direct mechanical agency of insects’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7395.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spruce 1908</ref>, 2: 408).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>