<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13123">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. J. Romanes   17 April 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15532</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13123 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13123.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13123.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">E. D. Romanes 1896, p. 112</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Romanes, E. D. 1896: 112</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Cornwall Terrace, 18</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-17">17 Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Looks forward to reading CD’s <hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Agrees that habits of sand-wasp are determined by natural selection.</p>
            <p>Experiment of exposing plants to flashing light gives uncertain result.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sand-wasp</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Earthworms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">habit</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">worms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-13" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>18 Cornwall Terrace, Regent’s Park, N.W.:</placeName>
                    <date>April 17, 1881.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Your long letter has been most refreshing to me in every way.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>I am looking foward with keen interest to the appearance of your book on Worms, and am unexpectedly glad to hear that my letter was of any use.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>I should very much like to see the book you mention, and from what you say about sending it I shall not order it. But there is no need to send it soon, as I have already an accumulation of books to review for ‘Nature.’<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>I am very glad that you think well of the Echinoderm work. Several other experiments have occurred to me to try, and I hope to be able to do so next autumn, as also the interesting experiment suggested by Frank of rotating by clockwork (as you did the plants) an Echinus inverted upon its aboral pole, to see whether it would right itself when the influence of gravity is removed.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>No doubt I must in my second book deal with instincts of all kinds, complex or otherwise.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Your ‘speculations’ on the sand-wasp seem to me very pithy— excuse the pun suggested by the analogy of the cattle— and I think there can be little doubt that such is the direction in which the explanation is to be sought. I also think that the difficulty is mitigated by the consideration that both the ganglion of the spider and the sting of the wasp are organs situated on the median line of their respective possessors, and therefore that the origin of the instinct may have been determined or assisted by the mere anatomical form of the animals—the wasp not stinging till securely mounted on the spider’s back, and when so mounted the sting might naturally strike the ganglion. But I have not yet read Fabre’s own account, so this view may not hold. Anyhow, and whatever determining conditions as to origin may have been, it seems to me there can be little doubt that natural selection would have developed it in the way you suggest.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>I have now grown a number of seeds exposed to the flashing light, but am not yet quite sure as to the result. About one seedling out of ten bends towards the flashing source very decidedly, while all the rest, although exposed to just the same conditions, grow perfectly straight. But I shall, no doubt, find out the reason of this by further trials. It is strange that the same thing happens when I expose other seedlings to constant light of exceedingly dim intensity. It looks as if some individuals were more sensitive to light than others. I do not know whether you found any evidence of this.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>I have just found that this year again I have been too late in asking them to send me cuttings of the vine for grafting. I did not know that the sap in vines began to run so early.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>I remain ever yours, very sincerely and most respectfully, | <hi rend="smallCaps">Geo. J. Romanes</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13118.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 April 1881</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref>, p. 95, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13118.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 April 1881</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13118.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 April 1881</ref> and n. 4. The book was <hi rend="italic">Der Kampf der Theile im Organismus</hi> (The struggle between the parts of the organism; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11230.xml">Roux 1881</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13118.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 April 1881</ref> and n. 3. CD had read an abstract of ‘Observations on the locomotor system of Echinodermata’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11092.xml">G. J. Romanes and Ewart 1881</ref>). CD and his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Francis Darwin</ref> had used a klinostat to rotate plants in pots, in order to negate the influence of gravity on plant movement (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 93). Francis suggested that Romanes could use a similar approach with <hi rend="italic">Echinus</hi> (a genus of sea urchins; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11232.xml">G. J. Romanes 1883b</ref>, pp. 134–5). ‘Aboral’ is a term used to describe the side of a sea urchin opposite its mouth; sea urchins have an oral/aboral axis rather than a dorsal/ventral one.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13118.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 April 1881</ref> and n. 7. Romanes refers to <hi rend="italic">Mental evolution in animals</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10553.xml">G. J. Romanes 1883a</ref>); he discussed the instincts of <hi rend="italic">Sphex</hi>, a genus of digger wasps, on pp. 299–303. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13118.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 16 April 1881</ref> and nn. 7 and 8. For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1578.xml">Jean-Henri Fabre</ref>’s account of the method used by the wasp to paralyse its prey, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10935.xml">Fabre 1879</ref>, pp. 94–100.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13069.xml">letter from G. J. Romanes, [6 or 13 or 20] March 1881</ref> and n. 3. CD had suggested the use of canary grass (<hi rend="italic">Phalaris canariensis</hi>) or cabbage (<hi rend="italic">Brassica oleracea</hi>) seedlings; see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12908F.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 13 December 1880</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Since 1875, Romanes had been carrying out experiments on graft hybrids to test CD’s hypothesis of pangenesis; see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 23,  <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10059.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 12 July 1875</ref>  and n. 8, and <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10554.xml">letter from G. J. Romanes, [after 8 January 1877]</ref>  and n. 5.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>