<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10366">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From M. T. Masters   24 January 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">18027</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10366 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10366.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10366.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 86</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 86</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3217.xml">Masters, M. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Gardeners’ Chronicle</placeName>
                <date when="1876-01-24">24 Jan 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>He is surveying the literature on the struggle for existence among pasture plants. Asks CD for the "many cases on record" of changed relations among plants under slightly changed conditions alluded to in the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. [See M. T. Masters, J. B. Lawes and J. M. Gilbert "Agricultural, botanical, and chemical results of experiments on the mixed herbage of permanent meadow, conducted for more than twenty years in succession on the same land (pt 2, The botanical results)", <hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond.</hi> 173 (1883): 1181–413.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">pasture plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">The Gardeners’ Chronicle Office, | 41, Wellington Street, Strand, W.C. | London</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 24 <hi rend="print">187</hi>6</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir/</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>There is an article by a gardener of ability and intelligence in this week’s Chronicle àpropos of tendrils to which I venture to call your attention— the facts he adduces are very curious and I have no doubt they are accurately recorded—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>—At p. 72 of the “Origin” you allude to the inter-relations between plants living in association and to the changes in those relations consequent on slightly changed conditions &amp;c—</p>
<p>As you allude to “many cases on record” I take the liberty of asking if you have any further note where such cases may be found?—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I know of Dureau de la Malle’s paper<ref target="#foot.f3"/>—scattered notices of Hooker’s<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and other botanists—and I am familiar with what Alph De Candolle says in his Geographie Botanique<ref target="#foot.f5"/>   But I think there must be other cases w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>. you had in view when you were writing the Origin— My object in putting the question is to see what has been written concerning the struggle for existence among pasture plants— As you know Mess Lawes &amp; Gilbert have for years been trying the effects of various manures on grass land as well as on cereal &amp; other crops—</p>
<p>The effects on the several grass plots are very remarkable the whole vegetation of the plot being in some cases altered  I have lately been engaged in tabulating and analysing the results obtained during the last twenty years and should like to co-relate the facts with others.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If you can without inconvenience favor me with any reference to the literature of the subject which I am not likely to have seen I shall be greatly obliged—but pray do not put yourself to any trouble in the matter</p>
<p>faithfully y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. | Maxwell. T. Masters</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In his paper in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, ‘Bunches v. tendrils’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8996.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Fish 1876</ref>), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1638.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Taylor Fish</ref> quoted extensively from the discussion of grape-vine tendrils in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi></ref>, pp. 137–9, where CD had concluded that they were modified flower peduncles. Fish described a method of increasing the yield in grape vines by weighing down flower-stalks, and suggested that when prevented from curling they could not degenerate into tendrils.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his discussion of ‘mutual checks to increase’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 71–6), CD referred (p. 72) to the complex ‘checks and relations’ between organic beings that struggled together in the same country. He gave two examples, the colonisation by new species of an enclosed section of heathland planted with Scotch fir, and the indirect link between the size of local cat populations and the size of red clover populations (<hi rend="italic">Trifolium pratense</hi>): if there were fewer cats to kill mice, the increased mouse population would result in increased destruction of the nests of the clover’s sole pollinators, humble-bees.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1432.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolphe Jules César Auguste Dureau de la Malle</ref> was one of the first to describe communities (<hi rend="italic">sociétés</hi>) of plants, and to describe changes in local flora following the construction of new roads or the introduction of non-native species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8995.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dureau de la Malle 1825</ref>; see especially pp. 359–60).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In the introduction to <hi rend="italic">Flora Indica</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> discussed the effect of competition between plant species on their geographical distribution (Hooker and Thomson 1855, pp. 41–2). In his copy of the work, now in the Darwin Archive–CUL, CD marked the passage in which Hooker described the life of a plant as being ‘as much one of strife as that of an animal’. Hooker repeated much of the argument in his later paper ‘On the struggle for existence amongst plants’ (Hooker 1867).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his <hi rend="italic">Géographie botanique raisonée</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1195.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. de Candolle 1855</ref>), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alphonse de Candolle</ref> gave detailed observations of the factors affecting plant populations.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1871.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Henry Gilbert</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2834.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Bennet Lawes</ref> had been investigating the effects of different manures on meadowland at Rothamsted Agricultural Station since the 1850s and had sent CD a number of their research papers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10090.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. H. Gilbert, 24 July 1875</ref>). The first part of their account of their experiments, on the agricultural results, appeared in 1879; Masters co-authored the second part, on the botanical results (Lawes <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1879–99).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>