<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9945">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. J. Romanes   21 April 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15501</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9945 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9945.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9945.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">E. D. Romanes 1896, pp. 20–2</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Romanes, E. D. 1896: 20</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1875-04-21">21 Apr 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Returns papers [unidentified].</p>
            <p>One on inheritance destitute of meaning. How can "force" act without any material on which to act? Discussion must assume truth of some such theory as Pangenesis.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>April 21, 1875.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In returning you —’s papers, I should like to say that the one on ‘Inheritance’ appears to me quite destitute of intelligible meaning.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It is a jumble of the same confused ideas upon heredity about which I complained when you were at this house.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> How in the world can ‘force’ act without any material on which to act? Yet, unless we assume that it can, the whole discussion is either meaningless, or else assumes the truth of some such theory as ‘Pangenesis.’<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In other words, as it must be ‘unthinkable’ that force should act independently of matter, the doctrine of its persistence can only be made to bear upon the question of heredity, by supposing that there is a material connection between corporeal and germinal cells—<hi rend="underline">i.e.</hi> by granting the existence of <hi rend="underline">force-carriers</hi>, call them gemmules, or physiological units, or what we please.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Lawson Tait says (p.60)—‘The process of growth of the ovum after impregnation can be followed only after the assumption either expressed or <hi rend="underline">unconsciously accepted</hi> of such a hypothesis as is contained in Mr. Darwin’s “Pangenesis;”’<ref target="#foot.f5"/> and it is interesting, as showing the truth of the remark, to compare, for example, p. 29 of the other pamphlet—for, of course, ‘Pangenesis’ assumes the truth of the persistence of force as the prime condition of its possibility.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If ever I have occasion to prepare a paper about heredity, I think it would be worth while to point out the absurdity of thinking that we explain anything by vague allusions to the most ultimate generalisation of science. We might just as well say that Canadian institutions resemble British ones because force is persistent. This doubtless is the ultimate reason, but our explanation would be scientifically valueless if we neglected to observe that the Canadian colony was founded by British individuals.</p>
<p>The leaf from ‘Nature’ arrived last night. I had previously intended to try mangold-wurzel, as I hear it has well-marked varieties. The reference, therefore, will be valuable to me.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Before closing, I should like to take this opportunity of thanking you again for the very pleasant time I spent at Down. The place was one which I had long wished to see, and now that I have seen it, I am sure it will ever remain one of the most agreeable and interesting of memory’s pictures.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>With kind regards to Mrs. Darwin, I remain, very sincerely and most respectfully yours, | G<hi rend="smallCaps">eo</hi>. J. R<hi rend="smallCaps">omanes</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The paper on inheritance was probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4606.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Lewis Sturtevant’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">The law of inheritance; or, the philosophy of breeding</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8746.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sturtevant 1875</ref>; see nn. 4 and 6, below). A copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD evidently visited Romanes while he was in London from 31 March to 12 April 1875 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Romanes was testing CD’s theory of pangenesis experimentally by producing graft hybrids (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 357–404 and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. J. Romanes, 14 January 1875</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8746.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sturtevant 1875</ref>, p. 15, states: <quote type="quote">The hypothesis of pangenesis demands the presence of granules or gemmules which are freely circulating through the system, and which are supposed to be transmitted from the parent to the offspring, and which can lie dormant or become developed in the generations that succeed. To me, this is unthinkable, and I prefer to suggest that the law of persistence of force requires that no change can take place in a cell without changing the possibilities of that cell in its multiplication and future development; that each cell is the sum of all the forces which have acted on it in the past and are acting in the present; that the intimate connection of the generative cells with the whole body, arising through their high endowment, stores up in them a greater store of possibilities, brought about by their extreme complexity of environment.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The quotation is from <hi rend="italic">The pathology and treatment of diseases of the ovaries</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tait 1874</ref>). Tait sent the essay to CD with his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 17 March [1875]</ref>. An annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8746.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sturtevant 1875</ref>, p. 29,  it is argued: <quote type="quote">The ideal cell repeats itself through the force which is stored within it. As forces have been received by the parent cell through nutrition, and as force must have been used by this cell in the support of the processes which accompany vitality, this cell cannot transmit itself, as itself was when first formed, to its own offspring, but transmits those forces only which itself possesses at the time of the generation or production of offspring.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD evidently sent a page from <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> that reported on grafted roots of mangold wurzel (mangel-wurzel), illustrating the transmission of special characters from the graft to the stock (<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 1 October 1874, p. 452).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Romanes visited Down on 17 April 1875 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. J. Romanes, 7 April [1875]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>