<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1167F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Richard Owen   [2 April 1848]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21463</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1167F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1167F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1167F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Houghton Library, Harvard (MS Hyde 77: 2. 82. 1)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_180.xml">Harvard Houghton</repository>
                    <collection>MS Hyde 77: 2. 82. 1</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1848-04-02">[2 Apr 1848]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml">Owen, Richard</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Apologises for length of notes of advice for microscopic work.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Lepas</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">microscope</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Brown, Robert</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Hooker, Joseph Dalton</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Sunday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Owen</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My notes have run out quite into a little treatise. There is not, however, a word which I should not have been most deeply grateful for, when I started on my voyage.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>If too long, there is no harm done, for you can cut it about as much as you like. I really felt it a relief of gratitude to my dear microscope praising it, after having worked for years with one, such as is generally sold. Hooker gave me many hints &amp; he is a really beautiful dissector, as I have seen. Both he &amp; R. Brown have praised to me beyond measure the Adies lenses, which I have recommended, as I have, also, found them excellent.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I do not think there can be any objection, though that of course is for your decision, to the note I have put, that the kind of microscope, recommended can be <hi rend="doubleUnderline">seen</hi> at Smith; for this is really the best advice that can be given.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I sent in my M.S a fortnight ago &amp; it has been lost, I believe at the Admiralty: is it not an accursed bore.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I will call on you, rather early on Wednesday morning, as I want much to have <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of an hour’s talk,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> &amp; likewise I want to look at Thompson’s Zoolog. Researches. &amp; Goadby’s preparations of the Lepas, especially that of the nervous system:— could you let me look at it, through a simple or weak compound microscope? If you sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be going out, w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> you be so very kind as to leave the Book &amp; preparations out for me.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Thanks for your Synopsis: it is quite instructive to read the mere Headings; how glad I shall be to see it in type.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Ever yours | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.1 cut] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘do’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.4 a … compound] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by two weeks having elapsed since CD sent off his chapter for the Admiralty manual and by CD’s visit to London (see nn. 5 and 6, below). The second Sunday after 21 March 1848, the day CD sent off the chapter, was 2 April.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD provided notes based on his experience during the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage for the section ‘On the use of the microscope on board ship’ in Owen’s chapter on zoology in the Admiralty manual (Herschel ed. 1849, pp. 389–95). CD had emphasised the importance of such a section in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1166.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Owen of [26 March 1848]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s strength of feeling about his new simple microscope, which he had been using since January, and his ‘hatred’ for his old one were expressed in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1166.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Owen of [26 March 1848]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker’s</ref> dissecting skills were apparent from the drawings of barnacles he had sent to CD in 1846, when he not only recommended the lenses sold by the Edinburgh optician and instrument maker <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_35.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander James Adie</ref> but also lent CD such a lens (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1012.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [26 October 1846]</ref>). Robert Brown was a highly skilled microscopist. For the relative merits of CD’s microscopes and an assessment of CD’s skill in microscopy, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4157.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Jardine 2009</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Owen retained CD’s note informing readers that the microscope could be viewed at ‘Messrs. Smith and Beck’s, opticians, of Colman Street, London’ (Herschel ed. 1849, p. 393 n.); James Smith and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_355.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Beck</ref> ran their business from 6 Coleman Street from 1847 to 1856.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had completed his chapter on geology for the Admiralty manual (Herschel ed. 1849, pp. 156–95) on 20 March 1848, and sent it to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Frederick William Herschel</ref> on 21 March (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 7, Supplement, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1166A.xml" resp="#automat">letter to W. A. B. Hamilton, 28 March [1848]</ref> and nn. 2, 3 and 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had mentioned going to London on Monday (presumably 3 April 1848) in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1167.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. S. Henslow, [1 April 1848]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4); although there is no evidence that CD stayed in London from Monday 3 April to Wednesday 5 April, his request to meet Owen early on Wednesday morning suggests that he would already be there. CD had expressed his wish for the meeting in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1166.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Owen, [26 March 1848]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4). He probably wanted to report his discovery of separate sexes in cirripedes of the genus <hi rend="italic">Ibla</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1167.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. S. Henslow, [1 April 1848]</ref> and n. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD probably wanted to read the third part, on the cirripedes, of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4721.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Vaughan Thompson’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Zoological researches</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9286.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Thompson 1828–34</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7630.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Goadby</ref> was highly praised for his dissections; he was an anatomical assistant at the Royal College of Surgeons, where he dissected <hi rend="italic">Lepas vitrea</hi> to show its nervous system (Owen 1843, pp. 157 and 173). In <hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851), p. xi, CD stated that both pedunculated cirripedes (which included the genus <hi rend="italic">Lepas</hi>) and sessile ones could be identified only by investigating their internal structures. By May 1848, CD himself had become adept enough at dissection to have determined the nervous systems of several genera of cirripedes (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1174.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 10 May 1848</ref> and n. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Owen may have sent CD a copy of his ‘Synopsis of the Hunterian lectures on the comparative anatomy and physiology of the vertebrated animals with warm blood’; he had commenced the lectures in March 1848 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9291.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Rupke 1985</ref>, pp. 240 and 243).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>