<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10188">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Edouard Bergson<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 October 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6896</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10188 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10188.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10188.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160: 173</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 173</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_405.xml">Bergson, Edouard</persName>
                <placeName>Warsaw</placeName>
                <date when="1875-10-10">10 Oct 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Asks CD’s opinion on whether there is a fundamental difference between the "primitive forms" of animals and plants. Mentions and rejects various views of major distinguishing characteristics.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">aboriginal forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00706_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5856px" height="7837px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00706_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5856px" height="7837px"/>
        <surface n="173:1r" xml:id="i706">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00706.jpg" width="5856px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00706_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5856px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00706.dzi" width="5856px" height="7837px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:1v" xml:id="i707">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00707.jpg" width="5813px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00707_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5813px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00707.dzi" width="5813px" height="7837px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:2r" xml:id="i708">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00708.jpg" width="5784px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00708_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5784px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00708.dzi" width="5784px" height="7837px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:2v" xml:id="i709">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00709.jpg" width="5784px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00709_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5784px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00709.dzi" width="5784px" height="7837px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:3r" xml:id="i710">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00710.jpg" width="5706px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00710_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5706px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00710.dzi" width="5706px" height="7837px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:3v" xml:id="i711">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00711.jpg" width="5706px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00711_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5706px" height="7837px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00711.dzi" width="5706px" height="7837px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Varsovie,</placeName>
                    <date>le 10 Octobre 1875.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>C’est pour la seconde fois que je prends la liberté de venir Vous importuner. La bienveillance que Vous m’avez témoignée, en me faisant l’honneur de répondre à ma première lettre, m’encourage encore à avoir recours à Votre extrême obligeance.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> </p>
<p>Il s’agit aujourd’hui d’une question sur laquelle je Vous supplierai de daigner me donner Votre opinion décisive.</p>
<p>Il y a quatre ans qu’il m’est venu une idée singulière: en réfléchissant aux merveilles de la nature, en en considérant la régularité et en voyant (grâce à Vos recherches) que tout y réglé et nous représente un développement et une perfection continuels, je me suis dit, que, comme il y a un lien incontestable entre les animaux supérieures et les inférieures (consistant en une perfection incessante), il en est peut-être ainsi entre le monde animal et le végétal.</p>
<p>En un mot, je croyais qu’il y avait eu un moment propice à ce que la cellule végétal quelconque s’était transformé en celle d’une créature animale.</p>
<p>Comme j’ai déjà 21 ans et un peu plus d’expérience, cette idée me paraît bien étrange; cependant si elle est absurde, elle renferme en elle des circonstances qui ne s’opposent pas à la possibilité de sa justesse. En l’approfondissant, j’ai trouvé que toutes les preuves qui furent désignées comme déterminant la différence, soit dite évidente, entre l’animal et la plante, sont en partie insuffisantes, en partie malfondées.</p>
<p>Pendant longtemps, on a considéré le mouvement ad libitum,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> comme étant exclusivement propre aux animaux; mais on a trouvé qu’il y a des germes de plantes aquatiques, ne donnant pas de fleures, qui, en état de vésicules encore, avant de perdre leurs cils et avant de pousser des racines, se meuvent à leur gré.</p>
<p>On a prouvé que, comme il y a de l’azote dans l’organisme animal, il y en a aussi dans celui de plantes.</p>
<p>Link a supposé que l’estomac est l’unique marque servant de distinction entre les deux mondes, dont il est parlé ci-dessus.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Mais, comme il y a des créatures qui sont privées de cet organe, ce point de vue tombe de lui-même.</p>
<p>Schleiden voulut faire valoir son opinion, en tâchant de nous persuader que les parties les plus importantes de l’animal sont intérieures, celles des plantes cependant—extérieures: ce qui est évidemment faux.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>En voyant que toutes ces opinions sont insuffisantes, Siebold pensait que la différence définitive gît dans la construction des parties primitives. Il prouva donc que la membrane de la cellule végétale diffère de celle de l’animal en ce que la première change seulement de forme par l’accroissement, et que l’autre possède, outre cette spécialité, encore celle de l’élasticité; mais Hermann Schacht a démontré la fausseté de cette affirmation.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Il n’existe donc aucune différence entre les parties primitives de l’animal et celles de la plante, si ce n’est que la force vitale en change les formes et qu’elle est, peut-être, parallèle à celle qui distingue les minéraux des plantes.</p>
<p>Mes occupations ne m’ont pas permis de trouver plus de preuves justifiant mon idée et mes recherches sont donc plutôt théoriques et superficielles; c’est pourquoi j’ose Vous demander, Monsieur, par la présente, de bien vouloir me dire: s’il y a une différence saillante entre la forme primitive de l’animal et celle de la plante? En supposant qu’il n’en existe point, mon opinion est elle absurde?</p>
<p>Vous êtes, sans contredit, l’homme unique qui peut répondre sous ce rapport quelque chose de décisif.</p>
<p>Il est certain que cette nature, si bizarre dans ses mystères pour nous, hommes profanes, est bien réglée et bien simple aux yeux du génie. L’histoire du progrès universel nous donne des preuves infaillibles de sa simplicité et de sa régularité. Heureux les génies à qui l’humanité doit l’explication des choses qui lui paraissent merveilleuses!</p>
<p>Vous êtes, Monsieur, l’un de ces élus! Vous avez mis en ordre ces masses d’animaux dispersés, en désignant qu’ils sont parents et en assignant le rôle respectif qu’ils ont joué dans l’histoire de la création. Je viens donc recourir, Monsieur, à Votre indulgence, en Vous priant de bien vouloir répondre aux questions énoncées précédemment.</p>
<p>Vous me prendrez, sans doute, ou pour un exalté ou pour un ignorant; les extrémités se touchent: si mon idée n’est pas juste, elle en est le contraire; mais pardonnez-la moi: c’est un des rêves de jeunesse et ce que Vous considérerez comme une impossibilité, mettez-le sur le compte d’un esprit rêveur, sur celui des recherches d’un adolescent.</p>
<p>Avant m’être décidé à Vous écrire, Monsieur, j’ai hésité entre la crainte de Vous importuner et le plaisir d’avoir Votre opinion. La première s’empara souvent de moi en me laissant dans un état du doute, cependant le cauchemar de mon idée me poursuit sans cesse; veuillez donc, Monsieur, me bien pardonner mon insistance à cet égard et agréer, avec mes remercîments anticipés, les assurances de ma respectueuse considération.</p>
<p>Edouard Bergson.</p>
<p>P.S. Daignez, Monsieur, me faire parvenir Votre bienveillante réponse par l’intermédiaire du Consulat Général de France à Varsovie (Pologne).</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Warsaw,</placeName>
                    <date>10 October 1875.</date>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>For the second time I am taking the liberty of importuning you. The benevolence you showed me, by doing me the honour of responding to my first letter, encourages me to appeal to your extreme obligingness again.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> </p>
<p>This time I am concerned with a question on which I beseech you to give your decisive opinion.</p>
<p>Four years ago a singular idea came to me: while reflecting on the marvels of nature, while considering its regularity and seeing (thanks to your research) that everything in it is regulated and demonstrates continual development and perfection to us, I said to myself that since there is an incontestable link between the higher and the lower animals (consisting of incessant perfection), there is perhaps such a one between the animal and plant worlds.</p>
<p>In a word, I believed that there had been a propitious moment in which a plant cell of some kind had transformed itself into the cell of an animal creature.</p>
<p>As I already have 21 years of experience, and a little more, this idea seems very strange to me; however, even if it is absurd, it contains some circumstances which are not opposed to the possibility that it is correct. In going into it thoroughly, I found that all the proofs designated as determining the difference between animals and plants, though supposedly evident, are in part insufficient and in part ill-founded.</p>
<p>For a long time, movement ad libitum<ref target="#foot.f3"/> was considered to be proper to animals alone; but it has been found that there are germs of aquatic plants which produce no flowers and which, while yet in the state of vesicles, move at will before losing their cilia and growing roots.</p>
<p>It has been proven that there is nitrogen both in the animal organism and in the organism of plants.</p>
<p>Link assumed that the stomach was the sole mark serving as a distinction between the two worlds discussed above.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But since some creatures are deprived of that organ, this point of view falls of itself.</p>
<p>Schleiden wanted to command respect for his opinion by attempting to persuade us that the most important parts of the animal are internal, while those of plants are however—external: which is evidently false.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Seeing all these opinions as insufficient, Siebold thought that the definitive difference lay in the construction of the primitive parts. So he proved that the membrane of the plant cell differs from that of the animal in that the former only changes in form during growth, while the latter possesses, besides that special property, also the property of elasticity; but Hermann Schacht has demonstrated the falsehood of that affirmation.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Thus there is no difference between the primitive parts of the animal and those of the plant, except that the vital force changes their forms and is, perhaps, parallel to the force that distinguishes minerals from plants.</p>
<p>My occupations have not allowed me to find more proof justifying my idea and my research is thus rather theoretical and superficial; that is why I am daring to ask you, Sir, herewith, to be so good as to tell me: if there is a salient difference between the primitive form of the animal and that of the plant? Supposing that none should exist, is my opinion absurd?</p>
<p>You are without doubt the only man who can say something decisive in this regard.</p>
<p>It is certain that nature, so outlandish in her mysteries for us profane men, is well regulated and simple to the eyes of genius. The history of universal progress gives us infallible proof of her simplicity and regularity. Happy the geniuses to whom humanity owes the explanation of things which seem marvellous to it!</p>
<p>You, Sir, are one of these elect! You have ordered these masses of disparate animals, showing that they are relatives and assigning the respective roles they have played in the history of creation. So I appeal to your indulgence, Sir, in asking you to be so good as to respond to the questions laid down above.</p>
<p>You will take me without doubt to be a fanatic or an ignoramus; the extremes meet: if my idea is not correct, it is the opposite; but forgive me for it: it is one of the dreams of youth; put what you would consider an impossibility down to a dreaming mind or the research of an adolescent.</p>
<p>Before making up my mind to write to you, Sir, I hesitated between the fear of importuning you and the pleasure of having your opinion. The first often overwhelmed me, leaving me in a state of doubt, but the nightmare of my idea constantly pursues me; so please, Sir, be so good as to forgive my persistence in this regard and believe me, with thanks in advance, yours truly.</p>
<p>Edouard Bergson.</p>
<p>P.S. Please send me your benevolent reply, Sir, by way of the General Consulate of France at Warsaw (Poland).</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the original French, see pp. 389–91.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Neither Bergson’s first letter nor CD’s reply has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Ad libitum</hi>: at one’s discretion; at will (Latin).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2939.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Friedrich Link’s</ref> remark on the animal stomach has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4217.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Matthias Jacob Schleiden</ref> had proposed that cells were the basic structural elements of all plants in <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Phytogenesis</hi> (Contributions to phytogenesis; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8792.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schleiden 1838</ref>). His remarks regarding differences between animals and plants have not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Karl Theodor Ernst von Siebold had discussed differences in plant and animal cells, noting that the principal difference was the rigid cell wall present in plants but not in animals (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8793.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Siebold 1848</ref>, pp. 8–9). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4201.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Schacht</ref> discussed the morphology and physiology of plant cells in <hi rend="italic">Die Pflanzenzelle, der innere Bau und das Leben der Gewächse</hi> (The plant cell, the inner structure and life of plants; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schacht 1852</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>