<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13166">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alexander Agassiz   19 May 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20237</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13166 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13166.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13166.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_39.xml">G. R. Agassiz ed. 1913</ref>, pp. 284–6</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Agassiz, G. R. 1913: 284</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_41.xml">Agassiz, Alexander</persName>
                <placeName>Cambridge Mass.</placeName>
                <date when="1881-05-19">19 May 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the structure and formation of the Florida peninsula. Part played by marine animals in building banks on which coral can thrive.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">marine animals</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Florida peninsula</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change><change when="2019-12-06" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-22" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-07-30" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="smallCaps">Cambridge</hi>,</placeName>
                    <date>May 19, 1881.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I find on my return from the Tortugas your most welcome letter of May 5.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am now at work on the Report of the Coral Reefs of the Tortugas, and hope during the course of the summer to be able to send it to you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As you well say, the fact that the Peninsula of Florida should have remained at the same level for so long a time is most surprising. This I consider to be in part due to the original orographic conditions of the Gulf of Mexico, as we have not only the Florida Peninsula but other equally important banks: Yucatan, Bahamas, and San Pedro Banks, all of which are characterized by a general dead level which they have evidently kept for an immense period of time. Yet on the other side of the Straits of Florida and all along the line of the larger Antilles, as far as Barbados, and along the northern of the Windward Islands, we have the <hi rend="underline">most distinct proof of elevation</hi>.…</p>
<p>I should feel at present inclined to assign to the action of large marine animals (such as Gorgoniæ, Starfishes, Mollusks, Echinoderms, Deep-sea Corals, Crustacea, etc.)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> a more important part in building up a plateau, up to the height at which corals can thrive, than to the pelagic fauna which I would look upon more as the cementing medium, but which, however, in some localities, such as are in the track of great oceanic currents, as the San Pedro, Yucatan and Florida and Bahama Banks, do yet form an important bulk in the mass of the débris added to the original bank, the level of which was due to the folding of the crust in much earlier periods, at a time when the principal orographic features were laid down. My experience has been that shells, etc., in these plateaus which are in the track of currents, are fairly well preserved after death, although covered with mud (made up mainly of the coral ooze and of Globigerina ooze)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> which cemented them to the older layer of dead shells, etc., below, and formed the base upon which the present living forms were thriving. Your objection that there is not great probability of finding in the Pacific as many banks as there are atolls is certainly a very strong one and one which seems to me can only be met by showing in subsequent surveys that these atolls are themselves only slightly raised patches upon large banks, the orography of which we do not as yet know.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> This is a problem in hydrography of the Pacific which I have had in view for a long time and hope to solve one of these days.</p>
<p>With reference to the chemistry of the reefs and the action of all this large amount of carbonate of lime held in suspense in the water, I must acknowledge I know nothing, and I do not see the why of the action of carbonic acid as a solvent at one depth and not at another—if not in exact proportions to the pressure. This part of Murray’s argument seems to me untenable, if I understand him correctly, and we seem to have viewed his explanation alike.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> There is constant talk of making borings at St. Augustine for sinking artesian wells, and whenever they start I shall be sure to keep close watch of their proceedings, which ought to settle a good many doubtful points as to the structure of the Florida Peninsula.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I am much pleased at what you say of my address; the part you refer to is just the one which seemed to me to throw some light on the infinite lines of affinities, which close study reveals, among otherwise distinctly related groups, and it was the very difficulty of expressing this affinity by any of our present methods of notation which made me almost despair of doing more than to follow a single character in its endless modifications in time and space.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13145.xml">letter to Alexander Agassiz, 5 May 1881</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In the event, Agassiz’s report was not completed until November 1882 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11405.xml">A. Agassiz 1882</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Gorgonia</hi> is a genus of soft corals (order Alcyonacea) sometimes referred to as sea fans. Starfishes (sea stars) are a class (Asteroidea) in the phylum Echinodermata; echinoderms (class Echinoidea) are in the same phylum. Mollusca is the phylum of molluscs. Most deep-sea or cold-water corals are stony corals (order Scleractinia) but there are also sea fans and black corals (order Antipatharia).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Marine foraminifera of the genus <hi rend="italic">Globigerina</hi> have calcareous tests or shells; the term ‘Globigerina ooze’ was used to characterise sediment containing shells of this and related genera.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13145.xml">letter to Alexander Agassiz, 5 May 1881</ref> and nn. 3 and 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13145.xml">letter to Alexander Agassiz, 5 May 1881</ref> and n. 5. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3464.xml">John Murray</ref> (1841–1914) had been the naturalist to the <hi rend="italic">Challenger</hi> expedition (<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">A brief report on the boring for an artesian well at St Augustine, Florida, appeared in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science</hi>, July 1887, p. 70; it revealed fossiliferous limestone with coral and shells at depths from about 90 to 770 feet.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Agassiz’s address was ‘Paleontological and embryological development’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11327.xml">A. Agassiz 1880</ref>). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13145.xml">letter to Alexander Agassiz, 5 May 1881</ref> and n. 7.</note>   
        </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>