<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8737">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alphonse de Candolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   14 January 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14128</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8737 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8737.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8737.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="inc"/>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Baehni (1955): 138</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 17</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 17</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml">Candolle, Alphonse de</persName>
                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                <date when="1873-01-14">14 Jan 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>, which has made him wonder whether his shyness in public until the age of 55 resulted from fear of subjecting his face to ridicule.</p>  
<p>Criticises F. Galton’s <hi rend="italic">Hereditary genius</hi> [1869] for neglecting environmental influence.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Hereditary genius</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Galton, Francis 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-11-16" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-11-16" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-11-16" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00064_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00064_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="17:1r" xml:id="i64">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00064.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00064_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00064.dzi" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="17:1v" xml:id="i65">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00065.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00065_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00065.dzi" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="17:2r" xml:id="i66">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00066.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00066_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00066.dzi" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="17:2v" xml:id="i67">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00067.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00067_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00067.dzi" width="3536px" height="5950px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Genève</placeName>
                    <date>14 Janvier 1873.</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Vous avez été bien bon de me communiquer vos impressions sur la plupart des articles de mon dernier ouvrage et je vois fort heureusement quelles ont été approbatives.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Comme nous cherchons tous les deux sincèrement et prudemment la vérité je suis toujours heureux de me rencontrer avec vous. Si j’ai quelquefois restreint les conclusions aux quelles on semblait arriver par la variabilité et la sélection, je les ai aussi étendues dans d’autres cas, et j’estime être resté fidèle à vos principes en montrant, pour l’espèce humaine, que souvent le jeu des phénomènes produit les effets opposés qui se neutralisent plus ou moins et rendent les modifications extremement lentes ou peu importantes.</p>
<p>Le volume sur les <hi rend="underline">Expressions</hi> que vous avez bien voulu m’adresser traite de sujets si nouveaux pour moi que j’avais tout à apprendre et n’ai rien à ajouter.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Les details sur les muscles de la figure sont une chose dont je ne m’etais jamais occupé et j’ai été surpris de la quantité de questions qui se rattachent au sujet. Sur un point cependant mes reflexions personnelles avaient devancé la lecture du livre, sans me conduire à aucune conclusion satisfaisante. J’ai souffert énormement jusqu’a l’age de 55 ans de timidité (shyness). C’est au point qu’autrefois, à l’ecole, j’aimais mieux me faire renvoyer que d’avoir à me lever pour repondre en public, et qu’ensuite dans plusieurs occasions j’ai fui devant des nominations à des présidences de sociétés ou d’administrations, même par des moyens ridicules, tels que des propos déplaisants tenus sur des personnes influentes ou une exagération d’opposition qui n’etait pas tout à fait vraie, pour éviter d’etre nommé. Les examens me faisaient trembler. Un discours dans les Assemblées législatives dont j’etais membre et où j’étais assez bien vu, dépassait mes forces. Une presentation à un souverain me rendait muet. A 55 ans je suis rentré pour quelques années dans les Conseils de notre république, et il s’est trouvé, à ma grande surprise, qu’il ne m’en coûtait plus de prendre la parole. J’avais pensé d’après cela qu’un changement s’etait fait dans mon système nerveux, par l’effet de l’âge. Il est vrai aussi que j’avais pu acquerir un sentiment plus juste de ma position à l’egard des autres. Après vous avoir lu je me suis demandé si la crainte de montrer une figure ridicule devant le public avait été jadis la cause de mes faiblesses. Or, excepté entre 18 et 25 ans et dans les réunions où il y avait des dames, je ne crois pas que cela soit arrivé. Autour de moi on faisait peu d’attention à la figure, mais on vantait beaucoup l’esprit et les talents. J’ai pensé que mon malheur, venait de l’hérédité. C’est de ma mère que je tenais ma disposition. Possible que dans sa famille on fut très vain de sa figure!</p>
<p>Les gens timides pour paraitre et parler sont quelquefois très audacieux dans leurs idées et même dans leurs écrits. Ayant été dans ce cas il m’a paru qu’une cause aggravante de l’embarras est le contraste (dont on a la conscience) qui existe entre ses propres opinions et celles des autres. La timidité isole et l’isolement augmente l’independance des opinions. J. J. Rousseau, un des hommes les plus audacieux dans ses livres, etait ridiculement timide. Lui, par exemple, tenait beaucoup à sa figure, qui etait agréable.</p>
<p>Jusqu’à votre publication je n’avais rien lu ou entendu de raisonnable sur cette question. Vous avez ouvert la voie, et surtout l’hérédité, ici comme ailleurs, explique beaucoup, mais il y a encore à perfectionner et completer en suivant vos indications.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton a été moins content que vous de ce que j’ai dit sur l’heredité intellectuelle. Il m’a adressé une longue et amicale lettre d’observations, à laquelle j’ai répondu dans le même esprit.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Je crois voir entre nous des <hi rend="underline">differences</hi> dans les conclusions et non des <hi rend="underline">oppositions</hi>. La tendance générale de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton et le titre de son livre l’indique, est de montrer l’hérédité comme cause unique ou principale de la succession d’hommes distingués dans une famille. S’il parle des autres influences d’education, exemples, traditions, etc, c’est accessoirement. J’ai cherché à établir que ces autres causes sont souvent prépondérantes et me suis efforcé de préciser leur part dans plusieurs cas. Ainsi nous sommes d’accord quand il faut démontrer par des faits que l’hérédité intellectuelle existe, mais nous <hi rend="underline">differons</hi> dans l’estimation des resultats de cette cause combinée avec d’autres. A vrai dire je n’estime pas avoir été contraire à M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton, mais venant après lui, je crois avoir completé son travail en tirant des faits semblables des conclusions plus variées et plus complètes.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Il se sera rendu, j’espère, à cette facon d’envisager nos travaux et il sait dailleurs à quel point j’ai rendu justice à ses recherches.</p>
<p>Dans sa lettre il me dit que les physiologistes anglais seront peu disposés à acquiescer à l’idée d’une influence de l’etat momentané des parents sur les ovules et spermatozoaires au moment de la conception ou fécondation. Il me fait remarquer, ce que je n’ignorais pas, qu’il s’ecoule quelquefois plusieurs jours entre le detachement de l’ovule et sa fécondation.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> De là, sans doute, il faudrait conclure que l’etat du mâle au moment essentiel aurait seul de l’importance, s’il s’agit d’un état physique ou moral tout à fait temporaire. Mais quand il y a une affection persistante pendant 8 jours, 15 jours, comme cela se voit, la femelle aussi pourrait modifier ses ovules. L’exemple que vous citez dans votre dernier ouvrage d’une femme âgée qui, se croyant enceinte, avait vu le sang se porter dans des organes où il n’etait plus en excès depuis longtemps, prouve bien l’effet d’une idée fixe sur les organes de la génération.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> De là à supposer, par exemple, que la crainte excessive d’une nouvelle grossesse ou une antipathie de la femme contre celui dont elle doit subir l’autorité maritale peuvent altérer les ovules avant leur fécondation, il n’y a pas loin. Cette influence d’idées fixes ou de passions momentanées, comme la colère, la peur, etc, est une hypothèse, deduite par analogie. Les faits connus sont principalement la lesion d’une chienne au moment de l’accouplement, que j’ai citée d’après Lucas, et les idiots nés de parents en état d’ivresse.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Depuis ma lettre à M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton, le hasard m’a fait connaitre un cas bien frappant de cette dernière catègorie. On me l’a raconté à titre d’anecdote amusante et graveleuse; je l’ai remarqué comme un fait physiologique important. Voici:</p>
<p>J’ai connu à Genève un propriétaire, que j’appelerai X, qui est mort à plus de 80 ans, après avoir joui d’une excellente santé, dans une position aisée. Ses facultés intellectuelles etaient plutot audessous de la moyenne, mais il a administré toujours sa fortune et s’est comporté comme un autre dans la vie ordinaire. Il etait d’un degré de capacité qui lui aurait permis de siéger dans un conseil municipal ou un jury ordinaire, ce qui lui est probablement arrivé. Son père et son frère étaient d’une intelligence un peu supérieure à la moyenne. Il avait épousé une femme intelligente, sans fortune, qui</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Alph de Candolle’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘O’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of 4th page</hi>: <hi rend="italic">pencil tick</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                    <date>14 January 1873.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You were very good to communicate to me your impressions of most of the articles in my latest work and I see with great joy that they were approbatory.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As we are both sincerely and prudently seeking the truth, I am always happy to meet you. If I have sometimes limited the conclusions apparently arrived at from variation and selection, I have also extended them in other cases, and I consider that I have remained faithful to your principles for the human species, in showing that the action of phenomena often produces opposing effects, which more or less neutralise one another and render modifications extremely gradual, or of little significance.</p>
<p>The volume on <hi rend="underline">Expressions</hi> that you were so good as to send me deals with subjects which are so new for me that I have had everything to learn and nothing to add.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The details on the facial muscles are a matter with which I had never concerned myself and I was surprised by the quantity of questions that relate to the subject. On one point however my personal reflections had preceded my reading of the book, without leading me to any satisfactory conclusion. I suffered enormously up to the age of 55 from timidity (shyness). It was at such a point that once upon a time, at school, I preferred to be sent out rather than to have to stand up and answer in public, and that later, on several occasions, I evaded being nominated as the president of societies or administrations, even by absurd means, such as making disagreeable remarks about influential people, or exaggerating the opposition in a manner which was not strictly true, in order to avoid being nominated. Examinations made me tremble. A speech before the Legislative assemblies of which I was a member, and where I was fairly well regarded, surpassed my strength. At an introduction to a sovereign I was struck dumb. At the age of 55 I re-entered our republic’s Councils for a few years, and to my great surprise, it so happened that I no longer paid dearly for taking the floor. After that I thought that a change had taken place in my nervous system as a result of age. It is also true that I may have gained a more precise sense of my position in relation to others. After reading you I asked myself whether the fear of cutting a ridiculous figure in public had formerly been the cause of my frailties. Now, apart from between the ages of 18 and 25 and in gatherings where ladies were present, I do not believe that was the case. In my circle little attention was paid to one’s appearance, but one’s mind and talents were highly regarded. I thought that my misfortune came from heredity. I take my disposition from my mother. Possibly in her family they were very conceited about their appearance!</p>
<p>People who are shy about appearing and speaking are sometimes very bold in their ideas and even in their writings. Having been in that case it seemed to me that an aggravating cause of the impediment is the contrast (of which one is aware) existing between one’s own opinions and those of others. Shyness isolates and isolation increases independence of opinions. J. J. Rousseau, one of the boldest of men in his books, was ridiculously shy. He, for example, greatly prized his appearance, which was agreeable.</p>
<p>Before your publication I had never read or heard anything reasonable on this question. You have opened the way, and heredity above all explains a great deal, here as elsewhere, but there is still more to perfect and complete, following your directions.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton was less pleased than you with what I said on intellectual heredity. He sent me a long friendly letter of observations, to which I responded in the same spirit.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I believe that there are <hi rend="underline">differences</hi> between our conclusions and not <hi rend="underline">disagreements</hi>. The general tendency of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton, as the title of his book indicates, is to show heredity to be the unique or principal cause of the succession of distinguished men in a family. If he speaks of other influences from education, example, tradition, etc, it is as an accessory. I have attempted to establish that these other causes are often preponderant and have endeavoured to show their precise role in several cases. So we are in agreement when it is a question of factually demonstrating the existence of intellectual heredity, but we <hi rend="underline">differ</hi> in our estimation of the results of that cause combined with others. As a matter of fact, I do not think I have opposed M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton, but, in succeeding him, I believe I have completed his work by drawing more varied and complete conclusions from similar facts.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I hope that he will yield to this way of envisaging our work and indeed, he knows the extent to which I have rendered justice to his research.</p>
<p>In his letter he tells me that English physiologists will be little disposed to acquiesce to the idea of an influence over the ova and spermatozoa coming from the momentary state of the parents at the moment of conception or fertilisation. He calls my attention to something of which I was not ignorant, that several days may pass between the detachment of the ovum and its fertilisation.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> From this, one ought doubtless to conclude that the male’s state at the critical moment would be the only one of significance, if it were a question of a wholly temporary physical or moral state. But where there is an affection persisting for a week or a fortnight, it is clear that the female might also modify her ova. The example you cite in your last work concerning an old woman who, believing herself to be pregnant, had seen blood entering organs in which it had not been present in excess for a long time, demonstrates the effect of a fixed idea on the organs of generation well.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> It is not far from there to the supposition that, for example, an excessive fear of a new pregnancy, or the woman’s antipathy towards him whose marital authority she must undergo, may alter the ova before their fertilisation. This influence of fixed ideas or momentary passions, such as anger, fear, etc, is an hypothesis, deduced by analogy. The principal known facts are the injury of a bitch at the moment of coupling, which I cited from Lucas, and idiots born to parents in a drunken state.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Since my letter to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Galton, a very striking case of this latter category has come to my attention by chance. It was recounted to me as an amusing and smutty anecdote; I noted it as an important physiological fact. Here it is:</p>
<p>At Geneva I knew a landowner, whom I shall call X, who died when he was over 80, having enjoyed excellent health, in a well-to-do situation. His intellectual faculties were rather below average, but he always administered his fortune and conducted himself like any other man in ordinary life. He possessed such a degree of capacity as would have allowed him to sit on a municipal council or an ordinary jury, which probably happened to him. His father and brother were of somewhat above average intelligence. He had married an intelligent wife without fortune, who</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 39–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Candolle refers to his <hi rend="italic">Histoire des sciences</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1873</ref>); see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8672.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alphonse de Candolle, 11 December 1872</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Candolle’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, Appendix V; see also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8593.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alphonse de Candolle, 2 November [1872]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Galton’s</ref> letter to Candolle and Candolle’s reply, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pearson 1914–30</ref>, 2: 135–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1873</ref> reflected critically upon Galton’s <hi rend="italic">Hereditary genius</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2706.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Galton 1869</ref>; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pearson 1914–30</ref>, 2: 134).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1873</ref>, pp. 311–12, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pearson 1914–30</ref>, 2: 136.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 341 n. 39, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, [29–31 March 1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Candolle 1873</ref>, p. 331. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lucas 1847–50</ref>, 2: 502, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Prosper Lucas</ref> reported a story of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Girou de Buzareingues</ref> about a bitch who was struck hard on the back while mating, and paralysed in the hindquarters for a few days afterwards; she gave birth to eight puppies, seven of whom had defective hindquarters.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>