<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8172">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Raphael Meldola   23 January [1872]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">2634</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8172 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8172.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8172.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">7pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">JA 23 72</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Poulton (1896): 201</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Oxford University Museum of Natural History (Hope Entomological Collections 1350: Hope/Westwood Archive, Darwin folder)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_312.xml">Oxford Hope</repository>
                    <collection>Entomological Collections 1350:</collection>
                    <idno>Hope/Westwood, Darwin folder</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1872-01-23">23 Jan [1872]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3289.xml">Meldola, Raphael</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the problems of mimicry as related to natural selection; the general variability of colour as a character; and the conditions necessary for natural selection to fix firmly a character.</p>
            <p>Encloses a Fritz Müller letter speculating that organisms respond to certain colours because of the prevalence of those colours in their environment.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mimicry</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Beckenham | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Jan 23. 1871</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The point to which you refer seems to me a very difficult one.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> the comparison of the amount of variability in itself w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be difficult. 2<hi rend="superscript">ndly</hi>. Of all characters, colour seems to be the most variable, as we see in domesticated productions. (3) I fully agree that selection if long continued gives fixity to characters. We see the reverse of this in the great variability of fancy races, now being selected by man. But to give fixity, selection must be continued for a very long period: pray consider on this head what I have said in the Origin about the variability of characters developed in an extraordinary manner, in comparison with the same characters in allied species.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The selection must also be for a definite object, &amp; not for any thing so vague as beauty, or for the superiority of one male in its weapons over another male, which can in like manner be modified. This at least seems to me partly to account for the general variability of secondary sexual characters. In the case of mimetic insects, there is another element of doubt, as the imitated form may be undergoing change which will be followed by the imitating form. This latter consideration seems to me, as remarked in my “Descent of man”, to throw much light on how the process of imitation first began—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I enclose a letter from Fritz Müller which I think is well worth reading, &amp; which please to return to me.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>You will see he lays much stress on the difficulty of several remotely allied forms all imitating some one species. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wallace did not think that there was so much weight in this objection as I do.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> It is however possible that a few species in widely different groups, before they had diverged much, sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have accidentally resembled, to a certain extent, some one species. You will also see in this letter a strange speculation, which I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not dare to publish, about the appreciation of certain colours being developed in those species which frequently behold other forms similarly ornamented. I do not feel at all sure that this view is as incredible as it may at first appear. Similar ideas have passed through my mind when considering the dull colours of all the organisms which inhabit dull-coloured regions, such as Patagonia &amp; the Galapagos I<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>s<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I suppose you know M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Riley’s excellent essay on mimicry in the last report on the noxious insects of Missouri or some such title.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I hope your work may be in every way successful &amp; I remain | dear Sir | yours faithfully | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.5 the … of] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.11 partly] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.1 well] <hi rend="italic">added in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.1 several] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the postmark. The amanuensis wrote ‘1871’ in error.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Raphael Meldola, 21 January [1872]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 185–9: ‘A part developed in any species in an extraordinary degree or manner, in comparison with the same part in allied species, tends to be highly variable.’ CD’s point was that a part highly developed in one species but not in other species of the same genus must have been developed relatively recently, and that the tendency to vary that underlay the development was probably still active.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 412, CD suggested that imitation might begin with two forms that resembled each other, one of which was protected by a noxious taste or odour, the other not. Natural selection would favour closer imitation of the protected species by the other, and if the protected species changed its colours as a result of sexual selection, the imitator would follow the same course.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD enclosed the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 14 June 1871</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had forwarded Müller’s letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref>; for Wallace’s comments, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7899.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 7 August 1871</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had wondered whether the generally dull coloration he had noticed in animals in the Galàpagos and in Patagonia arose because animals in that environment had not learned to appreciate bright colours; he added a note to this effect to the second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2d ed, p. 422 n. 34). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 2 August [1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The third volume of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Valentine Riley’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Annual reports on the noxious, beneficial and other insects in the state of Missouri</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6652.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Riley 1869–77</ref>) was published in 1871; the essay is on pages 159 to 172. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to C. V. Riley, 1 June [1871]</ref>.</note>
        </div>                
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>