<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13245F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   16 July 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21543</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13245F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13245F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13245F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 71</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 71</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>
                <date when="1881-07-16">16 July 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports de Bary’s opinion of Max Cornu. Accounts of various botanical experiments and observations.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-14" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-09" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-23" status="editorResponseCompleted">Responded <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>
                    <date>July 16/81</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have got rid of my lumbago by blue pills &amp; mustard plasters &amp; starvation &amp; am all right again.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I had two days in which I couldn’t rest decently in any position.</p>
                    <p>I asked de Bary about Max Cornu, and he said he was a clever man who began much better than he went on; his monograph on the Saprolegniæ, was very good but he has lately done nothing but Phylloxera   I know Dyer thinks him a great swell<ref target="#foot.f2"/>   Wortmann thinks Pfeffer’s new book very good &amp; not unreadable, though it has too much osmosis in it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have made a little Referat for the Bot Z on a paper by an American in Pfeffers new “Arbeiten”<ref target="#foot.f4"/>   He finds that if all the nectar is washed off a nectary it leaves off secreting tho’ if it is only sucked up leaving of course a certain film behind it begins again   When the secretion has been stopped by washing it can be started by putting a drop of syrup on the nectary. I have been hunting for the paper on staining living root hairs but cannot find it, I believe I can when I get home.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I showed de Bary the thing about the Loranthus which turns head over heels &amp; he didn’t believe in it a bit, chiefly as being an unknown observer in the Gard Chron   I must say I fully believe it, I dont see how a decent observer could make a mistake.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have been working at Bryonia embryos trying to trace the connection between the cell divisions in the embryo &amp; the fully formed root   It is horribly irregular with lots of queer oblique walls &amp; very difficult, but it is good practice as nothing is known about it, so that I cant go &amp; look in a book.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>There is a Lime with silvery underside to its leaves which twists its stalk so that the leaf becomes vertical, the parts of the tree in shade do not do so so it is a nice kind of paraheliotropism.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>When de Bary saw Pfeffer’s Arbeiten he said “Na, Pfeffer will auch einen Eisenbahn Zug für sich haben”<ref target="#foot.f9"/>   That is a train pupils hanging onto him”</p>
<p>It continues frightfully hot 85 all day indoors and I thingk over 90 in shade out of doors.</p>
<p>Please give Ubbadud my love and say I liked his bubbling fountain letter very much &amp; I will write to him next.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I shall be precious glad to get back<ref target="#foot.f11"/> | Yours affect | F. D.</p>
<p>Many thanks for auto &amp; photo<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Blue pills, containing mercury or a mercury compound, were recommended for constipation associated with lumbago (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref> s.v. blue pill; <hi rend="italic">Practitioner: a Journal of Therapeutics and Public Health</hi> 13 (1874): 312). The mustard plasters would have been a counterirritant.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had asked about <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8971.xml">Maxime Cornu</ref>: see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13237.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 8 July 1881</ref>. Francis was working with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref> in Straßburg (Strasbourg). Cornu’s doctoral thesis on the Saprolegniae (a synonym of Saprolegniaceae, formerly described as a family of fungus, but now classified as an oomycete or water mould) is <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9831.xml">Cornu 1872</ref>. For his work on <hi rend="italic">Phylloxera vastatrix</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Daktulosphaira vitifoliae</hi>, grape phylloxera), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9832.xml">Cornu 1874</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9833.xml">Cornu 1879a</ref>. Grape phylloxera is a small sap-sucking insect native to North America, accidentally introduced in the mid nineteenth century to Europe, where it devastated native grapevines. Francis also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">William Turner Thiselton-Dyer</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9180.xml">Julius Wortmann</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3766.xml">Wilhelm Pfeffer</ref>’s new book was his <hi rend="italic">Pflanzen physiologie</hi> (Plant physiology; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11209.xml">Pfeffer 1881</ref>). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10809.xml">Pfeffer 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Francis’s report on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8978.xml">William Powell Wilson</ref>’s ‘The cause of the excretion of water on the surface of nectaries’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9835.xml">W. P. Wilson 1881</ref>) was published in <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung</hi>, 26 August 1881, pp. 545–6. Pfeffer’s journal was, in fact, called <hi rend="italic">Untersuchungen aus dem botanischen Institut zu Tübingen</hi> (Studies from the Botanical Institute at Tübingen). The two volumes were produced while Pfeffer was at Tübingen and were essentially a forum for researchers at the institute working under Pfeffer to publish work related to Pfeffer’s own. Pfeffer was a former student of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref> and probably modelled his journal on Sachs’s <hi rend="italic">Arbeiten des botanischen Instituts in Würzburg</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">There is an annotated copy of Cornu and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8302.xml">Émile Mer</ref>’s paper, ‘Recherches sur l’absorption des matières colorantes par les racines’ (Researches on the absorption of coloured matter by roots; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9816.xml">Cornu and Mer 1878</ref>), in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">An article titled ‘A locomotive dicotyledon’ appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 9 July 1881, p. 42. It described the observations of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8979.xml">George Watt</ref>, professor of botany at the University of Calcutta, on germinating plants of <hi rend="italic">Loranthus globosus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Macrosolen globosus</hi>). According to Watt, the radicle fixed itself by means of a viscid disc, and then, if it found itself in an unfavourable site, lifted the seed to another spot, before releasing itself and adhering to a different site, a process that could be repeated several times.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Francis seems not to have published on <hi rend="italic">Bryonia.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Paraheliotropism: turning to minimise exposure to light (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 419). The lime tree may have been <hi rend="italic">Tilia tomentosa</hi>, the silver lime.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Literally, ‘Pfeffer too wants to have a railway train for himself’ (an allusion to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml">Bernard Darwin</ref>’s letter to Francis and Francis’s reply have not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Francis returned from Germany on 1 August 1881 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Presumably CD had sent an autograph and photograph for one of Francis’s colleagues.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>