<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11446">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alfred Moschkau<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>    26 March 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10114</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11446 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11446.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11446.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 252</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 252</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3421.xml">Moschkau, O. C. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1878-03-26">26 Mar 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes hereditary defect in ear muscle.</p>
            <p>Discusses influence of wet nurse on infant.</p>
            <p>Describes talking starlings.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">starlings</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">wet nurse</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Redaktion | des Illustrirten Briefmarken-Journal’s, der Saxonia | der Blätter für Autographen und Portraitsammler. Gohlis-Leipzig,</hi></placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="print">den</hi> 26. März <hi rend="print">187</hi>8.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Seit Langem habe ich es nicht gewagt Ihnen durch ein Schreiben lästig zu fallen. Trotzdem habe ich Ihrer Thätigkeit stets mein Augenmerk zugewendet und die Ihnen dargebrachten Huldigungen Ihrer Verehrer und der Engl. Universität mit hoher Genugthuung bemerkt.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Der herbe Angriff Virchows auf Ihre Lehre veranlasste mich die Feder zu einem Abweise desselben zu benützen, welchen ich Herrn Professor Häckel zusandte.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Zweck meines heutigen Schreibens ist erstlich Ihnen meinen höflichsten Dank zu sagen für die mir durch Aufnahme Ihnen übermittelter Notizen in Ihre Werke gewordene grosse Ehre; ferner Ihnen einige neue von mir gemachte Erfahrungen zur Begutachtung und späterer Benützung zu unterbreiten.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Der erste Fall betrifft die Vererbung einer Abnormität am Ohre eines Thüringers auf seinen Sohn. Der Vater hat nehmlich am linken Ohre in sofern einen <hi rend="underline">angeborenen</hi> Mangel, als ihm an der Ohrmuschel der <hi rend="underline">äusserste</hi>, oben umgeschlagene Rand fehlt. Sein Söhnlein kam mit ganz demselben Mangel behaftet zur Welt, ihm fehlt ebenfalls am linken Ohre der äusserste Rand der Ohrmuschel. Das Ohr hat dadurch bei Vater und Sohn einen mehr spitzen Character, ohne jedoch sehr aufzufallen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Zweitens möchte ich mir erlauben Sie auf Vererbung der Temperamente der <hi rend="underline">Ammen</hi> auf ihre <hi rend="underline">Säuglinge</hi> aufmerksam zu machen. Dieser Umstand ist hochwichtig und von diesem Standpunkte aus noch sehr wenig gewürdigt. So wie man zugiebt dass sich gewisse Krankheiten der Ammen (oder der säugenden Mutter!!) auf das Kind übertragen können, so wird man auch bestätigt finden, dass durch den Milchgenuss gewisse Fähigkeiten, namentlich aber die Temperamente eingesogen werden. “Die Milch der frommen Denkungsart”<ref target="#foot.f6"/> ist daher mehr wie Ironie. Giebt man diese Uebertragung aber zu, so steht man vor einem beachtenswerthen Factum, dem der Ammenfrage und der Frage ob dann das Ammenhalten überhaupt noch zu rechtfertigen ist. Mir liegen Beweise vor, das Kinder von phlegmatischen, verschlossenen Ammen gestillt, diese Temperamente und Characterart er u. behielten. Es wird also eine heitere, edlen Character eigene Amme der Seelenentwickelung der Kindes nützen, das Gegentheil ergiebt sich von selbst. Ich will also hieraus nur den Schluss ziehen, dass Fähigkeiten nicht nur vererbt resp. angeboren werden müssen, sondern durch Säugung und bei entsprechender Wahl der Amme auch <hi rend="doubleUnderline">angezüchtet</hi> werden können. Ich weiss nicht ob Sie mir hierin beistimmen werden?</p>
                    <p>Meine ferneren Notizen beziehen sich erneut auf “mit Verständniss” sprechende Vögel. In der sächsischen Lausitz wohnt ein alter Mann, der sich seit Jahrzehnten nur mit der Dressur der Staare beschäftigt. Ein Beispiel möge Ihnen bezeugen wie weit es dieser Mann, Namens Deutscher, in seinem Fache gebracht.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Er hatte einen Staar, den er noch flüge, d. h. zum Fliegen unreif, aus dem Neste genommen folgendes Gespräch gelernt:</p>
<table>
    <row>
        <cell rend="left">Wer bist du?</cell>
        <cell rend="centre">Der Staar:</cell>
        <cell rend="left">Ich bin der General Radezky<ref target="#foot.f8"/></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell rend="left">Wie alt?</cell>
        <cell rend="centre">"</cell>
        <cell rend="left">Ich bin siebzig Jahr.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell rend="left">Warst du tapfer?</cell>
        <cell rend="centre">"</cell>
        <cell rend="left">Sehr, sehr tapfer!</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell rend="left">Kannst du auch pfeifen?</cell>
        <cell/>
        <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell cols="3">   Auf diese Frage nun setzte sich der Staar in Position, commandirte von selbst an sich:—Achtung Musik!—und begann darauf das Volkslied: Schier dreissig Jahre bist du alt! zu pfeifen.</cell>
    </row>   
</table>
                    
<p>Dieser Vogel war ein wahres Prachtstück, ein Pfarrer erkaufte denselben und nach einem viertel Jahre frass ihm dessen Katze.</p>
                    <p>Noch gelehrter war ein Staar, welchen im Jahre 1867 ein Gasthofsbesitzer “zur Hummel” in Hörnitz bei Zittau in der Lausitz hielt.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Dieses Thier sprach soviel und pfiff so viele Melodien, dass der Eigenthümer die ganze Gelehrsamkeit des Staares auf einen grossen Zettel druckte, diese Zettel an die Strassenecken heftete und dadurch viel Gäste anzog. Auch dieser Staar soll, wie man mir sagte, schliesslich einer Katze zum Opfer gefallen sein.</p>
                    <p>Eine vor Jahren im zoologischen Garten zu Dresden gehaltene Spottdrossel, sprach wenig, aber mit sichtlichem Verständniss. Kam ein Besucher an ihren Käfig, so war die erste Frage: “Hast du Zucker?” Erhielt sie nun solchen, rief sie laut: “danke, danke!” Erhielt sie aber keinen, oder wurde sie geneckt, schrie sie mit richtiger Entrüstung: “Du alter Bauer!” was allgemein belustigte.</p>
                    <p>Mir scheint es als wenn der Staar am verständlichsten zu sprechen vermögend wäre. Weder obige Spottdrosseln noch die Papageien etc die ich gehört, waren so gut zu verstehen.</p>
                    <p>Soviel für heute. Es wäre mir sehr erfreulich wenn Ihnen diese Notizen von einigem Intresse wären. Ich verehre Sie mein Herr, sehr hoch und bin in meiner Heimath als ein Darwinianer förmlich verschrieen, möchte daher gern auch mein Scherflein zum Ausbau Ihrer Lehre, die in der Naturwissenschaft eine förmliche Revolution hervorrief u. Epoche machte, beitragen. Aus diesem Grunde wollen Sie meine Notizen nachsichtig aufnehmen und Sie würden mich durch einige Zeilen, ob ich Ihnen auch künftig meine Bemerkungen wieder unterbreiten darf, recht glücklich machen.</p>
<p>Gebe Ihnen der Himmel Gesundheit und Kraft, damit Sie noch recht lange sich dem Ausbau Ihrer schönen Lehre zu widmen im Stande sind.</p>
<p>In unbegrenzter Verehrung begrüsst Sie | Ihr | hochachtungsvoll ergebenster | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Alfred Moschkau | Schriftsteller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘very kind letter| Milk | Starling| (At work on physiology of Plants.’<ref target="#foot.f10"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Editorial Office | of the illustrated stamp journal, Der Saxonia | the paper for autograph and portrait collectors. Gohlis-Leipzig,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>26. March <hi rend="print">187</hi>8.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>For a long time I have not dared bother you with a letter. Nevertheless I have always followed your activities, and noticed with great satisfaction the tributes paid to you by your admirers and by the English university.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Virchow’s caustic attack on your theory caused me to pick up my pen and to write a refutation, which I sent to Professor Haeckel.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>The purpose of my writing today is firstly to thank you most kindly for the great honour you bestowed on me by including in your work communications I sent you; and further to submit a few of my recent findings for your examination and future use.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>The first case concerns the transmission of a deformity of the ear in a Thuringian to his son. The father has, you see, an <hi rend="underline">inborn</hi> defect in his left ear, in that the <hi rend="underline">outermost</hi> edge of the top of his ear shell is missing. His little son was born afflicted with exactly the same defect: in the same way the outermost edge of the ear shell of his left ear is missing. As a result, the ear in both the father and the son has a more pointed appearance, which is, however, not very noticeable.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Secondly, I would like to draw your attention to the transmission of the temperament of <hi rend="underline">wet nurses</hi> to their <hi rend="underline">infants</hi>. This circumstance is of great importance, yet it is very rarely appreciated in this light. Just as it is accepted that certain illnesses can be transmitted from the wet nurse (or nursing mother!!) to the child, it can also be confirmed that by drinking the milk, certain characteristics, but especially the temperament, can be imbibed. The expression ‘the milk of human kindness’<ref target="#foot_trans.f6"/> is therefore rather ironical. But if one allows that such transmission occurs, one arrives at a noteworthy fact, the question of wet nurses and whether keeping wet nurses is still at all justifiable. I have proof that children cared for by phlegmatic, withdrawn wet nurses received &amp; retained these temperaments and dispositions. So a wet nurse with a cheerful noble disposition will benefit the mental development of the child, and the opposite naturally follows. I therefore draw the conclusion that characteristics must not only be inherited at birth, but can also be <hi rend="doubleUnderline">bred</hi> through suckling and by the appropriate choice of a wet nurse. I do not know whether you agree with me on this?</p>
                    <p>My remaining notes have to do once more with birds talking “with comprehension”. In the Saxon Lusatia there lives an old man who has been occupied for decades just training starlings. An example will show you how far this man, whose name is Deutscher, has got in his field.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>He taught a starling that he had taken out of its nest when it was still unfledged, i.e., not yet able to fly, the following speech: </p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left">Who are you?</cell>
                            <cell rend="centre">The Starling:</cell>
                            <cell rend="left">I am General Radezky<ref target="#foot.f8"/></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left">How old?</cell>
                            <cell rend="centre">"</cell>
                            <cell rend="left">I am seventy years old.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left">Were you brave?</cell>
                            <cell rend="centre">"</cell>
                            <cell rend="left">Very, very brave!</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left">Can you whistle too?</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="3">   At this question the starling drew himself up, gave the command of his own accord:—Music!—and began thereupon to whistle the folk song: You’re almost thirty!</cell>
                        </row>   
                    </table>
<p>This bird was a real showpiece; a vicar bought it and after 3 months his cat ate it.</p>
                    <p>Even more learned was a starling which was kept by the proprietor of the guest house “zur Hummel” in Hornitz near Zittau in Lusatia in the year 1867.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> This animal talked so much and whistled so many melodies that the owner had the whole repertoire of the starling printed on a big sheet and hung the sheets up on street corners, so that it attracted a lot of guests. I am told that this starling also in the end fell victim to a cat.</p>
                    <p>A mocking-bird that was kept in the Dresden zoological garden years ago spoke little, but with obvious comprehension. If a visitor came up to its cage, then its first question was: “Have you any sugar?” If it got some, it called loudly: “Thank you, thank you!” But if it did not get any, or if it was teased, it cried with real indignation:  “You old peasant!”, which amused everybody.</p>
                    <p>It looks to me as though starlings were the most capable of speaking intelligibly. Neither the above-mentioned mocking-bird nor the parrots etc. that I have heard were so easy to understand.</p>
                    <p>Enough for today. It would gratify me very much if these notes were of any interest to you. I respect you, my dear Sir, very highly and am formally disparaged in my homeland as a Darwinian, and would therefore very much like to do my share in expanding your theory, which has brought about a veritable revolution &amp; started a new epoch in natural science. For this reason please treat my notes with indulgence; you would make me really happy with a few lines as to whether I may offer you my observations again in the future.</p>
<p>Heaven give you health and strength, so that you may be able to devote yourself for a very long time yet to the further elaboration of your fine theory.</p>
                    <p>With boundless respect I remain | yours | sincerely devoted | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Alfred Moschkau | Writer.</p>                   
                </div>     
            </div> 
            
            
            
            
                </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD was awarded the honorary degree of doctor of laws (LLD) at University of Cambridge on 17 November 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 3: 222).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In an address to the German Association of Naturalists and Doctors, Rudolf Carl Virchow had criticised <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel’s</ref> views on the teaching of evolution in schools; he remarked on the dangers of ‘personal speculation in science’, and claimed that the theory of descent was insufficiently proven, especially with regard to the origins of life (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10227.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Virchow 1877</ref>, and <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 22 November 1877, pp. 73–4, 29 November 1877, pp. 93–4). For more on the controversy over Virchow’s address, see the letter to K. H. von Scherzer, 1 April 1878 and n. 2. No publication by Moschkau on this subject has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 85 n. 52, CD had added information from Moschkau on a starling who said, in German, ‘Good morning’, to persons arriving, and ‘Goodbye, old fellow’, to those departing. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9184.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alfred Moschkau, 19 December 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had written about the inheritance of mutilations and deformities in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 22–4; on peculiar ear features as possible rudiments of an animal ancestor, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 22–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The quotation is from Friedrich Schiller’s <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Tell</hi>, 4. 3:  <lg><l>In gärend Drachengift hast du</l> <l>die Milch der frommen Denkart mir verwandelt.</l></lg> This may be translated as: ‘you have changed the milk of human kindness in me to a fermenting dragon’s poison’. ‘Frommen Denkart’ literally means ‘gentle (innocent) mindset’; ‘Denkungsart’ is a variant with the added meaning of ‘convictions’, and the usage is often ironic.
                </note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f6">The quotation in the original German is from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7679.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich von Schiller’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Tell</hi>, 4. 3: <lg><l>In gärend Drachengift hast du</l> <l>die Milch der frommen Denkart mir verwandelt.</l></lg>  This may be translated as: ‘you have changed the milk of human kindness in me to a fermenting dragon’s poison’. ‘Frommen Denkart’ literally means ‘gentle (innocent) mindset’; ‘Denkungsart’ is a variant with the added meaning of ‘convictions’, and the usage is often ironic. The English phrase ‘milk of human kindness’ is familiar from Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">Macbeth</hi> act 1, scene 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Lusatia (Lausitz) was part of the Kingdom of Saxony; in 1815 it was divided, with part of Upper Lusatia, including Dresden and Leipzig, remaining under Saxony and the rest transferred to Prussia (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>). Deutscher has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Radetzky</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Bertsdorf-Hörnitz and Zittau are now in the state of Saxony (Germany). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD’s note is for his reply (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11451.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Alfred Moschkau, 28 March 1878</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>