<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10314">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. H. Darwin to W. D. Whitney   21 December 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8001</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10314 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10314.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10314.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Yale University Library: Manuscripts and Archives (William Dwight Whitney Family Papers (MS 555): Box 23, folder 631 1875 Dec. 18-24)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_446.xml">Yale Manuscripts</repository>
                    <collection>W. D. Whitney Family Papers (MS 555)</collection>
                    <idno>Box 23, folder 631 1875 Dec. 18-24</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">Darwin, G. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1875-12-21">21 Dec 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5110.xml">Whitney, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Müller has sent <hi rend="italic">Chips</hi> [<hi rend="italic">from a German workshop</hi> (1867–75)] and a boring defence against WDW’s attack. GHD feels he is maligned for using the weight of CD’s name in his <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Review</hi> article. CD says Müller has misinterpreted a letter from CD as supporting him in his controversy with WDW.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Chips from a German workshop</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Contemporary Review</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Müller 1867–1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Dec 21. 75</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Both my Father &amp; I were very sorry to have missed seeing you when in England.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I hope I may be able to visit the U.S again some day &amp; then we may perhaps meet, even if you do not visit England again.</p>
<p>Max Müller sent the part of the ‘Chips’ to my Father, which contains his defence(!) against your attacks.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I confess that I found it so intolerably dull that I could not <hi rend="underline">read</hi> it, but I looked thro’ a great part of it. I am a little sorry that you are going to write in answer, as I think that very few will trouble themselves to read it (Max Müller) &amp; those who do so will see that it is the work of a man out of himself with anger. I of course did not perceive the various cases of injustice to your linguistic views to which you refer; these coming ex cathedrâ must be very galling. I confess I felt it a little hard on myself to be dragged into the foreground &amp; chaffed—rather savagely however.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>In my Contemp. article I thought I had made it pretty clear that I wrote as an ignoramus &amp; only intended to represent your views, with such comments as ordinary intelligence <hi rend="underline">without</hi> linguistic knowledge w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. allow me.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It was also unjust both to you &amp; me to coolly assume that you have manoeuvred to ‘get hold of the pen of the Son fondly hoping it would carry the weight of the father’s’—<hi rend="underline">sous entendu</hi> that I am rather a fool &amp; you rather a knave.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> One does not see the end of this kind of polemic &amp; if it were I myself, I think I should have been rather inclined to allow time to cool the heats of controversy &amp; bring forth the just view of the case. However it is very hard to put oneself in another’s place, &amp; I daresay I misjudge the difficulty of sitting down under the attacks of one bearing the name of great authority</p>
<p>Believe me | Yours faithfully | Geo. H Darwin</p>
<p>My Father dictates as follows to you:</p>
<p>“There is a sentence in the Chips in wh. M.M expresses great satisfaction at having received a letter from me, and which seems to imply that I had said that I thought that you were wrong in the controversy &amp; he Max Muller right, whereas there was nothing whatever in the letter which could bear any interpretation of this kind”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Whitney, who had spent the summer in England, attempted to meet CD in May 1875 and again in September (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10144.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. D. Whitney, 1 September 1875</ref> and n. 1). George had visited America between August and October 1871, and met Whitney at least twice (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8002.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Chauncey Wright, 11 October 1871</ref> and n. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3233.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Max Müller’s</ref> defence was in an essay recently published in the fourth volume of <hi rend="italic">Chips from a German workshop</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Müller 1867–75</ref>, 4: 473–549); he had sent a copy to CD in October (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10194.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Friedrich Max Müller, 13 October [1875]</ref>). Max Müller was responding to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8759.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Whitney 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Max Müller’s essay continued a debate over the origins of language between Max Müller, Whitney, and George Darwin that had started in 1874 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10194.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Friedrich Max Müller, 13 October [1875]</ref> and n. 3). A section of the essay, ‘Mr. George Darwin’s article in the “<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Contemporary Review</ref>”’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Müller 1867–75</ref>, 4: 482–5), took George to task for supporting Whitney’s views.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">George had published his article ‘Professor Whitney on the origin of language’ in the <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Review</hi> (G. H. Darwin 1874).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Max Müller made this statement in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Müller 1867–75</ref>, 4: 535. ‘<hi rend="italic">Sous entendu</hi>’ (French): insinuating.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Müller 1867–75</ref>, 4: 483. Max Müller probably referred to the letter to him of 5 January 1875.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>