<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10825">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Thomas Palmer   February 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10367</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10825 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10825.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10825.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 174: 14</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>174: 14</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3658.xml">Palmer, Thomas</persName>
                <placeName>Chislehurst</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1877-02-01" notAfter="1877-02-28">Feb 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on expression in his Pomeranian dog.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">dog</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Pomerania</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lower Camden | Chislehurst.</placeName>
                    <date>Febry. 1877.</date>
                    <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Though I have scrupiously and thoroughly read all your admirable books, more especially those relating to the science of botany; it was only a few weeks ago that I was tempted to invest in the one entitled “The expression of the emotions” this I have now read I may say thoroughly and I must say it has made me notice and remember many things which when they took place were unheeded.</p>
<p>Some years ago I had a dog of the Pomeranian species who was much attatched to me and who because he would not sleep in any other place was allowed the mat outside my bedroom door which was a sheep skin, this mat he used to scratch up into a lump at one end for his head to lie upon, after sundry turns he would lie down, the nose back and tail were in a complete line the back legs distended towards the tail, the front ones towards the nose but the head was always perched against the pillow at an angle of about 45<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. to the rest of his body in this way he would always lay if in a room his head was reclined against the leg of a chair or table but never flat: he was moreover a pugnacious rascal which latter accomplishment cost him his life, though he was exceedingly cautious, when fighting he would spring on his enemy like a cat &amp; would never approach another if he desired a fight in any other way: prior to making a spring he crouched just like a cat with head on the ground teeth fully uncovered ears set forward hair all on end and tail straight out, when in a friendly mood he never jumped up at you but would keep forming a circuit round you wriggling his body showing his front teeth and continually sneezing<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>And now no doubt you will think it curious that I should send you these particulars, well I have done so because I find nothing in your book to coincide with my faithful companions antics. When children we had a cat who used to watch for my Fathers return from town in the evening when it used to jump on his shoulder and caress him in the most affectionate manner this cat was a Persian and as a rule rather ill tempered</p>
<p>Hoping what I have said may interest you | I remain | Your’s respectfully | T<hi rend="superscript">hos</hi>. Palmer.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘There is no end to the many points which may be [‘observed’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] noted &amp; yet are not [<hi rend="italic">transposed from after</hi> ‘observer’] by a good observer’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 116–29, CD had described various facial movements and bodily gestures in dogs and cats.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>