<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3947">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Friedrich Rolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   26 January 1863</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10560</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3947 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3947.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3947.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) damaged</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 201</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 201</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4067.xml">Rolle, Friedrich</persName>
                <placeName>Bad Homburg</placeName>
                <date when="1863-01-26">26 Jan 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Pleased that his book, <hi rend="italic">Ch. Darwin’s Lehre</hi> [1863], has CD’s approval.</p> 
            <p>FR formerly a geologist, now a dealer in natural history objects.</p>
            <p>Most active supporter of CD’s theory is Gustav Jäger in Vienna.</p> 
<p>FR regards fossil <hi rend="italic">Hipparion</hi> as a link between horse and pachyderms.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Hipparion</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">horse</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pachyderms</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Ch. Darwin’s Lehre</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">dealer</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2514">Jäger, Gustav</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Vienna</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Rolle, Friedrich 1863</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">intermediate forms, gradation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00884_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00884_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="201:1r" xml:id="i884">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00884.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00884_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00884.dzi" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="201:1v" xml:id="i885">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00885.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00885_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00885.dzi" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="201:2r" xml:id="i886">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00886.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00886_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00886.dzi" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="201:2v" xml:id="i887">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00887.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00887_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00887.dzi" width="4121px" height="6525px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bad Homburg bei Frankfurt am M〈ain〉</placeName>
                    <date>den 26<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi>. Januar 1863.</date>
                    <salute>Geehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Entschuldigen Sie, wenn ich nicht eher Ihr gütiges Schreiben vom vorigen Herbst beantworte.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich wollte erst den Schluss meines kleinen Werkes “Darwin’s Lehre” abwarten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Ich war sehr erfreut zu sehen, dass meine Arbeit Ihren Beifall gefunden hat und ich hoffe dass Sie im Schluss-Hefte noch weitre Gegenstaende antreffen, welche Ihre Aufmerksamkeit auf sich ziehen. Sie werden manche Versuche finden der Palaeontologie die physiologische Seite abzugewinnen.</p>
<p>Ich bin eigentlich Geologe und Palaeontologe. Meine Hauptaufgabe war in den letzten Jahren die Ermittelung der Genealogie der europaeischen Meeres-Fauna und ihre Ableitung von den Tertiaeren Fossilien. Ich habe darüber nur wenig veroeffentlicht, denn ich verliess im letzten Frühjahre vor Beendung dieser Arbeiten das Kaiserl. Koenigl. Hofmineralien-Cabinet zu Wien, an dem ich fünf Jahre lang als Assistent, spaeter als Adjunkt stand.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ich habe mich seither in meiner Vaterstadt Homburg als Naturalienhaendler niedergelassen und hoffe mir auf diesem Wege ein unabhaengiges Fortkommen gewinnen zu koennen.</p>
<p>Ich wandte mich damals an den Buchhaendler H<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>. Suchsland in Frankfurt um den Auftrag zu einem wissenschaftlichen Werke.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> H<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Suchsland hatte in Zeitschriften von Ihrer Lehre Kenntniss erhalten und äusserte viel Antheil daran. Er übertrug mir daher eine Erläuterung derselben.</p>
<p>So fiel mir die Aufgabe zu, für die Erweiterung und Ausbreitung Ihrer Theorie zu wirken. Eigentlich ist der thaetigste Vertreter Ihrer Ansichten mein Freund Doctor Gustav Jaeger in Wien, ein geborner Schwabe, der Gründer und jetzt Director des zoologischen Gartens in Wien ist.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Gustav Jäger und ich waren schon Ihrer Ansicht, ehe wir noch Ihr Werk erhielten. Wir gedachten selbst ein gemeinsames Werk über die Genealogie der Thiere zu schreiben, Jaeger sollte den zoologischen und physiologischen Theil, ich wollte den geologischen und palaeontologischen Theil bearbeiten. Aber unsre Absicht gelangte nicht zu vollstaendiger Ausführung.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Als Ihr Werk erschien, übernahm es Jäger die Theorie in Wien durch oeffentliche Vortraege und in Zeitschriften zu erläutern. Ein Herr Pelzeln in Wien trat als sein Gegner auf.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Aber die oeffentliche Meinung sprach für Jäger. H<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pelzeln fand nicht einmal einen Raum zur Veroeffentlichung seiner Einwaende. Er liess seine Erwiederung daher als eigene Flugschrift erscheinen. (August von Pelzeln, Bemerkungen gegen Darwin’s Theorie vom Ursprung der Spezies. Wien bei Pichler 1861. 8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 17 pag.)<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Diese Flugschrift ist aber so arm, so albern und zugleich so fanatisch geschrieben, dass man sie am besten gar nicht aufführt und Jaeger hat auch darauf nicht geantwortet.</p>
<p>Jaeger hielt damals auch auf der Versammlung der deutschen Ornithologen zu Stuttgart einen Vortrag; als seine Gegner traten Professor Blasius (von Braunschweig) und Professor Altum (von Münster) auf.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Seit dieser Zeit hat Jaeger nichts mehr darin gethan, weil er zusehr mit der Begründung des Wiener Zoologischen Gartens beschaeftigt war. Doch beabsichtigt er demnaechst wieder hervorzutreten und ich bin bemüht ihn anzutreiben.</p>
<p>Unsre Professoren in Deutschland sind theils Ihre Gegner, theils schweigen sie.</p>
<p>Aehnliche Ansichten hat von jeher Professor Quenstedt in Tübingen gehabt. Aber er arbeitet ohne Methode und macht viele Fehler, daher er auch nie allgemeine Geltung in Deutschland gefunden hat.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Für Ihre Ansichten haben sich namentlich noch D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Weinland in Frankfurt (ehemals Assistent von Agassiz) und D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hensel 〈in〉 Berlin ausgesprochen.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Weinland hat 〈mich〉 bei meiner Arbeit sehr unterstützt〈. Hensel〉 kenne ich nicht von Person; Sie f〈inden〉 einige wichtige Bemerkungen in Hensel’s Schrift, über Hipparion in den Abhandlungen der Berliner Akademie.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Er bemerkt, dass das Pferd von den Pachydermen entfernt steht. Seine abnorme Fuss-Bildung zeigt das Pferd schon als Embryo. Es gibt aber monstroese Bildungen am Pferde, bei der die normale Pachydermen-Bildung des Fusses sichtbar wird. Dies ist ein Nachklang der Abstammung des Pferdes von Pachydermen. Die fossile Gattung Hipparion bestaetigt dies und liefert einen deutlichen Uebergang vom Pferd zu Rhinoceros, Hippopotamen und andren Pachydermen. Hensel sagt auch, dass rudimentaere Organe für jeden Naturforscher, der auf dem Boden der Realitaet steht, auf keine andre Weise naturgemaess erklaert werden koennen als durch Abstammung.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Sollte ich Ihnen irgendwie gefaellig sein koennen, so soll es mit Vergnügen geschehen. Besonders über tertiaere Mollusken oder andre palaeontologische Gegenstaende bin ich bereit.</p>
<p>Entschuldigen Sie, dass Ich Ihnen deutsch antworte, das Englische ist mir sehr wenig gelaüfig, Sie würden mein Englisch vielleicht nicht verstehen.</p>
<p>Es empfiehlt sich Ihnen, geehrtester Herr | Ihr hochachtungsvoller Diener | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Friedrich Rolle.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bad Homburg bei Frankfurt am Main</placeName>
                    <date>26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. January 1863.</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Please excuse me for not replying earlier to your kind letter of last Autumn.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> First I wanted to wait for the conclusion of my little work “Darwin’s Lehre”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I was greatly pleased to see that my work met with your approval and I hope that in the concluding part you will come across more matters that will attract your attention. You will find how much physiology can be gleaned from palaeontology.</p>
<p>I am basically a geologist and a palaeontologist. My main task in recent years was to establish the genealogy of the European marine fauna and its derivation from tertiary fossils. I have published only little on this subject, because last spring, before completing these studies I left the Kaiserl. Königl. Hofmineralien-Cabinet in Vienna, where for five years I had been first assistant and later adjunct.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Since then I have settled in my home town of Homburg as a dealer in natural history objects and hope in this manner to be able to earn an independent living.</p>
<p>At that time I turned to the publisher Herr Suchsland in Frankfurt, to obtain the commission for a scientific work.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Herr Suchsland had read about your doctrine in periodicals and expressed great interest in it. Therefore he commissioned me to write a commentary upon it.</p>
<p>Thus the task to broaden and spread your theory has fallen to me. The most active supporter of your views in Vienna is actually my friend Doctor Gustav Jaeger, a native Swabian, founder and now director of the Zoological Garden in Vienna.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Gustav Jaeger and I already shared your views even before we became acquainted with your work. We were thinking of writing a joint work on the genealogy of animals; Jaeger was to work on the zoological and physiological part, I on the geological and palaeontological part. But we did not succeed in fully realising our intentions.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>When your work appeared, Jaeger undertook to explain the theory in Vienna in public lectures and journals. A certain Herr Pelzeln presented himself as his opponent in Vienna.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> But public opinion spoke for Jaeger. Herr Pelzeln never once found a place for his objections. Thus he had his reply published privately as a pamphlet (August von Pelzeln, Bemerkungen gegen Darwin’s Theorie vom Ursprung der Spezies. Wien bei Pichler 1861. 8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 17 pag.)<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>However, this pamphlet is so poorly, so absurdly and at the same time so fanatically written, that it is best not to mention it at all, and Jaeger has not replied to it.</p>
<p>At that time Jaeger also gave a lecture at the annual meeting of the German ornithologists in Stuttgart; Professor Blasius (of Braunschweig) and Professor Altum (of Münster) spoke in opposition.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Since then Jaeger has done no more about it, because he was too occupied with the founding of the Vienna Zoological Garden. However, he intends to resume his efforts soon, and I am endeavouring to urge him to do so.</p>
<p>Our German Professors are partly your opponents, partly they say nothing.</p>
<p>Professor Quenstedt of Tübingen has always had similar views. But he works without method and makes many mistakes, and therefore has never found general acceptance in Germany.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Weinland of Frankfurt (a former assistant to Agassiz) and D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hensel of Berlin have pronounced themselves in favour of your views.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Weinland has strongly supported my work. I do not know Hensel personally; you will find some important observations in Hensel’s paper on Hipparion in the Proceedings of the Berlin academy.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> He remarks that the horse is distant from the Pachyderms. As an embryo, the horse already exhibits the abnormal pedal structure. However, there are monstrous structures in the horse in which the normal structure of the pachyderm foot is visible. This is an echo of the descent of the horse from the Pachyderms. The fossil genus Hipparion confirms this and provides a distinct transition from the horse to the rhinoceros, hippopotamus, and other pachyderms. Hensel says also that rudimentary organs cannot be explained naturally by any researcher with his feet on the ground except by descent.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>I would be happy if I could be of any service to you. I am especially willing to help with Tertiary molluscs and other palaeontological matters.</p>
<p>Please forgive me for replying in German, but I have so little command of English that you would not understand me if I were to write in it.</p>
<p>I am, dear Sir, | your obedient servant, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Friedrich Rolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.11, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the original German, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.11, pp. 86–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-3770.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to Friedrich Rolle, 17 October [1862]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6704.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rolle 1863</ref> was published in instalments, the first and second of which had been sent to CD before 17 October 1862. The publication of the third and fourth parts was announced on 19 January 1863 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Börsenblatt für den Deutschen Buchhandel</hi></ref> 30 (1863): 113). In translation, its title read: ‘<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Charles Darwin’s</ref> theory of the origin of species in the plant and animal kingdoms and its application to the history of creation’. In the foreword to the book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6704.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rolle 1863</ref>, p. [ii]), Rolle referred to CD’s approval of his efforts (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3770.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Friedrich Rolle, 17 October [1862]</ref> and n. 3). CD’s annotated copies of all four parts of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6704.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rolle 1863</ref> are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For a description of Rolle’s life in Vienna at the Kaiserlich-königliche Hofmineraliencabinet (Royal Imperial Cabinet of Mineralogy), and for a discussion of his reasons for leaving academic life and moving to Homburg in March 1862, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5249.xml">Martin and Uschmann 1969</ref>, pp. 18–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The publisher and bookseller <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4610.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Emil Suchsland</ref> was head of the Frankfurt firm <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Christian Hermann’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5249.xml">Martin and Uschmann 1969</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Jäger</ref> announced his support for transmutation and CD’s theory in lectures given at the annual meeting of the Deutsche Ornithologen-Gesellschaft in Stuttgart on 18 September 1860 (see n. 10, below), and at the Verein zur Verbreitung naturwissenschaftlicher Kenntnisse in Vienna on 10 and 15 December 1860 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4123.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jäger 1862</ref>; see n. 8, below). Jäger was one of the directors of the zoological garden in Vienna, which opened on 25 May 1863 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8263.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weinreich 1993</ref>, pp. 48–64).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Zoologische Briefe</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jäger 1864</ref>) included a chapter in which Jäger argued in support of the transmutation of species theory; the author claimed that this was written before the publication of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in 1859 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jäger 1864</ref>, pp. 36–56). There is a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jäger 1864</ref> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. For a discussion of Jäger’s reaction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8263.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weinreich 1993</ref>, pp. 36–47.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Rolle refers to the confrontation between August Pelzel von Pelzeln and Jäger at the meeting of the Zoologisch-botanische Gesellschaft in Vienna on 5 December 1860. Pelzeln had given a lecture in which he criticised CD’s theory, and which was later published as <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pelzeln 1861</ref>; CD’s annotated copy of this work is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. According to the report in the <hi rend="italic">Verhandlungen der kaiserlich-königlichen zoologisch-botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien</hi> 10 (1860): 98, Jäger strongly opposed Pelzeln’s view and offered to speak in support of CD’s theory (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4123.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jäger 1862</ref>; see also n. 7, above).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pelzeln 1861</ref>. See n. 8, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Jäger’s lecture in support of CD’s theory was given at the annual meeting of the Deutsche Ornithologen-Gesellschaft on 18 September 1860. In the subsequent discussion, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_98.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bernhard Altum</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_487.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Heinrich Blasius</ref> maintained that CD’s theory was a purely speculative and unsubstantiated hypothesis (see <hi rend="italic">Bericht über die XIII. Versammlung der Deutschen Ornithologen-Gesellschaft zu Stuttgart vom 17. bis 20. September 1860</hi>, pp. 6, 40–6). In the late 1860s, Altum, a clergyman and lecturer in zoology, became known as one of the most uncompromising opponents of the theory of evolution in Germany (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7510.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stresemann 1975</ref>, pp. 273–4, 328–32).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3895.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich August Quenstedt</ref> had been Rolle’s tutor at the University of Tübingen. In 1856, he published a popular book in which he made a number of remarks in favour of biological evolution and common descent (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6477.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quenstedt 1856</ref>, pp. 227–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">The references are to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5046.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Friedrich Weinland</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reinhold Friedrich Hensel</ref>. Weinland, a lecturer in zoology at the Senckenberg Museum, Frankfurt, had been an assistant to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> in Cambridge, Massachusetts, between 1855 and 1858 (<hi rend="italic">Zoologischer Beobachter</hi> 57 (1916): 160). In February 1861, he published a short but favourable review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8260.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weinland 1861</ref>). Hensel had been a tutor in natural history at the University of Berlin until 1860; three years later, he was commissioned to conduct zoological research in southern Brazil (<hi rend="italic">Leopoldina</hi> 18 (1882): 19–21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hensel 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Hensel mentioned CD’s theory briefly when he considered the importance of rudimentary organs and maintained that biological traits were gradually changing over time (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hensel 1860</ref>, pp. 69–70).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>