<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9680">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Auguste Forel   15 October 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3859</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9680 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9680.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9680.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 191;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Walser (1968): 134</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Universität Zürich, Archiv für Medizingeschichte (AfM ZH PN 31.2:793)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_453.xml">Zürich Archiv für Medizingeschichte</repository>
                    <idno>AfM ZH PN 31.2:793</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1874-10-15">15 Oct 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1686.xml">Forel, A.-H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Writes about AHF’s book on Swiss ants.</p>
            <p>Recounts his own observations on ants carrying cocoons.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ants</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Switzerland</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-02-18" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-02-18" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Beckenham, Kent.</placeName>
                    <date>Oct 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1874</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have now read the whole of your admirable work &amp; seldom in my life have I been more interested by any book.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> There are so many interesting facts &amp; discussions, that I hardly know which to specify; but I think, firstly, the newest points to me have been about the size of the brain in the three sexes, together with your suggestion that increase of mind-power may have led to the sterility of the workers.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Secondly about the battles of the ants, &amp; your curious account of the enraged ants being held by their comrades until they calmed down.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Thirdly the evidence of ants of the same community being the offspring of brothers &amp; sisters.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> You admit, I think, that new communities will often be the product of a cross between not-related ants. Fritz Müller has made some interesting observations on this head with respect to Termites.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The case of of <hi rend="underline">Anergates</hi> is most perplexing in many ways; but I have such faith in the law of occasional crossing that I believe an explanation will hereafter be found, such as the dimorphism of either sex &amp; the occasional production of winged males.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I see that you are puzzled how ants of the same community recognize each other; I once placed two ants (<hi rend="underline">F. rufa</hi>) in a pill-box smelling strongly of assafœtida, &amp; after a day returned them to their homes; they were threatened, but at last recognized. I made this trial thinking that they might know each other by their odour; but this cannot here have been the case, &amp; I have often fancied that they must have some common signal.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Your last chapter is one great mass of wonderful facts &amp; suggestions, &amp; the whole profoundly interesting. I have seldom been more gratified than by the honorable mention of my work</p>
<p>I should like to tell you one little observation which I made with care many years ago; I saw ants (<hi rend="underline">Formica rufa</hi>) carrying coccoons from a nest which was the largest I ever saw &amp; which was well known to all the country people near, &amp; an old man apparently about 80 years of age told me that he had known it ever since he was a little boy. The ants carrying the coccoons did not appear to be emigrating; following the line I saw many ascending a tall fir tree still carrying their coccoons. But when I looked closely, I found that all the coccoons were empty cases. This astonished me, &amp; next day I got a man to observe with me, &amp; we again saw ants bringing empty coccoons out of the nest; each of us fixed on one ant &amp; slowly followed it, &amp; repeated the observation on many others. We thus found that some ants soon dropped their empty coccoons; others carried them for many yards, as much as 30 paces, &amp; others carried them high up the fir tree out of sight.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Now here I think we have one instinct in contest with another &amp; mistaken one. The first instinct being to carry the empty coccoons out of the nest, &amp; it would have been sufficient to have laid them on the heap of rubbish, as the first breath of wind would have blown them away. And then came in the contest with the other very powerful instinct of preserving &amp; carrying their coccoons as long as possible; &amp; this they could not help doing although the coccoons were empty. According as the one or other instinct was the stronger in each individual ant, so did it carry the empty coccoon to a greater or less distance. If this little observation should ever prove of any use to you, you are quite at liberty to use it.</p>
<p>Again thanking you cordially for the great pleasure which your Work has given me, I remain with much respect— Yours sincerely | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>P.S | If you read English easily I should like to send you M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Belt’s book, as I think you would like it as much as did Fritz Müller<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD refers to <hi rend="italic">Les fourmis de la Suisse</hi> (Ants of Switzerland; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forel 1874</ref>); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9656.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Auguste Forel, 23 September 1874</ref>. CD’s heavily annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forel 1874</ref> is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 237–40).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Forel had observed that the mushroom bodies in workers (non-reproductive female) of the genus <hi rend="italic">Formica</hi>, thought to be the most intelligent ants, were very large. The same parts were smaller in reproductive females and much smaller in males (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forel 1874</ref>, p. 123). CD scored the section in his copy and added a note (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 238). Mushroom bodies are the section of the brain in ants and other Hymenoptera associated with complex behaviour.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Forel observed amazon-ants, in a state he described as rage, killing everything in sight until slaves from their colony calmed them (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forel 1874</ref>, p. 304).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See n. 6, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the first part of his study of termites (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1873–5</ref>, pp. 333–9), Müller had described two sexual forms of both male and female termites in a newly discovered species <hi rend="italic">Calotermes canellae</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Glyptotermes canellae</hi>); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 1 January 1874</ref> and n. 3. In the third part (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. Müller 1873–5</ref>, pp. 451–63), Müller argued that the existence of two forms of sexual reproduction in termites could be seen as confirmation of CD’s theory that crossing of individuals not closely related was beneficial or even necessary to the species; see letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> January 1874] and n. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Forel observed that the species <hi rend="italic">Anergates atratulus</hi> (the dark guest ant), which was a parasite of <hi rend="italic">Tetramorium caespitum</hi>, was devoid of workers and that there were no winged males, and concluded that all mating was between brothers and sisters, noting that any winged females that entered a nest already occupied by other <hi rend="italic">A. atratulus</hi> would be killed by the workers of <hi rend="italic">T. caespitum</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forel 1874</ref>, pp. 343–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Formica rufa</hi> is the red wood ant. CD mentioned the experiment in an undated note in DAR 205.11 (2): 106. The note refers to Moor Park, Farnham, Surrey, where CD stayed in 1857, 1858, and 1859. CD recounted the experiment in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 251.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD refers to observations of <hi rend="italic">Formica rufa</hi> made during his stay at Moor Park in July 1859. His note describing this case, headed ‘July 23/59/’ and marked ‘Mistaken Instinct’, is in DAR 205.11 (2): 96.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD had recommended <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Belt’s</ref> book <hi rend="italic">The naturalist in Nicaragua</hi> (Belt 1874) in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9661.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Forel of 28 September [1874]</ref>. He had sent a copy of the book to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> in January 1874 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 1 January 1874</ref>). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9422A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 20 April [1874]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>