<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11648">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Gaston de Saporta<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   9 August 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10618</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11648 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11648.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11648.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 36</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 36</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4181.xml">Saporta, L. C. J. G. de</persName>
                <placeName>Fonscolombe</placeName>
                <date when="1878-08-09">9 Aug 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Congratulations on election to the French Academy of Sciences, Botany Section.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">French Academy election</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">French Academy of Sciences, botanical section</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Fonscolombe | par le Puy— S<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> Réparade | (B. du Rhône)</placeName>
                    <date>le 9 aout 78</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur et honoré confrère,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>J’apprends aujourdhui par les journaux que vous avez été élu lundi dernier correspondant de la section de botanique à l’Académie des Sciences—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Je suis trop heureux de cet événement et trop flatté de voir mon nom inscrit près du votre pour ne pas venir vous témoigner ma vive satisfaction— Je vois aussi qu’on ne m’avait pas trompé en m’annoncant les dispositions de l’Académie à votre égard— Je crois fermement que vos idées font un chemin immense et qu’elles triompheront bientôt dans la science à mesure que les traditions de l’Ecole de Cuvier achèveront de séffacer.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Je crois aussi que les decouvertes et les observations iront en se multipliant d’année en années soit par l’étude de la nature vivante, soit par celle de la paléontologie— Mais dans le second de ces domaines, il faut ne pas vouloir de hâter et cheminer pas à pas.</p>
<p>Je continue dans ce moment l’examen des plus anciennes productions végétales à partir du silurien inférieur et j’acquiers la conviction que la vie organique était des lors <hi rend="underline">ancienne</hi> et <hi rend="underline">relativement complexe</hi>. Il devient visible de plus en plus que la végétation carbonifère et même précabonifère était divisée en deux portions presque égales de cryptogames vasculaires et de phanérogames gymnospermes— Ces Gymnospermes étaient même généralement plus élevées en structure que les survivantes de leur classe: les conifères et les Cycadées, et d’une façon générale lorsque un groupe ou une classe à décliné, les êtres de cette classe qui ont echappé, après qu’elle a eu perdu la préponderance, se rattachent à des rameaux inférieurs qui ont trouvé moyen de survivre en se soustrayant à la concurrence vitale.</p>
                    <p>La Souche gymnospermique d’où les Dicotylédones sont sorties, par suite d’une serie de combinaisons, a bien pu originairement se trouver inférieure aux autres types de gymnospermes— mais ceux-ci à raison même de leur perfection hâtiv ont dû succumber dans le combat pour la vie, lorsque les circonstances qui avaient favorisé leur estoc n’ont plus été les mêmes. J’ai développé ce point de vue dans un ouvrage sur le <hi rend="underline">monde des plantes avant l’homme</hi>, actuellement sous presse et qui résume tout ce que j’ai écrit précédemment sur la marche de l’ancienne végétation conçue au point de vue de l’évolution. J’aurai l’honneur de vous offrir cet ouvrage dans peu de mois.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Je vous prie d’agréer, Monsieur et honoré confrère, l’expression de mes sentiments | affectionants et devoués | C<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> G. de Saporta</p>
<p>Je vais être à Paris pour un mois d’aout et septembre | Hôtel et quai Voltaire</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Fonscolombe | par le Puy— S<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> Réparade | (B. du Rhône)</placeName>
                    <date> 9 August 78</date>
                    <salute>Sir and honoured colleague,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
                    <p>I see today from the newspapers that you were elected last Monday as correspondent of the botanical section of the Academy of Sciences—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am more than happy about this occurrence and all too flattered to see my name written near yours not to show you my great satisfaction— I see too that I was not wrong in bringing the actions of the Academy to your attention— I believe firmly that your ideas are carving out a great path and that they will soon triumph in science as the traditions of the school of Cuvier disappear completely.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I believe too that discoveries and observations will go on multiplying from year to year whether through the study of living nature, or through that of palaeontology— But in the second of these areas, one must not want to rush, but to advance step by step.</p>
                    <p>I am continuing at the moment to examine the most ancient vegetable productions from the lower Silurian onward and I have become convinced that organic life was from then on <hi rend="underline">old</hi> and <hi rend="underline">relatively complex</hi>. It is ever more clear that carboniferous and even precarboniferous vegetation was divided into two almost equal groups of vascular cryptogams and of gymnospermous phanerogams— These gymnosperms were also generally higher in structure than the surviving members of their class: the conifers and the cycads, and in a general sense when one group or class has declined, the beings of this class who escaped, after it had lost predominance, were linked to the lower branches who found a way to live on by avoiding the struggle for survival.</p>
                    <p>The gymnospermous lineage from which dicotyledons originated, as a result of a series of stratagems, may well have been originally found lower than other types of gymnosperms—but these, by the very reason of their premature perfection had to succumb in the struggle for life, when the circumstances that favoured their stock were not the same. I developed this viewpoint in a work on the <hi rend="underline">world of plants before man</hi>, currently in press and which summarises all that I have previously written on the progress of ancient vegetation understood from the point of view of evolution. I will have the honour to offer you this work in a few months.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>I beg you to accept, Sir and honoured colleague, my affectionate and faithful regards | C<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> G. de Saporta</p>
                    <p>I will be in Paris for a month in August and September | Hotel and quay Voltaire</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD was elected a corresponding member of the botanical section of the Académie des sciences on 5 August 1878 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11640A.xml">letter from J.-B. Dumas and Joseph Bertrand, 5 August 1878</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In December 1877, Saporta had alerted CD to the fact that CD’s name was going to be proposed for membership in the botanical section of the Académie des sciences, and that CD’s election was very likely (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml">letter from Gaston de Saporta, 16 December 1877</ref>). Saporta had been a corresponding member of the botanical section of the academy since 1876 (<hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus hebdomadaires des séances de l’Académie des sciences</hi> 83 (1876): 43). For more on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georges Cuvier’s</ref> influence on French science in the nineteenth century, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Appel 1987</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Saporta’s book, <hi rend="italic">Le monde des plantes avant l’apparition de l’homme</hi> (The world of plants before the appearance of man; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10489.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Saporta 1879</ref>), was published in December 1878 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11803.xml">letter to Gaston de Saporta, 22 December 1878</ref>). CD’s copy, inscribed, ‘A Monsieur <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Darwin</ref> | Comme un hommage respectueux’, is in the Darwin Library–CUL. </note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>