<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-555">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Robert FitzRoy   [20 February 1840]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1850</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-555 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-555.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-555.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 144: 117</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 117</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Upper Gower St, 12</placeName>
                <date when="1840-02-20">[20 Feb 1840]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml">FitzRoy, Robert</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Poor health has made him give up all geological work.</p> 
<p>Profits on their volumes [of <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi>] seem absurdly small.</p>  
<p>Looks back on <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage as the most fortunate circumstance in his life.</p> 
            <p>Finds marriage a great happiness.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Narrative</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1211">Darwins</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="ships" ref="#">Beagle</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">marriage</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>12 Upper Gower S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.</placeName>
                    <date>Thursday 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear FitzRoy.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I was very glad to receive your long letter— I had been for sometime wishing to hear of you, but did not like to write as I had nothing to communicate, excepting about myself, and that is and has been for some time a very dull subject. My health has been very indifferent during the two last months, and lately it has been rather worse but now I trust I am getting better.— My stomach as usual has been my enemy—but D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Holland tells me he thinks it is only secondarily affected—and that some other wheel works badly—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have been obliged to give up all Geological work which is no slight mortification, but I hope soon to set to work again. If I had had my health, I should have published my coral volume before this time.— I was much interested by your account of the sale of our volumes. I had not before any notion how many had been disposed of but I will now go some day and find out how many remain.— I should think there could not be many. What you mention about the probable profits according to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shoberls estimate appears to me quite absurdly small.—but I dare say it is all we shall ever get from the great man of Marlborough S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. <ref target="#foot.f3"/> For my own part I have ceased caring very much about the sale of my volume, the more I see of authorship the more desirable I find it to endeavour to become quite indifferent to the opinion of any excepting one’s friends and a few others.</p>
<p>I am not surprised at our never having met in the Street for I do not go to the west end of the town more than once a week, and I believe I have only seen Hyde Park once during the two last months— I can readily understand how very inconvenient you must find it, living at so great a distance as 20 miles, from your weekly journey’s end— I should think you would find a house near Town much pleasanter; for my own part, I do not think I shall ever venture out even as far as a suburban cottage.— I saw sometime since, a very short abstract, in one of the scientific Journals of a paper by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Whewell read at the Cambridge. Philosoph. Soc: giving an account of a new theory of the tides, in which he mentions your views and says his are taken partly from them.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The abstract was so brief that I could not understand the new views. I mention this in case you should not accidentally have before heard it.— Sulivan &amp; Usborne<ref target="#foot.f5"/> called on me the other day.— Usborne mentioned your kind exertions in his favour at the Admiralty.— His does certainly appear a peculiarly hard case— As for Sulivan his notions about non promotion being a stigma is quite preposterous—and I hinted to him the other day—plainly that such unremitting self thought was not very graceful in anyone— I have had a note from him from Chalford, in which he tells me that Sir. C Adams<ref target="#foot.f6"/> assured him, that if there had been a marriage” promotion,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> he would have been included in it,—with this Sulivan appears contented— I hope cordially that he may receive it soon.—</p>
<p>However others may look back to the Beagles voyage, now that the small disagreeable parts are well nigh forgotten, I think it far the <hi rend="underline">most fortunate circumstance in my life</hi> that the chance afforded by your offer of taking a naturalist fell on me— I often have the most vivid and delightful pictures of what I saw on board the Beagle pass before my eyes.— These recollections &amp; what I learnt in Natural History I would not exchange for twice ten thousand a year.</p>
<p>I find as you always prophesied would be the case being married, a very great happiness. My wife is perfectly well and begs to be kindly remembered to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. FitzRoy—. My little animalcule of a son, William Erasmus by name is also very well. He is 8 weeks old tomorrow, and has learnt to smile about a week since—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have nothing to wish for, excepting stronger health to go on with the subjects, to which I have joyfully determined to devote my life— Pray remember me very kindly to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. FitzRoy—whom I am glad to hear is well and your children.</p>
<p>Believe me | My dear FitzRoy— | Yours very truly, | Cha<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Darwin.</p>
<p>I fear you will have more trouble in deciphering this scrawl than it is worth.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.6 even as] ‘as’ <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘so’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.13 favour] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘behalf’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated from the reference in the letter to William Darwin’s being ‘8 weeks old tomorrow’. William was born on Friday, 27 December 1839. The Thursday on which this letter was written was therefore 20 February 1840, not the 21st, as CD dated it.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Later, in December 1840, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1452.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maria Edgeworth</ref> wrote to her half-sister as follows: ‘You know that he says he was ill in consequence of the sea voyage—that he was never a single day free from sea-suffering. But Dr. Holland tells us that the voyage was not the cause, only the continuance of his suffering—for that before he went to sea he was subject to the same. His stomach rejects food continually; and the least agitation or excitation brings on the sickness directly so that he must be kept as quiet as it is possible and cannot see any body’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1527.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Colvin, ed. 1971</ref>, pp. 571–2). Although CD appears to have told Dr Holland that he had suffered from a stomach ailment before the voyage, there is no reference to such illness in any of his surviving letters of the 1820s. Ralph Colp (1977, pp. 5–6) has inferred such an ailment from two letters from family members to CD (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. A. Darwin, [24 February 1825]</ref>, and letter from Catherine and Susan Darwin, 4 December [1825]) but neither gives clear evidence of serious stomach trouble of the sort frequently mentioned by CD after 1839.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1004.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Colburn</ref>, publisher of the <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref> and <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">No record of a paper by Whewell that answers this description has been found in the minutes of the Cambridge Philosophical Society. The <hi rend="italic">Report of the 9th meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of</hi> <hi rend="italic">Science held at Birmingham in 1839,</hi> Transactions of the sections, pp. 11–12 carries an abstract of a response made by Whewell to FitzRoy’s doubts about the views expressed in Whewell 1833, but there is no mention of any debt to FitzRoy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4847.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Burns Usborne</ref> was Master’s Assistant in the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Sir <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_24.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Adam</ref>, one of the Lords of the Admiralty, 1835–41 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Queen Victoria married Prince Albert on 10 February 1840.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘A biographical sketch of an infant’</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 191–200), in which CD records that William smiled when 45 days old.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>