<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-762">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. G. Ehrenberg   11 July 1844<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1471</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-762 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-762.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-762.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 163: 11</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>163: 11</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1480.xml">Ehrenberg, C. G.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1844-07-11">11 July 1844</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for shipments of earth samples. Sends copy of article describing Infusoria in samples ["Einige vorläufige Resultate … über das Verhalten des kleinsten Lebens in den Oceanen", <hi rend="italic">Ber. k. Preuss. Akad. Wiss. Berlin</hi> (1844): 182–207]. Asks for more information and samples, especially from the soundings of Ross’s expedition.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Infusoria</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">oceans</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Ber. k. Preuss. Akad. Wiss. Berlin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Ehrenberg, C. G. 1844c</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                    <date>d. 11<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi> Juli | 1844.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrtester Herr</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Vor nun 3 Wochen schrieb ich Ihnen durch die Gelegenheit des jungen Herrn Gladstone aus London, welcher sich erbot einen Brief zu besorgen. Ich hoffe daß seitdem dieser Brief in Ihren Händen ist.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Vorher hatte sich Dr. Dieffenbach erboten Ihnen die glückliche Ankunft der sehr interessanten Sendung zu melden. Meinen besten Dank für Ihre so große Freundlichkeit habe ich Ihnen bereits gemeldet und ich wiederhole ihn gern. Sie haben mich mit so reichem Material für meine Untersuchungen versehen daß ich noch lange daran zu zehren habe. Gestern sandte ich Ihnen durch die Gelegenheit des Herrn Gibsone aus Perth den gedruckten Auszug meines Berichtes über einen Theil Ihrer Sendung aus den Monatsberichten der berl. Akademie d. Wiss. Mai.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ich hatte ein Exemplar für Sie und eins für Herrn Dr. Hooker an Herrn Francis unter der Adresse des Herrn Richard Taylor Fleet Street Red Lion Court London addressirt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Ich hoffe daß Sie dieselben erhalten.</p>
<p>Auf Ihr heut angekommenes Schreiben vom 4<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi> Juli, melde ich Ihnen, daß alles was Sie für einer mikroskopischen Analyse für würdig halten mir höchst erwünscht ist. Alle Arten von See-Sand und Schlick oder thonartige Absätze des Meeres und großer Flüße sind auch in kleinen Mengen zuweilen reich an Formen. Was Sie mir über den Staubregen melden ist höchst interessant im Verhältniß zu meiner Analyse. Ich bitte daher um möglichst vollständige Details. Auch besonders was von Erd Proben aus großen Meeres-Tiefen erreichbar ist würde mir sehr willkommen seyn, zumal wenn auf der Admiralität vielleicht von den Rossschen kolossalen Grund-Messungen die Proben vorhanden wären.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Herr Francis, Fleet Street Red Lion Court London bei Herrn R. Taylor, hat wohl die Güte was Sie ihm für mich übergeben an mich gelangen zu laßen, im Fall Sie es nicht direct schicken wollen was vielleicht am Besten ist. In Hamburg besorgt der Kaufmann Herr G. Morgenstern am alten Wandrahm die unter meiner Adresse an ihn gesendeten Dinge hierher sicher und wohlfeil für mich.</p>
<p>In ausgezeichneter Hochachtung und Dankbarkeit verharrend</p>
<p>Ihr | ganz ergebenster | Dr C G Ehrenberg.</p>
<p>Die Salz Ablagerungen in Patagonien sind nicht reich an Leben, obschon ich von andern Orten her sehr reiche concentrirte Soolwässer besitze.</p>
<p>Isolirte Inseln aller Erdgegenden interessiren mich rücksichtlich ihres kleinsten Lebens besonders auch. Von den Gallopagos und von Ascension habe ich durch Ihre Güte gute Ausbeute.</p>
<p>Der Sand aus Keeling Atoll enthält nicht bloß todte Theile, sondern zum Theil lebend eingesammelte trockene kleine Thiere worunter auch manche Kieselschalen von Polygastrischen Infusorien. Es ist nicht bloß ein verdautes Excrement sondern ein kleines Lebens Gewühl, worin viel Corallenfragmente von weichen Corallen, wie ich es auch im Rothen Meere fand.  [DIAGRAM HERE] Asteromphalus Darwinii</p>
<p>Aus Terra del Fuego besitze ich jezt viel Material aber es fehlt mir dergleichen aus Californien, aus den Capverd. Inseln, von Sierra Leone, Congo, Angola, Ferner aus dem Süd-australischen Archipel von Neu Guinea bis zu den Marquesas I. Aus Neuholland besitze ich viel, aus Neu Seeland noch nichts, da die übersandten Stein Proben kein deutliches Resultat geben. Aus Guinea und Senegal besitze ich viel. Aus den Lakediven und Malediven noch nichts. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> Prof. C. G. Ehrenberg. Secret. d. Akad. d. Wissensch. | Berlin.</p>
<p>Unter den Linden 21.</p>
<p>pr. adr. d. Herrn Gustav Morgenstern | Meissner Porzellan Niederlage | am alten Wandrahm | Hamburg.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                    <date>11 July 1844</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It has been three weeks since I wrote to you through the opportunity presented by the young Mr Gladstone of London, who offered to carry a letter. I hope that this letter is now in your hands.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Previously Dr. Dieffenbach had offered to inform you of the fortunate arrival of the very interesting shipment. I have already sent my deepest thanks for your very great favour and I repeat it gladly. You have provided me with such rich material for my investigations that I will feast on them for a long time yet. Yesterday through the good offices of Mr Gibsone of Perth I sent you the printed offprint of my report (in the May issue of the <hi rend="underline">Monatsberichten</hi> of the Berlin Academy of Science<ref target="#foot.f3"/> ) on a part of your shipment. I had addressed a copy for you and one for Dr Hooker to Mr Francis at the address of Mr Richard Taylor Fleet Street Red Lion Court London.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I hope that you receive it.</p>
<p>In answer to your letter of July 4 which came today, let me say that I would very much like to have everything you consider worthy of a microscopic analysis. All kinds of sea-sand and mud or clay-like deposits of the sea and large rivers, even sometimes in small quantities, are rich in forms. What you told me about the rain of dust is extremely interesting with respect to my analysis. I therefore request details that are as complete as possible. Also especially any sediment samples that can be obtained from the great depths of the sea would be very welcome to me, particularly if perhaps the samples from Ross’s extensive deep sea-bed soundings are still available from the Admiralty.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Mr Francis, Fleet Street Red Lion Court London at Mr R. Taylor’s, has the kindness to forward what you give him for me. That is in case you do not want to send it directly which is perhaps best. In Hamburg the merchant Herr G. Morgenstern am alten Wandrahm takes care to send me safely and inexpen%sively everything that finds its way to him under my address.</p>
<p>Ever with greatest respect and thankfulness. Your | most devoted | Dr C G Ehrenberg.</p>
<p>The salt deposits in Patagonia are not rich in life, although I have highly concentrated brine from other places.</p>
<p>Isolated islands from every corner of the earth interest me especially with regard to their smallest forms of life. Through your kindness I have good yields from the Galapagos and Ascension.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAGRAM HERE] Asteromphalus Darwinii.</p> </figure> 
<p>The sand from Keeling Atoll contains not only dead parts, but also in part small dried animals collected alive, among them many siliceous shells of Polygastric Infusoria. It is not merely a digested excrement but a small bustle of life with many coral fragments from soft coral in it, such as I also found in the Red Sea.</p>
<p>I now possess much material from Terra del Fuego but I lack any from California, the Cape Verde Islands, Sierra Leone, Congo, Angola, or from the South Australian archipelago from New Guinea to the Marquesas I. I possess many from New Holland; nothing yet from New Zealand, since the rock samples sent give no clear result. I possess many from Guinea and Senegal. Still nothing from the Laccadives and Maldives. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Prof. C. G. Ehrenberg. Secret. d. Akad. d. Wissensch. | Berlin. | Unter den Linden 21.</p>
<p rend="left">pr. adr. d. Herrn Gustav Morgenstern | Meissner Porzellan Niederlage | am alten Wandrahm | Hamburg.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For the transcription of this letter in the original German, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, pp. 45–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Ehrenberg’s first letter to CD had not arrived. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-758.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C. G. Ehrenberg, 15 June 1844</ref>, n. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Ehrenberg 1844a. CD’s copy of the paper is in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1736.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Francis</ref> served as an assistant in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4674.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Taylor’s</ref> printing firm, located in Red Lion Court, Fleet Street. The paper was being sent to Taylor for publication in English (Ehrenberg 1844b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had offered specimens collected by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> during <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Clark Ross’s</ref> Antarctic expedition, see letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-733.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[27 January 1844]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-736.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">23 February [1844]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-747.xml" resp="#automat">letter to C. G. Ehrenberg, 20 April [1844]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>