<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11568F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. A. Greaves to G. H. Darwin   26 June 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21799</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11568F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11568F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11568F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">14pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 210.14: 13</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>210.14: 13</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1963.xml">Greaves, E. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Cheltenham</placeName>
                <date when="1878-06-26">26 June 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">Darwin, G. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>14 Pittville Parade,</placeName>
                    <date>June 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1878</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am much pleased that you all like D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin’s portrait, I had no fear about its being a valuable painting &amp; I have heard that it was a good likeness taken by Wright of Derby when the learned Doctor was in advancing years—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> With respect to its pedigree: that unfolds a piece of family history at which I often wonder in amazement as to its results, and which I thought every member of the Darwin family knew— Portraits many are to be found in Derbyshire households of the higher class I believe for when the Doctor was in the hey day of prosperity, every one wished for his portrait &amp; Wright must have realized a handsome fortune by them—but to return from this digression In the year 1772 May 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. a daughter was born to the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. named Susanna.  In the year 1774 May 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. was born another daughter named Mary—the offspring of a young and beautiful woman of the name of Parker, she had some position in the family of Col. Pole of Radbourne Hall, the Doctor being frequently there as the Physician of the family— Of their early life I know little, they were educated &amp; D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D: bought a very nice large house at Ashborne for them near Sir Brooke Boothsbys estate.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> They opened a school for young ladies &amp; what with their superior talents &amp; accomplishments educated the children of the higher families both in Derbyshire &amp; elsewhere; partly owing to the learned D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> patronage &amp; their own energies— They continued their school ’till Susanna married my Uncle Hadley a surgeon in the first practice, and a great friend of y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. ancestor; in the Zoonomia you will find his name mentioned, this was in the year 1809—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Mary P. continued to reside at A. with two other sisters the Misses Day the daughters of the above mentioned person who after a while married a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Day, &amp; were half sisters—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Two Pictures were given by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. D. to his daughters painted for them I expect, the one now in y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. possession was given to S: P. &amp; at her marriage she brought it to Derby where during my Uncle’s life-time it hung over the Dining-room mantel-piece. After Aunt’s death her daughters had it, then it came to her brother D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Henry Hadley &amp; he gave it to me—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I highly prized it, and am heartily glad, it s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be still valued—</p>
                    <p>The other Picture which belonged to Mary P. she gave to a niece the daughter of a brother of those two Days she did not turn out well, she however was fortunate in selling her Picture, it is in the National Portrait Gallery I saw it when in London, it is a lovely picture, painted when younger in a puce coloured coat— It is revarnished &amp; re-gilt—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> These daughters were looked upon with much favour, they were no common women, and were frequently at the Priory, indeed old M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. D.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> used to conclude her letters to them as “yr affect<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> mother”. They used to visit the Galtons’, at the Larches<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; indeed all their pupils looked upon them with affection— To myself Aunt Hadley was as a Mother to me, committed to her care by my Grandmother Hadley<ref target="#foot.f9"/> on her death-bed— What I owe to her can no tongue can tell, and her sister was equally my friend— I believe I am the sole depository of this family history D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. H. not mentioning it, neither Aunt, I learned it all from Miss Wharton, Miss P’s companion,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> whom she had educated—</p> 
                    <p>Amongst my belongings I have a book written by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. D. on Education<ref target="#foot.f11"/> for these daughters, for it was education in those days—&amp; other papers—some curious and not altogether papers elegant addressed “to Eliza’ Hadley<ref target="#foot.f12"/> by Edward Darwin of Mackworth near Derby, he was a great invalid dropsical, most kind and generous   Aunt used to drive over every week to see him, &amp; I being at school at Mackworth was called for &amp; what a day of delight we had Eliza, Henry &amp; myself—! I have often thought what w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. become of these things, seeing the present generation know nothing of their G<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Mother’s ancestry— &amp; of her connexions. When I am tired of them or rather have done with them, w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. you care to receive them? I am a great person for family relics, &amp; genealogies—</p>
                    <p>Sir Francis D.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Greaves<ref target="#foot.f14"/> &amp; myself that D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. D. died rather suddenly, but that he had good hope in his end— M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Schimmel Pennick was too severe—<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>You must please to excuse this scrawl, for the weather is just now rather trying &amp; makes my hand tremulous | With kind reg<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi>. to y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Father &amp; yourself I am, dear Sir, | Your’s most truly | E: A. Greaves</p>
<p>There is a nice little account of Wright, “on a description of Derbyshire a small book which I will find</p>
                    <p>Wright the painter, better known as “Wright of Derby”, was born in 1734. He studied in London under Hudson,<ref target="#foot.f16"/> at the same time as did Sir Joshua Reynolds. Owing to the ill feeling which not infrequently exists among men of talent, as well as lesser minds, Wright did not receive the title of R.A. when he was proposed, &amp; so deeply did he feel the slight that, on a subsequent occasion, when Newton,<ref target="#foot.f17"/> secretary to the Royal Academy, visited him at Derby with the offer of a diploma from the Society, he indignantly refused it. He died in 1797. From Black’s Tourist’s Guide.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Erasmus Darwin born at Elston, near Newark, Nottingham<hi rend="superscript">sh</hi>. Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1731</p>
<p>Died April 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1802</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In January 1878, CD had bought a portrait of his grandfather <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5257.xml">Joseph Wright of Derby</ref> from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1963.xml">Greaves</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11309F.xml">letter from E. A. Greaves, 3 January 1878</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2045.xml">Susanna Hadley</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3681.xml">Mary Parker Jr</ref> were the daughters of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3682.xml">Mary Parker Sr</ref>, who had worked on the estate of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3811.xml">Edward Sacheverel Pole</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8459.xml">Boothby</ref> lived at Ashbourne Hall, Derbyshire.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The school was established by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Susanna Parker</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Parker Jr</ref> in 1794, and Mary took sole charge after Susanna married <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2043.xml">Henry Hadley</ref> in 1809. Henry Hadley’s experiments on the communication of smallpox via the blood are detailed in Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 1: 405–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Parker Sr</ref> married <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8453.xml">Joseph Day</ref> in 1782; the daughters were probably <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7995.xml">Hannah Maria Day</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7996.xml">Ann Day</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Greaves was brought up by her uncle Henry Hadley and his wife, Susanna; after Susanna’s death the painting passed to their daughter, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8126.xml">Elizabeth Susanna Hadley</ref>, and son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8127.xml">Henry Hadley</ref> (1812–74).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Parker Jr’s</ref> picture was given to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7997.xml">Anna Maria Jerome</ref>, daughter of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7998.xml">Edwin Court Wilcox Day</ref>. Jerome sold the portrait in 1859 (National Portrait Gallery: NPG 88; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10567.xml">Ingamells 2004</ref>, p. 135).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1216.xml">Elizabeth Darwin</ref> (Erasmus Darwin’s second wife).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1802.xml">Samuel Tertius Galton</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1796.xml">Violetta Galton</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7999.xml">Ursula Hadley</ref> (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2045.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Susanna Hadley’s</ref> mother-in-law).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8000.xml">Barbara Ellen Wharton</ref> (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3681.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Parker Jr’s</ref> companion).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">A plan for the conduct of female education in boarding schools</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1792.xml">E. Darwin 1797</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8126.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Elizabeth Susanna Hadley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1221.xml">Francis Sacheverel Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8125.xml">Richard Greaves</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">In her autobiography, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4209.xml">Mary Anne Schimmelpenninck</ref> had insinuated in a series of memories from her childhood that Erasmus Darwin was a glutton and a non-believer, who scoffed at conscience and morality (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10569.xml">Hankin ed. 1858</ref>, 1: 152–4, 178–80, and 237–48).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8451.xml">Thomas Hudson</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8452.xml">Francis Milner Newton</ref> was the first secretary to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Academy</ref> of Arts.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">The quotation, with minor differences in punctuation, is from <hi rend="italic">Black’s tourist’s guide to Derbyshire</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10568.xml">Jewitt ed. 1868</ref>, pp. 163–4).</note>
        </div>      
          
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>