<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3334">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alfred Russel Wallace   30 November 1861</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8811</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3334 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3334.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3334.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="inc"/>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 356</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 6</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="high">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Sumatra</placeName>
                <date when="1861-11-30">30 Nov 1861</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Life on earth</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Amazon</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Phillips, John 1860</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Sumatra, 100 miles E. of Bencoolen</placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 30th. 1861</date>
                    <salute>My dear Mr. Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On an evening in the wet season in these Central forests of Sumatra, I occupy myself in writing a few lines to you to say a few things which I may otherwise forget altogether. About a year &amp; a half back I wrote to you from somewhere Eastward of Ceram, with more digested remarks on your book, but the letter with one to my agent Mr. Stevens never I believe reached Amboyna.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> All I can remember of them now is to the effect that <hi rend="underline">repeated</hi> perusals had made the whole clearer &amp; more connected to me &amp; the general &amp; particular arguments clearer &amp; more forcible than at first.</p>
<p>I have lent the book to two persons here in the East, neither of them with any but the vaguest &amp; most general knowledge of or taste for Natural History but both men of much reading &amp; with a taste for speculation &amp; theory wh. as Bentham says is but another term for thought.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The first Mr. Duivenbode of Ternate, a Dutchman educated in England, read it three times through before he returned it to me, expressing himself so much pleased &amp; interested that he wished to master the whole argument.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The other a merchant captain settled at Timor Delli with whom I lived 3 months kept it all the time, was constantly reading it &amp; we made it a subject of conversation almost whenever we met, &amp; when I was leaving he did not return it till the steamer arrived going over the recapitulations of the chapters &amp; the conclusion to get the most of it he possibly could—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> These humble testimonies prove I think both the attractive manner in which you have treated the subject &amp; the clearness with which you have stated &amp; enforced the arguments; &amp; I trust they will be as pleasing to you as I assure you they were to me.</p>
<p>I met the other day on board the Dutch steamer the Geologist accompanying a Prussian voyage of discovery &amp;c. “<hi rend="underline">Baron</hi> <hi rend="underline">Richthofen</hi>”. He has been t〈hro〉ugh Java where he has made large collections of fossils— He 〈is〉 going now to leave the ship &amp; travel in British India &amp; afterwards go to the Amoor &amp; overland to Europe to study &amp; improve himself in Geology.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> He seems a very intelligent &amp; good naturalist. He was reading your Book wh. he had borrowed in Java, &amp; on my asking him if he was a convert,—he smiled &amp; said “It is very easy for a Geologist.”<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have also seen <hi rend="underline">Dr. Schneider</hi> who has geologized in Timor— He assures me he found many teeth of <hi rend="underline">Mastodon</hi>,—also <hi rend="underline">terebratulæ orthoceras</hi> &amp; other molluscs. He had given most of his collection to the Zoologist of the same Prussian Expedition but says he has published descriptions of all the Timor fossils in the Batavian Journal of Nat. Sciences, I forget the Dutch title but you know the work no doubt—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> They are to be published this month I think he told me. 〈<hi rend="underline">part of page excised</hi>〉</p>
<p>I trust your great work goes on &amp; is soon to appear.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I hope however you will have it copiously illustrated. I am sure it will be for the publishers interest to do so as it will I have no doubt double the circulation. There are so many things that are weak when merely mentioned or described by numbers which become clear &amp; strong when an appeal is made to the eye. The <hi rend="underline">varieties of pigeons</hi> the <hi rend="underline">stripes</hi> <hi rend="underline">of horses</hi>, the variations in <hi rend="underline">ants</hi>, the formation of <hi rend="underline">honeycombs</hi> &amp; a hundred other things will all be better for good illustrations— They will also make the book newer &amp; more distinct from its forerunner in the eyes of the public to whom it will otherwise appear as perhaps a mere enlargement— If this point is not decided, pray take it seriously into consideration.</p>
<p>I see nothing but the Athenæum so know little of what is going on among Naturalists— Huxley &amp; Owen seem to be at open war, but I cannot glean that any one has ventured to attack you fairly on the <hi rend="underline">whole question</hi>, or ventured to answer the whole of your argument—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I see by his advertisement D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Brees professes to do so but have no notice of his book.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I have lately been very unsuccessful owing to unprecedented wet weather (the effect I suppose of the comet).<ref target="#foot.f11"/> This is my 〈<hi rend="underline">part of page excised</hi>〉</p>
<p>P.S. The shabby way in which your opponents 〈<hi rend="underline">several words missing</hi>〉 is amusing. First comes Owen with his new interpretation of what naturalists mean by “<hi rend="underline">creation</hi>” which it turns out is not <hi rend="underline">creation</hi> at all, but “<hi rend="underline">the unknown manner in which species have come into</hi> <hi rend="underline">existence</hi>”!!!<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Phillips I see adopts this new interpretation which ought certainly to raise up the bench of bishops against them,<ref target="#foot.f13"/> for what then becomes of “<hi rend="underline">special creation</hi>” &amp; “<hi rend="underline">special</hi> <hi rend="underline">adaptation</hi>” &amp; “intelligent forethought visible in each special creation”,—if <hi rend="underline">creation</hi> is not creation at all, but a mere convenient expression of ignorance of the laws by which species have originated.</p>
<p>Has my friend Bates sent you his papers on Amazon Insects, in wh. he gives details of “variation” which are a most valuable contribution to our cause—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> His papers also shew what mere blind work is the making of species from what may be called <hi rend="underline">chance</hi> <hi rend="underline">collections</hi>;—a species here, another there, a ♂ from one locality a ♀ from another, here a rare variety, &amp; from another place the typical form. Of course with such materials &amp; with localities often incorrectly indicated each succeeding <hi rend="underline">elucidator</hi> has but added to the confusion; &amp; the whole has formed a <hi rend="underline">chaos</hi>, till some one collecting &amp; observing for years over an extensive but connected district has been able to bring the whole into order. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Anor | Sumatra</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.2 knowledge … made it 2.8] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>3.7 “It … told me. 3.13] ‘A. Wallace | Nov. 20/1861’ <hi rend="italic">added in margin, ink</hi>; ‘18’<ref target="#foot.f15"/> <hi rend="italic">brown crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter to CD to which Wallace refers may be that dated [December? 1860] (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8), of which only a part is extant. Wallace gave CD his initial comments on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in a letter, now missing, dated 16 February 1860 (see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2807.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 18 May 1860</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Stevens</ref> acted as Wallace’s London agent, handling the natural history specimens he collected (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8126.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1905</ref>, 1: 266).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_399.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jeremy Bentham</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Wallace also mentioned Mr Duivenboden in the published account of his travels in the Malay Archipelago (Wallace 1869, 2: 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his autobiography, Wallace identified the ‘merchant captain’ as Captain Hart, owner of a coffee plantation situated ‘about a mile out of town’ of Dili on the island of Timor (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8126.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1905</ref>, 1: 375). For a map indicating the course of Wallace’s travels in the Malay Archipelago, see Wallace 1869.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4002.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferdinand Paul Wilhelm von Richthofen</ref> accompanied the Prussian East Asia expedition, under the leadership of Friedrich Albrecht, Graf zu Eulenburg, to Japan, China, and Thailand, 1859–62. He continued travelling in the Far East before visiting the western part of the United States (Sarjeant 1980).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2807.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Wallace, 18 May 1860</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8), CD remarked that ‘there are almost more Geological converts [to his theory] than pursuers of other branches of natural science.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schneider 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD had told Wallace in his letter of 18 May 1860 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8} that he was working on his ‘larger work’, which he planned to publish in separate volumes. Part of this material was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> in 1868.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> were engaged in a public debate concerning the anatomical differences between human and simian brains (see R. Owen 1861a and Huxley 1861a and 1861b). Several highly charged letters from the two were published in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> in March and April 1861. For references to the debate in CD’s correspondence, see the letters to T. H. Huxley, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3107.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">1 April [1861]</ref>, and to J. D. Hooker, 23 [April 1861].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_874.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bree 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The comet, described as one ‘of extraordinary splendour’, was first sighted at the end of June 1861 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Annual register</hi></ref> (1861), Chronicle, pp. 99–100).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Wallace refers to Owen’s reference to the ‘axiom of <hi rend="italic">the continuous operation of the ordained becoming of living things’</hi> in his unsigned review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> ([R. Owen] 1860b, p. 500). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3041.xml" resp="#automat">letter to T. H. Huxley, 3 January [1861]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">John Phillips addressed the question of the origin of species, criticising the account provided by CD in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6276.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Phillips 1860</ref>. For CD’s reaction to this book, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3176.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 5 June [1861]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Wallace and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Walter Bates</ref> had naturalised together in the Amazon region of South America (Marchant ed. 1916, 1: 25–30). Bates had sent CD a copy of his first paper on the insect fauna of the Amazon valley (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_444.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1861a</ref>) (see letters from H. W. Bates, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3092.xml" resp="#automat">18 March 1861</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3104.xml" resp="#automat">28 March 1861</ref>), and CD had heard Bates’s second paper on this topic (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_444.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1861b</ref>), read before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 21 November 1861 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3338.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. W. Bates, 3 December [1861]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">The annotation refers to CD’s portfolio of notes on the means of dispersal of animals and plants.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>