<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13129">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. R. Jesse   19 April 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14383</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13129 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13129.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13129.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp, encl (printed) 4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Soc. Abolition Vivisection (1881): 4</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 168: 60; DAR 168: 62/1 and 62/2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>168: 60, 168: 62/1, 168: 62/2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2566.xml">Jesse, G. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Macclesfield</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-19">19 Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses vivisection and contradicts CD’s defence of English physiologists.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-03" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-03" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-07" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00071_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00071_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="60:1r" xml:id="i71">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00071.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00071_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00071.dzi" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="60:1v" xml:id="i72">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00072.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00072_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00072.dzi" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="60:2r" xml:id="i73">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00073.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00073_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00073.dzi" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="60:2v" xml:id="i74">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00074.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00074_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00074.dzi" width="5569px" height="9449px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="60 foldout" xml:id="i75">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00075.jpg" width="9449px" height="8526px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00075_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="9449px" height="8526px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00168-000-00075.dzi" width="9449px" height="8526px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Henbury, Macclesfield, Cheshire.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>19 April 1881.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Since I had the pleasure of corresponding with you relative to some statements in your Work on the “Variation of Animals and Plants under Domestication” I have given much of my time to the questions of the Moral Right and True Philosophy of subjecting live Animals to painful Experiments for Scientific Purposes,—and I was sorry to find we were at variance in our Evidence before the Royal Commission as to our views upon a subject of such importance.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I see by “The Times” of yesterday that you assert “the accusations (of inhumanity) made against our English Physiologists were false”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Surely you must have made that statement without having perused the admissions made by Physiologists themselves before the Royal Commission in 1875. Pray permit me to refer you to some of those admissions and which are enclosed in this letter. And, kindly allow me to enquire of you,—why, if “the accusations of inhumanity were false”,—Her Majesty appointed a Royal Commission to enquire into the Practices of Physiologists?— Why an Act of Parliament was passed, (39 &amp; 40 Vict. Chap. 77.) “to amend the Law relating to Cruelty to Animals”?— and why Inspectors were appointed to watch the conduct of Licensed Physiologists and Report thereon?<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Relative to your statement as to “improvements in Medical Practice which may be directly attributed to Physiological Research”, and “the benefits already great” derived therefrom, I shall be happy to discuss with you the discoveries credited to Vivisection before the Royal Commissioners, before whom, as you may perhaps be aware, I gave Evidence on several days.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>As to Monsieur Pasteur,—surely we have plenty of Experimenters on Animals at home without crossing the Channel to seek for them and their discoveries.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Even as to Pasteur,—he has been loudly lauded lately as the discoverer,—not of a New Remedy,—but, of “A New Disease”! At the Académie de Médicine however during a Meeting in Paris in Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1880, one of the Members, Monsieur Bouillaud, said to Pasteur,—“You can see many interesting things through your Microscope, but that is no earthly use to us”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>If you would like to peruse the Correspondence on this question I have had with Professor Owen, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. T. Spencer Wells, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. T. Lauder Brunton, Professor Ferrier, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Grimshaw, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. Donnell, and other men of eminence, I shall be happy to forward the Letters to you.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Believe me | yours very sincerely. | George R. Jesse. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin, Esqe. | &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">To the</hi></p>
              <p rend="centre">People of Great Britain and Ireland.</p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">Society for the Total Abolition and</hi></p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">Utter Suppression of Vivisection.</hi></p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">from</hi></p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">“The Echo,” Wednesday, October</hi> 8, 1879.</p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">“The Morning Post,” Thursday, October</hi> 9, 1879.</p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">“The Globe,” Thursday, October</hi> 9, 1879.</p>
              <p rend="centre">“Publicity is the Soul of Justice.”—B<hi rend="smallCaps">entham</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
              <p rend="centre">“CANON DUCKWORTH</p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">on the</hi></p>
              <p rend="centre">MEDICAL PROFESSION” &amp; THE ABOLISHERS OF VIVISECTION.</p> 
<p>“—After D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. D<hi rend="smallCaps">upre’s</hi> address at Westminster Hospital, the prizes were distributed to the successful candidates by Canon D<hi rend="smallCaps">uckworth</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> who said— “… And here, gentlemen, may I make bold to say a word in defence of the humanity of the whole Profession, in answer to those <hi rend="italic">unjust aspersions</hi> which have lately been cast upon it? <hi rend="italic">To read some of the fanatical vapourings of people who are agitating for the total abolition of Vivisection</hi>, one might imagine that the sole object of most youths who embrace your profession is to find indulgence for the <hi rend="italic">most inhuman passions that can degrade our nature. I resent such an imputation on your behalf as a shameful libel</hi>; and I have never failed, when opportunity has been given to me, to state my firm belief that no stricter regulations than those which exist are needed to protect the lower animals from <hi rend="italic">wanton cruelty</hi> at your hands. It is to me inconceivable that, from among a public which is daily enjoying the benefit of your gentleness and sympathy, daily taking advantage of your ill-remunerated and self-denying labours, that there should be formed <hi rend="italic">a party so unjust to you, so ignorant of your proverbial character, and so blind to facts of every day experience.</hi>”*</p>
<p>*<hi rend="italic">Extracted from THE TIMES Newspaper of Saturday, the</hi> 4<hi rend="italic">th October</hi>, 1879.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
              <p>It is lamentable to see a Minister of Religion,—especially one holding so honourable a position as Canon D<hi rend="smallCaps">uckworth</hi>,—who, we understand, is a Fellow of Trinity College, Oxford;<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Chaplain to Her Majesty the Q<hi rend="smallCaps">ueen</hi>; and to H.R.H. the P<hi rend="smallCaps">rince</hi> of W<hi rend="smallCaps">ales</hi>,—using harsh and injurious language; exposing his own want of knowledge on a subject he expresses himself confidently and dictatorially upon; and casting unqualified censure on persons opposed to him in opinion who strive to abolish what they consider the unnecessary and unphilosophical practice of inflicting agony, disease, misery, and death, on reasoning and affectionate creatures, in the fallacious hope of greatly increasing knowledge, and preventing maladies which are Nature’s inevitable punishment for violation of her beneficent Laws.</p>
<p>C<hi rend="smallCaps">anon</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">uckworth</hi> cannot have perused the Evidence given by Physiologists before the Royal Commission, and the admissions they made in regard to themselves and in regard to others. At least, that is the most lenient and charitable view which can be taken of his conduct. He speaks of “<hi rend="italic">unjust aspersions</hi>” cast upon the whole Medical Profession—of “<hi rend="italic">fanatical vapourings of people who are agitating for the Total Abolition of Vivisection</hi>.” He uses the words “<hi rend="italic">shameful libel</hi>”—“<hi rend="italic">unjust</hi>”—“<hi rend="italic">ignorant</hi>”—“<hi rend="italic">blind to facts</hi>.”</p>
              <p>In answer to this attack made by the Rev. Canon D<hi rend="smallCaps">uckworth</hi>, we beg leave to refer him, and the reflective Public, to the “<hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on the Practice of subjecting Live Animals to Experiments for Scientific Purposes, &amp;c. Presented to both Houses of Parliament by command of Her Majesty</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">London: Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode.</hi> 1876. <hi rend="italic">Price</hi> 4/4.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> We cite him before the Tribunal of Conscience. We challenge the Rev. Canon to make his words good in the face of the following extracts from the above Book; for example:—</p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">evidence</hi></p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir William Fergusson, Bart., F.R.S., Sergeant-Surgeon to H.M. the Queen</hi><ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>“A<hi rend="smallCaps">nswer</hi>. The impression produced on my mind is that these experiments are done very frequently in a most reckless manner.</p>
<p>Q<hi rend="smallCaps">uestion</hi>. In a manner that, if it were known to the public at large, would call for interference on their part?</p>
<p>A<hi rend="smallCaps">nswer</hi>. Yes; and would bring the reputation of certain scientific men far below what it should be.”<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Emmanuel Klein, M.D., Assistant Professor of the Laboratory of the Brown Institution, &amp;c., London.</hi></p>
<p>“Q<hi rend="smallCaps">uestion</hi>. Then for your own purpose you disregard entirely the question of the suffering of the animal in performing a painful experiment?</p>
<p>A<hi rend="smallCaps">nswer</hi>. I do.”<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Rev. Samuel Haughton, M.D., F.R.S., Medical Registrar of the School of Physic of Trinity College, Dublin</hi>.</p>
<p>A<hi rend="smallCaps">nswer</hi> .... I would shrink with horror from accustoming large classes of young men to the sight of Animals under Vivisection. I believe that many of them would become cruel and hardened, and would go away and repeat these experiments recklessly, without foresight or forethought; science would gain nothing, and the world would have let loose upon it a set of young devils.”<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Henry Wentworth Acland, M.D., F.R.S., Regius Professor of Medicine in the University of Oxford, &amp;c.</hi></p>
<p>“A<hi rend="smallCaps">nswer</hi>.... : There has come to be a pursuit of knowledge in this direction, just as you pursue knowledge of metals with the ordinary apparatus of a chemical laboratory.</p>
<p>So many persons have got to deal with these wonderful and beautiful organisms just as they deal with physical bodies that have no feeling and no consciousness.”<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dr. John Sinclair, M.D., said he had</hi>—</p>
<p>“Performed Vivisection with and without anæsthetics; but more frequently with anæsthetics, <hi rend="italic">as finding it more convenient</hi>.”<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dr. John Anthony, M.D., asserted that Physiologists</hi>—</p>
<p>“Get the same sort of feeling as the woman is said to have who skins eels”—and that in a very short time their sense of humanity becomes blinded.<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dr. William Rutherford, M.D., Professor of Physiology, &amp;c., in Edinburgh University, proclaimed</hi>—</p>
<p>“It is wonderful! what one may do to a sheep dog without the animal making any commotion.”<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir George Burrows, Bart., M.D., President of the Royal College of Physicians, stated</hi>—</p>
<p>“He thought there had been great abuses in the performance of operations and experiments on living Animals.”<ref target="#foot.f21"/></p>
              <p>Perhaps the prejudice of the Rev. Canon D<hi rend="smallCaps">uckworth</hi> may estimate this undeniable testimony as to what he stigmatises as “<hi rend="italic">unjust aspersions</hi>,” “<hi rend="italic">fanatical vapourings</hi>,” and “<hi rend="italic">shameful libels</hi>.” It is, however, but the beginning of a tale—the unfolding of the first roll—the turning of the foremost page upon this sad subject. More, much more, might be quoted to the like effect. Enough, however, has been brought forward to justify us and refute our censurer.</p>
<p>We will conclude with words which we published in 1874 or 1875 on this question—“Let, therefore, the humane members of a most noble Profession, whose object is the alleviation of suffering, openly discountenance such acts,—acts which tend to the dishonour of their order; to create distrust of themselves in the public mind;—as, in the language of S<hi rend="smallCaps">amuel</hi> J<hi rend="smallCaps">ohnson</hi>, ‘they extinguish those sensations which give man confidence in man, and make the Physician more dreaded than disease itself.’ ”<ref target="#foot.f22"/></p> 
<p rend="centre">SOCIETY FOR THE TOTAL ABOLITION AND UTTER SUPPRESSION OF VIVISECTION.</p>
<p>Honorary Secretary and Treasurer,</p>
<p>GEORGE R. JESSE, <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">H<hi rend="smallCaps">enbury</hi>, <hi rend="smallCaps">near</hi> M<hi rend="smallCaps">acclesfield</hi>, C<hi rend="smallCaps">heshire</hi>.</p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">from</hi><lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <hi rend="italic">THE ECHO, Wednesday, October</hi> 8, 1879.</p> 
<p>It would be well in future if Canon Duckworth would discourse on matters that he best understands. At all events, let him stick to divinity, and leave medical and scientific men to take care of themselves. If, however, he will go beyond his depth, and talk on matters with which he is insufficiently acquainted, he may expect such scathing rebukes as that administered to him by the Society for the Suppression of Vivisection, which will be found in our advertisement columns to-day.</p> 
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">from</hi><lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <hi rend="italic">THE ECHO</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Thursday</hi>, <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 16, 1879.</p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="italic">CANON DUCKWORTH AND VIVISECTION</hi>.</p>
              <p rend="centre"><hi rend="smallCaps">to the editor of the echo</hi>.</p> 
<p>Sir,—I have the pleasure to enclose a letter from Dr. McCormick, R.N., the companion of Parry and Ross in their Arctic and Antarctic voyages.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> His views, as a surgeon and naturalist, on the question of vivisecting animals, will be read with interest by many persons.</p>
<p>I am, Sir, your obedient Servant, | G<hi rend="smallCaps">eorge</hi> R. J<hi rend="smallCaps">esse</hi>, | Hon<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. Sec<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>., &amp;c., Society Total Abolition of Vivisection. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Henbury, Macclesfield, Cheshire, Oct. 15.</p>
<p>“Ridgway Place, Wimbledon, October 12, 1879.</p>
<p>“My Dear Jesse,—The newspaper you kindly forwarded to me yesterday, therein directing my attention to the much to be regretted and lamentable use a clergyman like Canon Duckworth should have made of the high position he holds in our Established Church to attempt to bring the opponents of the cruel and useless, therefore wanton, system of Vivisection into unmerited obloquy when delivering the prizes at the Westminster Hospital, calls for some remarks.</p>
<p>“Before Canon Duckworth ventured to make use of the very strong language with which he assailed the members of an honourable and humane society, (who have most disinterestedly stood forth as the champions and defenders of the helpless and suffering portion of the animal creation against their persecutors and the unjustifiable exercise of man’s power over them for a purpose as inhuman as it is alien alike to the laws of their Great Creator and to those of man himself), he should have given us some proof of his own competency to deal with a subject so involved in difficulties as it is even to the experienced professional man; to whose province it properly belongs, rather than to the Theologian’s.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Although only one letter between CD and Jesse prior to 1881 has been found, in his book <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>, CD mentioned receiving information from Jesse on a number of topics  (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7739.xml">letter to G. R. Jesse, 4 May [1871]</ref>; <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi> 1: 30, 44, 45). For Jesse’s and CD’s testimony before the 1875 Royal Commission on the Practice of Subjecting Live Animals to Experiments for Scientific Purposes, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 219–24, 233–4.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The printed version of CD’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13115.xml">letter to Frithiof Holmgren, [14] April 1881</ref>, was published in <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 18 April 1881, p. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The Cruelty to Animals Act (An Act to amend the Law relating to Cruelty to Animals (39 &amp; 40 Vict. c. 77)) was enacted on 15 August 1876. The Act was somewhat vague on the appointment of inspectors, stating, ‘The Secretary of State shall cause all registered places to be from time to time visited by inspectors for the purpose of securing a compliance with the provisions of this Act’. It also allowed for ‘special inspectors’ to be appointed when deemed appropriate by the secretary of state.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For Jesse’s evidence, see n. 1, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had pointed out that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3707.xml">Louis Pasteur</ref>’s recent discoveries would, in the first instance, aid animals (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-13115.xml">letter to Frithiof Holmgren, [14] April 1881</ref>). Pasteur had discovered a vaccine for chicken cholera after experimentally infecting chickens with the disease; he published his results in December 1880 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11577.xml">Pasteur 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Although Pasteur’s work on the pathogen responsible for chicken cholera was reported on and discussed in two meetings in October 1880, no comment by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7078.xml">Jean-Baptiste Bouillaud</ref> was mentioned in the reports of either of these meetings (<hi rend="italic">Bulletin de l’Académie nationale de médecine</hi>, 5 October 1880, pp. 1008–17; 26 October 1880, pp. 1119–27).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml">Richard Owen</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9344.xml">Thomas Spencer Wells</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_693.xml">Thomas Lauder Brunton</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1620.xml">David Ferrier</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9345.xml">Thomas Wrigley Grimshaw</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3263.xml">Robert McDonnell</ref>.</note>  
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Jesse had inserted the text below (up to his signature as secretary of the organisation) as an advertisement in the newspapers mentioned and wrote brief letters to the editors of these papers, directing readers to read the advertisements (see, for example, the <hi rend="italic">Morning Post</hi>, 9 October 1879, pp. 1, 7). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_399.xml">Jeremy Bentham</ref> had written, ‘Publicity is the most effectual safeguard of testimony, and of the decisions depending on it; it is the soul of justice’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11579.xml">Dumont ed. 1825</ref>, p. 67).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1430.xml">August Dupré</ref> was lecturer in toxicology at Westminster Hospital medical school. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9346.xml">Robinson Duckworth</ref> was canon of Westminster; the graduation ceremony took place on 1 October 1879. Duckworth replied to Jesse in a <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Jesse of 13 October 1879</ref>, which was printed in the <hi rend="italic">British Medical Journal</hi>, 18 October 1879, p. 632.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For a fuller extract from Duckworth’s address, see <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 4 October 1879, p. 10.</note>  
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Duckworth had been a fellow of Trinity College, Oxford, from 1860 to 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_146.xml"><hi rend="italic">Alum. Oxon</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4883.xml">Queen Victoria</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 48–55; the section quoted is on p. 49.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2716.xml">Edward Emanuel Klein</ref>’s testimony had disgusted CD (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10235.xml">letter to T. H. Huxley, 1 November [1875]</ref>). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 182–9; the section quoted is on p. 183.</note>      
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2165.xml">Haughton</ref>’s testimony, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 98–106; the section quoted is on p. 102.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 41–8; the section quoted is on p. 43.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Jesse misidentified the witness; he was, in fact, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9347.xml">Alexander James Sinclair</ref>. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 289–91; the section quoted is on p. 290.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9348.xml">Anthony’s</ref> evidence, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 129–38; the section quoted is on p. 137. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4133.xml">Rutherford</ref>’s evidence, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 148–57; the section quoted is on p. 150.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7175.xml">Burrows</ref>’s evidence, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8615.xml"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi></ref>, pp. 5–12; the section quoted is on p. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">For the quotation from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2589.xml">Johnson</ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11580.xml">S. Johnson 1825</ref>, 4: 200. Jesse had quoted the same lines in his testimony to the Commission on vivisection (<hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commission on vivisection</hi>, p. 319).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3259.xml">Robert McCormick</ref> had been a surgeon with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3698.xml">William Edward Parry</ref>’s voyage to the north of Spitsbergen in the summer of 1827, and was surgeon and naturalist on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4082.xml">James Clark Ross</ref>’s Antarctic expedition, 1839–43 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>