<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12105">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   13 June 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5459</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12105 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12105.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12105.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B29–30</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B29–B30</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-06-13">13 June 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has completed his MS and sent it to Dallas.</p>
            <p>Has ignored Butler’s criticism of natural selection and corrected only his views of Buffon and Goethe.</p>
            <p>It would be best to drop EK’s text from book and quote only certain portions of it.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_714">Buffon, G. L. L.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_774">Butler, Samuel (b)</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1179">Dallas, W. S.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1904">Goethe, J. W. von</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-01" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-22" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-11" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-15" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-08-15" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00176_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00176_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <surface n="B:29r" xml:id="i176">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00176.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00176_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00176.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:29v" xml:id="i177">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00177.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00177_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00177.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:30r" xml:id="i178">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00178.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00178_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00178.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:30v" xml:id="i179">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00179.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00179_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00179.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 13.6.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Gerade, als gestern Ihre freundlichen Zeilen eintrafen, war ich so weit, den Schluss des Manuscriptes einpacken zu können, und habe ich denselben, Ihrem Wunsche gemäss, direct an Herrn Dallas gesendet.<ref target="#foot.f2"/>  Ich danke Ihnen herzlichst für die Mittheilung der Kritik der “Saturday Review”, die ich mit Vergnügen gelassen habe, und mir sehr angemessen erscheint; ich werde dieselbe an Herrn Dr. Hermann Müller weitergeben, um denselben von seinem Butler-Enthusiasmus zu curiren.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Er ist bereits wieder auf seinem Beobachtungsfelde in den Alpen. Was mich betrifft, so habe ich Butlers Angriffe gegen die Selections-Theorie vollkommen unberücksichtigt gelassen, weil sie mir <hi rend="underline">lächerlich</hi> erscheinen; nur hielt ich es für nöthig, mit einigen Zeilen seine Phantasien, dass Buffon ironisch geschrieben habe, und dass Göthe erst durch die Zoonomia auf verwandte Ideen geführt worden sei, abzuweisen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>In Betreff der Anordnung bin ich längst zu der Überzeugung gekommen, dass es das Beste sein wird, wenn meine Lebensbeschreibung von Dr Erasmus Darwin <hi rend="underline">ganz</hi> wegbleibt. Sollten darin einige kleine Partieen sein, die Ihnen mittheilenswerth erscheinen, so wäre ich Ihnen sehr dankbar, wenn Sie dieselben als Citat Ihrem Texte an geeigneter Stelle einverleiben wollten. Es scheint mir ferner das Richtige, die deutsche Ausgabe der englischen möglichst conform zu halten und höchstens am Ende einige erläuternde Noten hinzuzufügen, die Ihnen für englische Leser vielleicht überflüssig erscheinen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Andererseits könnten einzelne Abschnitte meiner Lebensbeschreibung, falls Sie dieselben nicht schon berücksichtigt haben, z.B. der Passus über die Enstehung des Botanic Garden einfach in den Abschnitt über die poetischen und wissenschaftlichen Arbeiten verpflanzt werden.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Dasselbe könnte mit der Kritik des Bot. Gard. geschehen. Eine andre Frage wäre es, ob es sich nicht vielleicht empfehlen möchte, meine Einleitung mit einigen kleinen textuellen Aenderungen, und ebenso das Capitel über die humanitären Verdienste für sich bestehen zu lassen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Die Beibehaltung der Einleitung würde mir darum nützlich erscheinen, weil darin die Nothwendigkeit einer zuverlässigeren Biographie, und warum eine solche für unsere Zeit von Interesse ist, auseinandergesetzt wird. Das Ganze könnte dann ganz passend, folgende, wie mir scheint, die Hauptschwierigkeiten lösende Anordnung erhalten:</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>I. 1, Ihre Präliminar-Notiz.</p>
<p>II. 1, Die Einleitung, als integrirender Theil des Essaÿ’s gedacht.</p>
<p>?2. Über Dr Darwins ärztliche/ und humanitäre Thätigkeit.</p>
<p>3. Geschichtlicher Abriss der Evol. Theorie vor Dr. Darwin’s Zeit.</p>
<p>4. Analÿse seiner poetischen und wissenschaftl. Werke.</p> </figure> 
                    <p>Ich wäre sehr froh, wenn Sie die kleinen Aenderungen, die diese Anordnung erheischen würde, an meinem Manuscript resp. Herrn Dallas’ Uebersetzung vornehmen wollten. Ich war leider anfangs in dem Wahne, dass Sie nur einige Zusätze und Verbesserungen zu dem Seward’schen Buche machen wollten, desto mehr freue ich mich, dass Sie statt dessen lieber ein ganzes Lebensbild gegeben haben, und ich werde nun meine Compilation unter keinen Umständen in die deutsche Ausgabe nehmen.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>Sehr dankbar wäre ich Ihnen, wenn Sie mir später von Ihrem Herrn Verleger, die Aushängebogen gleich nach der Fertigstellung im Reindruck senden lassen wollten. Auch möchte ich Sie bitten, mir zur Zeit freundlich mittheilen zu wollen, an welche Firma sich Herr Alberts wegen des Lichtdruck’s-Portraits wenden soll, damit er diese Angelegenheit, ohne Ihnen Umstände zu machen, dort erledigen kann.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Jedenfalls scheint mir, dass es in der Ordnung ist, wenn <hi rend="underline">er</hi> die Herstellungskosten trägt.</p>
<p>Ich wünschte sehr, Ihnen die Mühen abnehmen zu können, welche die Inscenirung des Ganzen Ihnen noch verursachen wird, aber andererseits scheint mir doch wieder das Beste, wenn Sie die nöthigen Umstellungen vielleicht unter Ihren Augen von einem Dritten machen liessen. Es ist mir eine sehr freudige Aussicht, Ihre ersten Bogen bald lesen zu können.</p>
<p>Inzwischen zeichne ich, hochverehrter Herr, | Mit dem herzlichsten Danke | Ihr treulich ergebenster | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>4.13 I. 1, … Werke. 4.17] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
            </div>
            
            
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>13.6.79.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Yesterday, just as your kind lines arrived, I was ready to wrap up the concluding part of the manuscript and I have sent it, as you wished, directly to Mr Dallas.<ref target="#foot.f2"/>  I thank you most cordially for sending the review in “Saturday Review”, which I read with great enjoyment and which strikes me as very apppropriate; I shall pass it on to Dr Hermann Müller, to cure him of his Butler enthusiasm.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> He is already back at his research station in the Alps. I myself have completely ignored Butler’s attacks on the theory of selection because they strike me as <hi rend="underline">ridiculous</hi>; but I considered it necessary to reject in a few lines his fantasies that Buffon had written with irony and that Göthe was led to similar ideas only through the Zoonomia.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Regarding the order I was long ago convinced that it would be best if my biographical account of Dr Erasmus Darwin were <hi rend="underline">wholly</hi> left out. Should it contain shorter passages that you deem relevant, I would be very grateful if you would incorporate them into your text at the appropriate place. It furthermore seemed right to me to keep the German edition as close as possible to the English edition and at the most to add at the end a number of explanatory notes that may seem superfluous to you for the English reader.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>On the other hand, individual passages of my biographical account, if you have not yet taken them into consideration, e.g. the passage on the origin of the Botanic Garden, could simply be transplanted into the section on the poetic and scientific works.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The same could be done with the criticism of the Bot. Gard. Another question would be whether it might perhaps be a good idea to leave my introduction, with a few small textual changes, and the chapter on humanitarian services as well, by themselves.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> There would be a point in keeping the introduction, it seems to me, for the reason that it explains the need for a more reliable biography and why such a biography is of interest for our times. The whole thing could then quite fittingly receive the following shape, which, it seems to me, would solve the main difficulties:</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>I. 1, Your preliminary notice.</p>
<p>II. 1, The introduction, as an integrating part of the essay.</p>
<p>?2. On Dr Darwin’s medical and humanitarian activities</p>
<p>3. Historical outline of evol. theory before Dr Darwin’s era.</p>
<p>4. Analysis of his poetic and scientific works</p> </figure> 
                    <p>I would be very glad if you were to carry out the required minor changes to this arrangement in my manuscript or Mr Dallas’s translation. At first I was unfortunately under the impression that all you wanted to do was make some additions to and corrections of the Seward book, I am all the more glad that you preferred to give a complete biographical sketch instead, and now I will not under any circumstances include my compilation in the German edition.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>I would be very grateful to you if later on you could arrange for the advance sheets to be sent from your publisher immediately after completion of the final printing. I should also like to ask you to kindly let me know when the time comes which company Mr Alberts should approach regarding the autotype portrait, so he can arrange this matter without bothering you.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> In any case, it seems to me appropriate that <hi rend="underline">he</hi> bear the production costs.</p>
<p>I do so wish I could relieve you of the burdens that the production of the whole thing will continue to cause you, but on the other hand it seems to me best if you perhaps were to let a third person make the necessary arrangements under your supervision. It is a very joyful prospect for me to be able to read your first sheets soon.</p>
<p>In the meantime I remain, most esteemed Sir, | With the most cordial thanks | Yours truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 274–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12096.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 9 June [1879]</ref> and n. 4. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> was translating Krause’s essay on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12096.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 9 June [1879]</ref> and n. 3. CD had sent a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10814.xml">[Pollock] 1879a</ref>, which was highly critical of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_774.xml">Samuel Butler</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Evolution old and new</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10523.xml">S. Butler 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12092.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 7 June 1879</ref> and n. 5. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_714.xml">Georges Louis Leclerc, comte de Buffon</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref> were contemporaries of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>, the author of <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>). Goethe had read German translations of <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Botanic garden</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>), and had written to a friend that he had been helped on his scientific paths by Darwin (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4365.xml">King-Hele 1986</ref>, pp. 170–1). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 136–7, Krause attributed similarities between Darwin’s and Goethe’s work to their both having studied Buffon and Linnaeus (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7100.xml">Carl von Linné</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the German translation of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, Krause reinstated a longer section on precursors of Erasmus Darwin and added over one hundred pages of notes (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 78–124, 180–286).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The section discussing how Erasmus Darwin came to write the <hi rend="italic">Botanic garden</hi> is in CD’s biographical sketch (<hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, pp. 89–92).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The published version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> contained a short introduction to the part by Krause, but this was not featured as a separate section (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 131–7); in the German version it became the first section of three in Krause’s portion of the book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 75–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Krause put most of his additional material on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref> into his lengthy note section in the German version (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 183ff.).</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_61.xml">Karl Alberts</ref> was Krause’s publisher.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>