<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13284A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   9 and 10 August 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20494</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13284A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13284A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13284A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 416–17; <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 15 September 1881, p.  459</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Möller, Alfred 1915-21 2: 416–17 (German translation); Nature 24 1881: 459</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Blumenau, Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1881-08-09">9 Aug 1881</date>
                <date when="1881-08-10">10 Aug 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for his letter of 21 June [<hi rend="doubleUnderline">13212</hi>].</p>  
<p>Is sending seeds of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis sepium</hi>, which came from a cross between a plant with long pistils and another with pistils intermediate in length. Perhaps some of the plants that come from them will have short pistils.</p> 
            <p>FM does not know who told Dr B [Wilhelm Breitenbach] that he had lost a whole library in the flood. In fact, he lost only a few books that he had left behind thinking they were safe where they were.</p> 
<p>Has taken the opportunity of a recent cold spell to test CD’s views on nyctitropism [night movements] in plants. Describes <hi rend="italic">Pandanus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oxalis sepium</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Has just received CD’s letter of 4 July and he is glad that his observations on the effects of rain on plants interested CD.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">13212</term>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="date" ref="#">1881.07.04</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oxalis sepium</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Pandanus</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_607">Breitenbach, Wilhelm</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-21" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-03" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-30" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Blumenau, Sa. Catharina, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>9. August 1881.</date>
                    <salute>Verehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Vor einigen Tagen empfing ich Ihren freundlichen Brief vom 21. Juni, und mit diesem Brief schicke ich Ihnen Samen von Oxalis sepium; sie stammen von zwei Pflanzen, die dicht beieinander in meinem Garten wachsen; die eine ist langgrifflig, die andere mittelgrifflig, so dass vielleicht unter den Sämlingen keine kurzgriffligen sein werden.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ausser den verschiedenen Arten von Oxalis gibt es hier sehr wenige krautartige verschiedengrifflige Pflanzen, doch hoffe ich bald Ihnen Samen von Coccocypselum senden zu können. Auch lege ich einige Samen von Dalbergia bei; dies ist eine von jenen Kletterpflanzen, welche die Stütze mit ihren nicht umgewandelten Aesten erfassen.…..<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Ich weiss nicht, wer dem Dr. B. erzählt haben mag, ich hätte viele Bücher bei unserem letzten Hochwasser verloren; ich habe alle gerettet. Nur eine Bücherreihe ist nass geworden, weil ich sie an ihrer Stelle hatte stehen lassen, als ich mein Haus verlassen musste; ich hielt es auch da noch für unmöglich, dass das Wasser sie erreichen könnte. Hätte ich irgend welchen grossen Verlust erlitten, so würde ich ohne Zögern Ihr grossmüthiges Anerbieten annehmen, für das ich Ihnen tief verpflichtet bin.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>We have had last week some rather cold nights (2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> to 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> C. at sunrise), and these have given me a new confirmation of your view on the meaning of the nyctitropic movements of plants.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Near my house there are some Pandanus trees, about a dozen years old; the youngest terminal leaves stand upright, whereas the older ones are bent down so as to expose their upper surfaces to the sky. These young leaves, though of course the most tender, are still as fresh and green as before; on the contrary, the older ones have suffered from the cold, and have become quite yellowish.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Again, the leaves of <hi rend="underline">Oxalis sepium</hi> were observed by me to sleep in a very imperfect manner during the summer, even after the most sunny days; but now, in winter, every leaflet hangs down in a perpendicular position during the whole night.</p>
                    <p>10. August. Grade jetzt empfing ich Ihren Brief vom 4. Juli, und es freut mich, dass meine Bemerkungen über die Stellung der Blätter verschiedener Pflanzen während des Regens Ihnen von einigem Interesse sind.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Von den Blättern, die ich grade untersucht habe, wurden diejenigen der folgenden Pflanzen durch kurzes Untertauchen nicht benetzt, sondern glänzten wie Silber unter dem Wasser: Oxalis sepium und einige andere Arten, Desmodium (2 Arten), Cassia (2 Arten), Acacia, Phyllanthus (die beiden in meinem letzten Brief erwähnten Arten und Ph. compressus), Cissampelos Pareira.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Schizolobium<ref target="#foot.f9"/> habe ich noch nicht untersucht, da die in meinem Garten befindliche Pflanze vor einigen Wochen abgehauen ist, weil sie zu üppig wuchs. Aber ich werde diese Pflanze auch bald untersuchen können.</p>
                    <p>Glauben Sie, werther Herr, dass ich bin mit grösster Hochachtung immer treulichst der Ihrige | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Blumenau, Sa. Catharina, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>9. August 1881.</date>
                    <salute>Esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>A few days ago I received your kind letter of 21 June, and I am sending you seeds of Oxalis sepium with this letter; they are from two plants that grow close together in my garden; one of them is long-styled, the other medium-styled, so that perhaps there may be no short-styled ones among the seedlings.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Except for the various kinds of Oxalis very few herbaceous heterostylous plants can be found here, but soon I hope to be able to send you seeds of Coccocypselum. I also enclose a number of seeds of Dalbergia; this is one of those climbing plants which grasp the support with their unmodified branches......<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>I do not know who may have told Dr B. that I lost a lot of books in our recent floods; I saved all of them. Only one row of books became wet because I left it in its place when I had to leave the house; even then I thought it impossible that the water could reach them. If I had suffered great losses of any kind, I would accept your generous offer without hesitation, for which I am profoundly indebted to you.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>We have had last week some rather cold nights (2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> to 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> C. at sunrise), and these have given me a new confirmation of your view on the meaning of the nyctitropic movements of plants.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Near my house there are some Pandanus trees, about a dozen years old; the youngest terminal leaves stand upright, whereas the older ones are bent down so as to expose their upper surfaces to the sky. These young leaves, though of course the most tender, are still as fresh and green as before; on the contrary, the older ones have suffered from the cold, and have become quite yellowish.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Again, the leaves of <hi rend="underline">Oxalis sepium</hi> were observed by me to sleep in a very imperfect manner during the summer, even after the most sunny days; but now, in winter, every leaflet hangs down in a perpendicular position during the whole night.</p>
                    <p>10 August. Just now I received your letter of 4 July, and I am pleased that my remarks on the position of the leaves of various plants during rain are of some interest to you.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Of the leaves that I have studied just now, those of the following plants were not wet after being briefly dipped into water, but glistened like silver under the water: Oxalis sepium and a few other species, Desmodium (2 species), Cassia (2 species), Acacia, Phyllanthus (the two species mentioned in my previous letter and Ph. compressus), Cissampelos Pareira.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Schizolobium<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I have not yet investigated, as the plant in my garden was cut back a few weeks ago because it grew too thickly. However, I will soon be able to examine this plant as well.</p>
                    <p>Believe me, dear Sir, I am with the deepest respect, always very truly yours | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I. According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref>, all <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>). Möller also found final drafts of some Müller letters among the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> papers and included these in their original English form (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 2: 72 n). Where the original English versions are missing, the published version, usually appearing in German translation, has been used. This letter appeared in full in German translation (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 2: 416–17); one paragraph from the letter was quoted by CD in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13338.xml">letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, [before 15 September 1881]</ref>, and has been given in the English of the printed source.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of the original German of the published source of this letter, see Transcript. According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref>, all <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5533.xml">Möller ed. 1915–21</ref>, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (Möller ed. 1915–21). Möller also found final drafts of some Müller letters among the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> papers and included these in their original English form (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 2: 72 n). Where the original English versions are missing, the published version, usually appearing in German translation, has been used. This letter appeared in full in German translation (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 2: 416–17); one paragraph from the letter was quoted by CD in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13338.xml">letter to Nature, [before 15 September 1881]</ref>, and has been given in the English of the printed source.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13212.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 21 June 1881</ref>; CD mentioned that he wanted to test the degree of infertility in illegitimate seedlings. No record of experiments of this nature has been found, but CD’s notes on his experiments with plants of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis sepium</hi>, dated between 12 September and 28 October 1881, are in DAR 67: 93. The experiments related to CD’s study of the effects of dripping water on the leaves. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Müller had sent CD dried flowers of an unidentified species of <hi rend="italic">Coccocypselum</hi> in 1867 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5559.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 2 June 1867</ref>). CD described them in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 133–4. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1457.xml"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi></ref>, p. 22, CD had reported that some <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia</hi> species ascended thick trees by twining, but Müller informed CD that species he had observed were branch-climbers (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4929A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 5 November 1865</ref>). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13212.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 21 June 1881</ref> and nn. 4 and 5. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_607.xml">Wilhelm Breitenbach</ref> was living at Porto Alegre in Rio Grande do Sul, the southernmost province of Brazil. Müller’s home was in the adjacent Santa Catarina province, to the north. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 560, CD concluded that the purpose of nyctitropic (sleep) movement was to protect the leaf blade from damage from radiation or loss of heat.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Pandanus</hi> is the genus of screw pine or pandan palm; although native to tropical and subtropical regions of Asia, Africa, and Oceania, some species have been introduced to similar regions of North and South America. Branches produce crowns of sword-shaped leaves.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13233.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 4 July 1881</ref>; CD had described Müller’s letter as ‘invaluable’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Müller had evidently sent CD seeds with his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13185A.xml">31 May 1881</ref>; these were received by early July (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13233.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 4 July 1881</ref>) and probably included the species mentioned here. <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi> is the genus of tick clover; both <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi> are in the family Fabaceae. CD’s notes about dripping water on <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi>, dated 17 May and between 21 and 25 August 1881, are in DAR 67: 65, 104–6. Notes on <hi rend="italic">Cassia floribunda</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Senna floribunda</hi>), dated between 26 July and 28 October 1881, are in DAR 67: 78–9. Notes on <hi rend="italic">Acacia lophantha</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Paraserianthes lophantha</hi>, plume albizia), dated between 8 July 1881 and 19 February 1882, are in DAR 67: 71, 111. For his earlier mention of <hi rend="italic">Phyllanthus</hi> species, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13185A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 31 May 1881</ref>. CD’s notes on <hi rend="italic">Phyllanthus consanguineus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P. compressus</hi>, dated between 9 July and 3 September 1881, are in DAR 67: 66–7, 70, 72–3, 80–1, 110. <hi rend="italic">Cissampelos pareira</hi> is velvetleaf; no notes by CD on this species have been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">On <hi rend="italic">Schizolobium</hi>, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13233.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 4 July 1881</ref> and n. 4.</note> 
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>