<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6783">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   15 June 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7889</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6783 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6783.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6783.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp ††</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 110: B115; Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Directors’ Correspondence 215/175)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>110: B115;</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <collection>Directors’ Correspondence 215/175</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1869-06-15">15 June 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>FM much gratified by the appearance of <hi rend="italic">Für Darwin</hi> translation.</p> 
            <p>Discusses dimorphism in Rubiaceae.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Rubiaceae</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fur Darwin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Müller, J. F. T. 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Itajahy, S<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                    <date>June 15. 1869.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been prevented from answering sooner your kind letters of March 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> by a botanical excursion, I made last month.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I do not know how to express my warm gratitude for all the pains, you have taken in the publication of the Translation of my little book, to which, after all, you attach far too much importance.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The three copies have arrived here safely; many thanks for them. I have been much gratified by the appearance of the book in its English dress, as well as by the Translation, which appears to me to be very good. I have to thank you also for the reviews in the “Athenæum” and the “Scientific Opinion”, which you have kindly sent me. I am sorry to learn from these reviews, that some expressions of mine have shocked the religious feelings of one of the reviewers.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I should indeed have suppressed or modified some passages, before offering my book to English readers.—</p>
<p>As to <hi rend="underline">Faramea</hi>, I am quite sure, that the two forms are really the long-styled and short-styled form of a single species.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The plant is very common in my own forest, and after examining numerous specimens, I cannot find any difference between the two forms excepting those in the sexual organs. The size of the flowers varies much, but is not characteristic of either form. Some long-styled flowers, which I had fertilized artificially with pollen from the opposite form, are yielding fruits.— A second very beautiful species of the same genus which grows near the mouth of the Itajahy, is probably also dimorphic; I have hitherto examined the flowers of only one plant; these were longstyled and the styles as long as in the longstyled form of the first species.—</p>
<p>Many thanks for the <hi rend="underline">Eschscholtzia</hi>—seeds, which will be sown in a few weeks.— It is curious to see, on what trifling circumstances fertility sometimes depends.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Thus I have in my garden several specimens of an endemic <hi rend="underline">Irideous</hi> plant (<hi rend="underline">Cypella</hi>?), which I suspected to be self-sterile.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I fertilized repeatedly numerous flowers with pollen of the same and of distinct plants, without obtaining a single pod. The unprotected flowers were regularly visited by insects; by these also, for months, did not yield a single fruit, when unexpectedly all the flowers, about 20 in number, which had opened on a certain day, produced fine pods. The plants have continued to flower after this time for many weeks, but without producing any more pods.—</p>
<p>That curious grass with spirally contracting barbs, the <hi rend="underline">Streptochæta</hi>, appears to be extremely rare here.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have looked in vain for more specimens at different localities; that part of my forest, where I had found it first, had been cut down in the meantime; a single specimen, which I had planted in my garden, seems to thrive well and will, I hope, furnish me with an opportunity of settling the points to which you allude in your letter.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>From seeds of a <hi rend="underline">long-styled</hi> white <hi rend="underline">Oxalis</hi>, legitimately fertilised with pollen of the longer stamens of the <hi rend="underline">mid-styled</hi> form I raised some plants; 8 of these have hitherto flowered and of these 4 are long-styled, 4 mid-styled and <hi rend="underline">none</hi> short-styled.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I enclose seeds of the second plant of <hi rend="underline">Begonia</hi> with monstrous flowers, of which I told you in my last letter. In this species, (probably the <hi rend="underline">Begonia obliqua</hi> of the Flora fluminensis),<ref target="#foot.f10"/> the panicles generally consist of either 5 or 11 flowers, of which 3 or 7 are male ones and the rest female ones and which are arranged in the following manner</p> 
<figure type="diagram">
<p>[DIAG]</p></figure> 
<figure type="diagram">
<p>[DIAG]</p></figure> 
<p>The male flowers (1) and (2) are often quite regular, or but little modified, one or two of the central stamens having the connectivum enlarged and provided with rudimentary stigmatic papillæ, whilst in those male flowers, which stand at the side of a female one, from one to three (or in the second plant even as many as 8) stamens are more or less completely transformed into pistils.</p>
<p>The female flowers have generally 5 divisions or petals, one of which is much smaller than the rest.</p>
<p>This small petal (α) and the male flower, which springs from</p> 
<figure type="diagram">
<p><figure type="inlinediagram"> 
<p>[DIAG]</p> </figure></p></figure> 
<p>the same point with the female one, are always placed on opposite sides of the latter. Sometimes the male flower is wanting and in this almost always a sixth petal (β) is present in the female flower.</p> 
<figure type="diagram">
<p><figure type="inlinediagram"> 
<p>[DIAG]</p> </figure></p></figure> 
<p>May we not venture to admit, that the abortion of the sixth petal in those female flowers, which are accompanied by a male one, is due to the pressure exerted on the young buds by the male flowers? And not the reappearance of the sixth petal in most of the cases, in which this pressure does not exist, be compared to the reappearance of a regular structure (pelorism) in central or terminal flowers?—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> In irregular flowers it is almost always, as far as I know, the posterior stamen, which first aborts, and this abortion might be explained by a pressure caused by the axis, from the side of which the flower springs. Now, if a flower-bud be placed at the very end of the axis, no such pressure could possibly be exerted; all the segments of the flower would have exactly the same position in relation to the axis; there would be no reason for one of them differing from the rest and thus the flower would become regular even without the law of reversion coming into play.</p>
<p>With sincere gratitude and respect, believe me, dear Sir, | very truly yours | Fritz Müller</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I have … readers.— 2.10] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 As … species.— 3.10] ‘faramea (Rubiaceæ)’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 Many … pods.— 4.9] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.6 by these … pods.— 4.9] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 That … short-styled. 6.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Eschotzia | Dimorphic Plant in <hi rend="italic">[</hi>growth<hi rend="italic">]</hi> | Begonia Hooker’ <hi rend="italic">pencil del ink</hi>; ‘Faramea’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi>; ‘(Claparède)’ <hi rend="italic">ink del ink</hi>; ‘(Peridromia)’<ref target="#foot.f12"/> <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The first part of this letter, down to paragraph six, ‘hitherto’, was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17. The last two pages were later found at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew; CD evidently sent them to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>. The footnotes to the first part of the letter have been altered. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">14 March 1869</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6668.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">18 March 1869</ref>. In a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6780.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 12 June 1869</ref>, Müller told his brother, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller</ref>, that he had travelled to the furthest part of his land to get supplies of garlic vine (<hi rend="italic">Pseudocalymma alliaceum</hi>) to use as rope for his garden fences (Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 158).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Müller refers to the translation of his book <hi rend="italic">Für Darwin</hi> (F. Müller 1864) into English as <hi rend="italic">Facts and arguments for Darwin</hi> (Dallas trans. 1869; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 14 March 1869</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The review in the 21 April 1869 issue of <hi rend="italic">Scientific Opinion</hi> (Anon. 1869) was positive, but the one in the 27 March 1869 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> was critical, and the author remarked, ‘It is to be feared that Dr. Müller’s moral code is rather Crustacean than Christian’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4671.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Leifchild] 1869</ref>). The reviewer, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2874.xml">John Roby Leifchild</ref>, had written a review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> for the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> that CD found unfair ‘under a theological point of view’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2538.xml" resp="#automat">letter to C. S. Wedgwood, [after 21 November 1859]</ref>). In his letter to his brother Hermann, Müller confided that he thought the remark about his moral code a rather good joke (Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 158).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 14 March 1869</ref> and n. 9. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 129, CD included an illustration by Müller of the different forms of flowers and pollen-grains in <hi rend="italic">Faramea</hi>. What Müller described as possibly a species of <hi rend="italic">Faramea</hi> was subsequently identified as <hi rend="italic">Rudgea jasminoides</hi> from specimens Müller sent to the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9458.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Baker 1956</ref>, pp. 27–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had sent seeds of <hi rend="italic">Eschscholzia californica</hi> (California poppy); see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 14 March 1869</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. 331–3, CD discussed the effects of climate on self-fertility in <hi rend="italic">E. californica</hi>, noting differences between plants grown in Brazil and England.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Cypella</hi> is a South American genus of the family Iridaceae. Müller later published observations on two species of <hi rend="italic">Cypella</hi> in ‘Biologische Beobachtungen an Blumen Südbrasiliens’ (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1883).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6549.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 12 January 1869</ref> and nn. 3–5, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 14 March 1869</ref> and n. 13. Müller had described the unusual floral structure of <hi rend="italic">Streptochaeta</hi>, which, he hypothesised, might be a connecting link between common grasses and other monocotyledons.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In his letter of 14 March 1869 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17), CD had suggested that Müller should try to determine whether the bracts of the grass were sensitive and how soon they became apical in the bud.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> (wood sorrel) species was identified at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, as <hi rend="italic">Oxalis martiana</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">O. latifolia</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">latifolia</hi>, Cuban purple wood-sorrel; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6943.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 18 October 1869</ref>). CD later described it as <hi rend="italic">Oxalis regnelli</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">O. triangularis</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">papilionacea</hi>, false shamrock) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 173.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6662F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 14 March 1869</ref>. CD had sent seeds of the first <hi rend="italic">Begonia</hi> to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref> for the collection at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6743.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to George Bentham, 10 May [1869]</ref>; Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Inwards book). An illustration of <hi rend="italic">Begonia obliqua</hi> appears in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9459.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Flora fluminensis</hi></ref> 10: tab. 48; the name was used illegitimately, however, and the plant figured is <hi rend="italic">Begonia fischeri</hi> (see Jacques and Mamede 2005, p. 580). An annotation at the end of the letter in an unknown hand reads, ‘Obliqua is an erect plant 2 feet high with only 2 sepals to male flowers’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Peloric flowers are aberrant forms in which a usually irregular floral structure appears regular or symmetrical. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 345–7, CD had discussed the tendency of terminal or central flowers to be peloric.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD’s notes are for his reply to Müller of 8 September [1869] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17); he refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Claparède</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Peridromia</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Hamadryas</hi> (the genus of cracker butterflies).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>