<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1251">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. A. Gould   20 August [1849]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3072</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1251 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1251.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1251.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">AU 20 1849</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Houghton Library, Harvard University (Augustus A. Gould papers, 1831–66 MS Am 1210: 229)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_180.xml">Harvard Houghton</repository>
                    <collection>MS Am 1210: 229</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1849-08-20">20 Aug [1849]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1931.xml">Gould, A. A.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks J. D. Dana for cirripede specimens. Describes his work. Comments on <hi rend="italic">Ibla</hi>. Would like to see AAG’s notes and figures on <hi rend="italic">Anatifa</hi>. Asks for references to cirripede descriptions by T. A. Conrad.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cirripede</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1190">Dana, J. D.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Aug 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I did not receive your very kind note of April 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; loan of Cirripedes through M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cuming until a fortnight since; for I have been absent from home &amp; all my work interrupted for the last five months. My health became so exceedingly bad, that I could do hardly anything, &amp; I consequently have been to Malvern &amp; tryed the Cold Water Cure under D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gully with great success. I am now at the Cirripedia again, but am allowed to work only two hours a day: I feel truly grateful for your kindness in assisting me: the sessile Cirripedes will come in very useful, when I come to that division,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> &amp; they shall hereafter be carefully returned to you: I believe I told you that I require to disarticulate a specimen of each species; without this being done it is impossible to describe or recognise the species: I trust you will not object to this; should you do so, there will be time to inform me. The Ibla is a species (not published) which I have named <hi rend="underline">I. Cumingii</hi> &amp; was found in numbers by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cuming at the Philippines: I have never seen it from elsewhere, except the specimen from Tavoy sent by you:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> it is in some Anatomical respects, perhaps the most interesting cirripede in the world.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I will send the Scutella to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gray at British Museum, as directed.</p>
<p>I have acted on your kind suggestion &amp; written to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dana</p>
<p>You say “that I have figures &amp; notes of 3 or 4 species of Anatifa which I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> copy for you if desired”: if you could let me have a specimen of such those figures &amp; notes would be of the greatest service to me, but without you have <hi rend="underline">minutely described</hi> the <hi rend="underline">internal</hi> surface of the valves, &amp; the Branchiæ of the animal, I find it quite impossible to recognise species of Anatifa. I see in the drawing sent the colours are marked <hi rend="underline">specimens</hi> of such w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be invaluable, for then I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> know the colouring.—</p>
<p>I thank you most cordially for your offer of further assistance: from my health &amp; the extreme difficulty of describing the species, I shall certainly be employed a year or two more on the Cirripedia—</p>
<p>Could you tell me in what works M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Conrad<ref target="#foot.f4"/> has described or is likely to have described Cirripedia: in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Cumings collection there as 2 or 3 species (especially a Pollicipes from California) named by him &amp; I am quite at loss to know where to look— Of course I do not intend for one second to hint to you to take the trouble to search for references; but as you have attended so much to shells you may be able to guide me where to search.— I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Conrad myself on this subject, but either my letter miscarried, or he thought I took too great a liberty in addressing him; anyhow I have had no answer.—</p>
<p>With my sincere thanks | Believe me | Your’s faithfully &amp; respectfully | C. Darwin</p>
<p>If you ever see an Anatifa adherent to a Crab, you may be almost sure it will be new &amp; interesting: there are several species, which I have been compelled to separate under a new generic name:<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am glad to say that I have had to run far more genera together, than to separate &amp; make new ones.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.1 of April 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.1 to] <hi rend="italic">before omitted point</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.1 “that I] ‘I’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘you’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">4.2 specimen of] ‘specimen’ <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘with’; ‘of’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.2 figures &amp; notes 4.3] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.5 of Anatifa.] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘—’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">5.2 employed] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">8.4 more] <hi rend="italic">after omitted points</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">8.5 than to separate] ‘to’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD was at work on the pedunculated cirripedes and did not begin to examine the sessile barnacles until April 1850 (‘Journal’; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix I). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854)</ref>, Gould is frequently cited as having provided specimens.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Gould’s specimen from Tavoy, Burma is described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>183.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Ibla cumingii</hi>, a species in which the sexes are entirely separated. The other species of the same genus, <hi rend="italic">I. quadrivalvis</hi>, is intermediate between usual hermaphrodite species and <hi rend="italic">I. cumingii</hi>, having hermaphroditic individuals and reduced complemental males.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1043.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Timothy Abbott Conrad</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>307 and (1854): 447, 465, citations of species named by him are from the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi>, volume seven (1837).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD, after some deliberation, decided to separate species of the new genus <hi rend="italic">Poecilasma</hi>, ‘generally attached to Crustacea’, from the genus <hi rend="italic">Lepas</hi>. He explained in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>72: ‘Although some of the species of Pæcilasma so closely resemble externally the species of <hi rend="italic">Lepas</hi>, yet if we consider their entire structure, we shall find that they are sufficiently distinct’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>