<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9072">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. W. Keen   26 September 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16264</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9072 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9072.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9072.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp inc †, CD note ††</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 89: 24–5, DAR 169: 2, and <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> 2d ed., p. 169 n. 19</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>89: 24–5</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Expression 2d ed., p. 169 n. 19</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2650.xml">Keen, W. W.</persName>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                <date when="1873-09-26">26 Sept 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends corrections of <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-04-08" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2017-04-08" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>1729 Chestnut St | Philada.</placeName>
                    <date>Sept. 26. 1873.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In reading carefully of late your Descent of Man, Sexual Selection, &amp; Expression of the Emotions I have been struck with some statements of facts which I regarded as erroneous &amp; also have been reminded of facts corroborating your statements or even going further, which I have jotted down &amp; propose to embody as briefly as possible. No one, so candid and so just as you are, will more rejoice I feel sure if an inadvertent error is eliminated than yourself. Pardon me therefore if I venture to call attention to such.</p>
<p>I quote pages from Appleton’s reprint of the Descent &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. 1872 &amp; the Emotions dated 1873.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Descent &amp; Sexual Selection Vol. I.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">p. 19 middle</hi>— You state that the platysma is an involuntary muscle. On the contrary it is a perfectly voluntary muscle &amp; can be brought into action as perfectly &amp; easily as any muscle. (P.S. You have corrected this in the book on Expression p 298 et seqq.)<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">p 20. middle</hi>.— The power of voluntarily moving the ears is not unusual as you intimate. <hi rend="underline">Many</hi> persons can do so. Most persons in <hi rend="underline">laughing</hi> &amp; even <hi rend="underline">smiling</hi> move the ears upwards &amp; I think forwards. Possibly the ears are <hi rend="underline">pushed</hi> up by the soft parts on the face but I think it is not so.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">p. 22 top</hi>. I have lately seen a medical friend in whose ears the tubercle instead of being turned inwards remains turned up- &amp; out-wards so that the ear is really a pointed one. If I can do so I hope to obtain for you a Photograph of the auricle.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Of course you have seen the recent article in Virchow’s Archiv on this Subject<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; are familiar probably with this peculiarity in Hawthorne’s fiction of “Transformation or The Marble Faun” in Donatello who resembles so strikingly the Faun of Praxiteles.*<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">p. 24. bottom</hi>. The peculiarity noticed by Mr. Paget as hereditary is I think not only (if particularly) hereditary, but, in this country, is very common with advancing age.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wayland late Pres. Brown Univ<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. &amp; the author of noted text books on Polit. Econ. Moral &amp; Mental Philos. &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. was noted for his bushy shaggy eyebrows &amp; his 2 living sons markedly resemble him in this<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">pp. 48–9</hi>. With respect to animals learning to avoid traps. With my friend Dr. S. Weir Mitchell I have had much to do with Rattlesnakes. We generally kept them in deep boxes &amp; caught them by means of a long pole with a leather noose at the end. A green (i.e. new) snake could be caught with perfect ease but in a few days after being caught 4 or 5 times he would dodge the noose &amp; in a little time considerable dexterity was required to catch them.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">p. 52 bottom</hi>. See Marsh’s Lectures on the Eng. Lang. p. 35 (note) for the Statement that the Massacre of the Sicilian Vespers was all arranged by <hi rend="underline">facial gestures</hi> alone no other gestures &amp; no words being used. &amp; some other Statements. The book referred to is <hi rend="underline">not</hi> his “Eng. Lang. &amp; its Early Literature”.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">p. 143</hi>. If you will observe carefully the hair is best developed not “on the chest &amp; face &amp; junction of the 4 limbs with the trunk” but in the <hi rend="underline">Median line</hi> of the body. E.g. On the head it comes to a <hi rend="underline">point</hi> in the median line both in front &amp; behind, if whiskers are absent a median<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>*An argument to support your view is the growth of the <hi rend="underline">hair</hi> up- &amp; for-wards on the <hi rend="underline">top</hi> of the auricle with advancing years, more than over the rest of the auricle except the lobule &amp; tragus</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">[at least 1 folio missing]</hi></p>
<p rend="left">assurance that it was so, &amp; that the holes were eaten where the pipes were not obstacles to progress I can scarcely believe that their intelligence has been so cultivated by familiarity with civilized man’s means for getting water as to lead to such an act of reason. I mention it however for what it is worth.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>One point in reference to sexual selection I have to suggest when I am done with my rambling &amp; I fear almost worthless letter. I do not know but that it should rather be classed however as natural selection in relation to sex. I mean the peculiar effect of certain diseases on one sex or the other by reason of the frequency with which it attacks one sex as compared with the other.</p>
<p>My memory may be at fault but I do not recall any allusion to it in any of your books. Yet it must have its influence both as to the number of Survivors of each sex &amp; as to the questions of inheritance in that sex alone or in major part. As an allied subject also I would suggest the fact now believed by many to be true (&amp; my self among the number) that Syphilis (&amp; possibly other diseases) though existing in the Father cannot be &amp; is not transmitted to the child except the mother be first infected ie. if she escapes direct infection the child will also. It is widely &amp; vehemently disputed by many Syphilographers but its supporters I think have the strongest side.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I hope you will pardon me Sir if I have fruitlessly taken up your time. What is of value if there be any I shall be delighted to have you weigh &amp; use if you think best.</p>
<p>While not able to follow you quite as far as you go, yet I accept most of it gladly &amp; as a daily teacher I enjoy the light you have shed on much that has been dark &amp; unmeaning. With the hope that your life may be spared a long while to cement what you have so well built I remain | very respectfully | Your Ob’t Sv’t | W. W. Keen M.D. | Lecturer on Anatomy in the Philadelphia School of Anatomy | Lecturer on Pathol. Anat. in the Jefferson Med. College Phila | Joint Author of Gunshot Wounds &amp; other Injuries of Nerves &amp;<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>(I beg leave to name these as an introduction)</p>
<p>I forgot to mention an inherited peculiarity in my children of the use of a <hi rend="underline">single muscle</hi>. My wife<ref target="#foot.f14"/> when perplexed or in deep thought often contracts the 2 Corrugator Supercillii muscles just enough to produce a single deep furrow but not a general frown; in fact it is rather almost a pit than a furrow its border is so sharply curved 
    <figure type="diagram" rend="inline width10"> 
        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_9072.jpg"/>
    </figure> 
 thus. I have 3 children all girls 5, 4 &amp; 2<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> years old.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> The eldest &amp; youngest resemble me <hi rend="underline">very</hi> markedly &amp; the middle one her mother. The eldest &amp; youngest both will frown when perplexed &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. but it is a more general frown while the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. child has the most striking reproduction of this her mothers use of the Corrugator.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>[Dr. Keen, of Philadelphia, calls attention (letter n. d.),<ref target="#foot.f17"/> to his paper in the ‘Med. and Surg. History of the War of the Rebellion (Surgical Part),’ vol. i. pp. 206–7, bearing on this point. A patient lost part of his skull by a gunshot wound, and recovered with a concavity on the surface of his head, into which the scalp dipped to the depth of an inch. Ordinary respiration did not affect the concavity, but on moderate coughing a little cone bulged up, and a severe cough changed the concavity into a convex surface rising above the surface of the head.]<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 In … this 7.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>1.5 candid … yourself. 1.6] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. … muscle. 4.3] ‘D’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 <hi rend="italic">p 20.</hi> … intimate. 5.2] ‘E D’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 <hi rend="italic">p. 22</hi> … one. 6.3] ‘E D’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 <hi rend="italic">p. 24</hi> … age. 7.2] ‘D E’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 <hi rend="italic">pp. 48–9</hi>. … them. 8.6] ‘Intellect of Snakes’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>9.1 <hi rend="italic">p. 52</hi> … Literature”. 9.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>10.1 <hi rend="italic">p. 143</hi> … body. 10.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi>; ‘Good’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.1 *An … tragus 11.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>12.1 assurance … side. 13.9] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>18.1 I … Corrugator 18.8] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Keen, Lecturer of anatomy’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘Intellect of Snakes’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi> ‘&amp; <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Man</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘Nakedness in Belts view<ref target="#foot.f19"/> | <hi rend="italic">Hair</hi> [‘eyebrows &amp;’ <hi rend="italic">del pencil</hi>] on body | Intellect of Snakes [<hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi>]’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi>; ‘D.= Descent | E expression’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon, del pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘Mustache &amp; goatee are mostly seen with age it also develops on the nose; it is mainly in the medial line on the neck, chest, belt &amp; back—on the pubes, &amp; the perinæum. The axillæ are morphologically the median line but pushed back (?!)—(N.B— there are often patches on the shoulders—The outer side of [‘for’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] arms &amp; legs. )’ <hi rend="italic">ink, del pencil</hi>, <hi rend="italic">square brackets in ms</hi>; ‘Russia〈n〉 Hairy [‘Man’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] Boy a sort of mane running down neck’<ref target="#foot.f20"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">D. Appleton &amp; Co</ref>. published American editions of CD’s works; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1968.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> US ed.</ref> was published in 1871 and reprinted in 1872, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2402.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> US ed.</ref> was published in 1873. Parts of this letter were previously published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21; since then, the end of the letter, from paragraph 12, ‘assurance that it was so’, to paragraph 21, ending ‘use of the Corrugator’, has been identified in DAR 169: 2. A middle section of the letter is still missing, but is partially accounted for by the note from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2401.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> 2d ed.</ref> reproduced at the foot of the letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2402.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> US ed.</ref>, pp. 298–303, CD described the movements (such as shuddering) that caused an involuntary contraction of the platysma myoides muscle, and noted how simulating these movements sometimes produced the same contraction. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 13, CD omitted the reference to the platysma’s movement being involuntary.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The tubercle, or blunt point, projecting inwards from the folded margin of the ear in some humans (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 22, fig. 2) was first drawn to CD’s attention by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5242.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Woolner</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Thomas Woolner, 10 March [1870]</ref>). CD viewed this point as a vestige of formerly pointed ears in humans or their ancestors. There is no evidence that Keen sent a photograph of his friend’s ears to CD.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Keen probably refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3312.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ludwig Meyer’s</ref> article in <hi rend="italic">Archiv für pathologische Anatomie und Physiologie und für klinische Medicin</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5406.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Meyer 1871</ref>), which maintained that the ‘Woolnerian tip’ visible on some ears was merely a random variation, not evidence for a former pointed ear-shape in humans. Rudolf Carl Virchow was the editor of <hi rend="italic">Archiv für pathologische Anatomie und Physiologie und für klinische Medicin</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5871.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nathaniel Hawthorne’s</ref> novel <hi rend="italic">The marble faun</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hawthorne 1860</ref>), also known as <hi rend="italic">Transformation</hi>, featured Donatello, count of Monte Beni, whose character combined human and animal qualities. His appearance was modelled on Praxiteles’s statue, the <hi rend="italic">Faun</hi>, which was on display in the Uffizi Gallery, Florence.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3643.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Paget</ref> had informed CD that the occurrence of eyebrows with some hairs longer than the others often ran in families (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 25).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Wayland</ref> had been president of Brown University, Providence. His sons were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6975.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Wayland Jr</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6976.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heman Lincoln Wayland</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD added this observation to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 352. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Silas Weir Mitchell</ref> had investigated the effects of snake venom on the nervous system as part of his research on the physiology of the cerebellum (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ANB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 54, CD had stated that humans’ unique use of articulate speech did not preclude the use of gestures and facial movements. The massacre of thousands of French inhabitants of Sicily had begun on Easter Monday 1282 with the killing of some French soldiers at vespers in Palermo (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6786.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Runciman 2012</ref>, pp. 214–27). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6282.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Perkins Marsh’s</ref> statement that facial signs alone were used to start the massacre was in his <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the English language</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5221.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. P. Marsh 1861</ref>, p. 35 n.), which Keen distinguished from Marsh’s <hi rend="italic">The origin and history of the English language, and of the early literature it embodies</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">G. P. Marsh 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 149. CD did not add the point about hair being best developed along the median line of the body to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref></note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The missing discussion probably had to do with rats’ gnawing holes in lead pipes to get water (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10253.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Arthur Nicols, [before 10 November 1875]</ref>, and this volume, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10586.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. A. Ransome-Marriott, 1 September 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD did not mention syphilis in the first edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 7, he used syphilis as an example of a disease that could be transmitted between humans and animals, showing that their tissues and blood were similar; however, he did not discuss the inheritance of the disease. Syphilographer: an expert in the study and treatment of syphilis (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Keen <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1864.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Corinna Borden Keen</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Corrine, Florence, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6034.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dora Keen</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">CD discussed the use of the corrugator muscles in frowning and deep thought in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 181 and 222–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">This comment, published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2401.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 169 n. 19, was probably drawn from the missing part of Keen’s letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 161 (and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2401.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 168–9), CD discussed how violent expiration (such as coughing) led to the dilation of blood vessels in the head, indicated by the rise and fall of the brain and the advance of the eyes in their sockets with each expiration. <hi rend="italic">The medical and surgical history of the war of the rebellion (1861–65)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Surgical volume</hi> part 1, vol. 2, pp. 206–7, recorded the accounts of various surgeons who had treated a soldier with the gunshot wound to the head; Keen had examined the patient mentioned in his letter in 1870 and believed that this case might throw light on the anatomy of the optic nerve. A longer account of the case was published in Keen and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7741.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomson 1871</ref>. There is an independently paginated offprint of Keen and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7741.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomson 1871</ref> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. CD scored the passages relating to coughing on pages 2 and 4, and wrote at the top of the pamphlet, ‘for Expression p. 2, 4’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 57, CD added, with some reservations, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Belt’s</ref> suggestion that hairlessness in the tropics was advantageous because it made getting rid of parasitical insects easier (see Belt 1874, p. 209). CD himself accounted for hairlessness as a secondary sexual characteristic acquired through sexual selection (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 58, 600–1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">CD had obtained the information about the Russian hairy boy from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander von Brandt</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8216F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to C. S. Tomes, 16 February [1874]</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>