<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4881">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Fritz Müller   10 August [1865]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1665</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4881 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4881.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4881.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 443a by Müller, J. F. T.</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 37</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 13</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Loan MS 10 no 1)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Loan MS 10</collection>
                    <idno>1</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1865-08-10">10 Aug [1865]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has read and admires FM’s work on species.</p>
            <p>Observations on Crustacea are good and original; asks FM to dissect and check some of CD’s observations on cirripedes.</p> 
<p>Has sent "Climbing plants" paper [<hi rend="italic">J. Proc. Linn. Soc. Lond.</hi> 9 (1865): 1–118] and would like to send <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Crustacea</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbing plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">J. Proc. Linn. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down. | Bromley. | Kent. S.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Aug 10</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been for a long time so ill that I have only just finished hearing read aloud your work on species.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> And now you must permit me to thank you cordially for the great interest with which I have read it. You have done admirable service in the cause in which we both believe. Many of your arguments seem to me excellent, &amp; many of your facts wonderful. Of the latter nothing has surprised me so much as the two forms of males.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have lately investigated the cases of dimorphic plants, &amp; I should much like to send you one or two of my papers if I knew how.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I did send lately by post a paper on climbing plants as an experiment to see whether it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> reach you.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>One of the points which has struck me most in your paper is that on the differences in the air-breathing apparatus of the several forms. This subject appeared to me very important when I formerly considered the electric apparatus of fishes.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Your observations on Classification &amp; Embryology seem to me very good &amp; original<ref target="#foot.f6"/>   They shew what a wonderful field there is for enquiry on the development of Crustacea; and nothing has convinced me so plainly what admirable results we shall arrive at in Natural History in the course of a few years.</p>
<p>What a marvellous range of structure the Crustacea present &amp; how well adapted they are for your enquiry! Until reading your book I knew nothing of the Rhizocephala; pray look at my account &amp; figures of Anelasma; for it seems to me that this latter Cirrepede is a beautiful connecting link with the Rhizocephala.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>If ever you have any opportunity, as you are so skilful a dissector, I much wish that you w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> look to the orifice at the base of the first pair of cirri in Cirripedes, &amp; at the curious organ in it &amp; discover what its nature is; I suppose I was quite in error, yet I cannot feel fully satisfied at Krohn’s observations.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Also if you ever find any species of Scalpellum, pray look for complemental males; a German author has recently doubted my observations for no reason except that the facts appeared to him so strange.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Permit me again to thank you cordially for the pleasure which I have derived from your work &amp; to express my sincere admiration for your valuable researches. Believe me | Dear Sir with sincere respect | yours very faithfully | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. I do not know whether you care at all about plants but if so I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> much like to send you my little work on the Fertilization of Orchids &amp; I think I have a German Copy.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Could you spare me a Photograph of yourself, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> much like to possess one?—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">7.1 Could … one?—-] <hi rend="italic">added in CD’s hand</hi></note>
                </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The reference is to Müller 1864, a study of the Crustacea that was supportive of CD’s theory of transmutation. CD had received a presentation copy from Müller before 21 November 1864, but found the German difficult to understand and had it translated (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 21 November [1864]</ref> and n. 6). The translation was probably made by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Camilla Ludwig</ref>, who had been governess at Down House between 1860 and 1863. CD’s Classed account book (Down House MS) records, under the heading ‘Science’, a payment to Ludwig of £5 11<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> on 10 June 1865 for translation. An annotated copy of Müller 1864 is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 609). CD’s annotated copy of the later translation by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> (Dallas trans. 1869) is in the Rare Books Collection–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 609).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In Müller 1864, Müller discussed the existence of two forms of male in some species of Crustacea and argued that this dimorphism could be seen as a result of natural selection. Müller’s example was a species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Tanais.</hi> Müller found that one form of male developed enlarged olfactory filaments, making it better at finding females, while the other form had enlarged chelae (claws), giving it an advantage in clasping females (see Müller 1864, pp. 13–19 and Dallas trans. 1869, pp. 20–9). The absence of intermediate forms was explained by the lack of any advantage conferred by such hypothetical forms. CD added this information to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 50 and 288.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD sent <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>; the last-named concerns trimorphism (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4929A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 5 November 1865</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, which was published on 12 June 1865 in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>). No presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref> has been found, but it is likely that CD sent Müller an author’s offprint. Müller resided at Destêrro on Santa Catarina Island off the coast of the state of Santa Catarina, Brazil. Destêrro is now Florianópolis.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Müller compared the structure of the air-breathing apparatus in certain non-aquatic species of two families of true crabs (Brachyura): shore crabs (Grapsoidae, now Grapsidae), and ghost and fiddler crabs (Ocypoda, now Ocypodidae). He observed that the structure and position of the apparatus differed in various ways in each family and argued that the differences could be explained only by assuming that each family adapted to an air-breathing existence independently (see Müller 1864, pp. 24–6, and Dallas trans. 1869, pp. 35–7). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 193–4, CD wrote that the electric organs in fish of widely differing species appeared difficult to explain within the framework of his theory, but conjectured that they might be explained as analogous features, that is, structures with similar functions that have developed independently in response to similar habits. In the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 226–8, he added Müller’s observations on these crab families.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">For Müller’s observations and remarks on crustacean embryology, see Müller 1864, pp. 31–65; his remarks on classification are on pp. 65–74 (see also Dallas trans. 1869, pp. 47–96, pp. 97–109). Müller noted that the use of embryological characteristics, although helpful in determining classificatory schemes, was by no means foolproof. He gave numerous examples of species or genera in which embryological similarity did not translate into adult similarity, or in which embryonic and adult stages were similar but the intermediate nauplius (larval) stages were disparate. He then devised a hypothetical classificatory scheme for the Crustacea to show the pitfalls of placing too great an emphasis on embryonic similarity (Müller 1864, pp. 73–4; Dallas trans. 1869, p. 109). In the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 494, CD added a reference to Müller’s classificatory scheme.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Rhizocephala is the name coined by Müller (see Müller 1862a and 1862b) for a highly unusual group of crustaceans that as adults are naked and limbless parasites attached to their crab hosts by means of root-like tubes, and that appear from the outside as sausage-like sacs. Müller had noted their similarity, in pre-adult stages, to cirripedes, placing them, not within what Darwin had described as the sub-class Cirripedia (barnacles), but alongside it (Müller 1864, p. 59; Dallas trans. 1869, pp. 88–9). CD had described <hi rend="italic">Anelasma</hi> as a ‘curious cirripede’ that lived ‘parasitic, with its peduncle imbedded in the skin of sharks’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, p. 170). When he described the species <hi rend="italic">A. squalicola</hi>, he could not find a cement gland or ducts, but noted that the peduncle had root-like branched filaments that, he conjectured, helped the animal to remain embedded in the shark’s skin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, p. 174). After reading Müller’s account of Rhizocephala, CD may have considered the branching filaments in <hi rend="italic">Anelasma</hi> to be an intermediate form between the cement ducts of other cirripedes and the root-like tubes of Rhizocephala.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, pp. 53–5, CD had described the empty orifice, which seemed to contain a nerve at its mouth, as possibly an auditory sac. His description was criticised by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2761.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August David Krohn</ref>, who identified the structure as a female genital aperture (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4503.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Krohn 1859</ref>, pp. 362–3). In a letter to the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>, [before 10 October 1862] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10), CD referred to Krohn’s paper, and asked whether any reader would ‘endeavour to discover ova within the so-called auditory sack’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_244.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘“Auditory-sac” of cirripedes’</ref>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 87; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 28 [September 1860]</ref> and nn. 4–6). For a discussion of the problem of the orifice see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5843.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newman 1993</ref>, pp. 368–71.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD refers to his discovery in 1848 of the small ‘complemental’ males attached to the bodies of hermaphrodites in the barnacle genus <hi rend="italic">Scalpellum</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, pp. 281–93, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Holland, 2 January 1865</ref>, n. 5). CD did not name in his published writings the German author who doubted this discovery; however, in 1863 the German zoologist Carl Eduard <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1851.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolph Gerstaecker</ref> had questioned CD’s account of the existence of complemental males in his <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der Zoologie</hi> (see Gerstaecker 1863b, p. 410). CD referred to the criticism in a letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 20 September [1873] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Males and complemental males of certain cirripedes’</ref>), and in his <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi></ref>, pp. 117–18. For CD’s discussion of complemental males in the genera <hi rend="italic">Scalpellum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ibla</hi> see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, pp. 281–93 (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5843.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newman 1993</ref>, pp. 377–82, for a discussion of CD’s work on complemental males). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 26 November [1864]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, which was translated into German in 1862 by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn</ref> (Bronn trans. 1862).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>