<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10821">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. C. Graham   30 January 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16995</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10821 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10821.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10821.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 165: 83–4</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>165: 83–84</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1941.xml" resp="high">Graham, C. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Public Library, Louisville, Ky.  </placeName>
                <date when="1877-01-30">30 Jan 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>He has defended Tyndall, CD, and others against attacks of a clergyman.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">clergyman</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4839">Tyndall, John</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00392_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3780px" height="6266px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00392_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3780px" height="6266px"/>
        <surface n="83-84:1r" xml:id="i392">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00392.jpg" width="3780px" height="6266px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00392_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3780px" height="6266px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00392.dzi" width="3780px" height="6266px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="83-84:1v" xml:id="i393">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00393.jpg" width="3639px" height="6019px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00393_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3639px" height="6019px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00393.dzi" width="3639px" height="6019px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="83-84:2r" xml:id="i394">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00394.jpg" width="5297px" height="7238px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00394_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5297px" height="7238px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00394.dzi" width="5297px" height="7238px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="83-84:2v" xml:id="i395">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00395.jpg" width="5108px" height="6985px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00395_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5108px" height="6985px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00165-000-00395.dzi" width="5108px" height="6985px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Office of | Public Library | and | Festival Halls, | Louisville, Ky.</hi></placeName> 
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">P. A. Towne, Manager. | Louisville,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>January 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, <hi rend="print">187</hi>7.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental"><hi rend="italic">M</hi>r Hon. Charles Darwin, M.A. F.R.S.</seg>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>As a convert to your doctrine and a defender of the faith against the pulpits of Louisville, I take the liberty of droping you a line, and of sending you my little Book.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The clergy, in this country, commenced a tirade upon modern scientists, and one of their ablest, said he would bring to shame the whole batch, and after annihilating Prof. John Tyndall, he would expose the heresy of Darwin, Huxly and Spencer; and his positions were so ridiculously unscientific, that I, in the judgement of sound thinkers in Louisville, annihilated him.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I sent to Prof. Tyndall one of my numbers, and he thought so well of it as to let me know he had received it, and I have his letter fraimed, to be seen in the Kentucky Musium, (Graham-Musium so called, becaus I bestowed it upon the Public Library,) and I am anxious to get a letter from you for the same purpose. I aim to get five letters only, from yourself, Tyndall, Huxly, Spencer and Draper,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> of our own country, which I purpose to have separately framed, and then inclosed in a large spledid frame, for our Musium and cabinet of Natural History, where I hope it may remain for centuries to come, by which time science will have gained the victory over ignorance and superstition.— Your Book has had a large circulation in Kentucky, and if I had any of my numbers of its defence on hand, I would send them to you.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Should you write, and I hope you may, let it be on one side only, of about the size of the smaller sheet, here inclosed, so that it can be framed.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I have one of the finest collections in the united states, the product of seventy years search throughout america, north and south, mostly fossils to which we have added the great Troost Cabinet of minerals, (at the cost of twenty five thousand dollars) said to be superior to Humboldts in <hi rend="italic">[</hi>Germania<hi rend="italic">]</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Supposing you may say, who are you thus boring me with your long letters, I will say, I am not John the baptist from the wilderness of locusts and wild honey and girdled about with leather, but one from the far wilderness of the far west of coons, opossums, wild beasts and savage forms, who not only girdled but dressed in leather. And now, I will say, my history has been published in full in the Histories of Kentucky, and the last devotes 60 pages to it and three pages to that of Mr. Clay, he being simply a politician and I having lived a long, rough and adventurous life.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>I was born in 1784 amidst the “<hi rend="underline">dark and bloody land</hi>”<ref target="#foot.f8"/> parted from savages and wild beasts, and being left an orphan without a friend or a dime in the world, it was to root pig or die, and better it was for me than to have heired a fortune and a herald of fame, as it threw me upon my own resources, which gave me health, strength and fortune, having retired on some two hundred thousand dollars. I never went to school in my life, and what book knowledge I have, has been acquired at night, never haveing lost one hour from active outdoor exertion through the day; and so far as I have published my thoughts, it has been from pencil notes set down in my various wanderings through the world, it being an illustrated book of nature ever open before me, and my own mind being present day and night, I thought for myself. I have been a soldier of three wars—first in 1812 against your country—secondly in the war of Mexico for independence from her mother country Spain, and thirdly, Jefferson Daveys, (late President of the southern Confederacy,) and myself, were messmates in the Black-hawk Indian war, of 1832.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I have been a prisoner twice by Indians, first in Canada, and secondly with the southern Comanchys and Appachys, on the borders of Mexico, and was once tied to be burnt.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I have spent two winters in Mexico, first during the civil war that dethroned the Emperor Iturbide in 1822,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> and again in 1852—was on one of the first railroad surveys to California—speculated at Chicago Galena and at the falls of St. Antony<ref target="#foot.f12"/>—hunted the Moose deer in the Adarhondic mountains, at the head of the great Hudson of New-York.— In short, I have checkered this continent over and over. I am now in my 93<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> year and my hand shakes so that I can with difficulty write, but my muscular strength and health is such that I can walk my 20 miles per day, and feel assured that I shall cast my first century behind me. In giving you a farther knowledge of ego, I—the <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> first person, I will say that Governor Bramlette of Kentucky, was a son in law of mine, General Adams of New Orleans also, and the Hon. Joseph Blackburn, a leader now in Congress, from Ashland, Mr. Clay’s district, is another<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>If Frederic Peal, son of Sir Robert, is living, he can tell you who I am, as he brought a letter to me from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Clay, and was with me, for a time, at Harrodsburg Springs, when on his way to the Mammoth cave.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Your Father’s writings were very popular in my class, when a student of medicine, and I feel assured that he was the very closest and most unerring observer, best of the animal and vegetable kingdoms that ever lived, and his doctrine of the sensorial powers will some day be granted as a mental axiom<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
                    <p>The reason why writers on the mind have been lost in wandering mazes and found no end, is that they have assumed an non entity, a thing that has no existence—and then nothing to show its powers. Mind, so called, is a result, some effect not a cause. You may see that I have <hi rend="italic">[</hi>examined<hi rend="italic">]</hi> and catered to popular sentiments, in my little book, as we must do, not to shock the faith of others too suddenly.</p>
<p>If you answer, direct to Doct. C. C. Graham, Public Library, Louisville, Kentucky, and if I am lucky with you, I will address Huxly and Spencer. I inclose you my advice to the wrangling parties for the Presidency, written a few days ago.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Most sincerely, | C. C. Graham, M. D.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">No publication by Graham has been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL or in the Darwin Library–Down. Graham may have sent a copy of his book <hi rend="italic">The true philosophy of mind</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Graham 1869</ref>); in it, Graham defended empiricism and attacked the clergy, while maintaining a broadly Christian outlook.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The clergyman has not been identified. Graham refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John William Draper</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The publications in which Graham defended <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> have not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD did reply in a now missing letter (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-12551.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from C. C. Graham, 28 March 1880</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 12551)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Graham had a large mineral collection and had excavated mammoth fossils at Big Bone Lick in 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10176.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duvall 2004</ref>, pp. 145–7). The mineralogical and fossil collection of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gerard Troost</ref>, consisting of over twenty thousand specimens, was sold to the Louisville Free Public Library by Troost’s estate in July 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Goldstein 1984</ref>, p. 142). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2443.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander von Humboldt</ref> had collected mineral specimens on his travels in North and South America and in Russia (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">NDB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The biography of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Clay</ref> in <hi rend="italic">A history of Kentucky</hi> was short, but he was mentioned several times throughout the book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. B. Allen 1872</ref>, pp. 236–8 and <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>). For the biography of Graham, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. B. Allen 1872</ref>, pp. 299–335.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In the last quarter of the eighteenth century, the Ohio River was often called ‘that dark and bloody river’ and the territory of the Ohio River Valley ‘that dark and bloody land’, in allusion to conflicts between settlers and indigenous people of the area (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Eckert 1995</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For more on the War of 1812, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10263.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. B. Turner 2000</ref>; on the Mexican War of Independence (1810–21), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10264.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McFarlane 2014</ref>; on the Black Hawk War (1832), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10265.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Trask 2006</ref>. Davis was a lieutenant in the First Infantry of the US Army during the Black Hawk War but did not take part in any fighting as he was on sick leave. He did escort Black Hawk (Mà-ka-tai-me-she-kià-kiàk), the leader of the Sauk rebellion, as prisoner to St Louis (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Scanlan 1940</ref>, pp. 178–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For the story of Graham’s capture by Indians near Fort Malden in Ontario and his escape, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. B. Allen 1872</ref>, pp. 309–10. While Graham was employed on the Survey of the Southern Atlantic and Pacific Railroad in 1852, his party was captured by Apaches and later ransomed (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10176.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duvall 2004</ref>, p. 148). There is no other mention of his having been captured by Comanches.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">In 1822, Graham went to Mexico City and was reputed to have smuggled out the constitution written for the new Mexican government (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10176.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duvall 2004</ref>, p. 148). Agustín de Iturbide was briefly emperor of Mexico, from May 1822 until his abdication in March 1823 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10610.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Britannica</hi></ref>, britannica.com, accessed 30 October 2015).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In 1832, Graham acquired a lead interest in the town of Galena, Illinois (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. B. Allen 1872</ref>, p. 313). The Falls of St Anthony were the only natural waterfalls on the Mississippi; the area began to be commercially developed in the 1830s (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10266.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wills 2005</ref>, pp. 17–27).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7939.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Elliott Bramlette</ref> married Mary Graham Adams, a widow, in 1874 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ANB</hi></ref>). Her first husband was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas E. Adams</ref>, a Confederate general. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7942.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Clay Stiles Blackburn</ref> married Theresa Graham in 1858 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_152.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ANB</hi></ref>). Graham probably alludes to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s</ref> ‘the adorable <hi rend="italic">I am</hi>’ or primal self (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10396.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Evans 2009</ref>, p. 330).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Graham had owned a spa at Harrodsburg Springs in Mercer County, Kentucky. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7943.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick Peel</ref>, son of Robert Peel, visited the establishment, bringing a letter of introduction from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Clay</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. B. Allen 1872</ref>, p. 334).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Erasmus Darwin, CD’s grandfather, had discussed his theory of sensorial powers in <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref>, 1: 32–3, 54–61).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">The enclosure has not been identified.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>