<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-38">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fanny Owen   [late January 1828]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5163</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-38 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-38.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-38.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 43</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 43</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3619.xml">Owen, F. M. (a)</persName>
                <placeName>[Brighton]</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1828-01-01" notAfter="1828-01-31">[late Jan 1828]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Tells him the Woodhouse family will set forth for return home.</p>
            <p>Reports on activities in Brighton.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Owen family</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Brighton</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Woodhouse</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">returning</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Brighton]</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Postillion,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You must have thought the <hi rend="underline">Housemaid</hi> most <hi rend="underline">awfully</hi> changed by the Brighton Air to suppose for a moment that she had dashed with <hi rend="underline">indignation</hi> your agreable letter into the flames and determined to treat its author with <hi rend="underline">merited disdain</hi>. The real reason why I did not long ago send you a <hi rend="underline">leetle</hi> effusion was that you told me you were going to <hi rend="underline">Cambridge</hi> the end of the month, now that word <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Cambridge</hi> sounded most formidable to my ears; I had visions of M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Burton</hi> <hi rend="underline">constantly</hi> starting up before me, which seemed to say, “Dear me Ma’am would you believe it Miss <hi rend="underline">Fanny Owen corresponds with a young man Ma’am</hi> at <hi rend="underline">the</hi> <hi rend="underline">University</hi>” this horrid phantom appear’d to me so often and worked upon my <hi rend="underline">heated fancy</hi> to such a degree that after <hi rend="underline">mature deliberation</hi> I thought it best to <hi rend="underline">remain silent</hi> and if the Postillion should be in a <hi rend="underline">fury</hi> at <hi rend="underline">my ingratitude</hi> to explain it all away when we shall meet once more at the Forest—&amp; now you see M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Burton has been the cause of all this I hope you will forgive the poor Housemaid— Of course you have heard of the wonderful event going to take place viz the Woodhouse family <hi rend="underline">actually</hi> going to set forth on their travels— Heaven grant the <hi rend="underline">old Van</hi> may not fall to peices before they reach <hi rend="underline">London</hi>: but I think it will be a miracle if it ever reaches its destination—</p>
<p>I suppose Shrewsbury is full of <hi rend="underline">gossip</hi> and <hi rend="underline">scandal</hi> as there has just been a meeting of all the surrounding families, to <hi rend="underline">stare at</hi> and talk <hi rend="underline">scandal</hi> of their neighbours— I suppose all the Shrewsbury young Ladies worked their <hi rend="underline">fingers ends</hi> off for the Bazaar, Caddy Pemby of course amongst the number &amp; I am very curious to hear what <hi rend="underline">they did</hi> and how the <hi rend="underline">valuable</hi> articles sold—it must have been good fun seeing <hi rend="underline">Miss Clarissa</hi> behind the Counter—</p>
<p>I was at a very gay Ball on Wednesday night plenty of <hi rend="underline">red Coats</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Moustachio’s</hi> which <hi rend="underline">you say must</hi> be pleasant I like Blue &amp; silver better—</p>
<p>I have been riding a great deal too lately which is very pleasant. When M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hill was here he got me a very nice Horse belonging to a <hi rend="underline">useful friend</hi> and since I have been riding with the Anson’s—</p>
<p>I must conclude this for I must write to my much injured Catherine— I only hope I may <hi rend="underline">appease you</hi> both &amp; excuse this scrawl but I have <hi rend="underline">such a Pen</hi> and besides never could write like any thing but what <hi rend="underline">I am</hi>, a <hi rend="underline">Housemaid</hi> so d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Postillion ever y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>| F Owen</p>
<p>Burn this as soon as read—or tremble at my fury and revenge—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>