<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5269">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Julius Victor Carus   7 November 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8683</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5269 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5269.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5269.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 53</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 53</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml">Carus, J. V.</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1866-11-07">7 Nov 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>JVC has been asked by Schweizerbart [CD’s German publisher] to revise H. G. Bronn’s translation of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>, and he will be pleased to try to do it.</p> 
            <p>Asks CD’s advice on what to do about Bronn’s notes and concluding chapter, with which JVC disagrees. Would CD agree to omission?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_657">Bronn, H. G.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">German publisher</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>39, Elsterstrasse | Leipzig,</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 7 1866.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Probably you will know already, that Mr. Schweizerbart, the publisher of Bronn’s translation of your work on the origin of species, has asked me to revise this translation, to mend and correct it as far as possible.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It is with the greatest pleasure that I will try to do it, partly because I am fully convinced that this work is the most important of our time, partly as it give me the opportunity to thank you not only for the copy of your work you sent me when it came out first,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but especially for the immense good you did with it to organic sciences in general. Yet, I should have scarcely ventured to write to you directly, if I had not to ask you to help me out of a puzzle. Surely the late Professor Bronn was one of our ablest naturalists and I have the greatest regard for his truly philosophical and earnest endeavours to bring Zoology on a higher, a more scientifical footing. But for one reason or another, because he was a “natural philosopher” of the old German school<ref target="#foot.f3"/> or because he was too much of a describing Zoologist, he was too anxious to allow your work to act freely upon the German public. According to the opinion of most of my younger colleagues he did not even deal fairly with it. I should not like to go as far as this, but I must confess, that I dislike strongly that sort of authoritative doubt and that sometimes quite ludicrous display of a so called higher scientific argumentation which he shows in his “Anmerkungen” and especially in his Epilogue.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But here comes my difficulty. You will be of course the most interested that your work should be presented to the German reader in a fair and unprejudiced form. Now do you think it fair of me, when I leave off all those remarks of Bronn’s which are according to my scientific conscience almost equal to nothing. Do you think it compatible with the due regard to Bronn’s memory if I was to separate his “Schlusswort”<ref target="#foot.f5"/> from the body of your work, with which it had nothing at all to do, and to modify it according to <hi rend="underline">my</hi> views of the question? I think I may do it. As the first two editions of his translation are existing, the history of the Science will take due notice of his position. But for my part I should not like to propagate his doubts, especially as I pointed already 1853 in my System of animal morphology (p. 5) to the <hi rend="underline">genealogical</hi> connexion of the present and past forms of animal life.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> If you would be so good as to write with one word that I may have liberty to do as I like best, I should be very much obliged to you.</p>
<p>Mr. Schweizerbart sent me some corrections Dr. Caspary had pointed out.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Most of these I knew before. With regard to the Guinea-fowl which is said to have been wrongly translated by Bronn, I must say, here Bronn was right. It is the Perlhuhn. But in that place you marked (p. 17 of the first English edition) you changed Guinea-fowl into Goose.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Allow me once more to say how much I am delighted to be able to associate my name in a way ever so humble with your work and believe me | My dear Sir | Yours most truly and respectfully. | Prof J. Victor Carus</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref> approached Carus to supervise the production of a translation of the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> after the job had been turned down by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2893.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav von Leonhard</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hans Bruno Geinitz</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 26 October 1866</ref> and n. 4). Two earlier German editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1860 and 1863) had been translated by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn</ref>, who died in 1862.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> had recommended Carus for CD’s presentation list for the first edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Carus refers to <hi rend="italic">Naturphilosophie</hi>: ‘the theory … that there is an eternal and unchanging law of nature, proceeding from the Absolute, from which all laws governing natural phenomena and forces derive’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). For more on <hi rend="italic">Naturphilosophie</hi> and research in natural history, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6587.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rehbock 1983</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jardine 1996</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had suggested that Bronn append ‘notes of <hi rend="italic">refutation</hi> or confirmation’ to the translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2687.xml" resp="#automat">letter to H. G. Bronn, 4 February [1860]</ref>). The first two German editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1860 and Bronn trans. 1863) contained several notes added by Bronn, elaborating on certain points or engaging in theoretical discussion of CD’s views. In addition, a twenty-five page epilogue written by Bronn attempted to guide the reader’s assessment of CD’s theory in light of Bronn’s own critical review of what he considered to be the main issues (see Bronn trans. 1860, pp. 495–520).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">‘Schlusswort’: epilogue.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to <hi rend="italic">System der thierischen Morphologie</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1289.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carus 1853</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_852.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Caspary’s</ref> letter to Schweizerbart has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, CD had changed the word ‘guinea-fowl’ to ‘goose’ in the sentence that, in the first three editions, read, ‘Has the little variability of the ass or guinea-fowl … prevented their domestication?’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 18, and Peckham ed. 1959, p. 90).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>