<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6918">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Victor Masson<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   29 September 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10066</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6918 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6918.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6918.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 64</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 64</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3214.xml">Masson, Victor et fils</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1869-09-29">29 Sept 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Asks CD to send 5th ed. of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> so Mlle Royer can use it in her work. Regret they have upset CD to the extent that he would reproach them so untowardly.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4113">Royer, C. A.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Masson, Victor et fils</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Paris, Place de l’Ecole-de-Médecine,</hi></placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="print">le</hi> 29 sept. 1869.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Nous ignorions absolument qu’une cinquième édition de votre <hi rend="underline">Origine des Espéces</hi> eût été publiée.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Il va de soi en effet que notre intérêt et celui de Madame Royer sont en cette affaire les mêmes que le vôtre, et que nous n’avions nulle raison pour faire quelque chose qui pût à la fois vous être désagréable, et diminuer la valeur de l’ouvrage que nous publions.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Madame Royer qui n’avait pas depuis longtemps eu le plaisir de recevoir de vos nouvelles, a fait l’achat de votre récent ouvrage pour s’en inspirer dans son travail.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Elle n’avait aucun motif pour ne pas acheter de même, si elle en avait su l’existence, la cinquième édition de <hi rend="underline">l’origine des Espèces</hi>, et en conférer le texte avec celui de sa traduction.</p>
<p>Nous écrivons par ce courrier à notre correspondant de Londres de nous envoyer un exemplaire, que nous remettrons à Madame Royer à son retour d’Italie où elle est en ce moment.</p>
<p>S’il est dans votre nouvelle édition quelque point que vous regrettez surtout de voir omis dans l’édition française, nous n’aurions quant à nous aucune répugnance à faire les frais d’un appendice de quelques pages, et nous vous prions de nous le signaler.</p>
<p>N’ayant jamais eu l’honneur jusqu’à présent d’etre en relations directes avec vous, nous regrettons vivement de vous avoir, bien involontairement, contrarié de telle sorte que votre première lettre contienne des reproches bien peu en rapport avec notre caractère, nos habitudes, et nous osons le dire, notre réputation dans le public savant.</p>
<p>Recevez Monsieur l’assurance de nos sentiments | très distingués | Victor Masson fils <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">M. Charles Darwin | Down | Beckenham | Kent. (S.E.)</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName><hi rend="print">Paris, Place de l’Ecole-de-Médecine,</hi></placeName>
        <date>29 Sept. 1869.</date>
        <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
       <div type="transcription"><p>We were absolutely unaware that a fifth edition of your <hi rend="underline">Origin of Species</hi> had been published.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p> 
        <p>It goes without saying that our interest and that of Madame Royer are the same as yours in this affair, and that we had no reason to do anything which might be disagreeable to you, while at the same time diminishing the value of the work we were publishing.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
        <p>Madame Royer, who had not had the pleasure of receiving any news from you for a long time, bought your recent work as a source of inspiration in her work.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Had she known of its existence, she had no motive not to buy the fifth edition of <hi rend="underline">the origin of Species</hi> as well, and to compare its text with that of her translation.</p> 
        <p>We are writing by this post to our London correspondent to send us a copy, which we shall give to Madame Royer on her return from Italy, where she is at present.</p> 
        <p>If there should be in your new edition any point which you would particularly regret to see omitted from the French edition, for our part we should have no objection to covering the cost of an appendix of several pages, and we beg you to indicate this to us.</p> 
        <p>Never having had the honour of being in direct communication with you until now, we deeply regret having, most unwittingly, displeased you to such an extent that your first letter contains reproaches that are most out of keeping with our character, our practices, and, we dare to claim, our reputation among the scientific public.</p> 
        <p>Please accept, Sir, the assurance of our most distinguished regards | Victor  Masson junior </p>   
        <p rend="left">Mr Charles Darwin | Down | Beckenham | Kent. (S.E.)</p></div>
        
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a translation of this letter in its original French, see pp. 415–16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The fifth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> was published in June (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from R. F. Cooke, 22 June 1869</ref>). CD had written to Masson to complain that a third French edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> had been prepared without reference to the fifth English edition (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Victor Masson, [after 29 September 1869]</ref>); however, no letter to Masson on this subject has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4113.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clémence Auguste Royer</ref> was the French translator of <hi rend="italic">Origin.</hi> Two editions had been published (Royer trans. 1862 and 1866). A third edition dated 1870 evidently appeared in 1869 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6955.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. J. Moulinié, 23 October [1869]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Masson refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>, which Royer discussed in her preface to Royer trans. 1870 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6955.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. J. Moulinié, 23 October [1869]</ref> and n. 5).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>