<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1241">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. S. Henslow   6 May 1849</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">12136</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1241 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1241.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1241.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">3pp C</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Darwin and Henslow</hi>: 163; <hi rend="italic">Emma Darwin</hi> 2: 123; <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 66 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 4: 235</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 145: 63 and Bernard Quaritch (dealers) (2023)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>145: 63</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_334.xml">Quaritch</repository>
                    <collection>(dealers)</collection>
                    <idno>2023</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Malvern</placeName>
                <date when="1849-05-06">6 May 1849</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml">Henslow, J. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes cold water cure he has been taking for two months at J. M. Gully’s establishment.</p>
            <p>Plans to go to BAAS meeting at Birmingham if health improves.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, good or improving</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2020">Gully, J. M.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Birmingham</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">meeting</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">BAAS</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">establishment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2023-10-06" status="alteredPostPublication">Corrected from image of original in auction catalogue</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>The Lodge, Malvern</placeName>
                    <date>May 6, 1849</date>
                    <salute>My dear Henslow</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    <p>Your kind note has been forwarded to me here. You will be surprised to hear that we all, children servants &amp; all have been here for nearly two months. All last autumn &amp; winter my health grew worse &amp; worse; incessant sickness, tremulous hands &amp; swimming head; I thought I was going the way of all flesh. Having heard of much success in some cases from the Cold Water Cure, I determined to give up all attempts to do anything &amp; come here &amp; put myself under D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gully. It has answered to a considerable extent: my sickness much checked &amp; considerable strength gained. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. G., moreover, (&amp; I hear he rarely speaks confidently) tells me he has little doubt but that he can cure me, in the course of time, time however, it will take. I have experienced enough to feel sure that the Cold Water Cure is a great powerful agent and upsetter of all constitutional habits. Talking of habits the cruel wretch has made me leave off snuff—that chief solace of life. We thank you most sincerely for your prompt and early invitation to Hitcham for Brit. Assoc. for 1850:<ref target="#foot.f1"/> if I am made well and strong, <hi rend="underline">most</hi> gladly will I accept it; but as I have been hitherto, a drive every day of half-a-dozen miles would be more than I could stand with attending any of the sections. I intend going to Birmingham, if able; indeed I am bound to attempt it, for I am honoured beyond all measure in being one of the V.P.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am uncommonly glad you will be there; I fear, however, we shall not have any such charming trips as Nuneham and Dropmore.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> We shall stay here till at least June 1st., perhaps till July 1st., and I shall have to go on with the aqueous treatment at home for several more months. One most singular effect of the treatment is, that it induces in most people, and eminently in my case, the most complete stagnation of mind: I have ceased to think even of Barnacles!</p>
                    <p>I heard sometime since from Hooker; but the letter was so purely Geological that I did not suppose it would interest Miss Henslow: How capitally he seems to have succeeded in all his enterprises. You must be very busy now: I happened to be thinking the other day over the Gamlingay trip to the Lilies of the Valley:<ref target="#foot.f4"/> are those were delightful days<ref target="#foot.f5"/> when one had no such organ as a stomach, only a mouth &amp; the masticating appurtenances. I am very much surprised at what you say, that men are beginning to work in earnest to Botany.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> What a loss it will be for Nat. History, that you have ceased to reside all the year in Cambridge.</p>
<p>My dear Henslow farewell yours most affectionately | C. Darwin</p>
<p>I hope that M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Henslow is much better: we are all flourishing.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">After the introduction of new regulations in 1848, the British Association listed the towns which had proferred invitations for future meetings. An invitation from Ipswich for 1849, ‘signed by the High Sheriff, the Bishop of Norwich, and eighty gentlemen of the Eastern Counties’, had been received by the British Association’s general committee at the meeting held in Swansea, 8–16 August 1848 (see <hi rend="italic">Report of the 19th meeting of the British</hi> <hi rend="italic">Association for the Advancement of Science held at Birmingham in 1849</hi>, p. xviii). Although Ipswich, close to Henslow’s parish of Hitcham, was evidently rejected for a meeting in 1849, the British Association may have planned to meet there in 1850, but, if so, the meeting was postponed until 1851. The 1850 meeting took place in Edinburgh.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD, much improved in health by September, was able to attend the British Association meeting. He was one of eight vice-presidents.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Henslow and his family had accompanied CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> on these outings to famous beauty spots at the time of the Oxford meeting of the British Association.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Wild lilies of the valley grew there (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref> 1: 67 n. 1). During CD’s undergraduate years, he and other young naturalists went on several entomological and botanical excursions to Gamlingay with Henslow.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The copyist wrote ‘are those were delightful days’, but the ‘are’ was probably a misreading of CD’s ‘ah’. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref>, who saw the original when editing <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref>, has ‘ah, those’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref> 1: 67).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">This refers to the improved status given to natural science in the universities as a result of educational reforms in 1848.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>