<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2767">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   25 April [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3518</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2767 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2767.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2767.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 174</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 24;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 305</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 166</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (13)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>13</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-04-25">25 Apr [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> reviews. Is annoyed at Richard Owen’s malignity [<hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Rev.</hi> 111 (1860): 487–532].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Ap. 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My dear Gray</p>
<p>I have no doubt I have to thank you for copy of a Review on the “Origin” in N. American Review.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It seems to me clever, &amp; I do not doubt will damage my Book. I had meant to have made some remarks on it; but Lyell wished much to keep it, &amp; my head is quite confused between the many Reviews which I have lately read. I am sure the Reviewer is wrong about Bees cells, ie about the distance; any lesser distance would do, or even greater distance, but then some of the planes would lie outside the generative spheres, but this would not add much difficulty to work—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The Reviewer takes a strange view of Instinct: he seems to regard intelligence as developed instinct; which I believe is wholly false.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I suspect he has never much attended to Instinct &amp; minds of animals, except perhaps by reading.</p>
<p>My chief object is to ask you if you could procure for me a copy of the New York Times for Wednesday March 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: it contains <hi rend="underline">a</hi> <hi rend="underline">very</hi> <hi rend="underline">striking</hi> review of my Book, which I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. much like to keep.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> How curious that about the two most striking Reviews (ie yours &amp; this) sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have appeared in America! This review is not really useful, but somehow is impressive.— There was good Review in the Revue des Deux Mondes April 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. by M. Laugel, said to be a very clever man.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Have you seen how I have been thrashed by Owen in last Edinburgh: he misquotes &amp; misrepresents me badly, &amp; how he lauds himself.— But the manner in which he sneers at Hooker is scandalous,—to speak of his Essay &amp; never allude to his work on Geograph. Distribution is scandalous.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> When Hooker’s Essay appeared Owen wrote a note, which I have seen, full of strongest praise! What a strange man he is. All say his malignity is merely envy because my Book has made a little noise. How strange it is that he can be envious about a naturalist, like myself, immeasurably his inferior! But it has annoyed me a good deal to be treated thus by a friend of 25 years duration. He might have been just as severe without being so spiteful.— Owen consoles himself by saying that the whole subject will be forgotten in ten years.—</p>
<p>Have you noticed how completely I have been anticipated by a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. P. Matthew, in Gardeners Chronicle.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Hooker about a fortnight ago staid here a few days &amp; was very pleasant; but I think he overworks himself. He is beginning to experimentise on various subjects at Kew, &amp; if he can but spare time I think he will be glad of it. He is going to try to degenerate our culinary vegetables. What a gigantic undertaking, I imagine, his &amp; Benthams Genera Plantarum will be!<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I hope he will not get too much immersed in it, so as not to spare some time for Geograph. Distribution &amp; other such questions.</p>
<p>I have begun to work steadily, but very slowly as usual, at details on Variation under domestication.</p>
<p>My dear Gray | Yours always truly &amp; gratefully | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.1 on] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘of’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.3 (ie yours &amp; this) 3.4] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.6 April 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">6.6 as not] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to the review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in the <hi rend="italic">North</hi> <hi rend="italic">American Review</hi> ([Bowen] 1860a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_566.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Bowen</ref>, professor of natural religion at Harvard University and a friend of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz’s</ref>, was the author of the review. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 18 [April 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">[Bowen] 1860a, pp. 494–9. In his copy of the review, CD wrote in pencil next to the discussion of bees’ methods of constructing cells: ‘All this mistaken’ ([Bowen] 1860a, p. 496).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Speaking of instinct, the reviewer stated that ‘in the infinite number of variations which he requires us to believe this faculty to have undergone, why has it never overstepped the clearly marked line which still divides it from reason?’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_824.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Bowen] 1860</ref>, p. 497). CD scored this passage in his copy of the review and added an exclamation mark in the margin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, 28 March 1860, p. 3, carried a long and generally favourable review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>. The review was unsigned, but the text suggests that it may have been written by James Hall, who was palaeontologist to the New York State Geological Survey. Referring to the most recent work on the earliest fossils in the geological record as support for CD’s theory, the reviewer stated that ‘the present writer had an opportunity last Summer, in company with Sir Wm. Logan, of examining a fossil from the Laurentian rocks of Canada—far older than the Silurian strata—which if it holds its authenticity, must be the intimation of a new and elder world of organic forms, into which research and induction may yet be prolonged.’ <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2978.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Edmond Logan</ref> was head of the Geological Survey of Canada. Although criticising some of CD’s views, the reviewer nonetheless stated: <quote type="quote"> It is clear that here is one of the most important contributions ever made to philosophic science; and it is at least behooving on scientists, in the light of the accumulation of evidence which the author has summoned in support of his theory, to reconsider the grounds on which their present doctrine of the origin of species is based. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Laugel 1860</ref>. There is an annotated copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">[R. Owen] 1860a. The article reviewed Hooker 1859 in addition to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 7 April 1860, pp. 312–13. See Appendix V. For CD’s reply to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Patrick Matthew</ref>, see letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [13 April 1860].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Bentham and Hooker 1862–83. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2728.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 12 March [1860]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>