<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-171">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. S. Henslow<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   18 May – 16 June 1832</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5217</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-171 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-171.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-171.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 22</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Darwin and Henslow</hi>: 52; <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 235 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 236</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Henslow letters: 12 DAR/1/1/12)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Henslow letters: 12 DAR/1/1/12</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Rio de Janeiro</placeName>
                <date when="1832-05-18">18 May &amp; 16 June 1832 </date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml">Henslow, J. S.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>His first letter to JSH since December. Recounts his seasickness, geologising and marine collecting at St Jago [Santiago, Cape Verde Is.]; his first tropical forest. Collecting small insects from the tropics. His Welsh trip with Sedgwick has been extremely valuable.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="date" ref="#">1831.12.00</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rio de Janeiro.</placeName>
                    <date>May 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1832</date>
                    <salute>My dear Henslow.—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have delayed writing to you till this period as I was determined to have a fair trial of the voyage. I have so many things to write about, that my head is as full of oddly assorted ideas, as a bottle on the table is with animals.— You being my chief Lord of the Admiralty, must excuse this letter being full of my’s &amp; I’s.— After our two attempts to put to sea in spite of the S.W.<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi> gales, the time at Plymouth passed away very unpleasantly.— I would have written, only I had nothing to say, excepting what had better be left unsaid: so that I only wrote to Shrewsbury.— At length we started on y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of December with a prosperous wind, which has lasted during our whole voyage:— The two little peeps at seasick misery gave me but a faint idea of what I was going to undergo.— Till arriving at Teneriffe (we did not touch at Madeira) I was scarcely out of my hammock &amp; really suffered more than you could well imagine from such a cause.— At Santa Cruz, whilst looking amongst the clouds for the Peak &amp; repeating to myself Humboldts sublime descriptions, it was announced we must perform 12 days strict quarantine.— We had made a short passage so “Up Jib” &amp; away for St Jago.— You will say all this sounds very bad, &amp; so it was: but from that to the present time it has been nearly one scene of continual enjoyment.— A net over the stern kept me at full work, till we arrived at St Jago: here we spent three most delightful weeks.— The geology was preeminently interesting &amp; I believe quite new:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> there are some facts on a large scale of upraised coast (which is an excellent epoch for all the Volcanic rocks to [be] dated from) that would interest M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lyell.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> One great source of perplexity to me is an utter ignorance whether I note the right facts &amp; whether they are of sufficient importance to interest others.— In the one thing collecting, I cannot go wrong.— St Jago is singularly barren &amp; produces few plants or insects.—so that my hammer was my usual companion, &amp; in its company most delightful hours I spent.—</p>
<p>On the coast I collected many marine animals chiefly gasteropodous (I think some new).— I examined pretty accurately a Caryophyllea &amp; if my eyes were not bewitched former descriptions have not the slightest resemblance to the animal.— I took several specimens of an Octopus, which possessed a most marvellous power of changing its colours; equalling any chamaelion, &amp; evidently accommodating the changes to the colour of the ground which it passed over.—yellowish green, dark brown &amp; red were the prevailing colours: this fact appears to be new, as far as I can find out.— Geology &amp; the invertebrate animals will be my chief object of pursuit through the whole voyage.— We then sailed for Bahia, &amp; touched at the rock of St Paul.— This is a Serpentine formation.— Is it not the only island in the Atlantic which is not <hi rend="underline">Volcanic</hi>?—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> We likewise staid a few hours at Fernando Noronha; a tremendous surf was running, so that a boat was swamped, &amp; the Captain would not wait.— I find my life on board, when we are in blue water most delightful; so very comfortable &amp; quiet: it is almost impossible to be idle, &amp; that for me is saying a good deal.— Nobody could possibly be better fitted out in every respect for collecting than I am: many cooks have not spoiled the broth this time; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brownes little hints about microscopes &amp;c have been invaluable.— I am well off in books, the Dic: Class: is <hi rend="underline">most useful</hi>.— If you should think of any thing or book that would be useful to me; if you would write one line E Darwin Whyndham Club<ref target="#foot.f5"/> St James Sq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.— He will procure them, &amp; send them with some other things to <hi rend="underline">Monte Video</hi>, which for the next year will be my head quarters.— Touching at the Abrolhos, we arrived here on April 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>; when amongst others I received your most kind letter: you may rely on it, during the evening, I thought of the many most happy hours I have spent with you in Cambridge.— I am now living at Botofogo, a village about a league from the city, &amp; shall be able to remain a month longer.— The Beagle has gone back to Bahia, &amp; will pick me up on its return.— There is a most important error in the longitude of S America, to settle which this second trip has been undertaken.— Our Chronometers at least 16 of them, are going superbly: none on record ever have gone at all like them.— A few days after arriving I started on an expedition of 150 miles to Rio Macaò, which lasted 18 days.— Here I first saw a Tropical forest in all its sublime grandeur.— Nothing, but the reality can give any idea, how wonderful, how magnificent the scene is.— If I was to specify any one thing I should give the preemenence to the host of parasitical plants.— Your engraving<ref target="#foot.f6"/> is exactly true, but underates, rather than exagerates the luxuriance.— I never experienced such intense delight.— I formerly admired Humboldt, I now almost adore him; he alone gives any notion, of the feelings which are raised in the mind on first entering the Tropics.—</p>
<p>I am now collecting fresh-water &amp; land animals: if what was told me in London is true, viz that there are no small insects in the collections from the Tropics.— I tell Entomologists to look out &amp; have their pens ready for describing.— I have taken, as minute (if not more so) as in England, Hydropori, Hygroti, Hydrobii, Pselaphi, Staphylini, Curculio, Bembididous insects &amp;c &amp;c.— It is exceedingly interesting observing the difference of genera &amp; species from those which I know. it is however much less than I had expected I am at present red-hot with Spiders, they are very interesting, &amp; if I am not mistaken, I have already taken some new genera.— I shall have a large box to send very soon to Cambridge, &amp; with that I will mention some more Natural History particulars.</p>
<p>The Captain does every thing in his power to assist me, &amp; we get on very well.—but I thank my better fortune he has not made me a renegade to Whig principles: I would not be a Tory, if it was merely on account of their cold hearts about that scandal to Christian Nations, Slavery.— I am very good friends with all the officers; &amp; as for the Doctor he has gone back to England.—as he chose to make himself disagreeable to the Captain &amp; to Wickham    He was a philosopher of rather an antient date; at St Jago by his own account he made <hi rend="underline">general</hi> remarks during the first fortnight &amp; collected particular facts during the last.—</p>
<p>I have just returned from a walk, &amp; as a specimen how little the insects are know.—Noterus, according to Dic Class. contains solely 3 European species, I, in one hawl of my net took five distinct species.— is this not quite extraordinary?.—</p>
<p>June 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.— I have determined not to send a box till we arrive at Monte Video.—it is too great a loss of time both for Carpenters &amp; myself to pack up whilst in harbor.— I am afraid when I do send it, you will be disappointed, not having skins of birds &amp; but very few plants, &amp; geological specimens small: the rest of the things in bulk make very little show.—</p>
<p>I received a letter from Herbert, stating that you have a vol: of Dic Class— Will you send it to Whyndam Club.— I suppose you are at this moment in some sea-port, with your pupils.— I hope for their &amp; your sake, that there will be but few rainy mathematical days.— How I should enjoy one week with you: quite as much as you would one in the glorious Tropics.—</p>
<p>We sail for Monte Video at the end of this month (June) so that I shall have been here nearly 3 months.— this has been very lucky for me.—as it will be some considerable period before we again cross the Tropic.— I am sometimes afraid I shall never be able to hold out for the whole voyage. I believe 5 years is the shortest period it will consume.— The mind requires a little case-hardening, before it can calmly look at such an interval of separation from all friends.— Remember me most kindly to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Henslow &amp; the 〈t〉wo Signoritas; also to L. Jenyns, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dawes 〈    〉 M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Peacock.— Tell Prof: Sedgwick he does not know how much I am indebted to him for the Welch expedition.— it has given me an interest in geology, which I would not give up for any consideration.— I do not think I ever spent a more delightful three weeks, than in pounding the NW mountains.— I look forward to the Geology about M. Video—as I hear there are slate there, so I presume in that district I shall find the junction of the Pampas of the enormous granite formation of Brazils.— At Bahia the Pegmatite &amp; gneiss in beds had same direction as observed by Humboldt prevailing over Columbia, distant 1300 miles: is it not wonderful?—</p>
<p>M Video will be for long time my direction:— I hope you will write again to me.— there is nobody, from whom I like receiving advice so much as from you.—</p>
<p>I shall be much obliged if you will get one of the engravings of poor M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ramsay &amp; keep it for me.— Excuse this almost unintelligible letter &amp; believe me dear Henslow—with the warmest feelings of respect &amp; friendship | Yours affectionately | Chas Darwin *S 2</p>
<p rend="left">June. 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</p>
<p>P.S. I found the other day a beautiful Hymenophallus, (but broke it to pieces in bringing home) &amp; with it an accompanying Leiodes.—a most perfect copy of the Barmouth specimen.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 my’s] ‘y’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘e’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.9 voyage] ‘v’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘g’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.17 from] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.18 arrived] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘came’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.22 that] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘&amp; I’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">1.26 &amp;] <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.2 some] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘many’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.2 Caryophyllea] <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>‘y’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘i’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">2.2 were] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘are’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">2.5 equalling] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘fa’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">2.9 will] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">2.11 Is] ‘s’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘t’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">2.16 out] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">2.23 Abrolhos] ‘Abrothos’ <hi rend="italic">in MS</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">2.27 a month] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘some’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">2.31 Rio] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">2.35 preemenence] <hi rend="superscript">3</hi>‘e’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘a’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">3.9 send] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘home’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">4.1 The] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Cap’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">4.3 not] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">5.3 I] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘&amp;’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">7.2 are] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘will’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">7.4 rainy] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘days’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">8.6 interval] ‘rva’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.21 ‘coast’; 1.22 ‘from’; 1.23 ‘ignorance’; 2.7 ‘&amp;’; 2.7 ‘up’; 3.7 ‘those’; 6.1 ‘box’; 6.2 ‘up’; 8.8 ‘Sedgwick’; 8.8 ‘know’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Henslow extracted passages from CD’s letters and, without his knowledge, read them to the Cambridge Philosophical Society. The extracts were then published with some editorial changes, usually minor, in a pamphlet privately printed for the Society (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3547.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henslow 1835</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 3–16). From this letter the following passages were extracted: <quote type="quote"> 1.8 ‘we started … December’ 1.8 1.18 ‘at St Jago … M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lyell.’ 1.22 1.25 ‘St Jago … companion’ 1.26 2.1 ‘On the coast … passed over.’ 2.7 2.10 ‘We then … formation.’ 2.11 2.23 ‘[After] Touching … April 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>’ 2.31 ‘A few days … 18 days.’ 2.32 3.1 ‘I am now … expected’ 3.6 5.1 ‘I have just … species.’ 5.3 8.14 ‘At Bahia … 1300 miles’ 8.16 </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s first field notebook (no. 1.4, now at Down House) contains geological observations of the Cape Verde Islands (briefly excerpted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi></ref>). More detailed notes are in the manuscript ‘Diary of observations on the geology of the places visited during the voyage, Part 1’ (DAR 32.1: 15–36). The Cape Verde mineralogical specimens are described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harker 1907</ref>. The entire collection is now in the Department of Earth Sciences, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Cambridge University</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">‘I had brought with me the first volume of Lyell’s <hi rend="italic">Principles of Geology</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4986.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1830–3</ref>), which I studied attentively; and this book was of the highest service to me in many ways. The very first place which I examined, namely St. Jago in the Cape Verde islands, showed me clearly the wonderful superiority of Lyell’s manner of treating geology, compared with that of any other author, whose works I had with me or ever afterwards read.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi></ref>, p. 77). Henslow had recommended that CD take the first volume of Lyell’s <hi rend="italic">Principles</hi> on the voyage, ‘but on no account to accept the views therein advocated’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 101). CD’s copy, preserved in Darwin Library–CUL, is inscribed ‘From Capt FitzRoy’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1783.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Darwin and Henslow</hi></ref>, p. 54 n. 1 for the modern view of the geology of St Paul Rocks.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Windham Club.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">This apparently refers to the French engraving ‘La Forêt du Brésil’. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-166.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Caroline Darwin, 25–6 April [1832]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-121.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Whitley, [9 September 1831]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-98.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Caroline Darwin, [28 April 1831]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>