<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10356">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   13 January 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5303</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10356 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10356.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10356.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 66</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 66</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1876-01-13">13 Jan 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends copy of <hi rend="italic">Arabische Korallen</hi> [1876].</p>  
<p>Comments on reception of his paper on "Gastrula" [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">10012</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Gastrula</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Arabische Korallen</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>13. Jan 76</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Hoffentlich haben Sie das neue Jahr in bester Gesundheit angetreten und arbeiten mit ungeschwächter Kraft an der Aufklärung der grossen biologischen Probleme, welche Sie durch die Reform der Descendenz Theorie und Ihre Begründung der Selections-Theorie der Wissenschaft geschenkt haben. Ich wünsche von Herzen, dass Ihnen Kraft und Lust dazu auch in diesen Jahre beständig bleiben möge!</p>
<p>Meine “Arabischen Korallen” werden Sie inzwischen erhalten haben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich hoffe dass Sie dem grossen Naturforscher, dem wir die Erklärung der merkwürdigen Korallen-Riffe verdanken, und der zuerst Licht in diese wunderbaren Producte gebracht hat, einige Freude bereiten mögen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In dieser Hoffnung bitte ich auch die Widmung der “<hi rend="underline">Monoxenia Darwinii</hi>”, als einer der einfachsten und primitivsten Korallen-Formen freundlich aufzunehmen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Es wäre mir sehr lieb, wenn Sie mir, hochverehrter Freund, Ihr kritisches Urtheil über die “Arabischen Korallen” zukommen lassen wollten.</p>
<p>Da Sie die Korallen-Bänke genauer studirt haben und besser kennen, als alle anderen Naturforscher, ist mir Ihr Urtheil darüber von ganz besonderem Werthe. Es würde mich sehr freuen, wenn die Darstellung der arabischen Korallenbank auf Taf. III Ihren Beifall finden sollte.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Mein Aufsatz über die “Gastrula und die Eifurchung” scheint unter den Fachcollegen mehr Beifall zu finden, als meine übrigen Arbeiten.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Mr. Ray-Lankester hat in der letzten Nummer vom “Quarterly Journal of Mikrosc. Science” einen Auszug in englischer Sprache gegeben.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Mit den besten Wünschen und den herzlichsten Grüssen bleibe ich auch im neuen Jahre, mein theurer Freund und Meister, | Ihr treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>13. Jan 76</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured, dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Hopefully you have started the new year in excellent health and are working with undiminished vigour on the elucidation of the great biological problems which you have given to science through your reform of the theory of descent and founding of the theory of selection. It is my heartfelt wish that your energy and your interest in the task may continue steadily also in the coming year!</p>
<p>My “Arabische Korallen” you will have received by now.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I hope they may delight the great naturalist to whom we owe the explanation of the extraordinary coral reefs, and who for the first time shed light on these marvellous products.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I beg you also to note that I named “<hi rend="underline">Monoxenia Darwinii</hi>” after you, as one of the simplest and most primitive forms among the corals.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I would appreciate it very much if you, most honoured friend, let me hear your critical views on the “Arabische Korallen”.</p>
<p>Since you have studied coral reefs more closely and know them better than any other naturalist, your judgment in this matter is of special value to me. I would be very pleased if the illustration of the Arabian coral reef on plate III met with your approval.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>My essay on the “Gastrula und die Eifurchung” appears to meet with more acclaim among my colleagues than all my other works.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Mr Ray-Lankester has provided a summary in English in the latest issue of “Quarterly Journal of Microsc. Science”.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>With the best wishes and my most cordial greetings I remain, my dear friend and master, also in the new year | Yours truly devoted | Ernst Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 16–18.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Arabische Korallen</hi> (Arabian corals; Haeckel 1876b) was a profusely illustrated book based on popular lectures with scientific explanations. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had published an explanation of the formation of coral reefs in 1842 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>). <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1572.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> 2d ed.</ref> had been published in 1874 and a German translation was published later in 1876 (Carus trans. 1876a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For Haeckel’s description and illustration of <hi rend="italic">Monoxenia Darwinii</hi>, see Haeckel 1876b, p. 12, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, p. 439. According to Haeckel, <hi rend="italic">Monoxenia</hi> was the earliest genus of Octocorallia (a subclass of Anthozoa (corals and sea anemones)), dating back to the Cambrian period (see Haeckel 1876b, pp. 77–8 and plate VI).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See Haeckel 1876b, plate III, facing p. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel had sent CD an offprint of ‘Die Gastrula und die Eifurchung der Thiere’ (The gastrula and egg-cleavage of animals; Haeckel 1875a); see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 7 November 1875</ref>. CD’s lightly annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester</ref> had summarised Haeckel 1875a in his paper ‘An account of Professor Haeckel’s recent additions to the gastræa-theory’ in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of Microscopical Science</hi> (Lankester 1876a).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>