<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-680A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Ernst Dieffenbach    4 July [1843]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20441</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-680A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-680A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-680A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">Hamburg 21 7 43</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 476–8</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Universitäts- und Landesbibliothek Darmstadt (Nachlass Künzel Br./3/VII/1)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_109.xml">Darmstadt</repository>
                    <collection>Nachlass Künzel</collection>
                    <idno>Br./3/VII/1</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1843-07-04">4 July [1843]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1322.xml">Dieffenbach, Ernst</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD gratified that ED wants to translate his <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>. Will send a copy of <hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi>, which contains a fuller treatment of topic. Perhaps ED would insert a note to this effect. Can lend woodcuts from <hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> if ED wants. CD will send a few corrections; he wants to amend way he criticised Agassiz’s glacier theory.</p> 
            <p>He is also enclosing a questionnaire concerning differences between races or varieties and species, about which he intends to publish sometime.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Journal</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">ice, ice-action, icebergs, glaciers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-09-07" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes">n.9</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | near Bromley | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>July 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have only this morning received your very obliging communication.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I assure you I have seldom been more gratified than at the distinction you have conferred on my Journal by translating it. I have some fears whether M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Colburn will permit the use of the Plate &amp; I am sure he will not gratis, but I have asked him to affix some price to it, &amp; if that price be moderate, I will willingly pay it &amp; transmit the plate for your use.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I will commence looking through my Journal &amp; will send you on thin paper a few corrections.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I transmit for your acceptance a copy of a small work on Coral-Reefs;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> perhaps you will be good enough to insert a note to the effect that the chapter in my Journal is only a <hi rend="underline">rough</hi> sketch of the facts &amp; details given in full in this work.— Would you like to have the use of the woodcuts, from my Coral-volume to illustrate that chapter; I could lend them you for no charge.— I also transmit copies of some papers; perhaps you will be so good as just to refer to the existence of two of them in notes—one to the account of the Concepcion earthquake<ref target="#foot.f5"/> —&amp; the other to the chapter, in which I treat of erratic boulders &amp; glaciers.— <ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Will you inform me pretty soon, whether you would like some of the woodcuts out of my coral-volume—<hi rend="underline">&amp; whether you intend to</hi> <hi rend="underline">print any part of the Appendix</hi>.— I would in that case wish the manner I speak of Agassiz altered, as I am ashamed of it, though convinced that his <hi rend="underline">extension</hi> of the glacier-theory is preposterous, though now fully aware what good service he has done in this department of Geology.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Would it be worth while for you to refer to Prof. Owens descriptions of the extraordinary fossils which I discovered in S. America.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I daresay there is a copy of the Zoology of the Beagle’s Voyage in Berlin &amp; the first Part contains descriptions of these fossils— I do not think it would take you long just to give a short sketch of these monsters, &amp; I think such a sketch would have some general interest.— I will endeavour not to make my corrections more bulky than I can help, &amp; I daresay if put in the form of a few notes, they would be the least trouble to yourself.— I hope that you as editor, with your extensive knowledge will add some criticisms or notes, which would add value &amp; interest to the work.</p>
<p>I have not yet read your work on New Zealand, though I have had it for some time on my list, having 〈been〉 <hi rend="underline">exceedingly</hi> interested by some extracts which ap〈peared〉 in the Gardeners Chronicle;—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I regret I saw 〈so〉 little of you before your long voyage:<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I 〈was〉 at that time much out of health, which is yet so far from reestablished &amp; has interrupted the prospects of my life, which I had anxiously hoped in a humble way to have devoted to science.—</p>
<p>It is most gratifying to me that your eminent countrymen Liebig &amp; the great Humboldt (to whose works I am indebted for my first wish to travel) should approve of my volume.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>You will see my address at the head of this letter—&amp; when you have leisure, I hope you will answer the foregoing queries: I will inform you of the result of my application to Colburn immediately that I receive his answer.—</p>
<p>Pray believe me dear Sir with much respect. | Yours very faithfully | C. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. I have been for some years employed in collecting facts in connection with the question of the difference between varieties or races &amp; species. This led me to print two or three years since some rather crude “Questions”—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Should you have an <hi rend="underline">unoccupied</hi> half hour at any time, would you oblige me by reading them over, &amp; make any remarks or answers (if such occur to you) on the margin &amp; return the paper to me. I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> feel greatly indebted, as “Species” is a subject, which I intend sometime to publish on.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.3 conferred] ‘r’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘f’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.4 is] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘was’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.4 <hi rend="italic">rough</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.7 the existence of 2.8] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.8 them] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘their’; <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘existence’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.4 convinced] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘fully’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.4 is] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.5 now] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.5 done] <hi rend="italic">before del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.12 if put in the form of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">3.12 they] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">8.3 rather crude] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dieffenbach’s letter has not been found. CD mentioned it in a <ref target="./DCP-LETT-680.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henry Colburn, 4 July [1843]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2). Dieffenbach had apparently informed CD of his intention to publish a German translation of CD’s <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi>. The translation appeared in 1844. A few pages of the translation, annotated by CD, are in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-680.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henry Colburn, 4 July [1843]</ref>. The publishing firm of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1004.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Colburn</ref> had issued both <hi rend="italic">Journal and remarks</hi> (1839) and the retitled version, <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi>, also published in 1839. The work contained two plates; CD refers to the map of South America, which was included in the German edition. See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Dieffenbach, 19 July [1843]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Dieffenbach, 15 August [1843]</ref>. The corrections were incorporated into the German edition.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> had been published by Smith, Elder, and Company in 1842. The woodcuts to which CD refers, illustrating the ring-forming atolls, are on pp. 2 and 3. Dieffenbach included them in the translator’s remarks at the end of the second part of the German edition (Dieffenbach trans. 1844, pt 2: 300).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">‘On the connexion of certain volcanic phenomena in South America’ (1840) (<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 53–86). This paper was not cited in the German edition.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">‘On the distribution of the erratic boulders and on the contemporaneous unstratified deposits of South America’ (1842) (<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 145–63). Dieffenbach cited this paper in his translator’s preface (Dieffenbach trans. 1844, p. x).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD refers to his criticism in the addendum of <hi rend="italic">Journal of</hi> <hi rend="italic">researches</hi>, pp. 617–8, of the views published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>. See also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-593.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Louis Agassiz, 1 March [1841]</ref>. Dieffenbach did not include the addendum in the German translation.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> described the fossil mammals from the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (<hi rend="italic">Fossil Mammalia</hi>). Dieffenbach cited Owen’s identification of several specimens in the remarks he appended to part one of the German edition (Dieffenbach trans. 1844, pt 1: 311, 312). An advertisement for <hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi> was also included at the back of the volume.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2036.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Dieffenbach 1843</ref>. The extracts were published in the <hi rend="italic">Gardener’s Magazine</hi> 19 (1843): 126–30. CD had entered the work into the ‘Books to be read’ section of his reading notebook and later recorded having read it on 30 November 1843 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4, Appendix IV, *119: 17v.; 119: 13a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Dieffenbach had lived in New Zealand between 1839 and 1841, acting as surgeon and naturalist to the New Zealand Company.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2443.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander von Humboldt’s</ref> praise of CD’s <hi rend="italic">Journal and</hi> <hi rend="italic">remarks</hi>, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 2, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-534.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alexander von Humboldt, 18 September 1839</ref>. See also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [3–17 February 1844]</ref>, in which CD told <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> that Dieffenbach translated his <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> ‘at the instigation of Liebig &amp; Humboldt’. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Justus von Liebig</ref> was a patron of Dieffenbach.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">For a transcription of CD’s ‘Questions about the breeding of animals’, drawn up in 1839, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 3, Appendix IV. There is no record of any reply from Dieffenbach.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>