<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12194">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   16 August 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5462</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12194 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12194.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12194.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B35–6</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B35–B36</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-08-16">16 Aug 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Regards his part only as material from which CD can select for English edition of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Regrets dropping comment on Erasmus Darwin’s evolutionary theory.</p>
            <p>Asks for translation of British plant names.</p>
            <p>Asks CD not to mention in introduction that EK’s part has been reduced.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">British</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1219">Darwin, Erasmus</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-24" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-04-27" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-31" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-11-19">Final proofreading queries checked <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00188_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00188_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        <surface n="B:35r" xml:id="i188">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00188.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00188_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00188.dzi" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:35v" xml:id="i189">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00189.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00189_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00189.dzi" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:36r" xml:id="i190">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00190.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00190_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00190.dzi" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:36v" xml:id="i191">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00191.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00191_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00191.dzi" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 16.8.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Aus Ihrem soeben empfangenen freundlichen Schreiben ersehe ich zu meinem grossen Bedauern, dass ich Ihnen—sehr wider meine Absicht!—eine Menge Schwierigkeiten, Bedenken und Hindernisse bereitet habe. Ich bitte Sie, mir darüber nicht böse zu sein; es wäre gewiss nicht geschehen, wenn ich diese Schwierigkeiten hätte voraussehen können. Aber wie ich mir erlaubte, Ihnen wiederholt zu sagen, habe ich meine Arbeit stets nur als <hi rend="underline">Material</hi> angesehen, aus dem Sie für die englische Ausgabe so viel oder so wenig entnehmen möchten, als Ihnen passend und geeignet erscheinen würde.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Ich bitte Sie daher nochmals dringend, hochverehrter Herr, der Publikation ganz diejenige Form geben zu wollen, welche Ihnen als die beste erscheinen wird, aber keinenfalls an ein Aufgeben des Planes zu denken, zumal Murray das Buch angezeigt hat, und die betreffende Notiz bereits durch alle möglichen englischen, französischen und deutschen Journale gegangen ist.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Auch heute zwar kann ich mich nicht enthalten zu glauben, dass für das deutsche, französische und amerikanische Publikum, die von Ihnen beabsichtigte Form zu fragmentarisch sein dürfte, denn unter Hunderten wird nicht <hi rend="underline">ein</hi> Leser im Stande sein, sich das Seward’sche Buch zu verschaffen, noch weiss auf dem Continent irgend Jemand etwas uber Canning’s Satire, oder könnte den botanischen Garten nachschlagen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Für das englische Publikum stimme ich Ihrer Ansicht überall bei, für das ausländische nicht.</p>
<p>Gleichwohl wird es mir als das Beste erscheinen, mich bei der deutschen Ausgabe genau an die englische anzuschliessen, weil ich vermeiden möchte, dass Sie an irgend einem Theile der deutschen Ausgabe Missfallen haben könnten.</p>
                    <p>Am wenigsten beklage ich den Wegfall der Bemerkungen über die Evolutionstheorie vor Dr. Erasmus Darwin; ich werde dieselben möglicherweise später einmal für sich im Kosmos geben, oder sie vielleicht bei einer ausführlichen Studie über die Geschichte des Descendenz-Gedankens verwerthen. Es ist daher an demselben keine Arbeit verloren und ich bedauere nur, Herrn Dallas die unnütze Mühe der Uebersetzung gemacht zu haben. Hat Ihnen Mr. Dallas das deutsche Manuscript mitgesendet, so möchte ich es von Ihnen zurückerbitten, sonst wende ich mich an denselben direkt?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Eine grosse Freude macht es mir, zu hören, dass Sie Ihre Ergänzungen, wie Sie es anfangs beabsichtigten, als Präliminar-Notiz voranstellen wollen. Es erschien mir das immer als das weitaus richtigste.</p>
                    <p>Da ich während des Septembers fortwährend auf Reisen sein werde, so möchte ich Sie bitten, falls der Druck des englischen Originals in dieser Zeit beginnen sollte, die Probebogen an meinen Freund, den Lehrer am französischen Gÿmnasium Dr. <hi rend="underline">Paul Voelkel</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Berlin, <hi rend="underline">Friedrich</hi>strasse (nicht <hi rend="underline">Frieden</hi>strasse!) 105. C. IV senden lassen zu wollen. Derselbe würde mir dann in der Uebersetzung etwas vorarbeiten, damit die deutsche Ausgabe nicht allzuspät käme.</p>
                    <p>Für den Fall, dass Sie den kleinen hübschen Brief, mit der Vorschrift: “To make love” aufnehmen wollen, möchte ich Sie noch um gütige Auskunft darüber bitten, ob die nachstehenden deutschen Volksnamen den englischen Pflanzennamen entsprechen würden:<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>1, Sweet-William, Bartnelke, Dianthus barbatus. (Hier würde im Deutschen wahrscheinlich besser Stolzer Heinrich (Inula Helenium) gesetzt werden müssen, da wir keinen entsprechenden Volksnamen für die Bartnelke haben.)</p>
<p>2, Honestÿ, Ehrenpreis (Veronica)?</p>
<p>3, Herbe of grace, Gnadenkraut, Gratiola?</p>
<p>4, Eye-bright, Augentrost, Euphrasia?</p>
<p>5, Motherwort, Mutterkraut, Pyrethrum Matricaria?</p>
<p>6, Heart’s Ease, Herzenstrost, Viola tricolor?</p>
<p>7, Cuckold-Pint, Kuckuckblume, Orchis?</p>
<p>8, Heart-Chokes, Herzgespann, Leonurus cardiaca?</p>
                    <p>9, Violents, wohl nur Wortspiel mit violent und violet? Oder giebt es eine violent genannte Pflanze?<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>Schliesslich möchte ich Sie noch bitten, in der Vorrede lieber nicht zu erwähnen, das meine Skizze gekürzt werden musste; das Publikum, welches den eigentlichen Sachverhalt nicht kennt, würde das leicht missverstehen und glauben können, meine Darstellung sei so weitschweifig und fehlerhaft gewesen, dass sie einer bedeutenden Kürzung bedurft hätte.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>Sollte ich—was in diesem Augenblicke nicht in meiner Absicht liegt,—bei der deutschen Ausgabe einige Erweiterungen für nützlich halten und hinzufügen, so würde es genügen, wenn ich in einer Vorrede zur deutschen Ausgabe bemerkte, es seien in der englischen Ausgabe aus guten Gründen Einzelnheiten weggeblieben, die dort theils zu bekannt, theils in leicht zugänglichen englischen Werken enthalten seien.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Ich glaube aber, wie gesagt, nicht, dass das geschehen wird, möchte mich vielmehr möglichst <hi rend="underline">wörtlich</hi> an die englische Ausgabe halten und bitte Sie noch mals herzlichst, dieselbe ganz nach Ihrem Ermessen zu gestalten, denn <hi rend="underline">Ihre</hi> Ansicht muss hier die <hi rend="underline">allein</hi> maassgebende bleiben. Ich bin böse auf mich, dass ich Ihnen soviel Skrupel und Zweifel, Mühe und Arbeit gemacht habe, aber ich bitte Sie zu glauben, dass es in der besten Absicht, optima fide, geschehen ist.</p>
<p>Mit dem Wunsche, dass Ihnen Ihr Sommeraufenthalt möglichst viel Freude und Erholung bringen möge, zeichne ich, hochverehrter Herr | Ihr | herzlich ergebener | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>7.4 Dr. … Berlin,] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.4 <hi rend="italic">Friedrichstrasse</hi> … käme. 7.6] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">new</hi> Address in Berlin | List of Plants for Krause’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">[</hi>Rengger<hi rend="italic">]</hi>’<ref target="#foot.f11"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>16.8.79.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>From your kind letters, just now received, I gather to my great regret that—very much against my intention!—I have given you a lot of difficulties, worries, and problems. I ask you not to be upset with me for this; it would certainly not have happened had I been able to foresee these difficulties. However, as I ventured to tell you repeatedly, I always considered my work simply as <hi rend="underline">material</hi> from which you could take as much or as little for the English edition as would seem appropriate and suitable to you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Thus I strongly advise you again, esteemed Sir, to give the publication just the shape you deem best, but on no account to consider giving up on the project, since Murray has already advertised the book and the notice in question has already appeared in all possible English, French, and German journals.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>But even now I cannot stop thinking that the form you intend would prove too fragmentary for the German, French, and American audiences, for there won’t be a <hi rend="underline">single</hi> reader among hundreds who will be able to get hold of Seward’s book, nor is anyone on the Continent acquainted with Canning’s satire, or able to look up the Botanical Garden.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> For the English audience I agree with your views entirely, but not for audiences abroad.</p>
                    <p>All the same it strikes me as best for the German edition to follow the English one exactly, since I would like to avoid the possibility of your being displeased with any part of the German edition.</p>
                    <p>I regret least the omission of the remarks on the theory of evolution before Dr. Erasmus Darwin; possibly I will offer them separately in Kosmos sometime later, or perhaps I shall use them for a more detailed study on the history of thought about descent. Thus no labour is lost and I only regret having caused Mr Dallas the unnecessary trouble of translating it. If Mr Dallas has sent you the German manuscript as well, may I have it back, or should I approach him directly?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>It greatly pleases me to hear that you want to put your supplementary remarks, as you intended on the outset, at the beginning, as a preliminary notice. This always struck me as most appropriate by far.</p>
                    <p>As I shall be travelling constantly during September, I would like to ask you, if printing of the English original resumes then, to have the galley proofs sent to my friend Dr <hi rend="underline">Paul Voelkel</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> a teacher at the French grammar school, Berlin, <hi rend="underline">Friedrich</hi>strasse (not <hi rend="underline">Frieden</hi>strasse!) 105. C. IV. He could then make a start on the preparations for the translation, so that the German edition would not appear too late.</p>
                    <p>In case you want to include the pretty little letter, with the prefix: “To make love”, I would ask you to kindly confirm whether the following German common names correspond to the English plant names:<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>1, Sweet-William, Bartnelke, Dianthus barbatus. (It would probably be better to insert Stolzer Heinrich (Inula Helenium) in the German translation, as we don’t have a corresponding common name for the Bartnelke.)</p>
<p>2, Honesty, Ehrenpreis (Veronica)?</p>
<p>3, Herbe of grace, Gnadenkraut, Gratiola?</p>
<p>4, Eye-bright, Augentrost, Euphrasia?</p>
<p>5, Motherwort, Mutterkraut, Pyrethrum Matricaria?</p>
<p>6, Heart’s Ease, Herzenstrost, Viola tricolor?</p>
<p>7, Cuckold-Pint, Kuckuckblume, Orchis?</p>
<p>8, Heart-Chokes, Herzgespann, Leonurus cardiaca?</p>
                    <p>9, Violents, probably just a wordplay on violent and violet? Or is there a plant that is called violent?<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>Lastly I would like to ask you please not to mention in the preliminary notice that my sketch had to be cut; readers who are unaware of the real circumstances might easily misunderstand this and come to think that my account had been so longwinded and riddled with mistakes that it needed to be pruned considerably.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>If—and at this moment this is not my intention—I should come to deem it useful for the German edition to make a number of additions, it would suffice if I remarked in the introduction to the German edition that for good reasons a number of details had been omitted from the English edition, partly because they are generally known, partly because they are contained in easily accessible English works.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>As I said, however, I doubt that this will happen, rather, I intend to follow the English edition as <hi rend="underline">literally</hi> as possible and would like to ask you cordially again to shape it wholly as you deem appropriate, for <hi rend="underline">your</hi> opinion must remain in this the <hi rend="underline">solely</hi> decisive one. I am angry with myself for having caused you so many scruples and doubts, so much trouble and work, but I beg you to believe it happened in the best of faith, optima fide.</p>
<p>Hoping that your summer holiday may bring you as much joy and rest as possible, I remain, most esteemed Sir | Yours | cordially devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 368–70.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause</ref> of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12192.xml">13 August 1879</ref>, CD had suggested substantial cuts to Krause’s manuscript for the English edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">John Murray</ref> had agreed to publish <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12080.xml">letter from John Murray, 3 June [1879]</ref>. For examples of advertisements and announcements, see <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 12 July 1878, p. 6, <hi rend="italic">Newcastle Courant</hi>, 18 July 1879, p. 6, and <hi rend="italic">Sheffield Independent</hi>, 19 July 1879, p. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Krause refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the life of Dr. Darwin</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_820.xml">George Canning</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1756.xml">John Hookham Frere’s</ref> poem ‘The loves of the triangles’ (a parody of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> poem <hi rend="italic">The loves of plants</hi> (part 2 of <hi rend="italic">The botanic garden</hi>); <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2674.xml">[Frere and Canning] 1798</ref>), and Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">The botanic garden</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Krause reinstated the section on evolutionary ideas before Erasmus Darwin in the German edition of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 78–124). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> had translated Krause’s German manuscript into English for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12184.xml">letter from W. S. Dallas, 6 August 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8480.xml">Paul Maximilian Voelkel</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Erasmus Darwin claimed to have discovered an old ‘receipt book’ in the closet of his bedchamber, entitled ‘A Bouk off verry monny muckle vallyed Receipts bouth in Kookery and Physicks’, one of which, ‘To make Love’, he transcribed in the letter to his fiancée, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8390.xml">Mary Howard</ref>, shortly before their wedding  (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml">King-Hele 1999</ref>, pp. 30–1). CD quoted the letter in full in his preliminary notice to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 21–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The German name for <hi rend="italic">Dianthus barbatus</hi>, ‘Bartnelke’, translates literally as bearded carnation. ‘Honesty’ is the common name of plants of the genus <hi rend="italic">Lunaria</hi>, known in German as ‘Silberblatt’ (silverleaf); ‘Ehrenpreis’ (literally, honour prize) is speedwell (plants of the genus <hi rend="italic">Veronica</hi>). ‘Herb of grace’ typically refers to rue in English (<hi rend="italic">Ruta graveolens</hi>) but can also refer to hedge-hyssop (<hi rend="italic">Gratiola officinalis</hi>), which in German is ‘Gnadenkraut’. Eyebright, or in German ‘Augentrost’ (literally, ‘eye comfort’), is the genus <hi rend="italic">Euphrasia</hi>. Motherwort is <hi rend="italic">Leonurus cardiaca</hi>; the German ‘Mutterkraut’ (mother herb) is feverfew (<hi rend="italic">Pyrethrum matricaria</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Tanacetum parthenium</hi>). Heart’s-ease is one of many common names for <hi rend="italic">Viola tricolor</hi>; in German, ‘Herzenstrost’ (‘heart comfort’) is an old name for horsemint (<hi rend="italic">Mentha longifolia</hi>). Cuckoo pint is <hi rend="italic">Arum maculatum</hi>; cuckoo flower is <hi rend="italic">Cardamine pratensis</hi>; ‘Kuckkuck Blume’ is an old German name for this species, which is in the mustard, not the orchid, family. The artichoke (heart-choke) is <hi rend="italic">Cynara cardunculus</hi>; the German ‘Herzgespann’ (from an old German word for a feeling of pressure on the heart) is motherwort (<hi rend="italic">Leonurus cardiaca</hi>), a traditional treatment for heart disease and anxiety. ‘Violents’ was a play on ‘violets’ and ‘violence’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD had suggested that he make a statement in the preface to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref> that Krause had enlarged his article in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>) and that Krause had given him permission to condense it for English readers; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12192.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 13 August 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In the German edition, Krause reinstated two introductory sections and added over 100 pages of notes (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>, pp. 75–124, 180–286).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD’s annotations are notes for his reply of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12198.xml">19 August [1879]</ref>.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>