<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8802">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Henry Reeks   8 March 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10459</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8802 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8802.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8802.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 82</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 82</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3956.xml">Reeks, Henry</persName>
                <placeName>Newbury</placeName>
                <date when="1873-03-08">8 Mar 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Insists that suckling babies pound and scratch mothers’ breasts. Perhaps CD’s evidence to the contrary comes from ladies, who only expose small portion of bosom, as opposed to working-class women.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">working-class</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>North End, | East Woodhay, | Newbury—</placeName>
                    <date>March 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1873</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I found your kind letter here tonight on my return from my home at Thruxton, and I beg to thank you sincerely for it, and for kindly writing my name in “Expression of the Emotions”<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I have the more pleasure in thanking you for your very kind and complimentary letter because I know how thoroughly you appreciate careful and accurate observations. Soon after I commenced studying natural history—now nearly 20 years ago—I remember reading an observation by Swammerdam<ref target="#foot.f2"/> to the effect that any misrepresentations were bound very soon to be found out, and I have always kept this very truthful remark fully in my mind. I was rather surprised to hear that you had no actual evidence of children “pounding” (or, as I termed it “kneading”) when sucking the breast.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Surely you have seen a young mother raise her hand and remove from her breast the tiny hand of her sucking infant: or have heard the, to me, familiar exclamation of “I must cut your nails, sweet pet; you begin to scratch”! It must be borne in mind that ladies when suckling their infants expose only the smallest possible portion of their breast; while the wives of farm laborers, especially during the summer, expose almost the whole of the bosom, and this gives the child a much better opportunity for pushing with its little hand while sucking. I have myself seen scratches on the bosoms of laboring women when suckling their children in the harvest field, and have been assured by them that they were done by the hands of their infants. Again, if the sock of a child is off when sucking you may almost invariably notice that it will repeatedly double and straighten its toes, which exactly corresponds to the habit described of my brother, only, from the position of a child when sucking, the foot cannot be pressed against any portion of the body of its mother.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I am sorry that I cannot give you any information about the drawing back of the ears of boars with well developed tusks when fighting, simply because we never allow such formidable animals to come in collision with each other: the encounter would probably prove fatal to one of them, and it would be highly dangerous to attempt to separate them; but I have seen boars with fairly developed tusks draw back their ears when apparently enraged with sows, which we have endeavoured to mate with them.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>From your lucid description of the trembling experienced after killing the first snipe I fancied that you must either be alluding to yourself, or that you must have been <hi rend="underline">with</hi> the youth at the time.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I should, perhaps, oftener give myself the pleasure of writing to you, but that I feel you must sometimes exclaim “I wish that everyone that wrote to me had to bring their own letters!” This would certainly keep back a multiplicity of useless correspondence— What I wish you would kindly do is this: when you have any problem which you think ought to be solved by any intelligent farmer, or really working naturalist that you will not hesitate to submit it to me. If I cannot answer it I will candidly say “don’t know,” but I trust very frequently to be able to help you.</p>
<p>An eighteen miles’ drive today, over the highest range of Hampshire Hills, in this cold wind has given me a wretched sick headache; I must, therefore, conclude with very kind regards, &amp; | Believe me, dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin, | very faithfully yours, | Henry Reeks <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To | C. Darwin, Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. FRS. &amp;c. &amp;c</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I found … mind. 2.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 I am sorry] <hi rend="italic">opening square bracket pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.3 the encounter … with them. 3.7] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 From … time. 4.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8703.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Reeks, 3 March 1873</ref> and n. 1, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8796F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henry Reeks, 5 March [1873]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4636.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jan Swammerdam</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8703.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Reeks, 3 March 1873</ref> and n. 2, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8796F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henry Reeks, 5 March [1873]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">William L. P. Reeks; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8703.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Reeks, 3 March 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8796F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henry Reeks, 5 March [1873]</ref>. Reeks’s observation was added to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2401.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 119 n. 39; the second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> was published after CD’s death.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8796F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Henry Reeks, 5 March [1873]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>