<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4190">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   28 May [1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14754</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4190 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4190.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4190.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 92</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 92</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>Edinburgh Botanic Gardens</placeName>
                <date when="1863-05-28">28 May [1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends abstract from <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Courant</hi> of his orchid sterility paper [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">4087</hi>]. Balfour altered title to obscure its theoretical nature.</p> 
            <p>Sends specimens showing curious variation.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchid</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Edinburgh Courant</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_259">Balfour, J. H.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Scott, John 1863</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Botanic Gardens [Edinburgh]</placeName>
                    <date>May 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I enclose copy from the Edinburgh Courant, of notice of late meeting of the Bot. Soc.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The abstract of paper on Orchid I made at the request of the Secretary;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> as I did it hurriedly with pencil, however, he has copied it very incorrectly; indeed in one place it is impossible to understand it at all. This I have attempted to correct in enclosed copy.— Similar mistakes will therefore be occurring in Gard. Chron.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It is very teasing.</p>
<p>You will perhaps be surprised at title now given. I think it is much less appropriate than the one I originally intended—Individual Sterility of Orchids: which clearly defined its nature.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Prof. Balfour proposed that now substituted: it has given it the appearance of a simple record of experiments destitute of any theoretical application.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The general reader at least will be somewhat surprised on passing from title to introductory remarks on Sterility! I was also anxious to emphasize the possibly individually limited nature of sterility manifested under my experience. Some may now be inclined to attribute to me a belief in the general sterility of their cultivated individual representatives; which is far from the truth. Indeed—as I have already stated—I am inclined to suppose that this will rarely if ever be the case—structural dimorphism of course excepted— certainly in cases of <hi rend="underline">Passiflora</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Lobelia</hi> <hi rend="underline">fulgens</hi>, it has only a limited application. <hi rend="underline">Individual</hi> plants of the latter, as well as the former, produce <hi rend="underline">seeds</hi> with <hi rend="underline">own</hi> <hi rend="underline">pollen</hi>—while others are absolutely <hi rend="underline">self-sterile</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Perhaps farther illustrations may be afforded after the notice of my experiments in Gard. Chron. In the event of such it will be necessary to state the existence of an <hi rend="doubleUnderline">individual</hi> <hi rend="underline">sterility</hi>; otherwise, they might be thought to disprove mine: as I have made no special allusion to it.</p>
<p>Will you kindly excuse the liberty I take, in asking you—time &amp; health permitting—to reply and afford an explanation of the different results.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>In notice you will also find a curious case of variation—at least the writer seems to consider it such—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Perhaps, I am wrong, in regarding it as of a similar nature to the well-known <hi rend="underline">laburnum case.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f10"/> The specimens sent are much mutilated—from careless packing—which prevents satisfactory comparisons; otherwise we might have been better able to judge. Differing, however, as it does in so many characters from the supposed normal form—more evidence is certainly required before we can regard it as simply a “<hi rend="underline">bud-variation</hi>”.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>I remain | Sir | Yours very respectfully | J. Scott</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.1 You will … nature 2.3] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.12 <hi rend="italic">Individual</hi> plants … <hi rend="italic">self-sterile</hi> 2.13] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 In notice … variation—] <hi rend="italic">cross in margin, brown crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi> of 28 May 1863 (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Scott refers to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi>, 28 May 1863, p. 8, which carried an article on the meeting of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh on 14 May 1863. See also n. 3, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Scott refers to an abstract of his paper on pollination experiments with orchids, which was read before the Botanical Society of Edinburgh on 14 May 1863. The paper was later published in full in the transactions of the society (Scott 1863a). There is a copy of Scott 1863a in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. The honorary secretary of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1981.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Kaye Greville</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5344.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Medical directory</hi></ref> 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">An abstract of Scott’s paper on pollination experiments with orchids (see n. 3, above), also appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 13 June 1863, p. 558. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, [3 June 1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Scott’s paper was entitled ‘Experiments on the fertilisation of orchids in the Royal Botanic Garden of Edinburgh’ (<hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi>, 28 May 1863, p. 8). The paper demonstrated the sterility of several species of <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi> when flowers were pollinated with pollen from the same plant (‘individual sterility’), and also showed that the same plants could be successfully fertilised when pollinated with pollen from a different species of <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">As regius keeper of the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hutton Balfour</ref> was Scott’s employer, as well as a leading figure in the Botanical Society of Edinburgh. Scott’s main theoretical point was that as there were varying degrees of sterility in the vegetable kingdom, which did not necessarily conform to recognised systematic affinities, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley’s</ref> use of sterility as the crucial test of the origin of species by natural selection (T. H. Huxley 1863b, pp. 107–8) was flawed (Scott 1863a, pp. 543–5). For a discussion of the background to this debate, see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix VI.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Scott expressed similar reservations about the general applicability of observations documenting own-pollen sterility in <hi rend="italic">Passiflora</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lobelia</hi> in his letters to CD of 3 March 1863 and 21 March [1863]. CD had encouraged Scott to experiment with <hi rend="italic">Passiflora</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lobelia</hi> to provide data on plants more easily fertilised by the pollen of another species than by their own pollen (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, letters to John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">19 November [1862]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">11 December [1862]</ref> and n. 21). He sent further information to assist Scott in his experiments on <hi rend="italic">Passiflora</hi> in March 1863 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4021.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 3 March 1863</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4031.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 6 March 1863</ref>). Scott published his observations on sterility in self-pollinated <hi rend="italic">Passiflora</hi> in Scott 1864d; they are summarised in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 137–8. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref> and n. 7. <hi rend="italic">Lobelia fulgens</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">L. cardinalis</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The reference is to a letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Bell</ref>, read at the meeting of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh, 14 May 1863, describing a plant of <hi rend="italic">Hibiscus tricuspis</hi> that produced branches bearing leaves and flowers widely different from the normal forms (<hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi>, 28 May 1863, p. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Cytisus adami</hi>, Adam’s laburnum, was thought to be a hybrid between <hi rend="italic">C. laburnum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. purpureus</hi>, two very distinct species. This tree was described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 387: ‘Throughout Europe, in different soils and under different climates, branches on this tree have repeatedly and suddenly reverted to both parent-species in their flowers and leaves’. CD did not regard this as a case of bud-variation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 389–91).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD defined bud-variation as ‘sudden changes in structure or appearance which occasionally occur in full-grown plants in their flower-buds or leaf-buds’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 373). CD did not include the case of <hi rend="italic">Hibiscus tricuspis</hi> in the chapter on bud-variation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 373–411). CD had asked Scott to send examples of bud-variation (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3991.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 16 February [1863]</ref> and n. 7).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>