<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9901">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Oswald Heer<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   23 March 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14325</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9901 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9901.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9901.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 131</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 131</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2199.xml">Heer, Oswald</persName>
                <placeName>Zurich</placeName>
                <date when="1875-03-23">23 Mar 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses his work [<hi rend="italic">Flora fossilis Arctica</hi>, vol. 4, pt 1 (1876)].</p>  
<p>Sends copy of [<hi rend="italic">Fossile Pflanzen von Sumatra</hi> (1874)]. Comments on climate in Tertiary period, especially on Sumatra.</p> 
            <p>Comments on theory of Thomas Belt concerning climatic change in ice age.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">glacial age</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Tertiary</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Flora fossilis Arctica</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fossile Pflanzen von Sumatra</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_383">Belt, Thomas</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Heer, Oswald 1874</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Heer, Oswald 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Zürich</placeName>
                    <date>23 März 1875.</date>
                    <salute>Mein geehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Empfangen Sie meinen wärmsten Dank für Ihren freundlichen Brief vom 8<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi>. März, welcher mir eine sehr grosse Freude gemacht hat.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Es ist für mich eine grosse Aufmunterung zu sehen, dass Sie so warmen Antheil an meinen Arbeiten über die arctische Flora nehmen u. wünsche nur, dass die neuen Beiträge zur fossilen Flora Spitzbergens, für welche gegenwärtig die Tafeln lithographirt werden, geeignet seien, diess Interesse zu erhalten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Sie bringen die eigentliche Carbon Flora u. Jura Flora Spitzbergens und füllen damit eine grosse Lücke in der Entwicklungsgeschichte der hoch nordischen Pflanzenwelt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Gewiss wäre es im höchsten Grade wünschenswerth ähnliche Sammlungen von der Südlichen Hemisphaere zu erhalten. Die Aussichten dafür sind aber nicht günstig. Doch gieng mir wenigstens ein lebhafter Wunsch in Erfüllung, nemlich fossile Pflanzen aus der Tropenwelt zu erhalten. Ich habe Ihnen in diesen Tagen eine kleine Abhandlung über tertiäre Pflanzen Sumatras übersandt.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Seither erhielt ich eine zweite reichere Sendung von da, welche der frühern etwa 20 neue Arten hinzufügt, so dass wir doch schon einige wichtigen Fingerzeige über das Aussehen der Flora Indiens zur Tertiarzeit bekommen.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Sie zeigen uns, dass die Tertiär Flora Sumatras der jetzt dort lebenden sehr ähnlich ist, sich also zu derselben ganz anders verhält als die Tertiär Flora der Schweiz zu der Jetztlebenden oder gar als die Tertiäre arctische Flora zu der Jetzt über den Norden verbreiteten Pflanzenwelt. Wir sind daher wohl zu dem Schlusse berechtigt, dass das Klima von Sumatra zur Tertiärzeit im grossen ganzen nicht verschieden war von dem Jetztigen, dass dasselbe also in der Tropenwelt sich gleich geblieben u. die grossen Aenderungen in demselben nur die gemässigte u. die Kalte Zone betreffen. Diese Aenderung scheint aber erst mit der obern Kreide begonnen zu haben u. in der unendlich langen Zeit von der Steinkohlenperiode bis zur obern Kreide scheint über die ganze Erde ein ähnliches Klima geherrscht zu haben, wie die Pflanzen u. Thiere der Unter=Carbon, der Carbon, der Trias, der Jura u. der untern Kreide von Grönland u. Spitzbergen zeigen. Wir können daher wohl sagen, dass das tropische Klima das Normalklima der Erde war u. es sich erst in relativ später Zeit auf die Länder zwischen den Wendekreisen zurückzog.</p>
<p>Dass der Rückgang ein allmäliger war zeigt das Verhalten der Flora der obern Kreide u. das Miocen der arctischen Zone, indem sie für das Miocen von Spitzbergen bei 78<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>N. Br. auf eine mittlere Jahrestemperatur von 8-9<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.C. schliessen lässt. Derselbe erreichte sein Maximum zur Gletscherzeit, während welcher die Tropenzone wohl schmäler war als gegenwärtig. Doch wird unter dem Aequator auch damals eine hohe Temperatur geherrscht haben, so dass wir wohl annehmen dürfen, dass Sumatra von den ersten Zeiten organischen Lebens bis Jetzt ein tropisches Klima besass u. die Umbildungen in der Pflanzen u. Thierwelt nicht durch die Aenderungen des Klima bedingt wurden. Es wird daher wohl die Entwicklung der organischen Welt unter den Tropen vielfach eine andere gewesen sein, als in der gemässigten u. in der kalten Zone, wo seit der obern Kreidezeit so ungeheuer grosse Umänderungen in den äussern Lebensbedingungen statt gehabt haben. Hier waren die Pflanzen u. Thiere genöthigt sich den neuen Verhältnissen anzupassen, während unter den Tropen diess Motiv wegfällt.</p>
<p>Es hat neuerdings Hr. Belt eine früher schon vielfach ausgeprochene Hypothese mit Geschick vertheidigt, dass die Klima- Aenderungen durch eine Aenderung der Stellung der Erdachse zur Sonne bedingt worden sei.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> In frühern Perioden soll die Sonne immer über dem Aequator gestanden haben, in Folge dessen habe die jetztige gemässigte Zone ein subtropisches, die arctische aber ein warmes Klima gehabt. Dann sei die Neigung der Erdachse entstanden u. in Folge dessen die Länder ausserhalb der Wendekreise kälter geworden. Diese Hypothese würde allerdings die oben besprochenen Thatsachen erklären, wenn die Angabe des Hrn. Belt von der Wirkung dieser Aenderung in der Stellung der Erdachse richtig wäre. Diess scheint mir aber gar nicht der Fall zu sein. Würde die Sonne immer über dem Aequator stehen, so würden ohne Zweifel die gemässigte u. kalte Zone einen viel wärmern Winter, anderseits aber einen kältern Sommer erhalten, es würden eben die Jahreszeiten ausgeglichen, aber die mittlere Jahrestemperatur würde wohl kaum geändert, so dass ich nicht absehen kann, dass auf solche Weise das grosse Räthsel gelöst weren kann.</p>
<p>Ich habe mit grossen Interesse den Vortrag unseres Freundes, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker über Ihre Untersuchungen betreffend die Insectivoren Pflanzen gelesen u. bin auf Ihr Werk sehr gespannt, daher ich Ihnen für dasselbe zu grossem Dank verpflichtet sein werde.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Sie aufs freundlichste begrüssend verbleibe | in grösster Hochachtung | Ihr ergebenster | Oswald Heer</p>
<p>Meinen besten Dank für Ihre Photographie. Sie hat mir grosse Freude gemacht.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Zurich</placeName>
                    <date>23 March 1875.</date>
                    <salute>My most honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Please accept my warmest thanks for your kind letter of 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March, which gave me a great deal of pleasure.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is a great encouragement to me that you take such warm interest in my work on Arctic flora and I only wish that my new contributions on the fossil flora of Spitzbergen, the tables for which are currently being lithographed, may be suitable to sustain your interest.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> They deal with the Carboniferous and Jurassic flora proper of Spitzbergen, and thus fill a large gap in the history of the development of the vegetable kingdom in the most northerly regions.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> No doubt it would be desirable in the highest degree to have comparable collections from the southern hemisphere. The prospects for this, however, are not favourable. Still, at least one keen wish of mine was granted, which was to get hold of fossil plants from the tropics. I have just now dispatched to you a small treatise on Tertiary plants in Sumatra.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Since then I received a second, richer consignment from there, which adds around 20 new species to the earlier one, so that we are already getting some important pointers regarding the appearance of Indian flora in the Tertiary period.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>They show us that the Tertiary flora of Sumatra is very similar to that living there now, and hence that its relationship to the latter is quite different from that of the Tertiary flora of Switzerland to that of the present day, or even that of the Tertiary Arctic flora to the plant life now common in the nordic zone. Thus we might be right in inferring that the climate of Sumatra in the Tertiary period was overall not different from the climate now, that the climate in the tropics has stayed the same, and that the great climatic changes have affected solely the moderate and cold zones.</p>
<p>This change, however, appears to have begun only in the Upper Cretaceous, and during the immensely long interval from the Carboniferous period to the Upper Cretaceous a similar climate seems to have prevailed all over the globe, as the plants and animals of the Lower Carboniferous period, the Carboniferous period, the Triassic, the Jurassic, and the Lower Cretaceous of Greenland and Spitzbergen show. Hence we can certainly say that a tropical climate was the normal climate on earth and that it drew back to the area between the tropics only relatively late. That the retreat happened gradually is shown by the flora of the Upper Cretaceous and the Miocene of the Arctic zone, as we can infer that the average annual temperature of the Miocene of Spitzbergen at 78<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> N. was between 8–9<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>C. The same retreat reached its maximum in the glacial period, during which the tropical zone was very likely narrower than it is now. But even then temperatures in the equatorial zone must have been high, so that we might surely assume that Sumatra possessed a tropical climate from the first days of organic life to the present, and that the transformations there in the plant and animal kingdoms were not the result of a change of climate. The development of the organic world in the tropics will have been different in many ways from that of the moderate and cold zones, where such immensely great transformations in the external conditions of life have taken place since the Upper Cretaceous period. Here the plants and animals were forced to adapt to the new conditions, while this factor is absent in the tropics.</p>
<p>Recently, Mr Belt has skilfully defended a hypothesis already frequently propounded earlier, namely that changes of climate were the result of a change of the position of the earth’s axis relative to the sun.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> In former times, the sun allegedly always stood right above the equator, and accordingly the current moderate zone had a subtropical, and the Arctic zone a warm climate. Then the earth tilted and as a result temperatures dropped in all zones beyond the tropics. This hypothesis would of course explain the facts discussed above, if Mr. Belt’s assertion about the change in the position of the earth’s axis were correct. This, however, does not seem to be the case to me. If the sun always stood above the equator, winters in the moderate and cold zones would doubtlessly be warmer, but summers, on the other hand, would be cooler; and so the seasons would be levelled out, but the average annual temperatures would hardly change, which is why I cannot see at all how the riddle would be solved this way.</p>
<p>With great interest have I read the paper of our mutual friend, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker, on your investigations of insectivorous plants, and it is with great anticipation that I am looking forward to your work, for which I shall be greatly indebted to you.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>With the kindest regards | I remain | with the greatest respect | Your devoted | Oswald Heer.</p>
<p>Many thanks for your photograph, I was delighted to receive it.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 117–19.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Oswald Heer, 8 March [1875]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Heer had sent CD the third volume of his collected work on fossil flora (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3491.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1868–83</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Oswald Heer, 8 March [1875]</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Heer’s work, ‘Beiträge zur fossilen Flora Spitsbergens’ (Contributions on the fossil flora of Spitsbergen; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8686.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1875</ref>), was first published in August 1875 in <hi rend="italic">Kongliga Svenska Vetenskaps-Akademiens Handlingar</hi>. Heer evidently did not send the monograph when it first appeared, since CD’s copy of the work, in the Darwin Library–CUL, forms the first part of volume 4 of Heer’s collected work on fossil flora (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3491.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1868–83</ref>), which was published in 1877.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD’s copy of ‘Ueber fossile Pflanzen von Sumatra’ (On fossil plants of Sumatra; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8685.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1874</ref>) is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Heer noted that he had been sent the specimens by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7497.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Rogier Diederik Marius Verbeek</ref>, the superintendent of the Geological Survey of Sumatra (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Verbeek published an account of the geology of Sumatra in the <hi rend="italic">Geological Magazine</hi> in October 1875, and briefly discussed the fossil plants he collected (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8755.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Verbeek 1875</ref>, p. 481). In 1883, Heer published a description of the collections sent by Verbeek in 1874 and 1875 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8687.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1883</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In ‘An examination of the theories that have been proposed to account for the climate of the glacial period’, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Belt</ref> argued that a great increase in the obliquity of the ecliptic of the earth’s orbit would produce colder temperatures while a great decrease would produce warmer temperatures (Belt 1874b, pp. 461–3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> had discussed CD’s research on insectivorous plants in his address to the Department of Botany and Zoology at the meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science (Hooker 1874a). The address was also published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> (Hooker 1874b).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>