<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11335">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Theodor von Heldreich<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   8 February 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17587</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11335 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11335.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11335.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 136</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 136</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2203.xml">Heldreich, Theodore von</persName>
                <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                
            
            <date when="1878-02-08">8 Feb 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for <hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Sends Greek translation of CD’s "Sketch of an infant".</p>
            <p>Is working for Greek acceptance of Darwinism.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Greeks</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Forms of flowers</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">Greek</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Athènes</placeName>
                    <date>le 27 Janv. | 8 Fevr. 1878<ref target="#foot.f2"/></date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>J’ai été absent d’Athènes &amp; ensuite malade à plusieurs reprises jusqu’à ces derniers jours: cela explique le grand retard avec lequel je reponds à votre honorée et aimable lettre du 9 Aout. J’ai reçu votre dernier ouvrage “<hi rend="underline">The different forms of flowers</hi>”, et je vous remercie infiniment de ce cadeau, qui a une très-grande valeur pour moi comme venant directement de vous.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Peut-être vous interessa-t-il de voir la <hi rend="underline">première</hi> traduction en Grec moderne d’un de vos ouvrages &amp; c’est pour cela que je vous envoie aujourd’hui la Feuille du Journal de Famille “ΕΣΤΙΑ”, dans laquelle se trouve la traduction de votre gracieux article “<hi rend="underline">Biographische Skizze eines Kleinen Kindes</hi>”, que j’ai lû avec tant d’interêt dans le Journal “<hi rend="underline">Kosmos</hi>”, <hi rend="underline">I. Heft 5</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> C’est, comme je viens de la dire, la première fois qu’un de vos écrits vient d’être traduit littéralement en Grec. Le traducteur est un jeune médecin Crétois le <hi rend="underline">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. S. Meliarakès</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> un de vos admirateurs &amp; disciples les plus-zêlés, qui sont encore assez rares en Grèce. Il n’est pas sans quelque danger &amp; il faut encore assez de courage moral pour avouer et se rallier à vos principes en ce pays, où l’on est encore sous l’empire du dogmatisme. Il faut préparer les esprits lentement et avec précaution; cependant la Verité triomphera encore ici, et il faut espérer que ce jour ne sera pas trop eloigné.</p>
<p>Je vous présente, mon cher Monsieur, mes salutations très-respectueuses &amp; sincères, avec lesquelles j’ai l’honnour de me déclarer | votre très-devoué serviteur | Th. de Heldreich</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                    <date>27 Jan. | 8 Febr. 1878<ref target="#foot.f2"/></date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I was away from Athens &amp; then ill several times, until these past few days: this explains the long delay in replying to your esteemed and kind letter of 9 August. I received your last work “<hi rend="underline">The different forms of flowers</hi>”, and I thank you very much for this gift, which has a very great value for me since it came directly from you.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Perhaps it would interest you to see the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> translation into modern Greek of one of your works, &amp; it is because of this that I send you today the Sheet of the Family Journal “ΕΣΤΙΑ”, in which is found the translation of your gracious article “<hi rend="underline">Biographische Skizze eines Kleinen Kindes</hi>”, which I read with so much interest in the Journal “<hi rend="underline">Kosmos</hi>”, <hi rend="underline">I. Number 5</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It is, as I have just said, literally the first time that one of your writings has been translated into Greek. The translator is a young Cretan doctor, <hi rend="underline">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. S. Meliarakès</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> one of your most zealous admirers &amp; disciples, who are still quite rare in Greece. It is not without some danger &amp; it still requires enough moral courage to espouse and to rally to your principles in this country, which is still under the rule of dogmatism. One must prepare minds slowly and with caution; however, Truth will yet triumph here, and one must hope that this day will not be far off.</p>
<p>I present to you, my dear Sir, my very respectful and sincere greetings, with which I have the honour to delare myself | your very loyal servant | Th. de Heldreich</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
           
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Heldreich gives both the Julian (27 January) and Gregorian (8 February) calendar dates.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11098.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Heldreich of 9 August 1877</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25), CD mentioned that he had directed his publisher to send a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Greek translation of CD’s <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Biographical sketch of an infant’</ref> appeared as ‘Καρόλος Δάρβιν: βιογραφικόν σχεδίασμα μικρού τινος παιδίου’ in <hi rend="italic">Εστία</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hestia</hi>, Hearth), 25 December 1877, pp. 817–25; a copy is in DAR 139.6. It was made from the German translation in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> 1 (1877): 367–76.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spyridon Miliarakis</ref>.</note>
        </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>