<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12032">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   5 May 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5455</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12032 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12032.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12032.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B22–3</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B22–B23</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-05-05">5 May 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends first part of MS of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>.</p>  
<p>Has found useful criticism of Anna Seward in J. G. Lockhart’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir Walter Scott</hi>.</p> 
            <p>CD should regard MS as a draft and correct anything that seems incorrect or questionable. Asks biographical questions about Dr Darwin. Can CD give information about origin of family name?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Life of Sir Walter Scott</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2969">Lockhart, J. G.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4303">Seward, Anna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-28" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-15" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-18" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-17" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by Alison Pearn. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2018-08-17" status="copyedited">Copyedited by Samantha Evans. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00162_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00162_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        <surface n="B:22r" xml:id="i162">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00162.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00162_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00162.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:22v" xml:id="i163">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00163.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00163_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00163.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:23r" xml:id="i164">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00164.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00164_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00164.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:23v" xml:id="i165">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00165.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00165_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00165.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 5.5.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Es war mir sehr schmerzlich, meinem Versprechen, Ihnen das beiliegende Manuscript eher zu schicken, nicht nachkommen zu können, da mich das ungewöhnlich kalte Frühjahrswetter dieses Jahres mittelst einer tüchtigen Erkältung vierzehn Tage arbeitsunfähig gemacht hatte.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich bitte Sie, diese Verzögerung freundlichst entschuldigen zu wollen, die Fortsetzung hoffe ich nun schneller liefern zu können. Das beifolgende Manuscript enthält nämlich nur die Einleitung, eine kurze Lebensskizze und eine Betrachtung der philanthropischen Verdienste des Dr. E. Darwin; es fehlt noch die Analÿse der poetischen und wissenschaftlichen Arbeiten desselben, die ich ebenfalls etwas zu erweitern wünschte. Es liegt mir dabei besonders daran, ihn von dem an vielen Stellen ihm gemachten Vorwurfe zu reinigen, er sei ein blosser Nachahmer von Sir Richard Blackmore oder Brooke: ich habe deren in Betracht kommende Werke nun gelesen und kann daraufhin bestimmt sagen, dass davon keine Rede sein kann.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>In der Lebensbeschreibung habe ich freilich nicht viel mehr geben können, als was ich in den Werken von Miss. Seward u. Dr. Dowson vorfand, aber einige Bemerkungen im Jahrgange 1802 des Gentleman’s Magazine und Anderes dienten zur Ergänzung. Auch den Widerruf der Miss. Seward habe ich noch glücklich gefunden; er steht in dem vierten Bande des Jahrgangs 1806 der Edinburgh Review.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Über Miss. Seward selbst fand ich einige sehr interessante Urtheile in Lockhardt’s Memoirs of the Life of Sir Walter Scott, die sehr geeignet sind, die Unzuverlässigkeit ihrer Nachrichten zu illustriren.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Ich habe deshalb eine kleine Einleitung hinzugefügt, und darin die Quellen über das Leben des Dr. E. D. zu charakterisiren.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Obwohl nun die neue Lebensbeschreibung nicht viel Neues bringt, so finde ich doch, dass sie durch eine bessere Gruppirung der einzelnen Daten ganz erheblich an Wirkung gewinnt; nicht allein das Buch der Miss. Seward, sondern auch die kleine Schrift von Dr. Dowson geben ihre Nachrichten so bunt durcheinander, dass sie keinen Genuss bei der Lecture aufkommen lassen. Mein Manuscript wird nun im Ganzen etwa 100 Octavseiten Druck umfassen; eine Veröffentlichung in einer Review wird dann allerdings wohl ausgeschlossen sein. Ich bitte Sie nun, hochverehrter Herr, vor Allem, dass Sie mein Manuscript nur wie eine Vorlage ansehen wollen, und daran ändern, was Ihnen falsch oder nur irgendwie bedenklich erscheint. Im Nachfolgenden möchte ich mir erlauben, Ihnen einige solcher Punkte namhaft zu machen, die mir zweifelhaft geblieben sind, und die mir der Ergänzung bedürftig erscheinen.</p>
<p>1. <hi rend="underline">Wann</hi> wurde Dr. Darwin mit Watt, Boulton u. Edgeworth bekannt?<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>2. Wohnte Edgeworth, ehe er nach Irland übersiedelte, in der Nähe von Lichfield?<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>3. Wer waren die mehrfach von Dr. Dowson citirten Mr. Galton und Mrs. Schimmelpenninck?<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>4. Zu welcher Zeit kaufte Dr. Darwin die Priorei bei Derby?<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>5. War Dr. Darwin durch seine erste Frau mit dem Philanthropen John Howard verwandt?<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                    <p>6. War Dr. D.’s <hi rend="underline">Vater</hi> ein Gelehrter, Gutsbesitzer, ?<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                    <p>7. Wie ist sein Sohn, Sir Francis D. zu dem Adelstitel gekommen?<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
                    <p>8. Möchte ich mir die Anfrage erlauben, ob Ihnen über die Herkunft Ihrer Familie oder des Familiennamens etwas Positives bekannt ist? Im Gentleman’s Magazine finde ich (Vol. LXXII.II p 653) ein Gedicht von Mr Rainsfold auf den Tod von Dr. E. D. abgedruckt, in welchem in den Namen <hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Derwent</hi> offenbar Beziehungen vorausgesetzt werden.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Nun sagt mir ein Sprachkundiger Freund die Sylbe Der, Dar sei keltisch und heisse Wasser, die Sylbe wen, went sei normännischen (dänischen) Ursprungs und heisse ebenfalls das Wasser, der Fluss, und er vermuthe, Ihre Familie müsse aus Wales stammen. Dabei ist mir der Ortsnamen Darwen in Lankastershire<ref target="#foot.f15"/> aufgefallen, und der Umstand, dass die Ortschaft, in welcher Edgeworth seinen Wohnsitz hatte Edgeworthstown heisst, gab mir die Idee, dass es mit Darwen und Darwin ähnlich sein könnte.</p>
                    <p>Ich erschrecke, Sie mit solchen Fragen zu quälen. Nehmen Sie, bitte, dieselben lieber für ungethan. Da Sie einige Briefe von Dr. E. D. mitzutheilen beabsichtigen, was höchlichst das Interesse der kleinen Schrift erhöhen würde, so habe ich Ihrem Plane wahrscheinlich vorgegriffen, indem ich den Brief, welchen Dr. D. eine Stunde vor seinem Tode an Mr. Edgeworth schrieb, in die Lebensbeschreibung aufnahm. Es schien mir dies deshalb passend, weil ich vorher den Bericht des G.’s Magaz., über seine letzten Lebensstunden, der von einem Verwandten oder Hausfreunde herzurühren scheint, wiedergegeben hatte, so dass die Ausführlichkeit an dieser Stelle motivirt erscheint. Wenn Sie den Brief aber lieber in dem Zusammenhange der übrigen geben wollen, so kann an jener Stelle leicht ein Hinweis auf die Sammlung eingeschaltet werden.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
                    <p>Ebenso habe ich die mir zugänglichen kurzen Notizen über die drei Söhne Charles, Erasmus und Robert, eigentlich nur in der Voraussetzung hinzugefügt, dass Sie dieselben vielleicht durch ausführlichere Nachrichten ersetzen würden.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
                    <p>Während ich eben im Begriffe war, diese gestern angefangenen Zeilen zu schliessen, traf Ihr freundliches Schreiben vom 2<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. Mai ein, woraus ich ersehe, dass Sie Ihre Erholungsreise morgen antreten wollen. Von ganzem Herzen wünsche ich Ihnen das angenehmste Wetter und einen guten erfrischenden Aufenthalt. Ich werde nun das Manuscript Ihrem Wunsche gemäss, noch heute direct an Herrn Dallas senden und ihn in Ihrem Namen bitten, sobald es seine Zeit erlaubt, mit der Uebersetzung zu beginnen.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> Er wird keine grosse Mühe haben, da ich alle Ausführungen aus Miss. Seward, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Dowson, Mr. Edgeworth, Lockhardt u. A. englisch copirt habe. Für die Analyse von Dr. D.’s Werken dürfte es wohl am einfachsten sein, wenn der Drucker einfach die Belagstellen aus der Zoonomia, dem Botanic Garden us.w. als Vorlagen erhielte?<ref target="#foot.f19"/> So sehr ich mich allezeit freue, wenn ich von Ihnen einige Zeilen erhalte möchte ich Sie doch bitten, Ihre kurze Erholungszeit nicht durch Correspondenz zu beeinträchtigen; es wäre mir viel erfreulicher, <hi rend="underline">nachträglich</hi> von Ihnen zu erfahren, dass Sie mit dem Erfolge der Arbeitsunterbrechung vollkommen zufrieden zu sein, Ursache haben.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>Inzwischen zeichne ich, hochverehrter Herr, mit den herzlichsten Grüssen und Wünschen | Ihr | treulich ergebenster | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>5.5.79.</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>It was very painful for me to have been unable to fulfil my promise to send you the enclosed manuscript sooner, for the unusually cold weather this spring rendered me unfit for work with a severe cold for a fortnight.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I beg you to kindly excuse this delay and I hope to be able to deliver the next instalment more promptly. You see, the enclosed manuscript contains only the introduction, a brief biographical sketch and an account of Dr E. Darwin’s services to philanthropy; still missing is the analysis of his poetic and scientific work, which I also desired to expand somewhat. In this I am especially concerned to clear him of the allegation against him made in many places, that he was merely an imitator of Sir Richard Blackmore or Brooke: by now I have read the works in question and as a result I can definitely say that there can be no question of this.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>In the biographical sketch I was of course unable to supply much more than what I found in the works of Miss Seward &amp; Dr Dowson, but a number of remarks in the Gentleman’s Magazine of 1802 and other sources supplied further information. The retraction of Miss Seward I found in the end, too; it is in the fourth volume of the Edinburgh Review for 1806.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I found a number of interesting assessments of Miss Seward herself in Lockhardt’s Memoirs of the Life of Sir Walter Scott, which are very suited to illustrate how unreliable her reports are.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I therefore added a small introduction, to characterise the sources for the life of Dr E. D.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>Although the new biographical portrait does not offer much that is new, I still think that it gains considerably in effect as a result of a better structuring of the details themselves. Not only in Miss Seward’s book, but also in the small piece by Dr Dowson the facts are presented in such a complete jumble that neither are a joy to read. My manuscript will comprise in all around 100 octavo pages; publication in a review will thus be out of the question. I beg you, most esteemed Sir, above all to treat my manuscript as just a draft and to alter in it what seems false or in any way questionable to you. In what follows I would like to list for your attention a number of such details that have remained dubious to me, and which appear to me to be in need of sorting out.</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="underline">When</hi> did Dr Darwin make the acquaintance of Watt, Boulton &amp; Edgeworth?<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>2. Before he moved to Ireland, did Edgeworth live near Lichfield?<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
                    <p>3. Who were Mr Galton and Mrs Schimmelpenninck whom Dr Dowson mentioned several times?<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>4. Around what time did Dr Darwin acquire the priory near Derby?<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>5. Was Dr Darwin related to the philanthropist John Howard through his first wife?<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
                    <p>6. Was Dr D.’s <hi rend="underline">father</hi> a scholar, landowner?<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                    <p>7. How did his son, Sir Francis D., acquire his title?<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
                    <p>8. I should like to inquire whether anything definite is known about the origin of your family or the family name? In the Gentleman’s Magazine (Vol. LXXII.II p 653) I found a poem by Mr Rainsfold on the occasion of the death of Dr E. D., which apparently assumes there to be a connection between the names <hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Derwent</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Now, a linguistically proficient friend tells me that the syllable Der, Dar is Celtic and means water, the syllable wen, went is of Norman (Danish) origin and also means water, the river, and he guesses that your family must be from Wales. Yet, I was struck by the place name Darwen in Lankastershire,<ref target="#foot.f15"/> and the fact that the place where Edgeworth had his residence is called Edgeworthstown gave me the idea that it could be similar with Darwen and Darwin.</p>
                    <p>I am frightened to bother you with such questions. Please, rather consider these unasked. As you are planning to communicate a number of letters by Dr E. D., which would dramatically increase the interest in the booklet, I have very likely anticipated your plan by including in my biographical sketch the letter which Dr D. wrote to Mr Edgeworth an hour before his death. This seemed appropriate as I had previously recounted the report of G.’s Magaz. about his last hours, which appears to come from a relative or friend of the family, so that the fullness of detail at this point seems justified. Should you however prefer this letter to appear together with the others, a reference to the collection could easily be inserted at this point.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
                    <p>Likewise, I inserted the brief notes I had access to about the three sons Charles, Erasmus and Robert only on the assumption that you will perhaps replace them with more detailed accounts.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
                    <p>While I was just about to conclude these lines, which I began yesterday, your kind letter of 2d May arrived, from which I gather that you intend to embark on your holiday tomorrow. With all my heart I wish you the most agreeable weather and a nice, refreshing stay. I will send the manuscript, in accordance with your wishes, directly to Mr Dallas this very day and I shall ask him in your name to begin with the translation as soon as he has time.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> He won’t have great trouble with it, for I copied out all the remarks from Miss Seward, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dowson, Mr Edgeworth, Lockhardt and others in English. For the analysis of Dr D.’s works it would be easiest, I daresay, if the printer were simply to receive the references from Zoonomia, the Botanical Garden etc. as a source?<ref target="#foot.f19"/> Though I am always delighted to receive a few lines from you, I would like to implore you not to spoil your brief holiday with correspondence; I would be happier to find out <hi rend="underline">later</hi> that you have reason to be fully satisfied with the success of your rest.<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>In the meantime, highly esteemed Sir, I remain with the most cordial greetings and wishes | Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD evidently thought Krause was closer to finishing his revisions to his account of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin (1731–1802)</ref> than he was (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12024.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 2 May 1879</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> philosophical poetry was said to have been inspired by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8433.xml">Henry Brooke’s</ref> poem ‘Universal beauty’, which, in turn, was thought to imitate <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8679.xml">Richard Blackmore’s</ref> physico-theological poem ‘Creation’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10751.xml">Hunt <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1806–7</ref>, 1: 215). CD had offered to look at Brooke’s poem for Krause (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-11969.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 2 April 1879</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had sent Krause a copy of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8551.xml">John Dowson’s</ref> lecture on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2132.xml">Dowson 1861</ref>; <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11949.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 24 March 1879</ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml">Anna Seward</ref> later retracted some of the comments she made in her memoir of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7126.xml">Seward 1804</ref>). The retraction appeared in a footnote to the essay review of her book in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10825.xml">[T. Thomson] 1804</ref>, pp. 236–7 n.). An obituary of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> was published in the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, May 1802, pp. 473–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2969.xml">John Gibson Lockhart</ref> included several references to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4303.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anna Seward</ref> in the first two volumes of his seven-volume memoir of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4262.xml">Walter Scott</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4848.xml">Lockhart 1837–8</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">This plan was abandoned in the final version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4981.xml">James Watt</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8434.xml">Matthew Boulton</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8398.xml">Richard Lovell Edgeworth</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Edgeworth often visited Lichfield for periods of time but he did not live there (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10685.xml">R. L. Edgeworth and Edgeworth 1820</ref>, 1: 111, 162, 165, 184, 204, 240, 247, 255–6, 325–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1801.xml">Samuel Galton</ref> and his daughter <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4209.xml">Mary Anne Schimmelpenninck</ref> are referred to in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2132.xml">Dowson 1861</ref> on p. 47, and pp. 16, 23, 47, 52, respectively.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> had inherited Breadsall Priory after the death of his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8435.xml">Erasmus</ref> in 1799, but did not move in until March 1802, just a month before his own death (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4366.xml">King-Hele 1999</ref>, pp. 330, 341).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8675.xml">John Howard</ref> was not related to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8390.xml">Mary Darwin</ref>, née Howard. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> had expressed his admiration of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8675.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Howard</ref> in his poem <hi rend="italic">The botanic garden</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>, pt. 1: 105, pt. 2: 89–90).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1237.xml">Robert Darwin (1682–1754)</ref> was a lawyer.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1221.xml">Francis Sacheverel Darwin</ref> was knighted in 1820.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8676.xml">Marcus Rainsford’s</ref> ‘Lines, on the death of the late truly benevolent and great Doctor Darwin, of Derby’ in the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, July 1802, p. 653, referred to the Darwent (also known as the Derwent) in Derbyshire, on the banks of which river he had spent many happy hours (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 653 n.). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Darwen is a market town in Lancashire.</note>
             <note xml:id="foot.f16">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>, p. 399, Krause had quoted the statement that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> death was peaceful and painless, as stated in the obituary in the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, May 1802, p. 473. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, Krause made no reference to the letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8398.xml">Edgeworth</ref>; CD referred to it on p. 62.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1210.xml">Charles Darwin (1758–78)</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8435.xml">Erasmus Darwin (1759–99)</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1234.xml">Robert Waring Darwin (1766–1848)</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12024.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 2 May 1879</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> had agreed to translate Krause’s account of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1791.xml">E. Darwin 1794–6</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1789.xml">E. Darwin 1789–91</ref>.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">CD was on holiday from 6 to 26 May 1879 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12024.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 2 May 1879</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>