<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6511">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. D. Hooker   [23 December 1868]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">4622</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6511 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6511.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6511.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 152: 446</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 102: 247; Linnean Society of London MS. SP 56</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>102: 247</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Kew</placeName>
                <date when="1868-12-23">[23 Dec 1868]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>T. H. Farrer’s paper is capital.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1599">Farrer, T. H.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-09-22" status="exportToCUDL">Exported to CUDL by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00503_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00503_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="247r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00503.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00503_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00503.dzi" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="247v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00504.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00504_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00102-000-00504.dzi" width="3009px" height="5445px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Kew</placeName>
                    <date>Wednesday</date>
                    <salute>Dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Is not enclosed a most charming description—writ by a Lady correspondent of mine in S Africa— please return it &amp; I will send it to Linn. Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>How are you all—? have you recovered the Busting?—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Farrer’s is a capital paper. I shall quote it in my “Students British Flora”—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Many happy returns of the Season to you &amp; your’s my dear old Darwin.</p>
<p>Ever yr affec | Jos D Hooker</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The <hi rend="underline">‘Stone Grasshopper’</hi></p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker in his Himalayan-Journal mentions a curious fact relative to a Lizard that he had captured in <hi rend="italic">[</hi>those<hi rend="italic">]</hi> regions. This reptile was party-colored, chiefly brown and yellow; upon its body were discoverd several ticks apparently of the same species, though differing in color; the ticks upon the brown portion of the Lizards body being brown, whereas those inhabiting the yellow parts were yellow.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Now let me tell you of just such another case which has come under my notice.— There is in this country a stout built square looking Grasshopper, which is called (from the great resemblance it bears to a piece of stone) the ‘Stone Grasshopper’.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> This insect though not common, is widely distributed over the country, frequenting stony ridges or rocky hill sides where the earth is but sparingly covered with shrubs and grasses: in such localities it is usually found dwelling amongst the loose broken rocks and pebbles from which (unless the creature is moving) it is scarcely distinguishable, so strikingly does it resemble in shape and color the stones amongst which it resides, and no matter what the formation or color of the rocks may be, our friend the ‘Stone Grasshopper’ will ‘follow suit’, it will be of precisely the same color or colors as the rocks and soil.</p>
<p>In the Valley of the Great Fish river<ref target="#foot.f7"/> where the argillaceous schist predominates, and from its friable nature is much broken up by the heat of the sun, it will be found that the color of this insect is blue like that of the blue slate-stone rocks, but upon the hills above (or the ‘Randt’<ref target="#foot.f8"/> as they are usually called) where the principle rocks are grey sandstone, its color is changed to a greyish yellow like that of the sandstone rocks.</p>
<p>Upon a ridge not far from this place (Highlands) where a conglomerate is croping out, and where the earth is strewn with many water-worn pebbles, some of them yellow and others of a mottled purple, I have found this species to occur in two different colors, some of the specimens being yellow like the yellow pebbles, and others of a mottled purple precisely of the same shades as the purple pebbles.</p>
<p>In the Queenstown<ref target="#foot.f9"/> district amongst the Syenitic dykes where the rocks and soil are of a dark color this insect pertaining to their nature is also of a dark color.</p>
<p>The outer coating or case of the ‘Stone Grasshopper’ is extremely hard and rough to the touch like the surface of a stone, and if by chance one of them is allowed to fall among the rocks the sound produced by its fall is like that made by one pebble striking against another, and the creature apparently receives no injury.</p>
<p>I have never seen this insect attempt to fly or move rapidly in any way whatever, unless in imminent danger of being trodden upon, when it will hop rather briskly out of the way— It seems contented to dwell forever upon or near the same spot and in all probability it has done so for ages from one generation to another, ever since this ancient continent of South Africa has stood in the same quiet and undisturbed position that it now occupies, until at length this grasshopper has grown to be the perfect creation that we now find it.</p>
<p>To some these facts may seem trifling but they are not in reality so, for they go a long way to advance and prove the truth of what M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin has so cleverly described in his ‘Origin of Species’ that the innumerable species of the animal kingdom—throughout the universe adapt themselves to surrounding circumstances, and through long periods of time grow into what we now find them— Creatures wonderfully adapted to fulfil their destiny amid the most variable conditions of life, no matter where those conditions may be—the mighty Glaciers of the North Pole, the boundless Ocean, or the “Stony rocks” and so it is with our friend the ‘Stone Grasshopper’—unable to fly, bite, sting, run away, or even to creep into a hole, or to defend itself in any way whatever— how short lifed would be its destiny—how soon would not the species become extinct—were it not marvellously protected by a coating so closely resembling that of <hi rend="underline">its brothers</hi> the stones and pebbles—that it is but rarely discovered by insectivorous animals and in its obscurity is comparatively safe.</p>
<p>I have told you that the case of the stone grasshopper is a hard case but (excuse the pun) let me hasten to undeceive you for his <hi rend="underline">case</hi> is by no means a hard one, the “lines have fallen to him in pleasant places”<ref target="#foot.f10"/> he is a happy little creature living in ease and plenty, basking the live long day in the sunshine, and chirping his merry song, and dun though his coat may be, he can nevertheless boast of rainbow-colored hues, for upon the inner part of his thighs are placed the most brilliant of shot colors, purple—blue, and red, and these I have no doubt he occasionally displays,— as for the rain it cannot wet him through, and to the wind he is equally indifferent for like Friar John in Marmion—“But little cares he or kens which way it blows!—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">M. E. Barber.</hi> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 25 December [1868]</ref>. In 1868, the Wednesday before 25 December was 23 December.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Hooker refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_271.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mary Elizabeth Barber</ref> and her paper ‘On the stone-grasshopper of Graham’s Town, South Africa’, read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> meeting of 4 February 1869 but not published (<hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London</hi> (1868–9): xlii).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Hooker refers to CD’s having sat for the sculptor <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5242.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Woolner</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6476.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 26 November [1868]</ref> and nn. 6 and 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Hooker refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer’s</ref> article ‘On the manner of fertilization of the scarlet runner and blue lobelia’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2462.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Farrer 1868</ref>). For more on Hooker’s planned ‘Students British Flora’, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6484.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [28 November 1868]</ref> and n. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See J. D. Hooker 1854, 1: 37.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In a later paper on the topic, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4806.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roland Trimen</ref> identified the species he found in the Grahamstown area as <hi rend="italic">Trachypetra bufo</hi> (R. Trimen 1871). Stone grasshoppers are now placed in the genus <hi rend="italic">Trachypetrella</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The Great Fish river is in the Eastern Cape province of South Africa.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Randt (now ‘rand’): in South Africa, a rocky ridge or area of high sloping ground, especially overlooking a river-valley (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Queenstown is in the Eastern Cape province of South Africa on the Komani river.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Barber refers to a passage from Psalms 16:6, ‘The lines are fallen unto me in pleasant places; yea, I have a goodly heritage.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Barber refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4262.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walter Scott’s</ref> poem <hi rend="italic">Marmion: a tale of Flodden Field</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7031.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. Scott 1808</ref>). In the poem the lines are (1st CantoXXIV): <quote type="verse"> But, when our John hath quaff’d his ale,<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> As little as the wind that blows,<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> And warms itself against his nose,<lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> Kens he, or cares, which way he goes. </quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>