<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7947">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. W. Reade   15 September 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14492</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7947 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7947.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7947.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 48</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 48</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3950.xml">Reade, W. W.</persName>
                <placeName>Kensington</placeName>
                <date when="1871-09-15">15 Sept 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Believes CD will not consider him a good Darwinian since he accepts natural selection only as a secondary law.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>11 S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Mary Abbot’s Terrace | Kensington</placeName>
                    <date>Sept. 15, 71</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I regret exceedingly to hear you have been ill.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Pray do not trouble to answer this letter; but before I publish I may perhaps venture to ask your opinion upon the views which I express on Evolution.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I thank you for your kind wishes; &amp; I assure you there is no one whose sympathy I prize so much as I do yours; &amp; no one whose approval I am so desirous to obtain. The intellect has its gratitude as well as the heart: and there is a filial affection which grows up in the mind towards those minds from which it has been fed. I will avail myself of your hint about extermination, &amp; express myself in vague &amp; general terms.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> After all I find on reference to the Descent that I have committed unconscious plagiarism &amp; that I really sent you your own ideas put in different language &amp; perhaps carried a stage farther on. It is a good sign when an idea is assimilated in that fashion. It looks as if it was true.</p>
<p>If I ever gain distinction as a Darwinian I shall no doubt have my enemies: but also I hope my friends; and after all the thing to be considered is the truth. I am sure you will agree with me that it is the business of the writer (I am a literary not a scientific man) to follow his intellect wherever it may lead him: &amp; not to calculate like a tradesman what is the article most in fashion. However any speculations I may offer on the origin of men will excite little attention from the theologians in comparison with my assaults on Christian history. In the forthcoming work I sketch the history of man &amp; I write the history of Christianity in the same spirit as I do that of Islam.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I am afraid you will not find me a <hi rend="underline">good</hi> Darwinian: for I am inclined to believe in Natural Selection being a secondary law. I shall probably discuss N. Selection in an appendix.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I recognise it as a law of nature as much so as Gravitation. However I will not write on it now— My ideas are still cloudy &amp; unformed. You have established the cause of Evolution at all events. Mivart’s book proves that.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I really doubt whether thirty years hence there will be an existing naturalist in Europe who will venture to deny it. That is all your work. For how did that theory stand before your <hi rend="underline">Origin</hi> was published? At a very low ebb, I imagine. What you say about facts without theory being unpalatable is true enough: an excellent instance is Tylor’s first work—which is cleverly written (the second is heavy) &amp; full of good matter.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Yet it is unknown to the great public.</p>
<p>Hoping your health will soon be quite restored | I remain | Yours very truly | Winwood Reade</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.3 (I am … fashion. 2.5] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">No reply to Reade’s letter of 12 September 1871 has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Reade refers to his <hi rend="italic">Martyrdom of man</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6556.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1872</ref>); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. W. Reade, 12 September 1871</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had evidently commented on the theory of human development that Reade outlined in his letter of 12 September 1871.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6556.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1872</ref> contains a section outlining Reade’s theories of the development of religion; Reade discusses Judaism (pp. 182–221), Christianity (pp. 221–49), and Islam (pp. 250–96).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, p. 6, CD described natural selection as ‘the most important but not the exclusive means of modification’ of species. There is no appendix on natural selection in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6556.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1872</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">On the genesis of species</hi> (Mivart 1871a) accepted evolution but gave natural selection only a restricted role.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Reade refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Burnett Tylor</ref> and his books <hi rend="italic">Researches into the early history of mankind and the development of civilization</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7898.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tylor 1865</ref>) and <hi rend="italic">Primitive culture: researches into the development of mythology, philosophy, religion, art, and custom</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7901.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tylor 1871</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>