<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11553">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Raphael Meldola   13 June 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">2668</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11553 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11553.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11553.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 129</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 129</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3289.xml">Meldola, Raphael</persName>
                <placeName>London, John St, 21</placeName>
                <date when="1878-06-13">13 June 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Would like to read Weismann’s essay on Daphnidae.</p>
            <p>Fritz Müller’s paper on odours emitted by butterflies was read at last Entomological Society meeting.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">butterflies</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Daphnidae</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_5050">Weismann, A. F. L.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Entomological Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>21 John St. | Bedford Row, | London W.C.</placeName>
                    <date>June 13/78</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am much obliged for your offer to lend me Weismann’s essay on <hi rend="underline">Daphnidæ</hi> which I shall be glad to read although I cannot pretend to any special knowledge of the Crustacea.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I want however to trace the steps which have led the author to believe in sexual selection as a cause for the colours of butterflies.</p>
                    <p>Fritz Müller’s paper on the “Odours emitted by Butterflies” was duly read at the last meeting— Bates seemed rather in doubt at to whether F. M. had conclusively demonstrated that the “fans”, “brushes” &amp;c in Lepidoptera were really scent organs. I think there can be no second opinion about this after reading F. M’s former papers which he was good enough to send me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> We had also an interesting paper by Peter Cameron “on the larvæ of <hi rend="underline">Tenthredinidæ</hi> with special reference to protective resemblance.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I exhibited Dr. Zacharias photographs of <hi rend="underline">Pterochroza</hi>—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> it appears that in one of the specimens the forewings had been broken off &amp; were stuck on again hind part before so that the neuration was somewhat “mixed”:— Thus:—</p> 
<figure rend="blockCentred width33"> 
    <graphic url="../images/DCP-LETT-11553.svg"/>
</figure> 
                    <p>Accompanying Fritz Müller’s letter &amp; paper there was an interesting specimen which will be duly described in our “Proceedings”. It was the elongated nectary of a sp. of <hi rend="underline">Hedychium</hi> which had caught a Sphinx-Moth by its proboscis— this frequently happens according to F. M. What a striking argument against the teleological theory of adaptations!<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Yours very sincerely, | R. Meldola.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11551.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter of 12 June [1878]</ref>, CD had offered to send Meldola <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Weismann’s</ref> third essay on Daphnidae (part of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9505.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1876–80</ref>). The essay explained the acquisition of bright colours in these crustaceans through sexual selection and posited a similar explanation for bright colours in butterflies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> ‘Notes on Brazilian entomology. Odours emitted by butterflies and moths’ (F. Müller 1878), sent with his letter to CD of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11463.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">5 April 1878</ref>, was read at the meeting of the Entomological Society of London on 5 June 1878. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Walter Bates</ref>, the president of the society, remarked at the meeting that ‘when collecting on the Amazons he had often observed the strong odour of vanilla emitted by certain butterflies. Without a more complete examination of the evidence, however, he was not prepared to admit that the tufts of hair or manes on the wings, &amp;c., of butterflies were scent-secreting organs’ (<hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London (Proceedings)</hi> (1878): xxvii). In 1877, Müller had published on sexual selection in Brazilian butterflies and on hair-tufts, felted spots, brushes, and similar structures in male butterflies (F. Müller 1877a and 1877b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10552.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Cameron 1878</ref>; Tenthredinidae is the largest family of sawflies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD sent <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5291.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto Zacharias’s</ref> photographs of leaf-mimic katydids to Meldola with his letter of 17 April 1878. For details, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11493.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Raphael Meldola, 3 May 1878</ref> and n. 2; for a report of Meldola’s exhibition of the photographs at the meeting, see <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London (Proceedings)</hi> (1878): xxiv.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">A brief description of Müller’s specimen appears in <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Entomological Society of London (Proceedings)</hi> (1878): xxiv. <hi rend="italic">Hedychium</hi> is the genus of ginger lilies; sphinx-moths belong to the family Sphingidae.</note>
        </div>      
          
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>