<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10557">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. F. Martins<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   5 July 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10093</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10557 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10557.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10557.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 62</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 62</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3197.xml">Martins, C. F.</persName>
                <placeName>Jardin des Plantes de Montpellier</placeName>
                <date when="1876-07-05">5 July 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Richard Gordon’s French translation of <hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi> [1877] is half printed.</p>  
<p>In Martins’ Introduction to [Éd. Barbier’s translation of] <hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi> [1877] he wants to include a complete bibliography of CD’s works: their extent is not generally known in France.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Climbing plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">French</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1922">Gordon, Richard</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Barbier, Edmond 1877</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Martins, C. F. 1877</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Jardin</hi> | <hi rend="print">des Plantes</hi> | <hi rend="print">de</hi> | <hi rend="print">Montpellier</hi>. | <hi rend="print">Montpellier</hi>,</placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="print">le</hi> 5 Juillet 1876.</date>
                    <salute>Cher Monsieur et illustre Maitre,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Mon gendre le D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gordon avance dans la traduction des Climbing plants: la moitié est imprimée.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Je revois et j’ajoute quelques notes aux Insectivorous plants qui renferment l’analyse des travaux les plus recents, Morren, Balfour, C. de Candolle &amp;c—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Je suis arreté p. 59 par une difficulté: ligne 4 containing 122 oz of carbonic acid. l’oz. valant 31 grammes cela ferait le poids enorme de 3 <hi rend="superscript">Kilogr.</hi> 782. n’y a-t-il pas une faute d’impression?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> R. S. V. P.</p>
<p>Vous avez bien voulu m’autoriser a ecrire une introduction à la traduction des Insectivorous plants; Je voudrais y joindre l’énumeration de tous vos travaux en histoire naturelle. On ne sait pas generalement en France combien ils sont nombreux, important et variés. J’ose donc prier un de vos fils de me communiquer la Liste complette de vos Memoires Scientifiques le titre, l’indication de Recueil dans le quel ils ont été insérés et l’année de la publication. Je me propose si vous l’approvez de les ranger sous 4 chefs. Ouvrages généraux, Zoologie, Botanique et Géologie.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je vous envoie la photographie des branches d’une touffe d’Antirrhinum majus decouverte sur un mur de la Faculté de Medecine par mon Aide de Botanique M. Faure.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> On voit que les jeunes rameaux axillaires s’enroulent autour des tiges et des feuilles. J’ai observé une touffe semblable dans un Jardin à Vichy; les petits rameaux avaient saisi les branches d’un rosier voisin. Ce fait semblerait prouver que certaines plantes peuvent être pourvues exceptionnellement d’organe de prehension.</p>
<p>Ne serait ce pas une reminiscence par atavisme des genres Lophospermum et Maurandia?<ref target="#foot.f7"/> La partie qui concerne ces plantes dans la traduction est dejà imprimée sans quoi je vous aurais demandé la permission d’en faire l’objet d’une Note.</p>
<p>Veuillez agréer avec bonté cher Monsieur et illustre maitre l’hommage de mon sincere devouement | Ch. Martins</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Jardin</hi> | <hi rend="print">des Plantes</hi> | <hi rend="print">de</hi> | <hi rend="print">Montpellier</hi>. | <hi rend="print">Montpellier</hi>,</placeName>
                    <date>5 July 1876.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir and illustrious master,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My son in law D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gordon is making progess with the translation of Climbing plants: half is printed.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am reviewing and adding a few notes to Insectivorous plants which include the analysis of the most recent works, Morren, Balfour, C. de Candolle &amp;c—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have been stopped at p. 59 by a problem: line 4 containing 122 oz of carbonic acid. An ounce equals 31 grams that would make the huge weight of 3 <hi rend="superscript">Kilogr.</hi> 782 is there not a printing error?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Reply please.</p>
<p>You have kindly authorised me to write an introduction to the translation of Insectivorous plants; I would like to add to it a list of all your works in natural history. In France it is not generally known how numerous, important and varied these are. Therefore I dare to request that one of your sons communicate to me a complete list of your scientific works the title, an indication of the collection in which they had been inserted and the year of publication. If you approve I plan to organise them under the headings. General works, Zoology, Botany and Geology.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I am sending you a photograph of branches of a bunch of Antirrhinum majus found on a wall of the Faculty of Medicine by my assistant botanist, M. Faure.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The young axillary branches can be seen to wind around the stems and leaves. I have observed a similar clump in a garden in Vichy, the little twigs had grasped the branches of a neighbouring rose bush. This fact would appear to show that certain plants could be specially equipped with a gripping organ.</p>
<p>Would this not be reversion by atavism of the genera Lophospermum and Maurandia?<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The section dealing with these plants in the translation is already printed otherwise I would have asked for your permission to make it the subject of a Note.</p>
<p>Would you kindly accept dear sir and illustrious master the tribute of my sincere devotion | Ch. Martins</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 225–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Gordon’s</ref> translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi></ref> was published in 1877 (Gordon trans. 1877).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his introduction to the French translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (Barbier trans. 1877, p. xi), Martins referred to recent work by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Édouard Morren</ref> showing the similarity in the process of digestion in animals and plants (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9206.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Morren 1876</ref>; see also Barbier trans. 1877, p. 423 n. 1) and to work by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_939.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Warner Clark</ref> confirming the absorption of animal matter by leaves of some insectivorous plants (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9208.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. W. Clark 1875</ref>). Martins discussed some of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7539.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Alexander Goldie Balfour’s</ref> results in experiments with <hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> in a note (Barbier trans. 1877, pp. 353–6; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9209.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. A. G. Balfour 1875</ref>). He also referred to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_811.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Casimir de Candolle’s</ref> research on the structure and movements of the leaves of <hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> (Barbier trans. 1877, pp. 373–4 n. 1; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9210.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. de Candolle 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See Barbier trans. 1877, p. 64. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edmond Barbier</ref> gave the equivalent of 122 ounces as 1729 cubic centimetres, but this was an error (122 fl. oz (imperial) is about 3466 cm<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>). In terms of weight, an ounce is about 28.35 grams.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See Barbier trans. 1877, pp. xvi–xxiii; Martins used these headings in his list of publications.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The photograph has not been found. <hi rend="italic">Antirrhinum majus</hi> is the common snapdragon. Faure has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Lophospermum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Maurandia</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Maurandya</hi>) are genera in the family Plantaginaceae (plantains); <hi rend="italic">Antirrhinum</hi> also belongs to this family. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> had mentioned a species of <hi rend="italic">Antirrhinum</hi> with coiling peduncles and two other California species that had hooking branches (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10329.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 28 December 1875</ref> and nn. 6 and 7).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>