<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3895">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi>   [before 10 October 1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20186</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3895 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3895.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3895.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 85</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 10: 451</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> n.s. 3 (1863): 115–16 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nat. Hist. Rev. n.s. 3 1863: 115–16</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1862-10-09">[before 10 Oct 1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3490.xml">Natural History Review</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>In his work on cirripedes [<hi rend="italic">Cirripedia</hi>, vol. 1 <hi rend="italic">Lepadidae</hi> (1851), pp. 53–5] CD described a particular organ as an "auditory-sac" although he was unable to trace the supposed nerve from it to any ganglion. August Krohn [in "Observations on the development of the Cirripedia", <hi rend="italic">Ann. &amp; Mag. Nat. Hist.</hi> 3d ser. 6 (1859): 423–8] concluded that the organ was ovarian. CD supposes that Krohn is correct, but gives further observations that suggest an auditory function. If someone could find ova within the curious organ it would confirm Krohn’s view.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cirripedia</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Lepadidae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">eggs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In my work on Cirripedes I have described an orifice, previously unobserved, beneath the first pair of cirri, on each side of the body, including a very singular elastic sack, which I considered to be an acoustic organ. Furthermore I traced the oviduct from the peduncle to a mass of glands at the back of the mouth, and these glands I called ovarian.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Dr. Krohn has recently stated that these glands are salivary, and that the oviduct runs down to the orifice, which I had thought to be the auditory meatus.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It is not easy to imagine a greater mistake with respect to function than that made by me; but I expressly stated that I could never succeed in tracing the oviducts into actual union with these glands; nor the supposed nerve from the so-called acoustic sack to any ganglion.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> As Dr. Krohn is no doubt a much better dissector than I am, I fully admitted my error and still suppose that he is right. Nevertheless, several facts can hardly be reconciled with his view of the function of the several parts. To give one instance: if any one will look at the figure of the Anelasma (Lepadidae, Pl. iv.),<ref target="#foot.f5"/> he will see how extremely difficult it is to understand by what means the ova coming out of the orifices (e) above referred to, could be arranged in the symmetrical lamellae which extend up to the summit of the capitulum: it must be observed that the ova are united together by a delicate membrane enclosing each ovum; moreover the cirri in this animal are in atrophied condition, without regular articulations, so that it is inconceivable how the ova can be transported and arranged by their agency.</p>
<p>I have lately received from an eminent naturalist, Prof. F. de Filippi, a paper (Estratto dall’ Arch. per la Zoolog. 31st Dec. 1861), chiefly devoted to the development of the ova of Cirripedes, in which the following passage occurs:—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>“The small size of <hi rend="underline">Dichelaspis Darwinii</hi> has not enabled me to verify the relationship discovered by Krohn between this problematical organ and the termination of the oviduct; but on the other hand the transparency of the tissues has enabled me to perceive a peculiarity of structure which may help to elucidate the question. Fig. 13 represents what I persist in calling a hearing organ. Within a cavity, the walls of which are united to the surrounding tissues, there is a pear-formed sack or ampulla. On the neck of this ampulla, at <hi rend="underline">a</hi>, are numerous minute lines parallel to each other and to the axis of the ampulla. I doubted at first whether the appearance of these lines arose from folds in the membrane, and therefore I separated some of the sacks, and I could then better convince myself that these lines correspond with true nervous fibres, thin and simple, embedded in the rather thick, resisting, and transparent substance which forms the walls of the ampulla. This circumstance seems to me to show clearly the sensitive nature of the organ, and hence to favour Darwin’s opinion, who considers them to be organs of hearing.”</p>
<p>My object in asking you to publish this note, is to induce some one to attend to this curious organ; to endeavour to discover ova within the so-called auditory sack; for as each cirripede produces so many eggs, assuredly this might be effected without great difficulty. It is, however, possible (as I believe was suggested by Mr. R. Garner at the British Association, but whose paper I have mislaid,) that cirripedes, like certain Entomostraca, may lay two kinds of eggs;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> one set passing out through the problematical orifices; and another set coming out of the body in sheets, in the manner suggested by me;—namely, the ova collecting under the lining membrane of the sack before the act of exuviation, with a new membrane formed beneath them; so that the layer of eggs becomes external after the act of exuviation.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> If this view, to which I was led by many appearances, be correct, improbable as it may seem, it ought not to be difficult to find a specimen with the old membrane of the sack loose and ready to be moulted, with the new underlying membrane almost perfect, and with the layer of ova between them. Or a specimen might be found which had lately moulted, with its skin still soft, (and this I believe that I saw) with a layer of eggs still loosely attached to the new lining membrane of the sack.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3756.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Huxley, 10 October [1862]</ref>. CD’s letter was published in the January 1863 number of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History Review</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_244.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘“Auditory-sac” of Cirripedes’</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 85–7)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, pp. 53–5, 57–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4503.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Krohn 1859</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, p. 57, CD stated: ‘I was not able to ascertain whether the two main ducts, coming from the peduncle, expanded to envelope them, or what the precise connection was’. He also reported, with regard to the supposed auditory nerve, that he had ‘not yet succeeded in tracing this nerve’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 54); CD noted that the salivary function of these glands had been asserted previously by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1170.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Georges Cuvier</ref> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 57).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to the Italian zoologist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1270.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Filippo De Filippi</ref>; the passage is translated from De Filippi 1861, p. 205. There is a presentation copy of this paper in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL, together with a manuscript translation, annotated by CD, of the section quoted here.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2726.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Garner 1861</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Garner</ref> read a paper entitled ‘On the structure of the <hi rend="italic">Lepadidae</hi>’ at the 1860 meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science, held in Oxford (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2726.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Garner 1861</ref>). However, in the report of the paper, no reference was made to the production of two kinds of eggs.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD’s lapse of memory (see n. 7, above) may be explained by the fact that Garner referred not only to ova passing out through the disputed acoustic apertures, but also to ‘broad sheets’ of ova, as described by CD in this letter. Unlike CD, Garner attributed the existence of such sheets to the ovipository action of a ‘so-called proboscis’, which arranged the ova into sheets after their emergence from the supposed acoustic apertures.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>