<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3423">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Henry Holland   30 January [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14354</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3423 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3423.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3423.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166.2: 240</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 240</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2337.xml">Holland, Henry</persName>
                <placeName>London, Brook St, 25</placeName>
                <date when="1862-01-30">30 Jan [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Is preparing a volume of his articles [<hi rend="italic">Essays on scientific and other subjects</hi> (1862)], to one of which he would like to add a postscript referring to CD’s <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> [pp. 100–1]. Sends proposed postscript for CD’s approval.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Essays on scientific and other subjects</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Holland, Henry 1862</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>25 Brook Street</placeName>
                    <date>Jan<hi rend="superscript">ry</hi>. 30</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I again write a few lines to you,—but on another topic.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have been asked at different times heretofore, &amp; again now, to reprint in a volume some of the Articles (chiefly on subjects of science) which I have contributed to the Ed<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; Q<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> Reviews.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I shall probably write no others, as I now have one or more companions in my distant journies to America, Asia, &amp;c, &amp; have therefore no need of that occupation in writing these Articles, which was a great comfort to me in the frequent solitariness of unfrequented places of travel.</p>
<p>I am therefore about to collect some nine or ten of the Articles into a volume;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; among the first of these will be one on <hi rend="underline">Life &amp;</hi> <hi rend="underline">Organization</hi>, published almost a year before your work on the <hi rend="underline">Origin of Species</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In this article some 8 or 10 pages are occupied on this <hi rend="underline">crucial question</hi>, &amp; mainly (though I hope without any irrational partiality) in vindication of the old doctrine<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>But I wish to add a postscript in relation to your work; &amp; I have just put down a few lines on the enclosed paper, which I send for your perusal, remarks, &amp; emendation. Suggest any change that you desire, or think good;—attending especially to the close of the first paragraph, where I have written what <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi> is not wholly consistent with fact, or with your wish that it should be so understood— But, I wrote it, with full design to submit it to you, before sending it to the printer.</p>
<p>Perhaps you will send me back the paper, with any comments or changes you may suggest?</p>
<p>In haste, but | Ever your’s affect<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi>, | H Holland</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f7"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The foregoing article was published a year before the appearance of Mr. Darwin’s remarkable work on the ‘Origin of Species’. Whatever be thought of some of the conclusions at which Mr. Darwin has arrived, the value of his work as a contribution to the Natural History sciences, and as a guide to their future successful pursuit, cannot be too highly estimated. Nor is it possible to speak too strongly of the candid spirit manifest throughout this volume; leading its author to anticipate objections and acknowledge all difficulties; and to state, even perhaps beyond his own belief in them, the conclusions to which his doctrine might be liable, if carried to its extreme inferences.</p>
<p>Thinking it well that the argument on the other side should be fully and fairly weighed, I have made only a few very slight alterations in the article now reprinted; one of these referring to the changes in the animal world due to the principle of natural selection, operating amidst the general struggle for existence. This principle, which Mr. Darwin has so largely and effectively used in his researches, may be considered in great degree a new path of inquiry; and one which, steadily pursued by exact and patient observation, cannot fail of conducting to important results. It is certain that at some future time a revision and reform will be required of all existing catalogues of genera and species. How far the needful curtailment may carry us is yet doubtful; but there is reason to presume that it will stop very far short of anything like unity of origin, even with unlimited concession of time for the process and progress of change. An original act of creation, <hi rend="underline">in time and under design</hi>, being assumed in every hypothesis, the conception of any primordial unity, capable of evolving and multiplying itself into all the actual forms of life, is infinitely more difficult than that of many distinct primitive forms, brought into simultaneous or successive existence by one designing and creating Power. Numbers, in truth (and this must ever be kept in mind), admit of no line or limitation, when applied to problems which pass so far beyond all human comprehension. Like in this to Time, similarly applied, their only boundary becomes that of Infinity.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by reference to the publication of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Holland 1862</ref> (see n. 4, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See the letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2337.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Holland</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3388.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">[3–14 January 1862]</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3390.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">15 January [1862]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[21 January 1862?]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Wellesley index</hi></ref> attributes seven essays in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> and nine essays in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi> to Holland in the period up to January 1862.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Holland 1862</ref>. The publication eventually included twelve essays. For CD’s negative judgment of Holland’s scientific writings, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 23 [June 1863]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Holland’s paper, ‘Life and organisation’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3734.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Holland] 1859</ref>), was published in January 1859. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> was published in November 1859 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1977</ref>, p. 75).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Holland discussed the ‘nature and permanence of Species’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3734.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Holland] 1859</ref>, pp. 244–52.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD approved Holland’s original version of the ‘postscript’, though expressing reservations about one section (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3435.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Holland, [1 or 8 February 1862]</ref>). The original manuscript that Holland sent to CD has not been found; the text published here is that given in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Holland 1862</ref>, pp. 98–9. There is an unannotated copy of the book in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>