<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3342">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   11 December [1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3539</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3342 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3342.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3342.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 200</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 39;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 381, 3: 300</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 368</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (62)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>62</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1861-12-11">11 Dec [1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the worsening relations between their two countries and the possibility of war.</p> 
<p>Expects <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> paper [<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 45–63] to be out soon.</p> 
            <p>Thanks AG for some facts on dimorphism.</p> 
<p>George Bentham has given him a list of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mentha</hi> species that are dimorphic like <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Is in a "thick mud" regarding design in nature.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Mentha</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oxalis</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Primula</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Orchids</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_398">Bentham, George</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">U. K.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">U. S.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">war</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">relations</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Gray.—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many &amp; cordial thanks for your two last most valuable notes.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> What a thing it is, that when you receive this we may be at war, &amp; we two be bound, as good patriots, to hate each other, though I shall find this hating you very hard work.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> How curious it is to see two countries, just like two angry &amp; silly men, taking so opposite a view of the same transaction! So far as I can see we rest entirely on Wilkes’ acting as Judge.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I fear there is no shadow of doubt we shall fight, if the two Southern rogues are not given up.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> And what a wretched thing it will be, if we fight on side of slavery. No doubt it will be said we fight to get cotton; but I fully believe that this has not entered into the motive in the least.— Well, thank [Heaven]<ref target="#foot.f6"/> we private individuals, have nothing to do with so awful a responsibility.— Again how curious it is that you seem to think that you can conquer the south; &amp; I never meet a soul, even those who would most wish it, who thinks it possible,—that is to conquer &amp; retain it. I do not suppose the mass of people in your country will believe it; but I feel sure if we do go to war, it will be with the utmost reluctance by all classes, ministers of government &amp; all.— Time will show, &amp; it is no use writing or thinking about it.—</p>
<p>I called the other day on D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Boott &amp; was pleased to find him pretty well &amp; cheerful;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I see, by the way, he takes quite an English opinion of American affairs, though an American in heart. Buckle might write a chapter on opinion being entirely dependent on Longitude!<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Hearty thanks for facts on dimorphism in Borragineæ.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> What a riddle is the Mertensia: I presume that it would be impossible to get seeds.— It is very kind of you to try &amp; send me the living plant of Houstonia. You may rely on it, I will send you a copy of my Primula paper as soon as I can get one; but I believe it will not be printed till April 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. &amp; therefore after my Orchid Book.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I care more for your &amp; Hooker’s opinion than for that of all the rest of world, &amp; for Lyell’s on geological points. Bentham &amp; Hooker thought well of my paper when read; but no one can judge of evidence by merely hearing a paper.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The only thing which has interested me of late is the making out that <hi rend="underline">Catasetum tridentatum</hi> is male, <hi rend="underline">Monacanthus viridis</hi> female, &amp; Myanthus barbatus the hermaphrodite, of the same species: this is clear, &amp; accounts for all 3 forms appearing sometimes on same plant: they differ as much as or more than a peacock &amp; pean-hen.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Bentham has given me list of species of Oxalis dimorphous like Primula &amp; some Menthas are so he says—but I am not sure that he distinguishes such cases as Thymus.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I have not yet had time to examine Amsinckia, which you sent me dried.—</p>
<p>If you can remember it, tell me when you write, how Dana is.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>Lyell is going to publish, what will be an interesting little Book on the Geological History of man, &amp; I believe he will touch on permanence of Species.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>With respect to Design, I feel more inclined to show a white flag than to fire my usual long-range shot. I like to try &amp; ask you a puzzling question, but when you return the compliment, I have great doubts whether it is a fair way of arguing. If anything is designed, certainly Man must be; one’s “inner consciousness” (though a false guide) tells one so; yet I cannot admit that man’s rudimentary mammæ; bladder drained as if he went on all four legs; &amp; pug-nose were designed. If I was to say that I believed this, I should believe it in same incredible manner as the orthodox believe the Trinity in Unity.— You say that you are in a haze; I am in thick mud;—the orthodox would say in fetid abominable mud. I believe I am in much the same frame of mind as an old Gorilla would be in if set to learn the first book of Euclid. The old Gorilla would say it was of no manner of use; &amp; I am much of the same mind; yet I cannot keep out of the question.</p>
<p>My dear Gray I have written a deal of nonsense. | Yours most cordially | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 How] ‘H’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘I’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.6 that of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">3.12 or more than] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">7.2 I like] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘When’</note>
                </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> affair (see n. 3, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Only one of the two letters mentioned has been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 9 November 1861</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In September 1861, the Confederate government appointed two special commissioners as envoys to Europe, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3205.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Murray Mason</ref> to London and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4384.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Slidell</ref> to Paris. Having successfully passed through the Union naval blockade of the southern coast, the envoys then transferred to the British mail packet, <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi>, in Havana on 8 November 1861. However, the Union ship <hi rend="italic">San Jacinto</hi> intercepted the British vessel, and, under threat of force, Mason and Slidell were seized and removed. At the end of November, the British cabinet instructed their minister in Washington to demand an apology from the United States government and the surrender of the Confederate envoys to British protection. Should these demands not be met, he was told to remove himself from United States territory. The London newspapers and periodicals carried extensive reports of the diplomatic negotiations over the conflict. For a full account of what became known as the ‘<hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> affair’, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2496.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferris 1977</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5132.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Wilkes</ref> was captain of the thirteen-gun sloop <hi rend="italic">San Jacinto</hi> that intercepted the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi>. International law allowed diplomatic dispatches to be seized as contraband of war. In Wilkes’s judgment, Mason and Slidell could be considered to be the physical ‘embodiment of despatches’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5147.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McPherson 1988</ref>, p. 390). For Gray’s strong reaction to the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> affair, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, p. 311.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">News that the United States government had decided to comply with British demands did not reach London until 8 January 1862.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The editors have followed <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> in supplying ‘Heaven’ as the word needed after ‘thank’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 2: 382).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The American-born physician and botanist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Boott</ref> was a friend and correspondent of Gray (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, pp. 311–12).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The historian <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_708.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Thomas Buckle</ref> promoted the use of scientific methodology as a basis for historical analysis. His ‘law of climate’, for example, suggested a statistical relationship between the nature of a country’s climate, the productivity of its soil, and the progress of its civilisation (see Buckle 1857, 1: 38 <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi>). CD had read Buckle’s <hi rend="italic">History of civilization in England</hi> in 1858 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV, 128: 23).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 9 November 1861</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD had read a paper on dimorphism in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> of London on 21 November 1861. It was published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society (Botany)</hi> 6 (1862): 77–96. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> was published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3463.xml">John Murray</ref> in May 1862.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref>, president of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> had attended the meeting at which CD’s paper was read (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3331.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Bentham, 26 November 1861</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3340.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Daniel Oliver, 7 December [1861]</ref>. On 3 April 1862, CD read a paper before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> entitled ‘On the three remarkable sexual forms of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi> <hi rend="italic">tridentatum</hi>, an orchid in the possession of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>’ (<hi rend="italic">Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society (Botany)</hi> 6 (1862): 151–7; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 63–9). He also described the forms in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 236. <hi rend="italic">Catasetum tridentatum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Monachanthus viridis</hi> are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum macrocarpum</hi>, the jumping orchid; <hi rend="italic">Myanthus barbatus</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum barbatum</hi>, the bearded catasetum.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3332.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from George Bentham, 29 November 1861</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">The American naturalist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana</ref> had experienced a severe breakdown of his health late in 1859.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> published <hi rend="italic">The geological evidences of the antiquity of man</hi> in 1863.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>