<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3908F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To John Scott   8 January [1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21160</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3908F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3908F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3908F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Hawick Archæological Society</hi> (1908): 67 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Transactions of the Hawick Archæological Society 1908: 67</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1863-01-08">8 Jan [1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD’s respect for JS’s indomitable work and interesting experiments increases steadily.</p> 
<p>His gratitude for the primulas and the astonishing <hi rend="italic">Gongora</hi> specimen.</p> 
            <p>Asks JS’s opinion about crossing a primrose with the pollen of a wild cowslip and of a cultivated polyanthus.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cowslip</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Gongora</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">polyanthus</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">primrose</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">primulas</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">exclamations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Bromley,</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 8th.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>What an indomitable worker you are and what a number of interesting experiments you are trying! I thank you for telling me about yourself; I felt respect for you before, and now this is sincerely increased.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>With your tastes, the fall in your circumstances must have been severely felt; but you have acted like a real man in making the best of things, and most truly do I wish you success in all your endeavours. I daresay a foreign appointment will be best in every way, and will be sure to offer a field for new observations; but I cannot avoid being sorry for it. Only imagine how grand it would be to see an insect at work at a Gongora, &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Very sincere thanks for all your great trouble taken about the primulas, which I received this morning.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have put them in my green-house, which is warmed at night; whether this is wise I know not. Your remarks on Gongora have interested me much, and I never saw a fresh specimen before. The labellum beats that of acropera. Do the tips of the basal inturned horns secrete any fluid? In one specimen, to the mouth of the stigmatis<ref target="#foot.f5"/> cavity there adhered a large protuberant drop of <hi rend="underline">very slightly</hi> viscid fluid, evidently in excess, but it supports your idea about acropera.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have put specimens in spirits, (for I am too busy now) and some day will look at ovates. I am quite confused about their genera.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Can the plants be kept too dry and so cause stigma not to secrete enough? I can keep pod of acropera till whatever time I get one of other germs for comparison.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I shall be quite nervous when I first look at seeds. I must write briefly.</p>
<p>[…] Never trouble yourself to answer my letters unless inclined to do so, and pray believe me with every good wish,—Dear Sir, | Yours sincerely, | Charles Darwin.</p>
<p>Have you not been put to some little expense about primulas? If so, I beg you to have kindness to inform me.</p>
<p>What say you to cross a primrose (heteromorphic) with pollen of wild cowslip and of a highly cultivated polyanthus, and see which in, say, ten pods of each, yielded most seed.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I am going immediately to build small hothouse, but whether my two rather ignorant men will succeed with the plants I know not.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For Scott’s discussion of his various experiments with orchids, and of his personal circumstances, see his letter to CD of 6 January 1863 (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Scott was hoping to move from his position as the foreman of the propagating department at the Edinburgh Botanic Garden to a foreign appointment (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref>). He and CD were interested in the pollination of orchids, including the tropical orchid <hi rend="italic">Gongora</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, and <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his letter of 6 January 1863 (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11), Scott wrote that he was sending CD three plants each of <hi rend="italic">Primula scotica</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P. farinosa</hi> for his observations and experiments on dimorphism.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Probably a mistranscription for ‘stigmatic’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Scott had sent CD <hi rend="italic">Gongora atropurpurea</hi> specimens (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref> and CD note). CD had examined the allied <hi rend="italic">Acropera luteola</hi>, which he called the ‘opprobrium’ of his work on orchids, as all the parts seemed ‘determinately contrived’ so that the plant should never be pollinated (<hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi>, p. 203). However, Scott had succeeded in pollinating <hi rend="italic">Acropera loddigesii</hi>, despite a stigmatic chamber as narrow as that of <hi rend="italic">A. luteola</hi>; he suggested that when out of its native habitat the stigmatic orifice might grow too dry, losing the viscid fluid that would aid pollination (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3800.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 11 November 1862</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3812.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 18 [November 1862]</ref>). CD discussed <hi rend="italic">Gongora</hi> in ‘Fertilization of orchids’, p. 154 (<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 150) and <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed., pp. 168–70, 276.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">‘Ovates’ is probably a mistranscription for ‘ovules’ and ‘genera’ a mistranscription for ‘genitalia’; in his note describing Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Gongora</hi> specimens, CD mentioned that he would put the ovarium in spirits to examine it (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref> and CD note).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">‘Germs’ is probably a mistranscription for ‘genera’. Scott had earlier offered to send CD his rapidly swelling <hi rend="italic">Acropera</hi> ovary, and continued to report on its growth (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3808.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 15 November [1862]</ref>, and <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref>; see also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 20 [February 1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Scott conducted crosses with species of Primulaceae on the advice of CD from 1862 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vols. 10–12, and Scott 1864). Following publication of ‘Dimorphic condition of <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’, CD continued making crosses of <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> species. For his work comparing crosses of primroses with cowslips and with polyanthus, see ‘Illegitimate offspring of dimorphic and trimorphic plants’, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Specific difference in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi>, and his notes in DAR 108.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The construction of CD’s hothouse was completed by mid-February 1863 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 11, Appendix VI). CD also refers to his servants <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Brooks</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2906.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Lettington</ref> (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vols. 11 and 12).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>