<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6967">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles Lyell   2 November 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6053</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6967 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6967.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6967.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Contemporary copy, incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">7pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The University of Edinburgh Centre for Research Collections (Gen.113.ff.3734–3737)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_124.xml">Edinburgh</repository>
                    <idno>Gen.113.ff.3734–3737</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
                <date when="1869-11-02">2 Nov 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on Huxley’s address ["Geological reform", <hi rend="italic">Q. J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</hi> 25 (1869): xxxviii–liii].</p> 
            <p>Physicists have ignored variation in sea-level in calculating effects.</p>
            <p>Doubts if sun only source of heat.</p>
            <p>Notes average depth of sea is 15 times height of land.</p>
            <p>Criticises CD’s concept of permanent continents.</p>
            <p>Sedimentary strata of Alleghenies must have derived from continent located where Atlantic is. Thinks enormous amount of denudation, submergence, and elevation may have accompanied relatively insignificant organic changes.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">continent</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">continents</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">sedimentary strata</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Q. J. Geol. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Alleghenies</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Atlantic</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">sun</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Huxley, T. H. 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">continuous or ‘broken’ land</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>2. Nov— 1869—</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have read the article, &amp; cannot attach the importance—to it which you seem to do.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> To me the most interesting parts of it are the quotations from Thomson, &amp; what is said about changes in the acceleration of the earth’s rotation, or that of the moon by the friction of the tides.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I do not yet comprehend the argument but am quite willing to believe that physicists will prove something important on this question; but it was surely a good hit of Huxley’s to point out that whatever calculations they have been making about the effects of the tides in the course of geological ages, must be very loose &amp; incomplete, if they took no account of the quantity of water locked up in the shape of ice at different periods, when for example the Miocene forests were flourishing at or near the pole with scarcely any ice, &amp; when at the height of the Glacial Period, Wales &amp; Yorkshire were covered by a sheet of ice.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am astounded at the coolness with which they talk of the theory of Helmholtz as to solar heat being the only one left to us, viz, that it is a hot body cooling &amp; that 10 or 15 millions is all that can be allowed to the geologist (p 438);<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; how they can speak of there being no access of energy into the sun than meteors, as if they knew so much of the universe as to warrant such assumptions.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I am said (p 422) to talk about <hi rend="underline">tens of thousands of millions of years</hi> as the very least period I will accept, but he takes care not to refer to any passage.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I suppose you have seen Geikie’s calculations that denudation like that of the Mississippi would reduce a mass of rock equalling in volume all the land now above the sea to sand, pebbles &amp; mud in 6.000.000 years—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Have you any where in reference to speculations of this kind spoken of the supposed fact that the average depth of the sea is 15 times as great as the average height of the land, the latter being 1000 &amp; the sea 15000.</p>
<p>You have spoken somewhere of the permanence of continents,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> to which in a general way I have no objection, but I should like you to consider 〈if〉 the sea 〈be less〉 deep (suppose even the mean depth to be 10.000 ft) would it not have a great bearing on the question of the rate of denudation &amp; permanence of continents. Nothing can be clearer to me than that the continent from which the sedimentary strata of the Alleghanies were derived was placed where the Atlantic is now situated.</p>
<p>The sedimentary strata of the Alleghanies being all Paleozoic are 42.000 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. thick. Do think of this &amp; give me any references to yourself or others which may bear upon it. I am sure it will have much to do with estimates of geological time. The rate of denudation must be balanced by an equal amount of volcanic movement &amp; the changes in species will have reference to these two forces &amp; will require probably as much time as you may at any time have thought.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>The permanence of continents depends greatly on the formation of deltas near the coast, or in other words, on rivers clearing themselves of mud, sand &amp; pebbles in the first receptacle they meet with—just as they leave behind all their sediment when they pass through a lake. If therefore the height of the land be to the average depth of the sea as 1 to 15—a moderate quantity of movement in the areas fringing the continents will cause the deltas to emerge &amp; the same matter will do duty several times over in 〈the cour〉se of the 6.000.000 years— But the same amount of movement will cause but little of the deep ocean to emerge if the <hi rend="underline">average</hi> depth be 3 miles— The movements however are sufficient at length to cause the submergence &amp; emergence of the bed of the deep sea, &amp; the changes of level seem to be going on so slowly that I cannot but think the conversion of great oceanic basins into continents &amp; of continents into oceanic basins may have been a work of as much time as your speculations have ever demanded— I do not think that the subaërial denudationists allow sufficiently for the constant repair of the loss of land by the up-lifting of comparatively modern strata thrown down near the coast,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> the Eocene strata are 12,000 feet high on the Alps &amp; the Miocene from 3000 to 7000 (?)ft— At the end of a great number of periods that chain may be as high as ever.—although the quantity of matter which has passed through the denudation mill may equal in volume all the land now above the sea yet this has been supplied by grinding the same stuff over &amp; over again. I still think that the quantity of movement shown by Moel Tryfaen &amp; by the submergence &amp; re-emergence of a large part of the British Isles while the Mollusca have been scarcely in the least changed implies that an enormous quantity of movement &amp; denudation corresponds to an insignificant amount of organic fluctuation.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Lyell refers to a review article by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4652.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter Guthrie Tait</ref>, ‘Geologic time’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Tait] 1869</ref>). No letter from CD to Lyell on this subject has been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 24 July [1869]</ref>. The article summarised <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4737.xml">William Thomson’s</ref> continuing criticism of uniformitarian thought in geology (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Brush 1996</ref>, pp. 36–8, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1079.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burchfield 1990</ref>, pp. 80–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Tait quoted Thomson several times in summarising the argument, supported by mathematical calculations, that ocean tides created enough friction to gradually diminish the rate of the earth’s rotation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Tait] 1869</ref>, pp. 416–19, 433–4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> had responded to Thomson’s argument regarding the earth’s speed of rotation, suggesting that the rate could actually have increased in the glacial period as ice accumulated at the poles, withdrawing water from the sea (see T. H. Huxley 1869c, p. li).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Tait wrote: ‘the only theory of solar heat left us is that developed by Helmholtz, which regards the sun as a hot body cooling; the heat having been produced during the falling together of its parts.’ Consequently, the earth was also thought to be cooling, and Tait estimated that the earth was only ten or fifteen million years old. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Tait] 1869</ref>, p. 438. For <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2207.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann von Helmholtz’s</ref> argument on the cooling of the sun, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3502.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Helmholtz 1856</ref>. See also Thomson 1862b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For a discussion of Thomson’s suggestion that the sun’s energy was partly replenished by meteors falling into it, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Tait] 1869</ref>, pp. 436–8. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1079.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burchfield 1990</ref>, pp. 28–33. For Lyell’s doubt as to whether physicists could determine long-term temperature changes of the sun and earth, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5034.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1872</ref>, 2: 213–14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Tait wrote (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Tait] 1869</ref>, p. 422): ‘ … <hi rend="italic">popular</hi> geologists … with no less authorities than Lyell, Ramsay, Darwin, and Jukes at their head, still talk with the wildest looseness about thousands and tens of thousands of millions of years as the very least periods they can accept’. The additional references are to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay</ref> and John Beete Jukes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Lyell is mistaking <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1836.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Archibald Geikie’s</ref> support of subaerial denudation (erosion by rivers and glaciers) as the primary erosive force with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1127.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Croll’s</ref> calculations of the erosive power of rivers presented in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1654.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Croll 1868</ref>. CD added Croll’s discussion to the fifth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 349–50; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to James Croll, 19 September 1868</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, chapter 11, ‘Geographical distribution’, CD wrote (pp. 357–8): ‘It seems to me that we have abundant evidence of great oscillations of level in our continents; but not of such vast changes in their position and extension, as to have united them within the recent period to each other and to the several intervening oceanic islands.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For Lyell on denudation, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5031.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1865</ref>, pp. 66–79; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5034.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1872</ref>, 1: 104–5, and 2: 180–97. The Allegheny Mountains extend south-west from New York State to Virginia, and form a portion of the Appalachian mountain range in the eastern United States. For CD’s most recent published discussion of the topic, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 352–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">On subaerial denudation as the major force of erosion, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to James Croll, 19 September 1868</ref>, n. 4. CD had recently added comments on denudation, including a reference to Lyell’s views, to the fifth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 348–9 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peckham, ed. 1959</ref>, p. 478).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Marine shells found in 1841 on Moel Tryfan, a mountain in North Wales, had suggested marine submergence to some geologists, including CD (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3575.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert 2005</ref>, pp. 277, 282, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_154.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Ancient glaciers of Caernarvonshire’</ref>). In 1861, the shells were found to be more modern than had previously been thought, suggesting that uplift had been surprisingly recent (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3270.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 30 September 1861</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5031.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1865</ref>, pp. 158–9).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>