<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7430">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   7 January 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7917</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7430 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7430.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7430.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian) †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 69</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 111: A77–8</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>111: A77–8</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                <date when="1871-01-07">7 Jan 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends his new work, <hi rend="italic">Ulteriori osservazioni sulla dicogomia</hi> pt 2, fasc. 1.</p>  
<p>Has found no nectar in <hi rend="italic">Orchis morio</hi> or <hi rend="italic">O. maculata</hi> in Italy and has seen no insects visiting the plants.</p> 
            <p>Gives his observations on cross- and self-fertilisation in cereals.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cereals</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Orchis maculata</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Orchis morio</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Ulteriori osservazioni sulla dicogomia</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Italy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dichogamy, sexual dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">nectar</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Vallombrosa | Firenze</placeName>
                    <date>7. Genn. 1871</date>
                    <salute>Onorevole Signore!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Prego la S.V. a voler aggradire l’omaggio di due esemplari d’un mio lavoro (Ulteriori osservaz. ecc. p<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> II. f. 1), e nello stesso tempo la ringrazio della cortese lettera del 23. X<hi rend="superscript">bre</hi> scorso, e degli utilissimi cenni che sono contenuti nella medesima.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Per colpa della pessima mia memoria, mi erano sfuggite le interessanti notizie che dà a pag. 2 e 3 (notes on the fertilization of Orchids) concernenti l’<hi rend="underline">Orchis morio</hi>, <hi rend="underline">O.</hi> maculata ecc. e i loro pronubi.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ora le ho riandate, e mi trovo costretto a modificare fortemente la mia opinione. È vero che io non ho mai trovato liquido entro la svescicatura dello sperone; ma quel che non mi è occorso di poter notare nella Liguria e nella Toscana, potrebbe benissimo accadere in altre regioni. Tanto più che vedo come le Orchis succitate siano visitate frequentemente in Inghilterra da molti insetti, Empis, Bombus, Apis, Eucera …,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> mentre io, in Liguria, non ho potuto giammai sorprendervi insetti; rarissime sono ivi le masse polliniche asportate via, e rarissimi gli ovarii abboniti.</p>
<p>Una osservazione che ho fatto pochi mesi sono mi fa credere realmente alla possibilita di una secrezione nettarea od analoga, subepidermica. Questo fenomeno è frequentissimo nelle Malpighiacee. Sospetto anche che abbia luogo presso alcune <hi rend="underline">Primulae</hi>, la cui corolla all’interno trovai svescicata in maniera affatto analoga agli speroni delle orchidi nostrane. Alla prima occasione rettificherò la mia troppo avanzata proposizione.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Io avrei da molto tempo pubblicato un breve cenno sulla fecondazione incrociata dei cereali. Le osservazioni che feci non mancavano d’interesse, ma io ebbi la sbadataggine di non iscriverle subito, cosicchè ora non oso di scrivere alcuna cosa in proposito per tema di non ricordarmi più bene dei dettagli.</p>
<p>Posso per altro guarentire positivamente</p>
<p>l<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> che nel grano (<hi rend="underline">Triticum</hi>) ogni fiore può fecondarsi da se stesso, perchè una parte del polline è versata dentro il fiore e l’altra parte è versata fuori all’atto preciso della deiscenza del fiore; deiscenza che dura circa un quarto d’ora.</p>
<p>2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> che nel <hi rend="underline">Triticum</hi> la dicogamia ossia la fecondazione incrociata non è esclusa, giacchè il fiore si rende deiscente, sebbene per poco tempo, e giacchè metà del polline è versato fuori nell’aria, in balìa del vento;</p>
<p>3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> che alcune piante di <hi rend="underline">Triticum</hi> allontanate l’una dall’altra, in modo da escludere il polline eteroclino,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> abbonirono tuttavia tutti i semi. Cosicchè per il <hi rend="underline">triticum</hi> è possibile la omogamia non meno che la dicogamia—;</p>
<p>4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> che nella <hi rend="underline">Secale</hi><ref target="#foot.f7"/> la dicogamia è quasi necessaria, perchè la deiscenza del fiore è totale e perchè la esserzione degli stimmi e delle antere è completa;</p>
<p>5<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> che nell <hi rend="underline">Hordeum vulgare</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p rend="left">le due serie dei fiori mediane nella spiga (b, b) non si aprono mai e quindi è impossibile per essi la dicogamia, e le quattro serie angolari dei fiori (a, a, a, a) si aprono un poco, e quindi per essi può succedere la omogamia e la dicogamia—</p>
<p>6<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. che infine l’<hi rend="underline">Hordeum distichum</hi><ref target="#foot.f9"/> offre un fenomeno interessantissimo.</p>
<p>Esso ha due specie di fiori gli uni destinati per la omogamia. Essi non si aprono mai, e la fecondazione è già avvenuta prima ancora che la spiga esca fuori completamente dalla sua vagina fogliare.</p>
<p>Gli altri fiori sono pochissimi, e sono destinati esclusivamente per la dicogamia. In grandezza superano assai i precedenti. Così nell’<hi rend="underline">Hordeum</hi> ossia in una pianta d’indole <hi rend="underline">anemofila</hi> si ripete quell’interessante fenomeno finora constato nelle sole piante entomofile dei generi <hi rend="underline">Viola</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Impatiens</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Vicia amphicarpa</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus amphicarpus</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> producenti due sorta di fiori, gli uni destinati per la omogamia e sprovvisti di corolla, di colori e di miele, gli altri destinati per la dicogamia, cioè colorati, corolliferi e nettariferi.</p>
<p>Mi riconfermo colla più alta stima e rispetto della S.V. onorevolissima | ossequentissimo discepolo | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 Prego … abboniti 2.10] ‘Dichogamy—Cleistogene—Dimorphism’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Cleistogene flowers in Hordeum | <hi rend="italic">[</hi>anemophilous<hi rend="italic">]</hi> plant—new &amp; good case’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Vallombrosa | Florence</placeName>
                    <date>7. Jan. 1871</date>
                    <salute>Honourable Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I beg Your Honour to accept the gift of two copies of a work of mine (Ulteriori osservaz. etc. pt II. fasc. 1), and I would also like to thank you for your kind letter of 23. December of the previous year, and for the most useful accounts enclosed in it.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Due to my terrible memory, I had forgotten about your interesting notes on pp. 2 and 3 (notes on the fertilization of Orchids), regarding <hi rend="underline">Orchis morio</hi>, <hi rend="underline">O.</hi> maculata etc. and the insects that fertilise them.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Now I have gone back to them and I find I must strongly modify my views. It is true that I have never found liquid in blistered spurs; but what I have not had the fortune to observe in Liguria and Tuscany could very well happen in other regions. All the more so since I see that the said orchids are frequently visited, in England, by a number of insects, Empis, Bombus, Apis, Eucera …,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> while I myself was never able to catch insects in the act in Liguria; there the pollen-masses that are carried away are most scanty, and mature ovaries are most rare.</p>
<p>An observation I made a few months ago leads me to entertain seriously the possibility of a nectareous or analogous secretion, underneath the lining. This phenomenon is most common in Malpighiaceae. I also suspect that it occurs in some <hi rend="underline">Primulae</hi>, whose corolla I have found blistered on the inside in a way wholly analogous to the spurs in our orchids. As soon as I get the chance I shall correct my too rash proposition.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Quite some time ago I should have published a brief account of the cross-fertilization of cereals. The observations I made were not without interest, but I was careless and did not write them up immediately, so that now I don’t dare write anything on the topic for fear of not remembering the details well enough.</p>
<p>I can however positively confirm</p>
<p>1. that in wheat (<hi rend="underline">Triticum</hi>) every flower can fertilise itself, since part of the pollen is turned towards the flower and the other part is turned outwards at the precise moment when the flower bursts open; this dehiscence lasts about a quarter of an hour.</p>
<p>2. that in <hi rend="underline">Triticum</hi> dichogamy or cross-fertilization is not excluded, for the flower opens up, if for a short time only, and half the pollen is turned outwards to the air, at the mercy of the wind;</p>
<p>3. that plants of <hi rend="underline">Triticum</hi> that are separated from one another, so as to exclude heterocline<ref target="#foot.f6"/> pollen, still develop all the seeds. For <hi rend="underline">triticum</hi>, homogamy is therefore no less an option than dichogamy—;</p>
<p>4. that in <hi rend="underline">Secale</hi><ref target="#foot.f7"/> dichogamy is practically a necessity, since the dehiscence of the flower is total and since the exsertion of the stigma and of the anthers is complete;</p>
<p>5. that in <hi rend="underline">Hordeum vulgare</hi><ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p rend="left">the two centre sets of flowers in the ears of corn (b, b) don’t ever open and therefore it is impossible that they could be dichogamic, and the four corner sets of flowers (a, a, a, a) open a little, and hence they may be homogamic or dichogamic.</p>
<p>6. finally that <hi rend="underline">Hordeum distichum</hi><ref target="#foot.f9"/> constitutes a most interesting phenomenon.</p>
<p>This plant has two kinds of flowers, one of them meant for homogamy. They never open, and fertilisation is hence completed even before the ear of corn has completely emerged from its leafy sheath.</p>
<p>Of the other flowers, there are very few, and they are exclusively dichogamic. In size they by far exceed the former. Thus, in <hi rend="underline">Hordeum</hi> and in <hi rend="underline">anemophilous</hi> plants, an interesting phenomenon can be observed that has hitherto been displayed only by entomophilous plants of the species <hi rend="underline">Viola</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Impatiens</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Vicia amphicarpa</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus amphicarpus</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> They produce two kinds of flowers, one destined for homogamy and not equipped with a corolla, colours and honey, the other meant for dichogamy, hence coloured and carrying a corolla and nectar.</p>
<p>Once again I remain with the highest esteem and respect for Your most revered Honour | your most devoted disciple | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Delpino refers to the first fascicle of the second part of <hi rend="italic">Ulteriori osservazioni sulla dicogamia nel regno vegetale</hi> (Further observations on dichogamy in the vegetable kingdom; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>). CD had received part I in 1869 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6866.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Federico Delpino, 22 August 1869</ref>). The work as a whole consists of two parts, and each part comprises several fascicles published at intervals. There is an annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref> in the Darwin Library–CUL. CD’s <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Delpino of 23 December 1870</ref> has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Delpino refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, pp. 142–3. <hi rend="italic">Orchis maculata</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Dactylorhiza maculata</hi>, the heath spotted orchid; <hi rend="italic">O. morio</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Anacampis morio</hi>, the green-wing orchid.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Empis</hi> is a fly genus; <hi rend="italic">Bombus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Apis</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Eucera</hi> are bee genera. CD discussed their visits to orchids in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, pp. 142–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">On CD and Delpino’s disagreement over whether nectarless flowers offered some other reward to visiting insects, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pancaldi 1991</ref>, pp. 123–9. Delpino retracted his ‘correction’ after further observations.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Heterocline: having male and female flower-heads or separate receptacles (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Secale</hi>: rye.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Hordeum vulgare</hi>: common barley.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Hordeum distichum</hi> is an alternative spelling of <hi rend="italic">H. distichon</hi>, now considered to be a variety of <hi rend="italic">H. vulgare vulgare.</hi> It was known as two-rowed barley. On <hi rend="italic">H. vulgare</hi> and <hi rend="italic">H. distichum</hi>, see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6965.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Federico Delpino, 1 November 1869</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 332–3, CD cited Delpino for having shown that some flowers of <hi rend="italic">Hordeum</hi> allowed cross-fertilisation.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The species <hi rend="italic">Vicia amphicarpa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus amphicarpus</hi> are both now <hi rend="italic">Vicia sativa</hi> ssp. <hi rend="italic">amphicarpa</hi>, subterranean vetch.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>