<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10676">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Geikie   16 November 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13356</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10676 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10676.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10676.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">inc? 5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> Geikie (1881): 141; <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 213; Newbigin &amp; Flett (1917): 74 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 144: 331</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 331</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1876-11-16">16 Nov 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1837.xml">Geikie, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>On JG’s <hi rend="italic">Great ice age</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses formation of drift deposits near Southampton.</p> 
<p>Comments on Axel Blytt [<hi rend="italic">Immigration of Norwegian flora</hi> (1876)].</p> 
            <p>Has had fearful misgivings that the step-like plains of Patagonia may have been caused by changes in level of sea, not land.</p> 
<p>Comments on book [Archibald Geikie, <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir Roderick I. Murchison</hi> (1875)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">drift deposits</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">plains</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Great ice age</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Immigration of Norwegian flora</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Life of Sir Roderick I. Murchison</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Patagonia</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Southampton</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Blytt, A. G. 1876</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Geikie, Archibald 1875</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dispersion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 16./76</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hope that you will forgive me for troubling you with a very long letter— But first allow me to tell you with what extreme pleasure and admiration I have just finished reading your “Great Ice Age”<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   It seems to me admirably done &amp; most clear. Interesting as many chapters are in the history of the world I do not think that any one comes nearly to the glacial period or periods. Though I have steadily read much on the subject, your book makes the whole appear almost new to me.</p>
<p>I am now going to mention a small observation made by me two or three years ago near Southampton but not followed out as I have no strength for <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> excursions—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I need say nothing about the character of the drift there (which includes palæolithic celts) for you have described its essential features in a few words at p. 506— It covers the whole country, even plain-like surfaces, almost irrespective of the present outline of the land.</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">possibly 1 sheet missing</hi>〉<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The coarse stratification has sometimes been disturbed, I find that you allude “to the larger stones often standing on end”; and this is the point which struck me so much.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Not only moderately sized angular stones, but small oval pebbles often stand vertically up, in a manner which I have never seen in ordinary gravel beds— This fact reminded me of what occurs near my home in the stiff red clay full of unworn flints over the Chalk which is no doubt the residue left undissolved by rain water— In this Clay flints as long &amp; thin as my arm often stand perpendicularly up; and I have been told by the tank diggers that it is their “natural position”! I presume that this position may safely be attributed to the differential movement of parts of the red clay as it subsided very slowly from the dissolution of the underlying chalk; so that the flints arrange themselves in the lines of least resistance. The similar but less strongly marked arrangement of the stones in the drift near Southampton makes me suspect that it also must have slowly subsided; and the notion has crossed my mind that during the commencement &amp; height of the Glacial period great beds of frozen snow accumulated over S. England, and that during the summer gravel &amp; stones were washed from the higher land over its surface and in superficial channels. The larger streams may have cut right through the frozen snow and deposited gravel in lines at the bottom. But on each succeeding autumn when the running water failed, I imagine that the lines of drainage would have been filled up by blown snow afterwards congealed, &amp; that owing to great surface accumulations of snow it would be a mere chance whether the drainage together with gravel &amp; sand would follow the same lines during the next summer.</p>
<p>Thus as I apprehend alternate layers of frozen snow and drift in sheets &amp; lines would ultimately have covered the country to a great thickness; with lines of drift probably deposited in various directions at the bottom by the larger streams— As the climate became warmer the lower beds of frozen snow would have melted with extreme slowness and the many irregular beds of interstratified drift would have sunk down with equal slowness; &amp; during this movement the elongated pebbles would have arranged themselves more or less vertically—</p>
<p>The drift would also have been deposited almost irrespective of the outline of the underlying land. When I viewed the Country I could not persuade myself that any flood however great, could have deposited such coarse gravel over the almost level platforms between the valleys. My view differs from that of Holst (p. 415.) of which I had never heard as his relates to channels cut through glaciers, and mine to beds of drift interstratified with frozen snow where no glaciers existed<ref target="#foot.f5"/>   The upshot of this long letter is to ask you to keep my notion in your head and look out for upright pebbles in any lowland country which you may examine, where glaciers have not existed. Or if you think the notion deserves any further thought but not otherwise to tell anyone of it, for instance M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Skertchly who is examining such districts<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Pray forgive me for writing so long a letter and again thanking you for the great pleasure derived from your book. | I remain | Yours very faithfully | Ch. Darwin—</p>
<p>I hope what I have written may be intelligible for as you will see, I have taken no pains on the style.</p>
<p>P.S. You speak in the early part of your book of the Glacier theory having preceded that of icebergs; but I heard of the latter seven or eight years before a word was spoken in England of the extension of Ancient Glaciers—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I am glad that you have read Blytt; his paper seemed to me a most important contribution to Botanical Geography. How curious that the same conclusions should have been arrived at by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Skertchly, who seems to be a first rate observer; and this implies as I always think a sound theoriser—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I have told my publisher to send you in two or three days a copy (2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Edit) of my Geological work during voyage of Beagle— The sole point which would perhaps interest you is about the step-like plains of Patagonia</p>
<p>For many years past I have had fearful misgivings that it must have been the level of the sea, &amp; not that of the land which has changed—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I read a few months ago your very interesting life of Murchison   Though I have always thought that he ranked next to W Smith in the Classification of formations &amp; though I knew how kindhearted, yet your book has raised him greatly in my respect notwithstanding his foibles &amp; want of broad philosophical views—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>C.D.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">There is an annotated copy of the second edition of Geikie’s <hi rend="italic">Great Ice Age</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Geikie 1877</ref>) in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 299–300). Although dated 1877, Geikie’s book was published between 1 and 15 November 1876 (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ circular</hi>, 16 November 1876, p. 922; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10655.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to James Geikie, 26 October 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s eldest son, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Erasmus Darwin</ref>, lived in Southampton.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The copyist’s numbered sheets omit sheet 2 at this point, but <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">LL</hi></ref> 3: 213) and Geikie (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Geikie 1881</ref>, p. 141) both reproduced the text as it stands with no indication that anything was missing.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD scored the passage in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Geikie 1877</ref>, p. 506, where Geikie claimed that river action could not account for the ‘coarse and tumultuous aspect’ often presented by Palaeolithic river gravels, including larger stones standing on end. Celts are prehistoric axe-like instruments (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1347.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Chambers</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In a footnote in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Geikie 1877</ref>, pp. 415–16, Geikie described <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7683.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nils Olof Holst’s</ref> theory of the formation of <hi rend="italic">åsar</hi> (long, winding, natural embankments in Scandinavia). Holst thought they formed as a result of river channels made by melting inland ice running over the ice sheet (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9335.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Holst 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4377.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sydney Barber Josiah Skertchly</ref> was working in the Fenlands and East Anglia for the Geological Survey (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Aust. dict. biog.</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Geikie had written, ‘Next succeeded the glacier theory of Agassiz, … and this again was followed by the iceberg hypothesis’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Geikie 1877</ref>, p. 24). The theories were intended to account for the transport of large boulders from one part of the country to another, and other phenomena of what had become known as the glacial drift. It was in 1840 that Agassiz had first mentioned that glaciers had existed in the British Isles (Agassiz 1840a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10433.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Axel Blytt, 28 March 1876</ref> and n. 1, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Blytt 1876</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Essay on the immigration of the Norwegian flora during alternating rainy and dry seasons</hi>). For Skertchly’s notes, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Geikie 1877</ref>, pp. 536–46, especially p. 545, on dry periods in the past.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2807.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Geological observations</hi> 2d ed.</ref> was published in November 1876 (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-10671.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 14 November 1876</ref>). On the step-formed plains of Patagonia, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2807.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Geological observations</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 197–202; CD thought the steps were formed by recent elevatory movements.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roderick Impey Murchison’s</ref> biography was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Geikie’s</ref> brother Archibald (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Geikie 1875</ref>). William Smith  was the first to work out the succession of geological strata in Britain by means of fossil markers (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>