<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9887">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. B. Dawkins   14 March 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14190</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9887 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9887.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9887.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 130</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 130</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1262.xml">Dawkins, W. B.</persName>
                <placeName>Owens College, Manchester</placeName>
                <date when="1875-03-14">14 Mar 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Is glad CD is pleased with his book [<hi rend="italic">Cave hunting</hi> (1874)].</p> 
            <p>Relationship between language and race. The Basques.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Basques</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cave hunting</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Dawkins, W. B. 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">The Owens College, | Manchester,</hi></placeName>
                    <date>14/3/75</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is a great satisfaction to me to hear that you are pleased with my imperfect, and to a great extent uncorrected and crude book, written under great pressure and with the idea that it was better to put it forward now, rather than wait for the polish and style of the future, which might never come.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> From your letter and its reception in America, and its translation into German,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am very happy in inferring that it has not been written in vain.</p>
<p>I have to thank you also for your note about Oxen—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Before I wrote I had persecuted Freeman, Stubbs and Green, and read Howel Dha, and the Records of the Kings Council, as far as Henry VII, in vain.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I cannot guess where Youatt<ref target="#foot.f5"/> found it: but it must have been in some Monastic roll or other.</p>
<p>As you are interested in the question of the northern extension of the Iberians or Basques the last discussion before the Anthropological Institute is not without point.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The philologers in the Sat. Rev. Athenæum etc have been laying down the law that language is a test of race, and have assumed that, as I did not take up its evidence on the Basque question, language had been altogether ignored in the enquiry.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> On the question being put to Prince Lucien Buonaparte, Sayce, Rhys, and Van Eys<ref target="#foot.f8"/> the other evening, “whether they considered that the Ethiopian could change his skin and whole physique as easily as his speech?”, the answer was obviously “no”. So that as the case stands at present three distinguished philologers hold that language is <hi rend="underline">not</hi> a test of race, and consequently the argument as to the Basques—the only argument urged against the Basque theory—falls to the ground. It further appeared in the debate that the Basque tongue has not been written more than two or three centuries, and that it is full of latin and gothic words.</p>
<p>Since the debate Rhys and Sayce have been following up the point which I urged “that the Finns are indistinguishable physically from the Celts,” and have met with fragments of Ugric grammar in Welsh and Erse—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Probably something of great value will be found out in this quarter— — but I must ask pardon for so long a letter | from | Yours very truly | W. Boyd Dawkins <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq F.R.S. | Down.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Plant which catches moths like <hi rend="italic">Apocynum</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter has not been found, but he had evidently written to comment on Dawkins’s book <hi rend="italic">Cave hunting: researches on the evidences of caves respecting the early inhabitants of Europe</hi> (Dawkins 1874a). Dawkins had sent CD a copy in October 1874 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Dawkins, 18 October [1874]</ref>). CD’s lightly annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–Down (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 188).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The German translation of <hi rend="italic">Cave hunting</hi> was published in 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8659.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dawkins 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9819F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Dawkins, 16 January [1875]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7433.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Augustus Freeman</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Stubbs</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Richard Green</ref> were historians. The laws of Hywel Dda (Cyfraith Hywel) are a system of native Welsh law named after the medieval Welsh king who was credited with the codification (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8701.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Law of Hywel Dda</hi></ref>). The records of the King’s Council date from 1386 to 1540, after which they are called records of the Privy Council (for more on these records, see the National Archives, ‘Privy Council since 1386’; www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/records/research-guides/privy-council-correspondence.htm).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5284.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Youatt</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9819F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Dawkins, 16 January [1875]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Dawkins refers to a discussion at the Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland on 9 February 1875, following the presentation of ‘The Basque and the Kelt’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Webster 1875</ref>). The printed paper included a detailed account of the discussion (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Webster 1875</ref>, pp. 20–9). It was a critique of Dawkins’s paper ‘The northern range of the Basques’, which had appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly Review</hi> in September 1874 (Dawkins 1874b). CD mentioned having read Dawkins’s paper in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9682.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Dawkins of 18 October [1874]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">An unsigned article, ‘Mr. Dawkins on the Basques’, appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, 12 September 1874, pp. 336–7. The reviewer, while accepting the anthropological evidence that Dawkins had highlighted, maintained that language remained an important tool for determining the migration of populations. Dawkins may also allude to a review of <hi rend="italic">Etruscan researches</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9339.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">I. Taylor 1874</ref>) in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 9 May 1874, pp. 625–6, in which the reviewer argued that when conflicting interpretations arose, philological evidence should outweigh ethnological evidence.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Lucien Bonaparte</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4195.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Archibald Henry Sayce</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7474.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Rhŷs</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Willem Jan van Eys</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In the discussion following <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Webster 1875</ref>, Dawkins countered the argument in ‘Mr. Dawkins on the Basques’ that the Basques might be of Finnish stock, by noting that Finns were a tall, fair, broad-headed race, physically indistinguishable from Kelts (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8757.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Webster 1875</ref>, p. 21). Finnish belongs to the Finno-Ugric language family.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>