<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11730">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Raphael Meldola   30 October 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">2670</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11730 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11730.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11730.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 130</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 130</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3289.xml">Meldola, Raphael</persName>
                <placeName>London, John St, 21</placeName>
                <date when="1878-10-30">30 Oct 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Plans to produce a translation of Weismann’s <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Descendenz-Theorie</hi> [1875–6] and would welcome a preface from CD.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Studien zur Descendenz-Theorie</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Weismann, A. F. L. 1875–1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Entomological Society | London</hi> | 21 John Street, | Bedford Row, | London W. C.</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 30/78</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Stimulated by your kind encouragement I have made every exertion to find some means of giving an English translation of Weismann’s “Studien zur Descendenz-Theorie” to the British Biological public &amp; I have at length succeeded in finding a man who offers to do the translating part of the undertaking at a mere nominal cost so that I propose to take the risk &amp; bring out the work.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
                    <p>My object in troubling you is to solicit your further support in the matter by asking you to do me the honour of writing a few prefatory remarks—a request which I should not have taken the liberty of making did I not know that the author of the book occupied such an elevated position in biological science.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Such a preface (however short) would moreover greatly add to the popularity of the work in this country &amp; would serve also to induce any publisher with whom I might enter into negociations to look upon the undertaking more favourably than he might otherwise be disposed to do.</p>
                    <p>There are one or two minor matters connected with this same subject about which I should much like to consult you before actually commencing &amp; I could much better treat of them in a short conversation with you if you would grant me that privilege. I am disengaged on Saturday afternoons &amp; Sundays &amp; if it would put you to no inconvenience I could come down at any time you like to fix. (Orpington Station?)<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Yours respectfully | R. Meldola.</p>
                    <p>P.S. I should wish it to be understood that this undertaking is to be done purely <hi rend="underline">con amore</hi><ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; for the sole purpose of making more widely known the existence of another large body of facts which can be explained only by the Descent Theory.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">No letter from CD encouraging Meldola to publish a translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Weismann’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Descendenz-Theorie</hi> (Studies in the theory of descent; Weismann 1875a and 1876) has been found. CD had introduced Meldola to Weismann's work and sent some of Weismann’s papers to him; Meldola then proposed the translation (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11148.xml">letter to Raphael Meldola, 22 September [1877]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11192.xml">letter from Raphael Meldola, 20 October 1877</ref>). Meldola himself was the named translator of the English edition (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10041.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1882</ref>). The translation included another of Weismann’s papers as the third part of the work (Weismann 1875b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD provided a brief prefatory notice to the English translation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10041.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1882</ref>, pp. v–vi).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The station nearest to CD’s home, Down House, was at Orpington, on a branch line of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4474.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">South Eastern Railway</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Con amore</hi>: with love (Italian; more often used as a tempo instruction in music).</note>
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>