<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11121">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. R. Wallace   31 August 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1794</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11121 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11121.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11121.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Marchant (1916) 1: 299</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Add MS 46434)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <idno>Add MS 46434</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1877-08-31">31 Aug 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Response to Wallace’s article ["The colours of animals and plants", <hi rend="italic">Macmillan’s Mag.</hi> (Sept 1877)] on sexual colours and "voluntary" sexual selection.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Macmillan’s Mag.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Wallace, A. R. 1877</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Aug 31. 1877</date>
                    <salute>My dear Wallace,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am very much obliged to you for sending your article; which is very interesting &amp; appears to me as clearly written as it can be.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> You will not be surprised that I differ altogether from you about sexual colours. That the tail of the peacock &amp; his elaborate display of it should be due merely to the vigour, activity, &amp; vitality of the male is to me as utterly incredible as my views are to you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Mantegazza published a few years ago in Italy a somewhat similar view.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I cannot help doubting about recognition through colour: our horses dogs, fowls, &amp; pigeons seem to know their own species however differently the individuals may be coloured. I wonder whether you attribute the odoriferous &amp; sound producing organs, when confined to the males to their greater vigour &amp;c. I could say a good deal in opposition to you, but my arguments would have no weight in your eyes &amp; I do not intend to write for the public anything on this or any other difficult subject. By the way I doubt whether the term voluntary in relation to sexual selection ought to be employed: when a man is fascinate〈d〉 by a pretty girl it can hardly be called voluntary, &amp; I suppose that female animals are charmed or excited in nearly the same manner by the gaudy males.</p>
<p>Three essays have been published lately in Germany which would interest you: one by Weismann who shows that the coloured stripes on the caterpillars of sphinx are beautifully protective: &amp; birds were frightened away from their feeding place by a caterpillar with large eye-like spots on the broad anterior segments of the body.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Fritz Müller has well discussed the first steps of mimicry with butterflies, &amp; comes to nearly or quite the same conclusions as you, but supports it by additional arguments.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Fritz Müller also has lately shown that the males alone of certain butterflies have odoriferous glands on their wings (distinct from those which secrete matter disgusting to birds) &amp; where these glands are placed, the scales assume a different shape making little tufts.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Farewell—I hope that you find Dorking a pleasant place? I was staying lately at Abinger Hall &amp; wished to come over to see you but driving tires me so much that my courage failed.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Chas. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Wallace sent a copy of the September issue of <hi rend="italic">Macmillan’s Magazine</hi>, which contained the first part of his article ‘The colours of animals and plants’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. R. Wallace 1877</ref>). CD’s annotated copy of the issue is in DAR 133: 18.1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD and Wallace had a longstanding debate about sexual dimorphism in regard to colour (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6375.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 18 September [1868]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6386.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 23 September [1868]</ref>; see also A. R. Wallace 1866, 1867, and 1868). In his article, Wallace argued that bright, intense colours were signs of robust health (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. R. Wallace 1877</ref>, p. 398); CD double-scored the passage in his copy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3154.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paolo Mantegazza</ref> had criticised CD’s theory of sexual selection in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>, especially the role of female choice (see Mantegazza 1871 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7963F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Paolo Mantegazza, 22 September 1871</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The first essay in the second volume of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Weismann’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Descendenz-Theorie</hi> (Studies on the theory of descent; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9324.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1876</ref>) was ‘Die Entstehung der Zeichnung bei den Schmetterlings-Raupen’ (The origin of markings on caterpillars of butterflies; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9324.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1876</ref>, pp. 1–137). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL. Weismann had studied caterpillars of <hi rend="italic">Chaerocampa elpenor</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Deilephila elpenor</hi>, the elephant hawk-moth) and <hi rend="italic">Chaerocampa porcellus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Deilephila porcellus</hi>, the small elephant hawk-moth).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1876 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. R. Wallace 1877</ref>, pp. 396–8. Wallace had earlier commented on some of Müller’s observations on mimicry (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 14 June 1871</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7899.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 7 August 1871</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Müller described the glands in his article ‘Ueber Haarpinsel, Filzflecke und ähnliche Gebilde auf den Flügeln männlicher Schmetterlinge’ (On hair-tufts, felted spots and similar structures on the wings of male butterflies; <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1877b). CD’s lightly annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In July 1876, Wallace had moved to Dorking, Surrey, which was near Abinger Hall, the home of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref>, where CD had visited from 20 to 25 August 1877 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6492.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raby 2001</ref>, p. 216, and CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>