<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8945">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   18 June 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9988</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8945 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8945.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8945.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian) †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 79</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 77: 152–3</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>77: 152–3</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                <date when="1873-06-18">18 June 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends information on <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus odoratus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Phaseolus multiflorus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pisum sativum</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Lathyrus odoratus</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Phaseolus multiflorus</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Pisum sativum</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00342_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00342_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="152r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00342.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00342_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00342.dzi" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="152v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00343.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00343_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00343.dzi" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="153r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00344.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00344_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00344.dzi" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="153v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00345.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00345_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00077-000-00345.dzi" width="3696px" height="6364px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                    <date>18. giugno 1873</date>
                    <salute>Onorevole Signore!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>La prego a volermi perdonare se ho tardato tanto a rispondere alla sua lettera ultima. Il fatto è che io sperava di darle più esatte e complete notizie intorno ai quesiti che si piacque di propormi.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Disgraziatamente ho potuto raccogliere pochissimo.</p>
<p>Il <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus odoratus</hi> è una pianta che nell’Italia media è poco coltivata e poco ricercata, massime in questi ultimi anni, dacchè essa è attaccata grandemente dall’<hi rend="underline">Oidium</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Nei giardinieri di Firenze è invalsa l’opinione che succeda incrociamento tra un individuo e l’altro, e che perciò non si possano conservar pure le varietà, se non che seminando separatamente gl’individui delle varie razze.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Un giardiniere botanico molto esperto, certo Sig. Paolo Baroni,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> mi assicurò che senza veruna cura per molti anni di seguito ebbe nella stessa ajuola sempre una stessa varietà; ma egli crede fermamente che non si sia propagata ivi per semi, bensi per gemme radicali perennanti (possibilmente per quei tubercoletti che si scorgono nelle radici de molti <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus</hi>).</p>
<p>Quanto poi al <hi rend="underline">Phaseolus multiflorus</hi> lo stesso giardiniere è nella più ferma convinzione, che per ottenere la varietà pura bisogni impedire del tutto l’incrociamento per mezzo degl’insetti.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Quanto al <hi rend="underline">Pisum sativum</hi> è una pianta che da noi si coltiva soltanto negli orti e nelle campagne, per comestibile. Ve ne sono parecchie varietà, e si conservano generalmente pure perchè da per tutto si coltivano in grandi masse separate. Del resto io non ho mai osservato insetti sul <hi rend="underline">Pisum</hi>; per cui credo che in mancanza d’insetti si possa perfettamente fecondare omogamicamente<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>La ringrazio delle cortesi espessioni a mio riguardo contenute nella sua lettera. Gl’incoraggiamenti d’una persona tanto autorevole mi sono di grande conforto; tanto più che vedo troppo <hi rend="underline">spesso</hi> come le mie idee trovano avversarii che mi sembrano meno giusti. Per esempio ultimamente io ricevetti una memoria di G. Bentham sulle Composte, nella quale mi vengono fatte delle critiche ben poco fondate. O non ha ben compreso la forza delle mie ragioni o ha dato una lettura troppo superficiale del mio scritto sulle <hi rend="underline">artemisiacee</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Credo che sarò in dovere di rispondergli, non per me ma per i principii che sostengo. Scientificamente parlando noi oggidì ci troviamo in una brutta crisi; vi ha tutta una vecchia scuola che non ha il coraggio di accettare in tutta la sua estensione la dottrina della trasformazione degli organismi. Ora per me questa dottrina è dottrina di fatto, non già ipotesi. Adunque si deve cominciare a farne applicazione alla tassonomia. Ma come mai i tassonomi dell’antica scuola potranno piegarsi alle nuove forme della tassonomia genealogica?</p>
<p>Ho avuto il libro del D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. E. Müller.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> È un libro prezioso sotto molti aspetti, e dovrà servire di punto di partenza alle numerose ricerche che dovranno essere fatte secondo la stessa direzione. Per altro in molte idee fondamentali non mi trovo punto d’accordo. E. Müller, con pazienza e precisione veramente germanica, ha <hi rend="underline">annoverato</hi> le visite degl’insetti, ma non le ha <hi rend="underline">pesate</hi>. Cosicchè in molti punti dovremo essere di diverso parere. Per esempio, secondo le di Lei osservazioni e secondo le mie, i fiori di trifoglio sono esclusivamente designati per le apiarie (è una pianta <hi rend="underline">melittofila</hi><ref target="#foot.f10"/>); ma per caso vi si poserà una <hi rend="underline">farfalla</hi>; ora di questa visita E. Müller terrà stretto conto, mentre io non credo farne il minimo caso, giacchè la reputo un accidentalità destituita di ogni funzione. Del resto mi sembra un opera utile e conscienziosa in grado insigne.</p>
<p>Gradisca, Uomo celeberrimo, gli attestati della mia profondissima stima ed ossequio. | Suo devotissimo discepolo | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.1 Il … <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus</hi>). 2.10] ‘not much [<hi rend="italic">ink over pencil</hi>] cultivated; but firm [<hi rend="italic">ink over pencil</hi>] belief in Florence that vars. must [<hi rend="italic">ink over pencil</hi>] be separated [‘se’ <hi rend="italic">ink over pencil</hi>]’</note>
                <note>3.1 Quanto … degl’insetti 3.3] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon;</hi> ‘same gardener [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] believes it necessary to prevent crossing by insects’ <hi rend="italic">pencil;</hi> ‘Ph. multiflorus note’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 Quanto … omogamicamente 4.5] ‘Does not know about Pisum’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 La … Delpino. 7.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Sweet Peas’ <hi rend="italic">red crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Bottom of letter pencil</hi>:<ref target="#foot.f11"/>
                    <figure type="inlinediagram">
                        <formula>
                            <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> 
                                <mfenced open="{" close="}">
                                    <mtable>
                                        <mtr>
                                            <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>&#x93;Kerner</mtext></mtd>
                                        </mtr>
                                        <mtr>
                                            <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>H. Muller</mtext></mtd>
                                        </mtr>			
                                    </mtable>
                                </mfenced>
                                <mspace linebreak="newline"/>
                                <mtable>
                                    <mtr>
                                        <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>   Moths</mtext></mtd>
                                    </mtr>
                                    <mtr>
                                        <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>   Bentham</mtext></mtd>
                                    </mtr>	
                                    <mtr>
                                        <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>   Lathyrus</mtext></mtd>
                                    </mtr>
                                </mtable>
                                <mspace linebreak="newline"/>                                
                                <mfenced open="" close="}">		
                                    <mtable>
                                        <mtr>
                                            <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>  Pisum sativum</mtext></mtd>
                                        </mtr>
                                        <mtr>
                                            <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>  Bees visit</mtext></mtd>
                                        </mtr>
                                        <mtr>
                                            <mtd columnalign="left"><mtext>  Explanation</mtext></mtd>
                                        </mtr>
                                    </mtable>
                                </mfenced>                                
                            </math>
                        </formula>
                </figure>
               </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                    <date>18. June 1873</date>
                    <salute>Esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I beg you to forgive the long delay in replying to your recent letter. You see, I had hoped to be able to give you more precise and more complete information regarding the questions that you deigned put to me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Most unfortunately I could gather only very little information.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus odoratus</hi> is a plant that in central Italy is cultivated hardly at all and researched only a little, above all in recent years, because it has been greatly attacked by <hi rend="underline">Oidium</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Among the gardeners of Florence the view prevails that crossing between one individual race and another may occur, and that consequently the varieties cannot be preserved, unless one sows them separately.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> A very experienced plant breeder, a certain Sig. Paolo Baroni,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> assured me that after many successive years during which they had not been attended to, there was always the same variety in the same flower bed; he firmly believes, however, that it did not propagate there through seeds, but rather through perennial root buds (possibly through these little tubercules one can see in the roots of many <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus</hi>).</p>
<p>Regarding <hi rend="underline">Phaseolus multiflorus</hi>, then, the same gardener is absolutely convinced that in order to obtain the pure variety one must above all prevent crossing by means of insects.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Regarding <hi rend="underline">Pisum sativum</hi>, over here this plant is grown only in kitchen gardens and in the country, as foodstuff. There are quite a few varieties of it, and they generally remain pure because they are mostly grown in great separate masses. Apart from that, I have never observed insects on <hi rend="underline">Pisum</hi>, and I therefore believe that in the absence of insects homogamic fertilisation is perfectly possible.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I thank you for the courteous words about myself in your letter. To receive encouragement from such an authority is a great comfort to me; all the more so since far too <hi rend="underline">often</hi> I see my ideas find critics who strike me as less fair. Most recently, for example, I received a note by G. Bentham on composites, in which I suffered fairly unfounded criticism. Either he has not understood the force of my argument, or he must have given my work on <hi rend="underline">Artemisiaceae</hi> a too superficial reading.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I believe I owe him a response, not on my account but for the principles that I uphold. Scientifically speaking we find ourselves in a nasty crisis these days; there is this whole old school here, which consists entirely of people who lack the courage fully to accept the doctrine of the transformation of organisms. Now for me, this doctrine is factual truth, not just a hypothesis. Well, then we must apply it to taxonomy. But how could the taxonomists of the ancient school ever bow to the new forms of genealogical taxonomy?</p>
<p>I have received D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. H. Müller’s book.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> It is very valuable in many respects, and it surely must serve as the starting point for numerous investigations that must be undertaken in the same direction. Having said that, I don’t find myself wholly in agreement with quite a number of fundamental points in it. H. Müller, with truly Germanic patience and precision, has <hi rend="underline">counted</hi> the visits of insects, but he has not <hi rend="underline">weighed</hi> them. As a result, he and I must differ on many points. For example, according to your observations and mine, clover flowers are designed exclusively for bees (it is a <hi rend="underline">melittophilous</hi> plant);<ref target="#foot.f10"/> by accident, however, a <hi rend="underline">butterfly</hi> might land on it; now, such a visit H. Müller will count strictly, while I would not make anything of it, since I would regard it as an accident without the slightest function. Apart from this, the book seems to me very useful to me and conscientious in the highest degree.</p>
<p>Most distinguished man, allow me to assure you of my most profound esteem and regard | Your most devoted disciple | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 258–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had asked whether different coloured varieties of <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus odoratus</hi> (sweetpeas), <hi rend="italic">Pisum sativum</hi> (garden peas), and <hi rend="italic">Phaseolus multiflorus</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Phaseolus coccineus</hi>; runner-beans), intercrossed when left unprotected from insects (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Federico Delpino, 1 May 1873</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Oidium</hi> is a genus of fungi that causes powdery mildew.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD quoted Delpino’s remarks in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 156. He was unable to account for the fact that varieties of <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus odoratus</hi> never intercrossed in England but did so in northern Italy (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 168–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Baroni was head gardener of the Giardino dei Semplici in Florence (<hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 5 January 1878, p. 22).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 168, CD remarked of <hi rend="italic">Phaseolus multiflorus</hi>: ‘there is reason to believe that varieties growing near one another intercross’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD concluded that the many varieties of <hi rend="italic">Pisum sativum</hi>, though growing in close proximity, very seldom intercrossed (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, p. 169).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref> criticised Delpino’s classification of the Artemisiaceae (Delpino 1871) for relying too exclusively on different pollination mechanisms (Bentham 1873a, pp. 342–3). CD had received Delpino’s paper in 1871 and suggested that he send it to Bentham (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Federico Delpino, 22 November 1871</ref>). The family Artemisiaceae is now subsumed within the family Asteraceae (sunflowers).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD had remarked on the excellence of Herman Müller’s <hi rend="italic">Die Befruchtung der Blumen durch Insekten und die gegenseitigen Anpassungen Beider</hi> (The fertilisation of flowers by means of insects and their mutual adaptations; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>) in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8892.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Delpino of 1 May 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">‘Melittophilous’ refers to plants that rely on bees for pollination; from ‘melitta’: bee (Greek). For CD’s interest in the pollination of <hi rend="italic">Trifolium</hi> (clover) by bees, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 94–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD’s annotation is a note for his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8951.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Delpino of 25 June [1873]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>