<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-548B">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To William Walton   [1840–2]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20359</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-548B by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-548B.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-548B.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 2: 246–7</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Walton 1844, pp. 50–1</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Walton, William 1844: 50–1</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <date notBefore="1840-01-01" notAfter="1842-12-31">[1840–2]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4952.xml">Walton, William</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes the range of conditions under which the guanaco thrives and the ease with which it can be tamed.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">guanaco</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
<p>“Perhaps there is no animal in the world which, in its wild state, flourishes under stations of such different, and indeed directly opposite characters, as the guanaco. I saw them on the hot deserts near Northern Chile, where the climate is excessively dry; on the borders of perpetual snow, at the height of 12,000 feet; and on the rocky and bare mountains of the same country. They swarm in great herds on the most sterile plains of gravel, composing Patagonia. Formerly they were numerous on the grassy savannahs stretching on the banks of La Plata, where during half the year the summer is hot, and in the winter abundant rain falls; and lastly, the guanaco lives on the peat-covered mountains, and in the thick entangled forests of <hi rend="underline">Tierra del Fuego,</hi> of which country the climate is far more humid and boisterous, and the summer less warm, than in any part of Great Britain. I could perceive no difference in the guanacos of these several regions. If the alpaca be the same species, or has the same constitution, as the guanaco, these facts regarding the range of the latter are interesting, as they show under what various conditions we might expect the alpaca to thrive. I will only add, that the guanaco so easily becomes tame, that young ones, caught and brought up at farm-houses, seldom leave them, although ranging at full liberty near their native plains.”</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated on the basis of the letter to the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, 13 May [1840–2].</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>