<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13117">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>   14 April [1881]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15671</idno>
            
            
            
            
           
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13117 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13117.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13117.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 228–9</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 28 April 1881, pp. 603–4</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature, 28 April 1881, pp. 603–4</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-14">14 Apr [1881]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3491.xml">Nature</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Summarises a letter from Fritz Müller [missing] giving details of leaf movement in <hi rend="italic">Mucuna</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Bauhinia</hi>. CD is especially interested in the paraheliotropic movements, which appear to be as common as sleep movements.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Bauhinia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Desmodium</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Mucuna</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-09-20" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-27" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p rend="centre"><hi rend="bold">The Movements of Leaves</hi></p> 
<p>F<hi rend="smallCaps">ritz</hi> M<hi rend="smallCaps">ueller</hi> has sent me some additional observations on the movements of leaves, when exposed to a bright light.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Such movements seem to be as well developed and as diversified under the bright sun of Brazil, as are the well-known sleep or nyctitropic movements of plants in all parts of the world. This result has interested me much, as I long doubted whether paraheliotropic movements were common enough to deserve to be separately designated. It is a remarkable fact that in certain species these movements closely resemble the sleep movements of allied forms. Thus the leaflets of one of the Brazilian Cassiæ assume when exposed to sunshine nearly the same position as those of the not distantly allied Hæmatoxylon when asleep, as shown in Fig. 153 of “The Movements of Plants.”<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Whereas the leaflets of this Cassia sleep by moving down and rotating on their axes, in the same peculiar manner as in so many other species of the genus. Again, with an unnamed species of Phyllanthus, the leaves move forwards at night, so that their midribs then stand nearly parallel to the horizontal branches from which they spring; but when they are exposed to bright sunshine they rise up vertically, and their upper surfaces come into contact, as they are opposite. Now this is the position which the leaves of another species, namely <hi rend="underline">Phyllanthus compressus</hi>, assume when they go to sleep at night.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Fritz Müller states that the paraheliotropic movements of the leaves of a Mucuna,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> a large twining Papilionaceous plant, are strange and inexplicable; the leaflets sleep by hanging vertically down, but under bright sunshine the petiole rises vertically up, and the terminal leaflet rotates by means of its pulvinus through an angle of 180<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, and thus its upper surface stands on the same side with the lower surfaces of the lateral leaflets. Fritz Müller adds, “I do not understand the meaning of this rotation of the terminal leaflet, as even without such a movement it would be apparently equally well protected against the rays of the sun. The leaflets, also, on many of the leaves on the same plant assume various other strange positions.” With one species of Desmodium, presently to be mentioned as sleeping in a remarkable manner, the leaflets rise up vertically when exposed to bright sunshine, and the upper surfaces of the lateral leaflets are thus brought into contact. The leaves of <hi rend="underline">Bauhinia grandiflora</hi> go to sleep at an unusually early hour in the evening, and in the manner described at p. 373 of “The Movements of Plants,” namely, by the two halves of the same leaf rising up and coming into close contact: now the leaves of <hi rend="underline">Bauhinia Brasiliensis</hi> do not sleep, as far as Fritz Müller has seen, but they are very sensitive to a bright light, and when thus exposed the two halves rise up and stand at 45<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> or upwards above the horizon.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Fritz Müller has sent me some cases, in addition to those given in my former letter of March 3, of the leaves of closely-allied plants which assume a vertical position at night by widely different movements; and these cases are of interest as indicating that sleep-movements have been acquired for a special purpose. We have just seen that of two species of Bauhinia the leaves of one sleep conspicuously, while those of a second species apparently do not sleep at all. The leaves of <hi rend="underline">Euphorbia jacquiniæflora</hi> depend vertically at night, whereas those of a dwarfish Brazilian species rise vertically up at night.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The leaves of this Euphorbia stand opposite one another—a position which is rather rare in the genus; and the rising movement may be of service to the plant, as the upper surfaces of the opposite leaves mutually protect one another by coming into contact. In the genus Sida the leaves of two species rise, while those of a third Brazilian species sink vertically down at night.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Two species of Desmodium are common plants near Fritz Müller’s house: in one the leaflets move simply downwards at night; but in the other not only do the three leaflets move vertically down, while the main petiole rises vertically up, as is likewise the case with <hi rend="underline">D. gyrans</hi>, but in addition the lateral leaflets rotate so as to stand parallel with the terminal leaflet, behind which they are more or less completely hidden.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> This, as far as I have seen, is a new kind of nyctitropic movement; but it leads to a result common to several species, namely, that of packing the three leaflets closely together and placing them in a vertical position.</p>
<p>C<hi rend="smallCaps">harles</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">arwin</hi> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Down, Beckenham, Kent, April 14</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
          
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the date of publication of this letter in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For Müller’s earlier observations, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13061.xml">letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 22 February [1881]</ref>. In that letter, published in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 3 March 1881, CD had summarised information on leaf movement contained in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12996.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 9 January 1881</ref>. The information in this letter was probably from the now missing part of the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13068A.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 28 February 1881</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had coined the term ‘paraheliotropic’ to describe the movement of leaves during the day to reduce intense illumination (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 419). <hi rend="italic">Cassia</hi> is a genus of the legume family (Fabaceae). <hi rend="italic">Haematoxylon</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Haematoxylum</hi>, the genus of logwood) is in the same family. For the image of <hi rend="italic">Haematoxylon campechianum</hi> (bloodwood tree), see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 369. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In a short article in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>, ‘Verirrte Blätter’ (Stray leaves; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11328.xml">F. Müller 1881b</ref>), Müller described and figured the movement of leaves of a plant of an unnamed species of <hi rend="italic">Phyllanthus</hi> (the genus of leaf flower) growing in his garden.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Mucuna</hi> is a tropical genus of mostly lianas of the legume family (Fabaceae).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Bauhinia grandiflora</hi> a synonym of <hi rend="italic">B. aculeata</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">grandiflora</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">B. brasiliensis</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">B. forficata</hi>) have bi-lobed leaves that fold along the midrib. Müller described and figured the folding of the leaves in the latter species in ‘Eine Beobachtung an <hi rend="italic">Bauhinia brasiliensis</hi>’ (An observation on <hi rend="italic">Bauhinia brasiliensis</hi>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11329.xml">F. Müller 1882</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, p. 388, CD had noted that young leaves of <hi rend="italic">Euphorbia jacquiniaeflora</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Euphorbia fulgens</hi>, scarlet plume) slept by hanging vertically downwards.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Sida</hi> is the genus of fanpetals (family Malvaceae). In <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, p. 322, CD noted that leaves of <hi rend="italic">S. rhombifolia</hi> (arrowleaf sida) and <hi rend="italic">S. retusa</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">S. alnifolia</hi>) rose up vertically at night, while those of <hi rend="italic">S. napaea</hi> fell.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Desmodium</hi> is the genus of tick trefoil (family Fabaceae). CD discussed the movements of <hi rend="italic">Desmodium gyrans</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Codariocalyx motorius</hi>, the telegraph or semaphore plant) in <hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi>, pp. 357–65.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>