<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11558">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Arnold Dodel-Port<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   18 June 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16761</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11558 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11558.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11558.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 198</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 198</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1342.xml">Dodel-Port, Arnold</persName>
                <placeName>Zurich</placeName>
                <date when="1878-06-18">18 June 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on positive response to publication [of <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>]. CD’s approval will help make an English edition possible. Rejects suggestion that CD should subscribe.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Atlas der Botanik</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Dodel-Port, Arnold 1878</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Hottingen | Zürich,</placeName>
                    <date>18. Juni 1878.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Herrn Charles Darwin in Down, Beckenham | Kent. England.</seg>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Mit grosser Genugthuung haben wir aus Ihrem Geehrten vom 15. d. Ms gesehen, dass Sie mit der Art und Weise der Ausführung unseres Tafelwerkes sehr zufrieden sind. So viel jetzt bekannt ist, wird unser “Atlas” von allen Seiten mit Anerkennung &amp; Freude begrüsst.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Von allen Seiten kommen die besten Nachrichten &amp; zwar von den namhaftesten Repräsentanten deutscher Wissenschaft, so von Prof. Julius Sachs in Würzburg, Oscar Brefeld in Berlin, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hermann Müller in Lippstadt, der uns noch weitere Materialien für Blumentafeln offerirt &amp; Anderen mehr. Die Hoffnungen der Herausgeber &amp; Verleger scheinen somit in Erfüllung zu gehen und das ganze Werk wird zweifelsohne innerhalb der nächsten 2 Jahre vollendet werden können.</p>
                    <p>Sie waren so freundlich, uns die Adresse eines englischen Verlegers von Schulbüchern mitzutheilen, wofür ich Ihnen herzlich danke. Mein Verleger wird sich also ohne Zweifel an die genannte Londoner Adresse wenden.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Von eminentester Bedeutung für die Ausbreitung unseres Atlas auch im <hi rend="underline">englischen</hi> Sprachgebiet wird der Umstand sein, dass <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi> ein so lebhaftes Interesse an der Ausführung unseres Vorhabens genommen haben, und für uns gibt es keine grössere Satisfaction als <hi rend="underline">Ihr</hi> Beifall gerade in Sachen jener Tafeln, die namentlich der Veranschaulichung der Blumen-Theorie (Fremdbestäubung) gelten, die ja durch <hi rend="underline">Ihre</hi> Initiative so schnell &amp; siegreich die Welt erobert hat. Ueberall wird die Salvia-Tafel von Gelehrten &amp; Laien mit gleich grossem Interesse entgegengenommen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (Der Verleger wird noch weitere 1000 Exemplare nachdrucken lassen.) Sie sehen, dass man durch <hi rend="underline">Anschauung</hi> für eine wissenschaftliche Wahrheit erfolgreich Propaganda machen kann. Es wird uns jetzt nicht schwer sein, einen englischen Verleger zu gewinnen und wir hoffen, die englische Ausgabe auch schon in zwei Monaten im Buchhandel zu sehen.</p>
                    <p>Sie schreiben gegen den Schluss ihres Geehrten: “I hope that you will allow me to become a regular subscriber to the work”.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Hiegegen muss ich Sie bitten, zu entschuldigen, wenn ich feierlich gegen dieses Ihr Vorhaben protestire. Ich verdanke Ihnen, hochgeehrtester Herr, so unendlich Viel, dass mir in meinem ganzen Leben nie möglich sein wird, Ihnen diesen Dank in würdiger Form abzustatten. Es ist nur ein Versuch, diese meine innerste Gesinnung schwach anzudeuten, wenn ich mir erlaube, Ihnen von Zeit zu Zeit davon Kenntniss zu geben, was wir bearbeiten. Ohne Sie &amp; Ihre Alles befruchtende Wissenschaft wäre auch unser Atlas nicht zu Stande gekommen. Sie erlauben also gütigst dass wir Ihre Subscription <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi> annehmen, sondern stolz &amp; glücklich sein werden, Ihnen die folgenden Lieferungen gleichfalls zu übermachen als warmer Gruss vom Continent.</p>
<p>Ich verbleibe in dankbarster Gesinnung und | innigster Verehrung | Ihr ergebenster | Arnold Dodel-Port</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Hottingen | Zurich,</placeName>
                    <date>18. June 1878.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Mr Charles Darwin in Down, Beckenham | Kent. England.</seg>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>With the greatest satisfaction we gathered from your honoured letter of the 15th of the month that you are very pleased with the manner in which our atlas has been executed. As far as we know at the moment, our “Atlas” is being received from all sides with appreciation &amp; joy.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> From every quarter we receive the best news, that is, from the most renowned representatives of German scholarship, for example from Prof. Julius Sachs in Würzburg, Oscar Brefeld in Berlin, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hermann Müller in Lippstadt, who is offering us yet more material for the plates of flowers, &amp; many others as well. Thus the hopes of the editors &amp; publishers appear to be coming true, and without doubt it will be possible to complete the entire work within the next 2 years.</p>
                    <p>You were so kind as to communicate to us the address of an English publisher of textbooks, for which I thank you cordially. No doubt my publisher will contact the London address you provided.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>For the dissemination of our atlas, in the <hi rend="underline">English</hi>-speaking world as well, the circumstance that <hi rend="underline">you</hi> have taken such a lively interest in the execution of our project will be of most eminent importance, and for us there is no greater satisfaction than <hi rend="underline">your</hi> approval particularly as concerns those plates that illustrate the theory of flowers (cross-fertilisation), which as we know has captured the world so quickly and so victoriously due to <hi rend="underline">your</hi> initiative. The plate of Salvia is received everywhere with great interest on the part of scholars &amp; laypersons alike.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (The publisher will have a further 1000 copies printed.) As you can see, it is possible to make successful propaganda for scientific truth through <hi rend="underline">visual means</hi>. Now it will not be difficult to get an English publisher interested and we hope the English edition will be out in two months’ time.</p>
                    <p>You write towards the end of your honoured letter: “I hope that you will allow me to become a regular subscriber to the work.”—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> But I must beg you to forgive me for solemnly protesting against your plan. I owe you, most esteemed Sir, so infinitely much that in my whole life it will never be possible for me to express my thanks adequately. It is merely as a feeble attempt at intimating my innermost sentiments that I allow myself occasionally to report to you about our work. Without you &amp; your all-enriching science our atlas would not have come together. Therefore kindly allow us <hi rend="underline">not</hi> to accept your subscription, but let us be proud &amp; happy to make the subsequent instalments over to you as well, as a warm greeting from the continent.</p>
<p>I remain in the deepest gratitude and | the most heartfelt veneration | yours devoted | Arnold Dodel-Port</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div> 
         
         
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 240–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11554.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Arnold Dodel-Port, 15 June 1878</ref>. Dodel-Port had sent CD the first part of his botanical atlas (Dodel-Port and Dodel-Port 1878–83).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11554.xml">letter to Dodel-Port of 15 June 1878</ref>, CD had recommended Longman &amp; Co. as a publisher for the English translation; an English translation of the explanatory texts for the atlas was published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">W. &amp; A. K. Johnston</ref> (Dodel-Port and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9591.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dodel-Port 1880–3</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Dodel-Port had drawn CD’s attention to the plate of <hi rend="italic">Salvia sclarea</hi> (Dodel-Port and Dodel-Port 1878–83, plate 11) because CD had worked on the genus for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11552.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Arnold Dodel-Port, 12 June 1878</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11554.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Arnold Dodel-Port, 15 June 1878</ref>.</note> 
        </div>      
          
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>