<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-837">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From C. G. Ehrenberg   13 March 1845<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1897</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1988">1988</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-837 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-837.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-837.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="03">3</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German) †, CD note</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 39: 59a–c</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>39: 59a–c</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1480.xml">Ehrenberg, C. G.</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1845-03-13">13 Mar 1845</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Regrets J. D. Hooker did not visit Berlin.</p>
            <p>Describes legal difficulties of Ernst Dieffenbach.</p>
            <p>Lists species of Infusoria found in dust samples. Discusses origin of Atlantic dust. Discusses Infusoria in cosmetic paint from Tierra del Fuego and Patagonian earth. Thanks CD for samples. Would like samples from sea-bed.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Infusoria</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">dust</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1322">Dieffenbach, Ernst</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2357">Hooker, J. D.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Berlin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                    <date>d. 13 Maerz 1845.</date>
                    <salute>Mein hochzuverehrender Herr</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><anchor xml:id="ann.a1" type="annotationStart"/>Leider ist Herr Dr. Hooker nicht nach Berlin gekommen und somit haben sich die Erfüllungen Ihrer Wünsche noch mehr verspätet.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Da sich heut eine Gelegenheit biethet Ihnen das Manuscript über den Meteorstaub wieder zuzu-senden, so ergreiffe ich dieselbe obschon ich dadurch gehindert bin Ihnen ausführlicher zu schreiben. Zuerst spreche ich einige Worte über Dr. Dieffenbach, der leider schon bei Ankunft Ihres ersten Briefes nicht mehr in Berlin war. Der arme Mann hat, wie Ihnen wohl bekannt ist, sein Vaterland verlaßen müßen, weil er in politischen Beziehungen gewesen war, die nicht geduldet wurden. Um dieß für sein weiteres Fortkommen weniger schädlich zu machen hatte er eben eine Reise angetreten mit der er sich zu gerichtlicher Vernehmung und wo möglich Reinigung in Gießen stellen wollte, in der Hoffnung bald los zu kommen. So sizt er aber nun bereits <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> Jahr in Gießen, ohne das gewünschte Resultat zu erreichen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Im Herbste war ich selbst auf mehrere Monate verreist und dann sehr beschäftigt. Ihren zweiten Brief habe ich stets bei mir zur Erinnerung gehabt, ich habe alsbald an Dr Dieffenbach geschrieben und von ihm beiliegende Antwort erhalten. Hoffentlich haben Sie durch den Buchhändler die gewünschten Sachen nun schon erhalten.</p>
<p>Was Ihre vortrefflichen Nachrichten und besonders Materialien über den atlantischen Meteorstaub anlangt, so kann ich Ihnen denn nun auch das Resultat der Untersuchung mittheilen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Außer den schon früher verzeichneten 37 mikroskopischen Organismen,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> welche den Meteorstaub erfüllen und bilden helfen haben sich nun noch 29 andere erkennen laßen diag Cocconema Lunula Eunotia Argus —— granulata —— longicornis —— Pileus —— quaternaria —— tridentula —— Triodon Gallionella decussata Grammatophora oceanica Gomphonema gracile Navicula Bacillum Pinnularia viridula</p>
<p>—— Amphidiscus armatus —— obtusus Lithodontium rostratum —— platyodon Lithostylidium biconcavum —— crenulatum —— Clepsammidium —— Emblema —— obliquum Lithostylidium Rhombus —— rostratum —— Rajarum —— unidentatum Spongolithis cenocephala —— Fustis</p>
<p>—— Textilaria globulosa.ramme</p>
<p>Diese sind nun dadurch sehr merkwürdig, daß auch unter ihnen keine einzige der eigenthümlichen mir schon mannichfach bekan〈n〉ten Küstenformen von Senegambien und aus der Sahara überhaupt aus Africa ist. Nur Lith. Rajarum ist mir auch aus Isle de France<ref target="#foot.f6"/> bekannt.<anchor xml:id="ann.a4" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>Unter allen 66 Formen ist keine neue, indem Eunotia longicornis sehr ähnlich in Ungarn fossil vorkommt.</p>
<p>Dagegen wie unter den ersten 37 Arten 2 characteristisch für America waren, so sind unter den lezten 29 wieder 4 welche Guiana und Senegambien gemeinsam sind, nämlich Eunotia quaternaria Eunotia tridentula [Eunotia] Pileus Amphidiscus obtusus.</p>
<p>Ferner verhalten<anchor xml:id="ann.a2" type="annotationEnd"/> sich alle 6 von Ihnen mir übersandten Staub-Arten ganz gleich. Sie zeigen alle eine sehr reiche Mischung von Kieselschaligen Infusorien und auch gleicher Arten.</p>
<p>Man kann nun mit Sicherheit aussprechen, daß aller Staub der 6 Proben aus einer und derselben Quelle kommen muß. <anchor xml:id="ann.a3" type="annotationStart"/>Dieser Quelle läßt sich noch näher kommen.— Vorher waren nur Süßwasser Thierchen vorgekommen, diese konnten aus der Mitte eines Festlandes seyn. Jezt sind auch 2 reine Seethierchen dabey gefunden, Grammatophora oceanica und Textilaria globulosa. So muß nun die Quelle des Staubes eine Küsten-Gegend seyn. Am nächsten liegt freylich die afrikanische Küste, aber es sind keine afrikanischen Formen darunter, obschon viele davon Weltbürger sind. Dagegen sind nun 6 Südamerikanische dabei.</p>
<p>Ferner habe ich ermittelt, daß der Wind mit welchem der Staub niederfällt, nach Angabe der Schiffer nie ausdrücklich der Harmattan ist, sondern daß es der Passat-Wind ausdrücklich ist. Sie haben ihre eigne Erfahrung mit scharfer Unterscheidung nicht hervorgehoben, was aber sehr wünschenswerth ist. Wahrscheinlich stehen Ihnen noch Schiffs-Journale zu Gebote um diess scharf zu ermitteln. Lebende Dinge habe ich nicht dabey gefunden, solche nemlich die schnell eingetrocknet noch Organe zeigten.— <anchor xml:id="ann.a5" type="annotationStart"/>Es wäre gut auf San Jago und an der afrikanischen Küste directe vergleichende längere Beobachtungen über diesen wunderbaren Staub zu veranlaßen. Sie scheinen alle Mittel nahe zu haben um dieß zu erreichen und werden nun gewiß es versuchen.<anchor xml:id="ann.a6" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>Recht interessant war mir auch Ihre Schminke aus dem Feuerland die ebenfalls aus Infusorien besteht, das erste dort vorgekommene fossile Lager. Ich habe bis jezt 18 Species ermittelt, wovon keine neu ist aber lauter Süßwasser-Formen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Die weiße Erde in Patagonien würde ich für ein vulkanisches Product halten.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Sie erscheint bimsteinartig, nämlich wie verwitterter Bimstein und ich habe auch darinn, aber nur wenig, fast unkentliche, doch mir noch deutlich werdende Infusorien Schalen erkannt. Es ist vorläufig eine Species der Gattung Fragilaria, wie es scheint, nennbar. Ich habe leider jezt zu viel andere Beschäftigung um recht intensiv die Sache zu verfolgen, doch halte ich das Verhältniß für sehr interessant wenn es nicht allzu lokal ist. Ist die Erde nur staubig, nicht festes Gestein? Wie mächtig schätzen Sie die Lagerung? wie weit die Ausdehnung? Stunden? Meilen? Sollte es wirklich Hunderte von Meilen weit ausgedehnt seyn, wenn ich recht verstehe, so müßen deutliche vulkanische Gebirgs Formen es so weit begleiten.</p>
<p><anchor xml:id="ann.a7" type="annotationStart"/>Weiter kann ich Ihnen für heut keine Nachricht geben. Nur noch großen Dank für die übersandten reichen Materialien, Ihnen und Herrn Dr. Hooker der leider verschmäht hat einige Zeit unter uns, die wir ihn recht freundlich aufgenommen haben würden, zu verweilen.</p>
<p>Aus großen Meeres Tiefen von beiläufig 10000 bis 20000 Fuß, man will ja 24000 F. gemessen haben wären mir die kleinsten Proben sehr erwünscht, mit oder ohne Talg des Senkloths.</p>
<p>In herzlicher Hochachtung verharrend<anchor xml:id="ann.a8" type="annotationEnd"/> | Ihr | ganz ergebenster | Dr C G Ehrenberg<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note target="#ann.a1" targetEnd="#ann.a2"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 3.11 Textilaria globulosa] <hi rend="italic">added pencil cross</hi>; ‘marine’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi> </note>
                <note> 3.13 Grammatophora oceanica] <hi rend="italic">added pencil cross</hi>; ‘marine’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi> </note>
                <note target="#ann.a3" targetEnd="#ann.a4">‘?’<hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a5" targetEnd="#ann.a6"><hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 9.9 Mittel] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi> </note>
                <note> 10.2 das erste dort vorgekommene] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi>; ‘?’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi> </note>
                <note> 11.10 Gebirgs] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi>; ‘<hi rend="italic">[reverse question mark]</hi>.’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil over</hi> ‘?’ </note>
                <note target="#ann.a7" targetEnd="#ann.a8"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> <hi rend="italic">Top of second page</hi>: ‘Patagonian tuff—&amp; Fuegian paint’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi> </note>
                <note> <hi rend="italic">Bottom of last page</hi>: ‘Pampas— | Cordillera Honestone | my infusoria’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi> ‘I believe nothing particular’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi> </note>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                    <date>13 March 1845</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Unfortunately Dr. Hooker did not come to Berlin and thus there will be further delays in carrying out your wishes.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Since I have an opportunity today of returning to you the manuscript on the atmospheric dust, I am taking it although it prevents me from writing to you in more detail. First I want to say a few words about Dr. Dieffenbach, who unfortunately had already left Berlin when your first letter arrived. As you may know, the poor man had to leave his fatherland because he had political connections that were not tolerated. In order to make this less damaging to his future career, he set out on a journey to Giessen in order to appear before a judicial examination where he might clear himself. He hoped to get away soon, but he has already been sitting in Giessen now for half a year without accomplishing the desired result.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I myself was travelling for several months in the autumn and was then very busy. I always had your second letter with me as a reminder. I wrote immediately to Dr Dieffenbach and received the enclosed answer from him. I hope you have already received the things you wanted from the book dealer.</p>
<p>As for your excellent reports on the Atlantic atmospheric dust and particularly your material, I can now also inform you of the result of the investigation.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Apart from the 37 microscopic organisms partly constituting the atmospheric dust which have already been listed earlier,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> another 29 can now be recognised</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>Cocconema Lunula Eunotia Argus —— granulata —— longicornis —— Pileus —— quaternaria —— tridentula —— Triodon Gallionella decussata Grammatophora oceanica Gomphonema gracile Navicula Bacillum Pinnularia viridula</p>
<p>—— Amphidiscus armatus —— obtusus Lithodontium rostratum —— platyodon Lithostylidium biconcavum —— crenulatum —— Clepsammidium —— Emblema —— obliquum Lithostylidium Rhombus —— rostratum —— Rajarum —— unidentatum Spongolithis cenocephala —— Fustis Textilaria globulosa.</p> </figure> 
<p>Now these are especially remarkable, since there is not one among them of the characteristic coastal forms from Senegambia the Sahara or from Africa generally that I have frequently come across. Lith. Rajarum alone is also known to me from the Isle de France.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Among the 66 forms none is new, since Eunotia longicornis appears in similar fossil form in Hungary.</p>
<p>However just as 2 of the first 37 species were characteristic of America, 4 of the last 29 are common to Guiana and Senegambia, namely Eunotia quaternaria Eunotia tridentula [Eunotia] Pileus [and] Amphidiscus obtusus.</p>
<p>Furthermore all 6 of the dust types you sent me react similarly. They all exhibit a very rich mixture of siliceous shelled infusoria and also others of similar species.</p>
<p>It can now be said with confidence, that all the dust from the 6 samples must come from one and the same source. This source can be determined still more closely.— Only freshwater animal species appeared earlier; these could be from the middle of a continent. Now two exclusively saltwater animals have been found among them, Grammatophora oceanica and Textilaria globulosa. Thus the source of the dust must be a coastal region. To be sure the African coast lies closest, but there are no African forms among them, although many of them are citizens of the world. However there are now 6 South American ones among them.</p>
<p>I have further determined that according to the seamen the wind that carries the dust is never the harmattan, but that it is specifically the trade wind. You have not made a sharp distinction in setting forth your own experience, but this would be highly desirable. You probably still have ship’s journals at your disposal that would allow you to check this point. I have not found living things among them, that is any that dried quickly and still exhibit organs.— It would be good to institute direct, lengthy comparative observations on San Jago and along the African Coast concerning this remarkable dust. You seem to have all the necessary means at hand to accomplish this and I am confident you will certainly attempt it.</p>
<p>Your face paint from Tierra del Fuego was also very interesting to me. It also consists of infusoria, the first fossil deposit that has come from there. Thus far I have determined 18 species of which none is new but all are exclusively freshwater forms.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I would consider the white earth in Patagonia a volcanic product.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> It looks like pumice, that is, like weathered pumice and I have recognised in it a few almost indistinguishable infusorial shells, just a few, yet still clear to me. It may tentatively be identified as a species of the genus Fragilaria. Unfortunately I now have too much else to do to pursue the matter intensively, yet I consider the material very interesting if it is not just a local phenomenon. Is the earth only dusty, no solid rock? How massive do you consider the deposit? How far does it extend? Leagues? Miles? Should it really extend for hundreds of miles, if I understand correctly, it must be accompanied over that distance by clearly volcanic mountain formations.</p>
<p>I cannot give you any further news for today. Merely the warmest thanks for the rich material you and Dr. Hooker have sent. It is unfortunate that he declined to spend some time with us, for we would have received him in a most friendly way.</p>
<p>I would very much like to see even the smallest samples from great depths of the sea, of about 10000 to 20000 feet; after all, I hear depths of 24,000 F. have been measured. These may be either with or without tallow from the plummet.</p>
<p>Remaining with cordial respect | Your | most devoted | Dr C G Ehrenberg<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For the transcription of this letter in the original German and CD’s annotations, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, pp. 153–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Since <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> intended to visit Berlin, CD had asked Ehrenberg to return by him the manuscript of ‘An account of the fine dust which often falls on vessels in the Atlantic Ocean’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 199–203) and also to urge <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Dieffenbach</ref> to return the materials CD had sent to him for the German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-819.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to C. G. Ehrenberg, 23 January [1845]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-832.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [late February 1845]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Dieffenbach</ref> had been implicated in the April 1833 storming of the Frankfurt guardhouse by a militant liberal group and had had to flee Germany. In 1843 he was informed that proceedings against him had been dropped in Prussia; however, he was not able to return permanently to his home in Giessen until he had permission from authorities in Hesse-Darmstadt (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_523.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bell 1976</ref>, pp. 19–21, 87–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Ehrenberg (1845a, pp. 64–6) had reported on these findings before the Berlin Academy on 27 February 1845.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Described in Ehrenberg 1844a, pp. 194–207.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Mauritius.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Described in Ehrenberg 1845a, pp. 63–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Described in Ehrenberg 1845b, pp. 143–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD’s abstract of this letter is in DAR 39.1: 59c.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>