<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9976">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From T. C. Brown   12 May 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6995</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9976 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9976.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9976.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160: 324</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 324</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_673.xml">Brown, T. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Cirencester</placeName>
                <date when="1875-05-12">12 May 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Notes absence of material on fossil coral reefs in CD’s 2d edition [<hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> (1874)]. Has been collecting specimens from a fossil reef near his home for four years; gave many to Oxford.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Coral reefs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01401_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01401_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
        <surface n="324:1r" xml:id="i1401">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01401.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01401_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01401.dzi" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="324:1v" xml:id="i1402">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01402.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01402_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01402.dzi" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="324:2r" xml:id="i1403">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01403.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01403_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01403.dzi" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="324:2v" xml:id="i1404">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01404.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01404_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01404.dzi" width="3017px" height="5091px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Further Barton, | Cirencester.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>12 May 1875</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On looking over your new Edition of “Coral Reefs” which embraces not only your own discoveries respecting them, but also observations of other Corallists, I find it relates exclusively to <hi rend="underline">recent and living Reefs</hi>, and does not enter upon <hi rend="underline">Fossil</hi> Coral Reefs.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am quite aware that most of the latter do not exist in well preserved distinct Reefs, and therefore only offer to the Geologist a disjointed collection of Corals—for description of which we have the Paleon Books of the French Corallists Edwardes &amp; Haime, continued by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Duncan, which are valuable as containing descriptions of various species, but are defective in a very important part which forms the basis of your work on Coral Reefs—viz Coral History—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This therefore leaves a vacuum to be filled, in Fossil Coral Reefs, and which if you were young, might afford delightful employment and greatly help to establish the truths of all Coral History. My object in thus addressing you, is to inform you, that I discovered in the upper beds of the Great Oolite a distinct Coral Reef, and it being located near my residence, I have during the last four years, been collecting the Corals, numbering nearly 100 species and varieties, and having been the sole collector, have secured almost every kind by the aid of the Quarry Men.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The result has astonished and delighted me, for I found the Reef contained almost every class, from Nullipora &amp; Millipora to the ordinary species, and also Parasitic Corals.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It likewise clearly shews the cause of extinction of life, vizt By lime mud<ref target="#foot.f5"/> on depression of the Reef. So important did I consider the result that I thought it my duty to make it known, in order to encou〈r〉age Geologists located on other formations, to do as I had done—study any local Reef and preserve every specimen—more than this, I found I could not do, for I was not qualified to give scientific descriptions, or get up a popular illustrated work of my Reef. I have therefore endeavoured to enlist my friend P<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Prestwich now located at Oxford on the Oolites, and I hope he will give Geologist by and by a History of a <hi rend="underline">fossil</hi> Reef.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> To enable him to do this I hope this summer to shew him the Reef, and I have deposited in the Oxford Museum specimens of all found up to January last, which I mention, as you are more likely to visit Oxford than Cirencester, with the specimens I sent a catalogue illustrated by my pen, in which some profound Geologi〈ca〉l questions connected with Fossil Reefs are noticed.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> To give you an idea of a Nullipora, I have slipped into the envelope my nos. 1 &amp; 2.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>1 shewing what I suppose to be an early stage of a Coral that must have been a hollow sphere, into which in life water entered, and when by degrees the coral marble filled it. No 2 being the same coral filled up. No 1 shews the Oolitic matter which must have been injected on depression.</p>
<p>Yours | Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> C Brown | <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq</p>
<p>PS after writing my letter I thought you would like to read <hi rend="underline">my</hi> <hi rend="underline">views</hi> on “Origins” &amp; have sent it by the Book post.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1572.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> 2d ed.</ref> was published in 1874 (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ circular</hi>, 1 July 1874). CD’s book focused on coral reefs from a geological perspective, and did not discuss the coral species present in the formations; the only mention of semi-fossil coral (on one of highest mountains of Tahiti) occurs on page 183.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3335.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Milne-Edwards</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jules Haime’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">A monograph of the British fossil corals</hi> was continued by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1422.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peter Martin Duncan</ref>; both series were published by the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Palaeontographical Society</ref> (Milne-Edwards and Haime 1850–4 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">P. M. Duncan 1866–72</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The Great Oolite near Chichester is a limestone formation dating from the Middle (or Bathonian) Jurassic.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The genera <hi rend="italic">Nullipora</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Millepora</hi> (also known as fire coral) had long been considered to be primitive corals (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4540.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lamarck 1801</ref>, pp. 373 and 374), but neither is a true coral. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1572.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 93 and 105, CD suggested that reefs were formed by many different species of coral adapted to live at different depths and dependent upon specific external conditions.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Lime mud is a carbonate sediment derived from sources such as calcareous algae, and occurs in a wide range of marine zones, from pelagic to intertidal (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8852.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Allaby 2013</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3854.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Prestwich</ref> had been appointed professor of geology at Oxford University in 1874; Oxford lies in the centre of outcrops of Oolitic limestone that cross Britain from the south west to the north east. Oxfordian Oolitic limestone belongs to the Late Jurassic Corallian Group (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Challinor 1978</ref>, s.v. Jurassic system). Brown had suggested that Prestwich publish a scientific account of the specimens from the fossil reef in November 1874 (see <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from T. C. Brown to Joseph Prestwich, 24 November 1874</ref>, Archive Collections of the Oxford University Museum of Natural History).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The fossils from the Upper Bathonian strata of the Middle Jurassic period collected by Brown from a site three miles west of Cirencester are in the Earth Collections of the Oxford Natural History Museum; some were presented to the museum via John Phillips in 1873 and the others via Prestwich in January 1875 (www.oum.ox.ac.uk (accessed 3 February 2014)). Brown’s catalogue is in the Archive Collections of the Oxford University Museum of Natural History.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">These enclosures have not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD would have returned the book to Brown; he did not make use of any comments by Brown in the revised edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> that was published in 1876 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> (1876)</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>