<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-17">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Catherine Darwin   [26 October 1825]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6019</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-17 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-17.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-17.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">OC 26 1825</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 204: 21</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>204: 21</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1212.xml">Darwin, E. C.</persName>
                <placeName>[Shrewsbury]</placeName>
                <date when="1825-10-26">[26 Oct 1825]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Shrewsbury news.</p>
            <p>Glad he likes Edinburgh.</p>
            <p>They have been going to plays performed by a travelling company he knows.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1211">Darwins</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Edinburgh</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Shrewsbury</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">news</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">travelling company</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Shrewsbury]</placeName>
                    <date>Thursday Evening—</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Papa and Susan are gone to dinner at the Salts’;<ref target="#foot.f1"/> and I, being alone, will write this page to you, and give you an account of all our gay proceedings of late. This letter bids fair to be very complex, I think; Papa has written a message to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hawley on the bottom flap, which you must tear off, and give to him. We were very glad to hear of your safe arrival; and that you are so nuch pleased with Edinburgh— Papa sends his best thanks for the very nice letter he received and, remember that every little particular will be interesting— I must just mention that Edinburg<hi rend="doubleUnderline">h</hi> is spelt with an <hi rend="underline">h</hi> at the end; and <hi rend="underline">altogether</hi> has only <hi rend="doubleUnderline">one</hi> <hi rend="underline">l</hi>, not <hi rend="underline">all</hi>together, as you spelt it in your letter to Papa; do not be very cross at this, dear Charley.— I assure you I miss you very much, both to walk with me, and also for <hi rend="underline">you know what</hi>; and as for poor Shelah<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and Spark, they look the pictures of melancholy, and are really grateful for any notice, from any body.— I have not yet told you how gay we have been lately; we have been as constant play goers as you can have been; for Macready<ref target="#foot.f3"/> has been here for the three last nights, and all our hearts, that were not quite gone before, are lost now— On Monday he acted William Tell, a beautiful play, &amp; written by the same Liverpool gentleman as your favourite Virginius.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He takes a little boy about with him, who acts the part of William Tell’s son very well indeed. On Tuesday, it was Othello, which is a disagreeable Play, I think to see; and besides we had such a horrid Desdemona; we were in great want of your <hi rend="underline">lovee</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brudenell,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> who, it is said here, is gone to the Edinburgh Theatre. I hope you will see her there. On Wednesday (Macready’s Benefit) we had Virginius again, which he acted more beautifully than any thing I ever saw in my life, and which I quite agree with you, in thinking by far his best character. He had promised to act in the Farce that night;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> but was so much offended at the empty houses &amp; slight applause on Monday &amp; Tuesday, that he would not.— He looks ill, &amp; is said to be much out of health; he is going to his house in North Wales for a short time, to recruit his strength.— Fanny Wedgwood came over here again yesterday, on purpose to see him, and Caroline<ref target="#foot.f7"/> returns with her and Emma<ref target="#foot.f8"/> to Maer this morning, so we are quite a small party again—</p>
<p>What was the name of the schoolfellow you met with at the Hotel? how surprised you must have been—</p>
<p>Good bye, dear Charles, pray write soon— My love to Erasmus; ever yr<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> | E.—C.—D—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Probably the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4156.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Salt</ref>s. Salt was a partner of the Shrewsbury law firm of Dukes and Salt.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Darwin family dog.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3123.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Charles Macready</ref>, who was at the height of his fame at this time.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Virginius</hi> (1820) and <hi rend="italic">William Tell</hi> (1825) by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2726.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Sheridan Knowles</ref>. His plays were ‘a genuine and frequently popular attempt to blend heroic grandeur with a domesticity familiar to his audiences (“the scene is the Forum, but the sentiments those of the ‘Bedford Arms’ ”)’. (<hi rend="italic">McGraw-Hill encyclopaedia of world drama</hi> 2 (1972): 484).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">London playbills of September and October 1824 have <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_689.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mrs Brudenell</ref> acting, mainly in comedies, at the Covent Garden and the Haymarket Theatre, but not in Macready’s company (Harvard College Library Theatre Collection).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">At benefit performances, the proceeds of which went to the acting company, it was Macready’s custom to add a light comedy to the programme (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Archer 1890</ref>, p. 61).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1208.xml">Caroline Sarah Darwin</ref>, CD’s elder sister.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Emma Wedgwood</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>