<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6911">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Albert Günther   [before 27 September 1869]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19338</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6911 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6911.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6911.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">Amem 6pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 82: B16–20; DAR 84.2: 168</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>82: B16–20,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>84.2: 168</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1779.xml">Günther, A. C. L. G.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1869-09-26">[before 27 Sept 1869]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Replies to CD’s queries on sexual habits and differences in fish and lizards.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fish</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex differences</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>1. I have described <hi rend="underline">Mollienesia</hi> <hi rend="underline">petenensis</hi> with a dorsal fin ornamented with ‘a row of large rounded spots’ because this is sufficient for specific description.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ichthyologists rarely describe bright-colored ornamentations, because they are most subject to variation as regards form, number intensity &amp; color (what is blue in one individual, may be green or even red in another, as in many Labridæ),<ref target="#foot.f3"/> &amp; because they disappear or change in spirit, &amp; therefore, are of no specific value. I perfectly recollect that, when I received the examples of <hi rend="underline">Moll</hi>., spots of dark &amp; bright (bluish) colors were mixed; after the specimens had been in spirit for some time, the bright shades disappeared, &amp; now I could not exactly state their distribution. The large round spots may have been dark, blackish, or violet; this I cannot decide; but they were certainly surrounded by a lighter ring (true ocelli), as it is also indicated in the figure.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>2/ I have also heard that certain American Chromids sit on a nest, but I do not know which sex; nor do I recollect that any exact observations have been published about this.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Knowing several American Ichthyologists, shall I write to one of them?</p>
<p>3. Since I saw you last, I have subjected Solenostoma to a careful examination. We have about a dozen females of about the size of the specimens figured in the Fish. of Zanzibar, &amp; one male only, of about <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> the size of the females.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>a./ It may be concluded from this disproportion of male &amp; female specimens, either that males are scarcer than females, or that males always are of much smaller size than females. I am inclined to believe the latter, because of those Cyprinodonts<ref target="#foot.f7"/> in which the male is much inferior in size to the female, we always receive many more females than males, simply for that reason, that smaller fish escape more easily through the meshes of the net or to the eye of the collector than larger ones.</p>
<p>b./ The male example we possess, is much more uniformly colored, less spotted, less ornamented, than the females, which were put into spirits at the same time.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>c/ Kaup’s assertion that the males have marsupial sacs, is not founded on actual observation; he fancied this to be the case, because it is so in the true Lophobranchs.— In Solenostoma it is the female, which carries the ova in a pouch formed by the ventral fins; in the male (Kaup evidently never saw a male) the ventral fins are quite free &amp; do not form a pouch.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>4/ I cannot find any positive evidence of a Lizard uttering a sound during courtship.</p>
<p>5/ In male &amp; female <hi rend="underline">Iguana</hi> <hi rend="underline">tuberculata</hi> I find the dorsal crest equally developed; slight differences in the length of the lobes are more properly accounted for by the age of the individuals.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>6/ <hi rend="underline">Chamæleo</hi> <hi rend="underline">bifurcus</hi> from Madagascar. Nothing positive known about the colors. The projections certainly not of a bright colour<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>7/ <hi rend="underline">Chamæleo</hi> <hi rend="underline">owenii</hi> from West Africa. Its colors are known to me from examples in spirit only, &amp; from those they do not appear to be brighter than in other species; they vary much, some specimens being spotted, others uniform. The female has not a trace of a horn. The horns of the male are osseous, in fact excrescences of the facial bones, each horn being covered by a smooth sheath which is part of the general integument. In fact the horns of this species are in structure identical with the horns of those Ruminants which do not shed their horns.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>8/ Nothing is more common than true ocelli in Reptiles &amp; especially in Frogs &amp; Toads; but the ocelli are more frequently black with a white, yellow, red or blue ring, than light-colored with black ring.</p>
<p>9/ In Lizards the females are more frequently the larger sex, than the males; the fact is, I do not at this moment recollect one species, in which the male is the larger.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> You must recollect that lizards propagate before they have ceased growing, &amp; therefore it would be hazardous for a Museum-naturalist to decide from his examples which is the larger sex in each species. In our European lizards the females are the larger; and very large examples of foreign species are generally females.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.3 Knowing … them?] <hi rend="italic">triple scored pencil</hi>; ‘Yes’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6913.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Günther, 27 September [1869]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6903.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Günther, 21 September 1869</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Labridae is the family of rainbowfishes and wrasses.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Günther refers to plate 86 in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3207.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Günther 1864–6</ref>. CD included Günther’s description of <hi rend="italic">Mollienesia petenensis</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Poecilia kykesis</hi>) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6903.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Günther, 21 September 1869</ref> and n. 7. For more on nesting behaviour in these fishes see Tweddle <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1998.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The reference is to Playfair and Günther 1866. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6903.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Günther, 21 September 1869</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Günther refers to the family Cyprinodontidae, pupfishes. CD discussed their sexual differences in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 7, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD reported Günther’s information on the coloration of <hi rend="italic">Solenostoma</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Solenostomus</hi>) in <hi rend="italic">Decent</hi> 2: 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The former order Lophobranchii is roughly equivalent to the present suborder Syngnathoidei (pipefishes and seahorses), which includes the genus <hi rend="italic">Solenostomus</hi> (ghost pipefish). Günther refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2645.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Jakob Kaup</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6903.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Albert Günther, 21 September 1869</ref> and n. 9. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 22, CD cited Günther for the information on the marsupial sac in female <hi rend="italic">Solenostoma.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD cited Günther’s information on crest size in <hi rend="italic">Iguana tuberculata</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Iguana iguana</hi>) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD described and illustrated the large bony projections on the upper part of the skull in the male <hi rend="italic">Chamaeleon bifurcus</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Furcifer bifidus</hi>) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 34–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD described the three horns of the male <hi rend="italic">Chamaeleon owenii</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Chamaeleo oweni</hi>) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 35–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD appears to have misread Günther on this point. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 32, he reported on Günther’s authority that male lizards are generally larger than females.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>