<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8309">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. H. Schmick   3 May 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10636</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8309 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8309.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8309.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 56</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 56</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4221.xml">Schmick, J. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Cologne</placeName>
                <date when="1872-05-03">3 May 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Having sent CD his two essays outlining his theory on "A secular transposition of oceans" [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">7368</hi>], JHS now forwards to CD a book he believes establishes his theory as an "eternal law of nature" [<hi rend="italic">Die neue Theorie periodische säkularer Schwankungen des Seespiegels</hi> [periodischer!?] (1872)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cologne, | Trutzenberg 68.</placeName>
                    <date>Mai 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1872.</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>About eighteen months since I had the honour to send you two essays of mine, in which my new theory on “A secular transposition of oceans” was developed, and established by facts of geology, geography and natural history.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I then also told you of a book of mine to be published as soon as possible, in which particularly facts of geology and geognosy were to be adduced as so many evidences of the truth of my theory, and in which I intended to explain the breaks or intermittence of the series of petrifactions. You had the kindness to acknowledge the receipt of the two essays, to encourage me in the pursuit of researches and to style as <hi rend="underline">greatly meritorious for science</hi> a result as promised in my letter to you. That result is now obtained, as far as I can see, and I have the pleasure of forwarding to you, together with this note, the book, in which I think to have succeeded in establishing my theory as an “eternal law of nature”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I wish you would not shun the trouble to read the work and to mediate, if possible, its more general notoriety among English geologists, to whose enquiries we are indebted for so numerous important facts concerning the formation of the earth’s crust.</p>
<p>I remain with the most distinguished consideration | Yours | ob. serv. | Dr. H. Schmick.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7368.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. H. Schmick, 12 November 1870</ref>. Schmick refers to his <hi rend="italic">Die Umsetzungen der Meere und die Eiszeiten der Halbkugeln der Erde, ihre Ursachen und Perioden</hi> (The transpositions of the seas and the ice ages of the hemispheres of the earth, their causes and periods; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6949.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schmick 1869</ref>) and his <hi rend="italic">Thatsachen und Beobachtungen zur weiteren Begründung seiner neuen theorie einer Umsetzung der Meere durch die Sonnenanziehung und eines gleichzeitigen Wechsels der Eiszeiten auf beiden Halbkugeln der Erde</hi> (Facts and observations to further justify his new theory of a transposition of the seas through the attraction of the sun and a simultaneous alternation of ice ages in both hemispheres of the earth; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6950.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schmick 1871</ref>): there are annotated copies of both books in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s letter to Schmick has not been found. Schmick refers to his <hi rend="italic">Die neue Theorie periodischer säkulärer Schwankungen des Seespiegels und gleichzeitiger Verschiebungen der Wärmezonen auf Nord- und Südhalbkugel der Erde</hi> (The new theory of periodic secular changes in sea level and simultaneous shifts in the warm zones of the north and south hemispheres of the earth; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schmick 1872</ref>). No copy has been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>