<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7326">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alexander Onufrievich Kovalevsky<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   25 September 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17765</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7326 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7326.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7326.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 52</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 52</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2749.xml">Kovalevsky, A. O.</persName>
                <placeName>Naples</placeName>
                <date when="1870-09-25">25 Sept 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Outlines the evidence for his view that ascidian larvae are true vertebrates presented in his paper ["Weitere Studien über die Entwicklung der einfachen Ascidien", <hi rend="italic">Arch. Mikrosk. Anat.</hi> 7 (1871): 101–302]. CD can cite this as confirmation of AOK’s earlier claims.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ascidian</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">vertebrates</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Arch. Mikrosk. Anat.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Kovalevsky, A. O. 1871</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">larvae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00211_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3881px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00211_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3881px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="52:1r" xml:id="i211">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00211.jpg" width="3881px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00211_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3881px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00211.dzi" width="3881px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="52:1v" xml:id="i212">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00212.jpg" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00212_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00212.dzi" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="52:2r" xml:id="i213">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00213.jpg" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00213_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00213.dzi" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="52:2v" xml:id="i214">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00214.jpg" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00214_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00214.dzi" width="3769px" height="6209px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="52 foldout" xml:id="i215">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00215.jpg" width="6988px" height="6193px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00215_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="6988px" height="6193px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00169-000-00215.dzi" width="6988px" height="6193px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Naples.</placeName>
                    <date>25 Septem 70.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Mon frère me fait savoir, que vous desiréz inserer dans l’ouvrage que vous publiez une citation, que mes nouvelles etudes sur le developpement des Ascidres constatent mes premieres assertions que les larves des Ascidres simples sont des animaux vertebrés.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Les resultats de mes nouvelles rescherches sur le developpement des Ascidres sont maintenant sous presse, dans l’Archiv fur Mikroscopische Anatomie de <hi rend="underline">Max Schultze</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Dans cet article, je constate, a l’aide d’une serie de nouvelles observations, que les larves des Ascidres sont de vraies vertebrés, que leurs systeme nerveux se forme a laide d’un sillon dorsal qui se ferme dans tube—système nerveux des Ascidres; je constate encore que la chorde dorsale des larves des Acidres se developpe de la même maniere que chez les vertebrés; Je donne des dessins de la coupe transversale de la larve (fig.) qui presente le systeme nerveux <hi rend="superscript">(n)</hi>, la chorde <hi rend="superscript">(ch)</hi>, l’intestin <hi rend="superscript">(d)</hi> et les cellules musculaires <hi rend="superscript">(m)</hi></p> 
    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width45"> 
        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_7326_french.png"/>
    </figure> 
<p>J’espère que j’aurais le plaisir de vous faire parvenir un exemplaire de mes nouvelles études sur le developpement des Ascidres dans le courant du moi Novembre ou Decembre.—</p>
<p>Pendant l’anné passé (1869) j’ai étudié l’embryologie des annelides et je trouvé que la chorde dorsale existe chez beaucoup des Annelides.— Peût–être vous vous rapeléz Monsieur, du grande tube nerveux(?)—<hi rend="underline">riesiege Rohren Nervenfasern</hi> que Leydig a decrit chez les Lumbricus;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> <hi rend="underline">Claparéde</hi> (Zeitschrift fur Wissenschaftliche Zoologie Bd. XIX p. 588, 89–90) a demontrés que cet enorme quasi Nerv se trouve à lexterieur de la Nevrilemme.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Mes etudes sur l’embryologie de ces <hi rend="underline">tubes</hi> m’ont demontré qu’ils se forment de la même maniere que la chorde des vertebrés. Je trouvai chez les embryons des Lumbricidae trois feuilles embryonaire—correspondant aux trois feuilles embryonnaire des vertebrés; du feuille exterieure se forme le systeme nerveux et l’epitehlium exterieur, du feuille interieur (Darmdrüsenblatt)<ref target="#foot.f6"/> l’epithelium du canal instestinal, du feuille mediane les muscles, la nevrileme et <hi rend="underline">les chordes ou “riesiege Röhrenfasern”</hi> de Claparède.</p>
<p>Mon Etude sur l’embryologie de Lombric est sous presse dans le Memoires de l’Acad. de St. Petersbourg.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Mon frère m’ecrit qu’il vous serait agreable si j’etudie l’organisation du mal des cirripèdes (Scalpellum) ainsi que l’histoire du developpement et de formation du mal et de ses organes genitaux en comparaison avec la femelle.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Je ferais tout mon possible pour ressoudre ces ?? d’autant plus que je rencontrait un fait pareile chez des autre forme, chez la Bonelia viridis.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Pressisement, je trouvé, que le mal de Bonelia est une petite Planaire, ou mieux Turbellaire, d’un millimetre.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Les males se trouvent dans l’uterus de la femelle, on trouve dans chaque Bonelia femelle 4 ou 5 males— Dans l’organisation du male on trouve plusieur cas de ressemblanse avec la femelle; l’organisation des organe genitaux du male et de la femelle se ressemble beaucoup.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Il est bien possible que dans la Bonelia nous trouverons un exemple, que seulement un sexe (femelle) changeat graduellement sa forme primitive, tendit que l’autre sexe (le mal) resta dans sa forme primitive de Turbellaire. J’espère de pouvoir étudier le developpement de la Bonelia, cela devra resoudre la question.</p>
<p>Je resterais a Naples encore toute une anné et je serais extrément heureux si je pourais vous être utile ou en vous envoyant quelque forme de la faune du golfe de Naples, ou en faisant quelques études dont les resultats vous interesserais exclusivement</p>
<p>En vous envoyant cette lettre, Monsieur, je profite de l’ocasion pour exprimér tout mon devouement aux idées dont vous avez enrichit la science et de vous priéer d’agréer ma salutation le plus distingué | Prof. A Kowalevsky</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Naples.</placeName>
                    <date>25 Septem 70.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My brother has let me know that you want to insert a citation in the work you are publishing, to the effect that my new studies on the development of the Ascidians confirm my earlier assertions that the larvae of simple Ascidians are vertebrate animals.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>The results of my new research on the development of the Ascidians are now in press, in <hi rend="underline">Max Schultze</hi>’s Archiv fur Mikroscopische Anatomie.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In this article, I confirm, with the help of a series of new observations, that the larvae of the Ascidians are true vertebrates, and that their nervous system forms by means of a dorsal sulcus which closes into a tube—the nervous system of the Ascidians; I also confirm that the dorsal chord of the larvae of the Ascidians develops in the same way as in the vertebrates; I give drawings of the transverse section of the larva (fig.) which shows the nervous system <hi rend="superscript">(n)</hi>, the chord <hi rend="superscript">(ch)</hi>, the intestine <hi rend="superscript">(d)</hi> and the muscle cells <hi rend="superscript">(m)</hi></p> 
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width45"> 
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_7326_english.png"/>
                    </figure> 
<p>I hope that I shall have the pleasure of sending you a copy of my new studies on Ascidian development in the course of the month of November or December.—</p>
<p>In the last year (1869) I have studied annelid embryology and I have found that the dorsal chord exists in many Annelids.— Perhaps you recall, Sir, the great nerve tube(?)—<hi rend="underline">riesiege Rohren Nervenfasern</hi> that Leydig describes in Lumbricus;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> <hi rend="underline">Claparéde</hi> (Zeitschrift fur Wissenschaftliche Zoologie Bd. XIX p. 588, 89–90) has demonstrated that this enormous quasi Nerve is found outside the Neurilemma.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> My studies on the embryology of these <hi rend="underline">tubes</hi> have shown me that they form in the same way as the vertebrate chord. I found three embryonic layers in Lumbricidae embryos—corresponding to the three embryonic layers in vertebrates; the nervous system and the exterior epithelium form from the external layer, the epithelium of the intestinal canal from the internal layer (Darmdrüsenblatt),<ref target="#foot.f6"/> the muscles, the neurilemma and <hi rend="underline">the chords or “riesiege Röhrenfasern”</hi> of Claparède from the median layer.</p>
<p>My study on Earthworm embryology is in press in the Memoirs of the Acad. of St. Petersburg.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>My brother writes that it would please you if I studied the organisation of the male in cirripedes (Scalpellum) as well as the history of the development and formation of the male and of his genital organs compared with the female.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I would do everything I could to resolve these ??, the more so because I have encountered a comparable fact in another form, Bonelia viridis.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Namely, I find that the male of Bonelia is a small Planarian, or rather Turbellarian, a millimetre long.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> The males are found in the female’s uterus, and in each Bonelia female one finds 4 or 5 males— In the male’s organisation one finds several cases of resemblance with the female; the organisation of the genital organs of the male and female is very similar.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> It is indeed possible that in Bonelia we find an example in which just one sex (female) gradually changed its primitive form, whilst the other sex (the male) remained in its primitive form, the Turbellarian. I hope to be able to study the development of Bonelia, that ought to resolve the question.</p>
<p>I will remain at Naples for another whole year and I should be most happy if I could be of service to you either by sending you some form of fauna from the gulf of Naples, or by carrying out some studies whose results would be of interest exclusively to you</p>
<p>In sending you this letter, dear Sir, I shall take the opportunity to express all my attachment to the ideas with which you have enriched science and to offer you my most distinguished greetings | Prof. A Kowalevsky</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Alexander’s brother was Vladimir Onufrievich Kovalevsky. See the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 5 September [1870]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Kovalevsky refers to A. O. Kovalevsky 1871 and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4240.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Johann Sigismund Schultze</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 205, CD referred to Kovalevsky’s earlier paper on the embryology of ascidians (A. O. Kovalevsky 1866b) and to the fact that Kovalevsky had done further research on the subject, but did not cite the later article. No copy of A. O. Kovalevsky 1871 has been found in the Darwin Archive.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘Riesiege Rohren Nervenfasern’: giant tube of nerve fibres (German; a reference to the median giant fibre). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2917.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Franz von Leydig</ref> described this organ in <hi rend="italic">Lumbricus</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4741.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leydig 1864</ref>, pp. 154–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Claparède</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1409.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claparède 1869</ref>. Claparède noted the similarity between the nerve sheath of the earthworm and the myelin sheath of vertebrates (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1409.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claparède 1869</ref>, p. 590).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">‘Darmdrüsenblatt’: gut-gland-layer (German; a reference to the endoderm).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Kovalevsky refers to his paper on the embryology of worms and arthropods (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. O. Kovalevsky 1869</ref>). It appeared in the 1871 volume of <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de St.-Pétersbourg.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD’s letter to Vladimir Onufrievich Kovalevsky has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 20 September 1870</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Bonelia viridis</hi> is an incorrect subsequent spelling of <hi rend="italic">Bonellia viridis</hi>, the green spoonworm.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Bonellia viridis</hi> is no longer placed within the family Planariidae of the class Turbellaria. It is in a separate phylum, Echiura.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Bonellia viridis</hi> is sexually undifferentiated in larval stages, and differentiation is determined by environmental factors alone. For more on the development of sexes in this species, see Berec <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2005.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>