<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2713">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   24 February [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3601</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2713 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2713.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2713.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 169</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 99</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 106</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (23)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>23</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-02-24">24 Feb [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Last sheets of AG’s review of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> have arrived. CD’s comments and criticisms.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1860c</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Feb 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Gray</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I received yesterday your kind letter &amp; the remaining sheets of the Review, which I forwarded to Hooker, to go to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Boott &amp; then to Lyell.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>This remainder of the Review most fully confirms my opinion that it is by far the most able which has appeared, &amp; you will have done the subject infinite service. And now I most sincerely hope that it will cost you no more labour.—   Lyell quite agreed with me that the two first sheets were the best thing which has appeared on the subject.—</p>
<p>Thank you much for your letter, which as it contains such curious botanical facts, I have sent to Hooker. Why should you call one of the best essays ever written (at least in my opinion) on Geograph. Distribution of Plants “unfortunate”. I really hope, as a punishment to myself, that I may be found egregiously wrong about the warmer period subsequent to the Glacial Epoch.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Certainly very much more has to be made out about the latest geological periods.—</p>
<p>I am very glad to think (if I understand rightly, but I must reread your letter) that the greater resemblance of N.E. America than of N.W. America to Asia in its plants, is not quite so great an anomaly as it at first appears.—</p>
<p>I have been interested by your theological remarks in the Review, but I must reconsider them. It has always seemed to me that for an Omnipotent &amp; omniscient Creator to foresee is the same as to preordain; but then when I come to think over this I get into an uncomfortable puzzle <hi rend="underline">something</hi> analogous with “necessity &amp; Free-will” or the “Origin of evil”, or other such subject quite beyond the scope of the human intellect. I was interested the other day in reading the Life of Newton by Brewster to find that Leibnitz actually attacked the Law of Gravity as “subversive of all Natural Religion’!!<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He further attacked Newton for having used gravity ”<hi rend="underline">an occult quality</hi>“ to explain the motions of the Planets.—   Newton answered that it is philosophy to explain movement of wheels of clock, though the cause of descent of the weight could not be explained. This seems to me rather to bear on what you say of Nat. selection not being proved as a vera causa.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I cannot but think you lay rather too much stress on new organs appearing in the animal kindgom, at least, it is most difficult to show any number of new organs.—   Milne Edwards has tried with very little success.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> One sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> never forget such transitions or at least such gradations, as a swim-bladder into a Lung.— So even with the Eye, as numerous fine gradations can be shown to exist, the perfecting this wondrous organ by Nat. Selection I must look at as a difficulty to our imagination &amp; not to our reason.—</p>
<p>In the M.S. additions sent you for any future edition, there is one blundering sentence, herewith corrected. If I knew there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be a second American Edition I would send a few more additions &amp; corrections</p>
<p>With most sincere thanks for all your extreme kindness— Believe me | Yours most sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">3.6 latest] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘later’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">5.2 to me] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘clear’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">5.2 &amp; omniscient] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">5.6 by Brewster] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to [Gray] 1860a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Gray’s letter to CD has not been found. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2708.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [23 February 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD refers to a paper on the flora of Japan (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gray 1859</ref>), in which Gray proposed that there had been a post-glacial, as well as a pre-glacial, warm period during which the plants of northern America and northern Asia intermingled. For CD’s comments on the postulated post-glacial warm period, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, letters to J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2461.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">11 May [1859]</ref>, and to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, 24 December [1859].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Brewster 1855</ref>, 2: 284–5. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2707.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 23 February [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2704.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 18 February [1860]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD followed <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3335.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Milne-Edwards</ref> in believing that organs were generally transformed through performing increasingly specialised functions rather than formed <hi rend="italic">de novo</hi>. See Milne-Edwards 1851 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 354.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>