<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2059">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Victor de Robillard    26 February 1857<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">9055</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2059 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2059.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2059.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="inc">†</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 205.3: 287</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>205.3: 287</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4036.xml">Robillard, Victor de</persName>
                <placeName>Mauritius</placeName>
                <date when="1857-02-26">26 Feb 1857</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>The species of Mollusca at Mauritius are almost all different from those of surrounding islands, which confirms the belief that the islands were elevated from the ocean rather than separated from the continent by volcanic action.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Mollusca</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">continent</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">ocean</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Mauritius</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">volcanoes and earthquakes</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00640_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00640_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="287.1r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00640.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00640_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00640.dzi" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="287.1v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00641.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3989px" height="6490px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00641_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3989px" height="6490px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00641.dzi" width="3989px" height="6490px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="287.2r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00642.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00642_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00642.dzi" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="287.2v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00643.jpg" rend="portrait" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00643_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00205-00003-000-00643.dzi" width="4016px" height="6535px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Port Louis, | Ile Maurice,</placeName>
                    <date>le 26 Fév<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> /57.</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>J’ai reçu votre lettre du 7 D<hi rend="superscript">bre</hi>. dernier &amp; vous remercie des démarches que vous avez faites près de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Cuming pour les coquilles;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> je vois par la réponse écrite qu’il vous a faite qu’il désire plutôt vendre qu’échanger; je lui ai écrit alors et lui envoie une liste des coquilles que je désire, afin d’en connaître les prix.</p>
<p>Je vais maintenant vous donner les renseignemens que vous me demandez, dans le sens de mes idées:</p>
<p>Vous dites que dans quelques cas, les mêmes mollusques se trouvent habiter différentes iles, quoique séparées par la mer. Dans les iles qui nous environnent, il est bien rare de voir les mêmes coquilles terrestres sur des iles différentes— Maurice a beaucoup plus de terrestres que Bourbon,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> et ce ne sont pas les mêmes espèces, à l’exception d’une agathine commune &amp; d’un petit cyclostome des bois— toutes les coquilles terrestres des Iles Seychelles n’existent pas à Maurice ni celles de Madagascar, ce qui confirmerait l’opinion de ceux qui pensent que les iles se sont élées isolément du sein de l’océan &amp; n’ont pas été séparées par des révolutions volcaniques et des feus sous-marins, comme quelques uns le prétendent—</p>
<p>Je ne pense pas que des oeufs puissent être transportés d’une île à une autre, par la mer; ils rencontreraient trop d’ennemis pour pouvoir arrivés sur un autre rivage, où les chocs dans tous les cas pourraient aussi détruire le principe vital—</p>
<p>Il y a plusieurs années on a transporté ici une belle agathine à bouche rouge de Madagascar, qui s’est beaucoup répandue &amp; s’est de suite acclimatée.</p>
<p>Quant aux mollusques d’eau douce, il y a deux à trois espèces de Maurice qu’on rencontre à Bourbon; je les crois indigènes aux deux Iles, sans qu’on les ait portés de l’une à l’autre. Le voyage de leurs oeufs, devant descendre à la mer par les débordemens de Rivière, ne doit cependant pas se faire d’une ile à l’autre, devant être détruits de la même manière que ceux des mollusques terrestres—</p>
<p>Maintenant je crois qu’il est très facile de porter des espèces d’une ile à l’autre, soit par les mollusques eux-mêmes soit par leurs oeufs, il ne suffirait pour cela que la volonté de l’homme.</p>
<p>Quant aux plus récentes découvertes d’oiseaux de Maurice ou de Bourbon, on n’a rien rencontré de nouveaux, depuis le Dronte &amp; le Solitaire—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>à Bourbon il y a un oiseau qui vit dans les solitudes des bois des montagnes, qui y devient très rare, il est connu sous le nom de Huppe;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> il n’a jamais été rencontré à Maurice—</p>
<p>Parmis les insectes, je remarque depuis peu d’années ici, un papillon bleu, qu’on dit exister à Madagascar &amp; un autre blanc, qui serait de la côte d’afrique— Comment sont-ils arrivés ici? on présume que c’est par des plantes sous lesquelles les oeufs se seraient trouvées attachées lorsque l’insecte a pondu.</p>
<p>Vous me demandez si pendant les ouragans des objects légers pourraient être transportés de Bourbon à Maurice? d’après la théorie admise pour la formation de ce grand ébranlement de la nature &amp; de la manière dont ils se forment &amp; se déplacent, il est un fait certain acquis par nombre d’observations, c’est</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note> 0.3 Mon cher … idées: 2.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 3.3 bien rare] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi> </note>
                <note> 3.5 l’exception … Madagascar 3.7] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 4.1 Je ne pense … vital— 4.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 5.2 sans] ‘sans’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi> </note>
                <note> 5.3 Le voyage … le solitaire— 7.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi> </note>
                <note> 8.1 à Bourbon … montagnes,] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi> </note>
                <note> 9.1 Parmis … c’est 10.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 10.1 Vous … c’est 10.4] ‘Hurricanes circular so not good to transport’<hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note> <hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘19’<ref target="#foot.f6"/> <hi rend="italic">brown crayon</hi> </note>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Port Louis, | Mauritius</placeName>
                    <date>26 Feb /57.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have received your letter of 7 December and I thank you for the approaches you have made to Mr Cuming for the shells;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I see from the written reply that he has made to you that he wants to sell rather than exchange; thus I have written to him and am sending him a list of the shells that I want in order to find out the prices.</p>
<p>I shall now give you the information that you asked me for, according to my view of things:</p>
<p>You say that in some cases, the same molluscs are found inhabiting different islands, although separated by the sea. In the islands that surround us, it is very rare to see the same land shells on different islands— Mauritius has many more land shells than Bourbon,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> and they are not the same species, with the exception of an achatina in common and a small cyclostome of the woods— none of the land shells of the Seychelles exist on Mauritius nor do those of Madagascar, which would confirm the opinion of those who believe that the islands have risen in isolation from the depths of the ocean and have not been separated by volcanic upheaval and submarine eruptions, as some maintain—</p>
<p>I do not think that eggs could be transported by the sea from one island to another; they would encounter too many enemies to be able to reach another shore, where the shocks in any case could destroy the vital principle—</p>
<p>Several years ago a beautiful red-mouthed achatina of Madagascar was brought here, which has spread much and has quickly become acclimatised.</p>
<p>As for the freshwater molluscs, there are two or three species of Mauritius that are found on Bourbon; I think they are indigenous to the two islands without having been transported from one to the other. Their eggs must travel down to the sea through the overflowing of rivers but the passage from one island to another should not happen, they should be destroyed in the same manner as those of land molluscs—</p>
<p>I believe that now it is very easy to transport species from one island to another, either the molluscs themselves or their eggs, it only takes the will of man.</p>
<p>As for the most recent discoveries of birds on Mauritius or Bourbon, nothing new has been encountered since the Dodo and the Solitaire.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>On Bourbon there is a bird which lives secluded in the mountain woodlands, which is becoming very rare there, it is known by the name of Huppe;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> it has never been met with on Mauritius—</p>
<p>Among the insects, I have noticed for a few years here, a blue butterfly, which is said to exist on Madagascar and a white one, which may be from the African coast— How have they arrived here? Presumably by means of plants underneath which the eggs happened to have been attached when the insects laid.</p>
<p>You ask me whether during hurricanes light objects could be transported from Bourbon to Mauritius? Following the accepted theory of the formation of this great disturbance of nature and from the manner in which they are created and move, it is a certain fact established by a number of observations, that is</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French and CD’s annotations, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, pp. 347–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1149.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Cuming</ref> had assembled one of the largest shell collections in Britain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Bourbon, now called Réunion, was a French colony in the Indian Ocean, 130 miles south-west of Mauritius.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The dodo of Mauritius and the solitaire of Bourbon were extinct (Strickland and Melville 1848, pp. 27, 60).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Réunion huppe is now extinct (Staub 1976).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The number of CD’s portfolio of notes on the geographical distribution of animals.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>