<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1226">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. E. Strickland   15 February 1849</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8277</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1989">1989</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1226 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1226.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1226.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="04">4</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ACCS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Museum of Zoology Archives, University of Cambridge (Strickland Papers)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_79.xml">Cambridge UMZ</repository>
                    <collection>Strickland Papers</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4592.xml">Strickland, H. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Tewkesbury</placeName>
                <date when="1849-02-15">15 Feb 1849</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Clarifies the notion and use of type-species and applies it to CD’s problem with <hi rend="italic">Conchoderma</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Conchoderma</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">archetypes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">identification</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>The Lodge | Tewkesbury</placeName>
                    <date>Feb 15. 1849</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>When I proposed to use <hi rend="underline">Lepas</hi> for <hi rend="underline">Balanus</hi>, it was owing to my ignorance that <hi rend="underline">Lepas</hi> was properly a name of the pedunculate division. In order to have some kind of rule to go by in subdividing genera, it is necessary to trace out the original <hi rend="underline">type-species</hi>, on which, like the lineal descendant of an ancient family, the original estates privileges &amp; <hi rend="underline">title</hi> must be for ever entailed. That is the theory, but it happens unluckily that a <hi rend="underline">type</hi>-species is a modern idea— Linnæus &amp; his immediate successors considered all the the species in a genus as free and equal, and no more thought of making one species the “type”<ref target="#foot.f1"/> than a Yankee would think of making his eldest son the head of the family.</p>
<p>But as in our modern practice we find that a <hi rend="underline">type-species</hi> is a very useful, or rather an essential, idea in the subdivision of genera, we are obliged by a kind of fiction to assume that all genera, Linnæus’s included, have a type-species. There are 2 ways of doing this, one by invariably adopting the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> species in the list as the type, the second by determining from etymological or historical sources, the most appropriate species to bear this honour. The former plan is based on <hi rend="underline">fact</hi> &amp; is unattended with trouble, hence it has been uniformly followed in Gray’s Genera of Birds.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> plan is frequently based on <hi rend="underline">opinion</hi>, &amp; involves a laborious research into ante-Linnæan authors. Nevertheless an exclusive adherence to the former plan often produces gross &amp; intolerable absurdities (such as calling the Snipes <hi rend="underline">Numenius</hi> &amp; the Balearic Cranes, exclusively, <hi rend="underline">Grus</hi>, &amp;c because they happened to stand first in Linnæus’s list of species.). I therefore consider that where we can get clear proof from classical or ante-Linnæan authorities as to the particular species or group to which any generic name properly belongs, such species should be considered as the type; but where no such clear proof exists, then the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> species in the list of the author who first defined the genus is to be taken as the type— Now I, in my last letter, not knowing the history of the word <hi rend="underline">Lepas</hi>, followed the last principle, but as you state that old authors used it only in a <hi rend="underline">pedunculate</hi> sense, of course <hi rend="underline">L. anatifera</hi> is the type of <hi rend="underline">Lepas, Linn.</hi> &amp; accordingly <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Lepas</hi> <hi rend="underline">restricted</hi>, should, as you propose, supersede <hi rend="underline">Anatifera, Anatifa</hi>, &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Respecting Lepas aurita; as Olfers in 1814 made it the type of Conchoderma, so it must for ever remain, be the <hi rend="underline">limits</hi>, &amp; consequently the <hi rend="underline">definition</hi>, of Conchoderma, what they may. Olfers might have made another genus contemporaneously or subsequently of <hi rend="underline">L. vittata</hi>, or he might have been unacquainted with such a species,—that is quite immaterial. Oken had no business to give a new name to a genus which included another man’s <hi rend="underline">type-species</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Of course you will understand that by <hi rend="underline">type-species</hi> I only mean a conventional distinction, referring only to <hi rend="underline">words</hi>, not to <hi rend="underline">things</hi>; and like human titles, only used as a matter of convenience. Nature knows no more of <hi rend="underline">type-species</hi> or “typical groups” than she does of Dukes and Marquesses. Swainson indeed, &amp; other Quinarians talk very mysteriously about “<hi rend="underline">types</hi>” as if the latter got their coronets from Nature &amp; not from Man, but all that appears to me to be <hi rend="underline">fudge</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Yours very truly | Hugh E Strickland</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2443.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Farber 1976</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">G. R. Gray 1844–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>67 n. explains CD’s retention of <hi rend="italic">Lepas</hi> as the generic name.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>136–52, <hi rend="italic">Conchoderma</hi> is used for the genus that includes <hi rend="italic">Lepas aurita</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Branta</hi> spp. of Oken. <hi rend="italic">Conchoderma aurita</hi> is a misspelling of <hi rend="italic">C. auritum</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5966.xml">Olfers 1818</ref>, p. 178).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The quinarian system of classification, proposed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3118.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Sharp Macleay</ref> and his followers, arranged organisms into groups and sub-groups, each of which contained five forms whose affinities to one another were such that they could be depicted in the form of a circle. Macleay believed that such a regular scheme existed in the natural world and was evidence of God’s plan of creation. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6037.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ospovat 1981</ref>, pp. 101–13, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1976</ref>, pp. 83–7. For CD’s comments on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4632.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Swainson’s</ref> views on ‘type’, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 3, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-744.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 31 March [1844]</ref>; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-745.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 5 April 1844</ref> and n. 4.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>