<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13249">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Emily Talbot   19 July 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8204</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13249 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13249.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13249.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 6</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 54;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 24 (1881): 565</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Journal of Speculative Philosophy</hi> 15 no. 2 (April): 206–7</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Papers on infant development: published by the Education Department of the American Social Science Association, January, 1882</hi></bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 232</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">University of Chicago Library, Special Collections Research Center (Miscellaneous Manuscript Collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_86.xml">Chicago</repository>
                    <collection>Misc MSS</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1881-07-19">19 July 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4657.xml">Talbot, Emily</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Interested in investigation of child development. Suggests questions. Does education of parents influence mental power of children? Desirable to test statement that coloured children at first learn as fast as white but afterwards fall behind. Does pitch of chidren’s voices vary with mood? Children’s tastes often related to occupation of progenitor. Do these last?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">coloured children</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">white children</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">affinity and analogy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">education</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-01-17" status="footnoted">Footnoted <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-10" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-23" status="editorResponseCompleted">Responded <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent.</hi> | (<hi rend="print">Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi>)</placeName>
                    <date>July 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1881</date>
                    <salute>Dear Madam</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In response to your wish I have much pleasure in expressing the interest which I feel in your proposed investigation on the mental &amp; bodily development of infants.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Very little is at present accurately known on this subject, &amp; I believe that isolated observations will add but little to our knowledge, whereas tabulated results from a very large number of observations systematically made, would probably throw much light on the sequence &amp; period of development of the several faculties. This knowledge would probably give a foundation for some improvement in our education of young children, &amp; would show us whether the same system ought to be followed in all cases.</p>
<p>I will venture to specify a few points of enquiry which, as it seems to me, possess some scientific interest. For instance does the education of the parents influence the mental powers of their children at any age, either at a very early or somewhat more advanced stage?<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This could perhaps be learnt by school-masters or mistresses, if a large number of children were first classed according to age &amp; their mental attainments, &amp; afterwards in accordance with the education of their parents, as far as this could be discovered. As observation is one of the earliest faculties developed in young children, &amp; as this power would probably be exercised in an equal degree by the children of educated &amp; uneducated persons, it seems not improbable that any transmitted effect from education would be displayed only at a somewhat advanced age. It would be desirable to test statistically in a similar manner the truth of the often repeated statement that coloured children at first learn as quickly as white children, but that they afterwards fall off in progress.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> If it could be proved that education acts not only on the individual, but by transmission on the race, this would be a great encouragement to all working on this all-important subject.</p>
<p>It is well known that children sometimes exhibit at a very early age strong special tastes, for which no cause can be assigned, although occasionally they may be accounted for by reversion to the taste or occupation of some progenitor; &amp; it would be interesting to learn how far such early taste are persistent &amp; influence the future career of the individual. In some instances such tastes die away without apparently leaving any after effect; but it would be adviseable to know how far this is commonly the case, as we should then know whether it was important to direct, as far as this is possible, the early tastes of our children. It may be more beneficial that a child should follow energetically some pursuit, of however trifling a nature, &amp; thus acquire perseverance, than that he sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be turned from it, because of no future advantage to him.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I will mention one other small point of enquiry in relation to very young children, which may possibly prove important with respect to the origin of language; but it could be investigated only by persons possessing an accurate musical ear. Children even before they can articulate express some of their feelings &amp; desires by noises uttered in different notes. For instance they make an interrogative noise, &amp; others of assent &amp; dissent in different tones, &amp; it would, I think, be worth while to ascertain whether there is any uniformity in different children in the pitch of their voices under various frames of mind.</p>
<p>I fear that this letter can be of no use to you, but it will serve to show my sympathy &amp; good wishes in your researches.</p>
<p>I beg leave to remain | Dear Madam | Yours faithfully | Charles Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To | M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Emily Talbot.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 (<hi rend="italic">Railway … S.E.R.</hi>)] <hi rend="italic">parentheses added</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">4.1 mention] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘mention’ </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Talbot’s letter to CD has not been found. As secretary of the education department of the American Social Science Association, Talbot was organising research into infant development; see <hi rend="italic">Papers in infant development</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9841.xml">Talbot ed. 1882</ref>). This letter was published in Talbot ed. 1882, pp. 6–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For CD’s speculation on the inheritance of the effects of education, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 565 (a discussion of the difference between men and women in intelligence).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9923.xml">Hunt 1863</ref>, pp. 387, 390.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his autobiography, CD recalled that as a child, he collected shells, seals, franks, coins, and minerals. ‘The passion for collecting, which leads a man to be a systematic naturalist, a virtuoso or a miser, was strong in me, &amp; was clearly innate as none of my sisters or brother ever had this taste’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6562.xml">‘Recollections’</ref>, p. 356). </note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>