<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5173">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   2 August 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19311</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5173 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5173.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5173.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">AL incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="AL inc">†, 2 sketches †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 76: B33, 33a; DAR 157a: 81, 102; DAR 142: 38</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>76: B33,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>142: 97,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>157a: 102</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1866-08-02">2 Aug 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Gives some observations on orchids and on some plants which seem to be dichogamous.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dichogamy, sexual dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro, Brazil</placeName>
                    <date>August. 2. 66.</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Your kind letter of May 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> arrived here only July 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In the meantime I could observe but a few specimens of one of our species of <hi rend="underline">Oxalis</hi>; the length of the styli is very variable even in the flowers of the same plant, but whether the species is really trimorphic, I am not yet able to say.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In my last letter I gave you a short account of an Orchid having three fertile stamens.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The species is not very rare and I have already seen numerous ears, all the flowers of which showed the same number of fertile stamens. In a closely allied species from Bahia,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> which I saw in the garden of a Frenchman, I was much surprised at finding but one fertile stamen as in other plants of the tribe. It is curious, that the number of fertile stamens while it furnishes an excellent character for dividing the Orchids into two main groups, in this case is not even of generic value.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Have you ever seen the flowers of <hi rend="underline">Notylia</hi>?<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The stigma forms a very narrow slit, to which I found it impossible to cause the pollinia to adhere; at the same time the ovula have a very rudimentary appearance. Thus for some time I supposed the plant to be a male one, but afterwards I met with seed-capsules, the columna of which had evidently borne an anthera, while the stigma seemed to have been of the same form as in the supposed male flowers. Besides I convinced myself that in some other Orchids the ovula are in a very rudimentary estate at the time when the flower is expanded and that only some weeks afterwards they become ready for impregnation. This is, for instance, the case with two self-fertilizing species of the tribe of Epidendreae; (one of them belongs to the genus <hi rend="underline">Isochilus</hi>).— Of these species I can send you some drawings if you sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> desire it.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>The fine Orchid, of which I send you a drawing, seemed to me to be interesting by the two stigmas being widely separated and situated at the inside of leaf-like processes projecting beyond the anther.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>In your paper on the dimorphism of <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi> you say that it had occurred to you, that possibly a species might be dimorphic in function, though not in structure.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Some observations, which I casually made, seem to confirm this view and to prove that some species are completely barren or nearly so with pollen of the same individual plant. Thus I saw a large plant of an <hi rend="underline">Octomeria</hi>; it had more than eighty monophyllous stalks,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> each with about a dozen yellow flowers; on most of the stigmas which I examined I found numerous (6–12) pollinia; but this plant yielded only <hi rend="underline">two</hi> seed-capsules. Afterwards I have seen other plants, apparently of the same species, with numerous seed-capsules. I must add, that in the neighbourhood of the first plant I could not detect any other plant of the same species.— A very large plant of a <hi rend="underline">Serjania</hi>, widely spreading over a hedge, and as far as I know, about a mile distant from the next plant of the same species, (the same, from which the fig. 20 of my paper on the wood of climbing plants<ref target="#foot.f11"/> was taken) was covered for many weeks by thousands of flowers, which were visited all the day long by numberless insects, (—humble-bees, beetles, butterflies, etc.—); but only very few seed-capsules were produced in the last weeks and I suppose, from their appearance, that none of these capsules, (as yet unripe), will give good seed.— Last year I had raised some plants of <hi rend="underline">Eschscholtzia</hi> <hi rend="underline">californica</hi>; one of them began to flower about a month before the others, and in this time it yielded not even a single seed-capsule; but no sooner had a neighbouring plant expanded its first flowers, than germens<ref target="#foot.f12"/> of the former plant began to swell; the second plant was fertile from the beginning.—</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">one or more sheets missing</hi>〉</p>
<p>Seeds use to fall to the ground, as soon as the seed-capsules open and in this case they are commonly dark-coloured;<ref target="#foot.f13"/> if on the contrary, they remain attached to the open valvæ,<ref target="#foot.f14"/> in all the cases, I know, either the seeds themselves, or the arillus, or the interior of the valvæ are brightly coloured so as to attract the attention,<ref target="#foot.f15"/> which may carry the seeds to distant places. Thus the large valvæ of a <hi rend="underline">Tabernaemontana</hi> are filled with a bright red pulpa;—the black and shining seeds of a <hi rend="underline">Paullinia</hi> are half-imbedded into a white arillus and fixed to red valvæ,—and the seeds of a fine small tree related to Acacia or Inga, which also for some time remain attached to the valvæ, are black and white and visible at a great distance.—</p>
<p>〈<hi rend="underline">half a page excised</hi>〉 hundred miles beyond the actual sea-coast was once covered by a huge glacier!—?—<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>I am very glad to hear that Nägeli and my old friend Oscar Schmidt are with us.—<ref target="#foot.f17"/> My brother, D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hermann Müller of Lippstadt, (Prussia) who is thoroughly conversant with the natural history of mosses, is collecting the facts bearing on the change of species, which these plants may offer.—<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>Wishing that this letter may find you in good health, believe me, dear Sir, with sincere respect very truly yours</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" n="1">
<ab><ref target="#foot.f19"/></ab>
<div type="transcription"><figure type="diagram"> 
<p>Columna of <hi rend="underline">Notylia</hi>. <hi rend="underline">a</hi>. from the side. <hi rend="underline">b</hi>. front view. <hi rend="underline">c</hi>. from the side after removing anther. <hi rend="underline">d</hi> transversal section.—</p> </figure> </div>
        
    </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" n="2">
 <ab><ref target="#foot.f20"/></ab>
<div type="transcription"><figure type="diagram"> 
<p>June. 5 66. anther. labellum. 3/1columna front view. nectarium. columna from behind. stigma. anther. 15/1 pollinia. F.M. pinx.<ref target="#foot.f21"/></p> </figure> </div>
                </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 Your kind … desire it.— 3.11] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 The fine … the same species. 5.10] ‘Dichogamy <hi rend="italic">Fr. Muller</hi> Aug 22—1866—’ <hi rend="italic">added in margin blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 In your … beginning.— 5.21] <hi rend="italic">scored ink</hi></note>
                <note>5.5 <hi rend="italic">Octomeria</hi>] ‘Malaxideæ?’ <hi rend="italic">added above ink</hi><ref target="#foot.f22"/></note>  
                <note>5.17 Last year … beginning.— 5.21] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi>; ‘Escholtzia’ <hi rend="italic">added red crayon</hi>; ‘Dichogamy Fritz Muller Aug 2. 1866—’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 Seeds … distance.— 6.9] <hi rend="italic">enclosed in square brackets, blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 hundred … yours— 9.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure 1</hi>: ‘stigma so narrow a slit that pollinia cannot be inserted (Probably long [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] pedicel in)’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi><ref target="#foot.f23"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">CD note</hi>: Beauty of seeds or of inside of pods for dissemination: F. Muller. Aug. 1866 | In Portfolio for addition to Dom. Animals, a letter with coloured drawings of other seeds.<ref target="#foot.f24"/></note>
            </div>
    </div>
            

            
            

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 23 May 1866</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 23 May 1866</ref>, CD had mentioned <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Hildebrand’s</ref> recent work on trimorphic species of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> and asked Müller to investigate whether there were different forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi> in his area. CD put the specimens that Müller enclosed in an envelope labelled ‘Oxalis Brazil variable   F. Muller Aug 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>/66/’. The specimens are in DAR 142: 97.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Müller refers to his letter of 1 June 1866, which has not been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5196.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 23 August [1866]</ref>). He did, however, give an account of the orchid with three fertile anthers in letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4240.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Johann Sigismund Schultze</ref> (2 June 1866) and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller</ref> (1 July 1866; the letters are reproduced in Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 83–4, 86–9). Müller described the orchid as a species of the orchid tribe Epidendreae with three fertile anthers, two in the outer whorl and one in the inner whorl (see Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 87–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Bahia is a state (formerly a province) in north-eastern Brazil. CD described the area in his <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, pp. 589–91.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The ‘two main groups’ that Müller refers to are the Cypripedioideae (lady’s slipper orchids), which have two fertile anthers, and most other orchids, which have one. Müller later published his observations on the species of <hi rend="italic">Epidendrum</hi> with three fertile anthers (see F. Müller 1868a, 1869, and 1870) and CD added a reference to Müller’s work in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 148.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See first enclosure. Müller sent CD specimens of <hi rend="italic">Notylia</hi> attached to the diagram. These are in DAR 142: 38.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In botanical nomenclature, a ‘tribe’ is a subdivision of a family, and contains a number of genera. <hi rend="italic">Isochilus</hi> is one genus within the tribe Epidendreae. No drawings of <hi rend="italic">Isochilus</hi> by Müller have been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL, but a diagram found in Müller’s papers, dated 24 July 1866, and identified as <hi rend="italic">Isochilus</hi>, is reproduced in Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 87.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Müller enclosed an unlabelled drawing of an orchid and a specimen of the flower with this letter. These are in DAR 76: B33a. See second enclosure and n. 21. The orchid in the drawing has been identified as <hi rend="italic">Sophronitella violacea</hi>, a Brazilian member of the subtribe Laeliinae, which also includes <hi rend="italic">Isochilus</hi> (identification made by Robert L. Dressler from a scan of Müller’s drawing; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1981</ref>, p. 226, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2146.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1993</ref>, p. 275).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Müller refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref>, p. 82 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 104).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Monophyllous: ‘of a plant: having a single leaf or leaflet’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The reference is to F. Müller 1866b, and figure 20 of the table that accompanied the article.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Germen: ‘an ovary’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD pasted this paragraph into his Experimental notebook and added some notes (DAR 157a: 81; the fragment has since been moved to DAR 157a: 102). See CD note transcribed below the letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Valve: ‘one of the halves or sections of a dehiscent pod, pericarp, or capsule’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Müller presumably meant ‘to attract the attention of birds’. In another letter in which he discussed the function of brightly coloured seeds, Müller wrote that the mechanism was clearly designed to attract birds (see <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Fritz Müller to Hermann Müller, 29 October 1866</ref>, reproduced in Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 94–8; the reference is on p. 95).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">The preceding part of this section of the letter has not been found. Müller may be referring to the hypothesis advanced by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> that the Amazon valley was once covered by a huge glacier (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5198.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 27 August 1866</ref> and nn. 3 and 4). Müller had mentioned Agassiz’s research on the Amazon river in an earlier letter (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4929A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 5 November 1865</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Müller refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3473.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Wilhelm von Nägeli</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4223.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Oskar Schmidt</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 23 May 1866</ref> and n. 16). Schmidt had been a friend of Müller’s ever since they were students at Greifswald (Möller ed. 1915–21, 3: 25).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller</ref> later published a group of articles on mosses in <hi rend="italic">Verhandlungen des botanischen Vereins der Provinz Brandenburg</hi> vol. 8; one of these presented evidence from mosses that supported Darwinian transmutation theory (H. Müller 1866). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Müller affixed a specimen of <hi rend="italic">Notylia</hi> to the diagram. CD put the diagram and specimen into an envelope labelled, ‘Orchids. F. Muller Aug 2. 1866’. See n. 6, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">See n. 8, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">F.M. pinxit: ‘F. M. drew [it]’ (Latin).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">The genus <hi rend="italic">Octomeria</hi> was included in the orchid tribe Malaxideae (Malaxeae) by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4776.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lindley 1853</ref>, p. 181). It is now generally put in the tribe Epidendreae (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mabberley 1997</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">CD described the pedicel of the pollinium in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 6–7. In modern orchid terminology, the pedicel of the pollinium is called the stipe (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1981</ref>, p. 315).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">CD refers to a portfolio of notes and material for <hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi> He kept a number of such portfolios, amassed over a long period of time and since dispersed. The likely contents of some portfolios were reconstructed when some of CD’s papers were catalogued in 1932 (see DAR 220: 13). One portfolio is described as follows: ‘Scraps and notes on variation’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>