<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11342">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Carl Kraus<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   [31?] January 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17815</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11342 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11342.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11342.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 102</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 102</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2757.xml">Kraus, Carl (b)</persName>
                <placeName>Pardubitz</placeName>
                <date when="1878-01-31">[31?] Jan 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends birthday greetings and respects.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="social" ref="#">birthday greetings</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Pardubitz | Bohemia | Austria.—</placeName>
                    <date>Ende Januar 1878.—</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">“Knowledge is power”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></seg>
                    <salute>Euer Hochwolgeboren!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                
<p>Diesen Monat feiern Sie hochgeehrter Herr im Kreise Ihrer Lieben ihren Namens-Tag, und kann ich diesen Moment nicht unterlassen, um Ihnen einen Beweisz meiner Hochachtung und Verehrung für Ihre genialen Lehren, auszusprechen; wollen E Wolgeboren die herzlichsten Glückwünsche zu diesem Feste, von Einem aus der grossen Anzahl Ihrer stillen Verehrer, und Bewunderer, am Continent gütigst annehmen, welche im Satze ihren Ausdruck finden: “die Natur möge Sie hochgeehrter Herr, unseren grössten Natur-Forscher, noch viele Jahre in Ihrer bisherigen Thätigkeit für den Fortschritt der Gesammt Wissenschaft und Cultur erhalten”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Was Sie hochgeehrter Herr für die richtige Weltanschauung geleistet, will ich mich nicht erkühnen in wenigen Worten auszusprechen, ein jeder verständig Denkende weisz es zu würdigen und musz mit Recht sagen: “Es ist eine Freude zu leben, eine Wonne Zeitgenosse Darwins zu sein, dessen Namen über unsern Jahrhundert strahlt”. Unser geniale Ernst Haeckel hat erst kürzlich in einer glänzenden Festrede, den Erfolg des Darwinismus auf die Gesammt-Wissenschaft besprochen,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> und mögen Sie hochgeehrter Herr, der erleuchtete Eremit von Down, noch Jahre lang an den allgemeinen Erfolg Ihrer Lehre sich erfreuen. Ich war leider verhindert, mich an der Festgabe Ihrer deutscher Anhänger anzuschlieszen, daher wollen Sie hochgeehrter Herr diese nachträglich eingelangten Glückwünsche gütigst annehmen,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> und schliesze ich mit den erhabenen Worten D. Fr. Strauss:</p>
<p>“Jeder denkende Mensch, der weisz, was am Wunder hängt, wird Darwin als einen der edelsten Wolthäter der Menschheit preisen”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Mit dem Ausdruck meiner Verehrung und Hochachtung, | zeichne mich als | ehrfurchtsvoller Bewunderer | Charles Kraus.</p>
<p>Erlaube mir die höfl. Anfrage zu stellen, ob meiner Photographie ein Plätzchen im Kreise Ihrer Anhänger &amp; Bewunderer vergönnen würden?</p>
<p>“A sign of unalterable admiration”!<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Pardubice | Bohemia | Austria.—</placeName>
                    <date>Late January 1878.—</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">“Knowledge is power”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></seg>
                    <salute>Your Honour!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>This month you, esteemed Sir, are celebrating your name day in the circle of your loved ones, and I cannot miss this opportunity to express my respect and esteem for your ingenious theories; may your honour kindly accept the most heartfelt felicitations for this celebration from one of your many silent admirers and worshippers on the continent, felicitations which find expression in the sentence: “May nature preserve you, most esteemed Sir, our greatest naturalist, for many years yet so you may continue to labour for the advance of the whole of science and culture.”<ref target="#foot.f3"/> What you, esteemed Sir, have done for the true view of the universe, I do not dare sum up in just a few words; every person of common sense appreciates it and will rightly say: “It is a pleasure, a joy, to be a contemporary of Darwin, whose name shines radiantly over our century.” In a recent brilliant speech, our ingenious Ernst Haeckel discussed the impact of Darwinism on science as a whole.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> May you, most esteemed Sir, the inspired hermit of Down, rejoice over the universal success of your theory for many years yet. Unfortunately I was unable to participate in the gift presented to you by your German followers, so please, dear Sir, kindly accept my belated felicitations.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I close with the sublime words of D. Fr. Strauss:</p>
<p>“Every thinking man who knows what stands or falls with the idea of the miracle, will praise Darwin as a most noble benefactor of mankind.”<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>With admiration and respect, | I sign as | a reverential worshipper | Charles Kraus.</p>
<p>I permit myself to inquire politely whether my photograph might be granted a place among those of the circle of your followers and admirers?</p>
                    <p>“A sign of unalterable admiration”<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>


<div type="footnotes">
    <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
    <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 37–8.</note>
    <note xml:id="foot.f2">The phrase is often attributed to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_221.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Bacon</ref>; ‘ipsa scientia potestas est’ appears in his <hi rend="italic">Meditationes sacrae</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9668.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bacon 1826</ref>, 10: 308).</note>
    <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s 69th birthday was on 12 February 1878.</note>
    <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel gave a speech, ‘Ueber die heutige Entwickelungslehre im Verhältnisse zur Gesammtwissenschaft’ (On the modern doctrine of evolution in relation to general science), on 18 September 1877 at the annual assembly of German naturalists and physicians in Munich (Haeckel 1877). There is a copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
    <note xml:id="foot.f5">In 1877, German and Austrian scientists had sent CD an album of photographs of themselves to celebrate his birthday (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10826.xml">letter from Emil Rade, [before 16] February 1877</ref>, and <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Appendix V); the album is at Down House. For Krause’s photograph, see plate on p. 507.</note>
    <note xml:id="foot.f6">The quotation is from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4590.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Friedrich Strauss’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Der alte und der neue Glaube</hi> (The old and the new faith; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7507.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Strauss 1872</ref>, p. 177).</note>
    <note xml:id="foot.f7">The quotation appears in the German and Austrian album, with the photograph of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8282.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Josef von Doblhoff-Dier</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10178.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gries 2006</ref>, p. 65).</note>
</div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>