<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11425">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   14 March 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20162</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11425 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11425.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11425.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 416–7</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 144: 436 </bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 436</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-03-14">14 Mar 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD gives his opinion on how the physiological laboratory at Kew should be equipped. It would be a pity if the laboratory were not supplied with as many good instruments as their funds could provide.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Kew</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">physiological laboratory</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Beckenham, Kent.</placeName>
                    <date>March 14th, 1878.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Dyer,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have a very strong opinion that it would be the greatest possible pity if the Phys: Lab., now that it has been built, were not supplied with as many good instruments as your funds can possibly afford.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It is quite possible that some of them may become antiquated before they are much or even at all used. But this does not seem to me any argument at all against getting them, for the Laboratory cannot be used until well provided; and the mere fact of the instruments being ready may suggest to some one to use them. You at Kew, as guardians &amp; promoters of Botanical Science will then have done all in your power, &amp; if your Lab. is not used the disgrace will lie at the feet of the public. But until bitter experience proves the contrary I will never believe that we are so backward. I should think the German laboratories would be very good guides as to what to get;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but Timiriazeff of Moscow who travelled over Europe to see all Bot. Labs, &amp; who seemed so good a fellow, would I should think give the best list of the most indispensable instruments.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Lately I thought of getting Frank or Horace to go to Cambridge for the use of the Heliostat there;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> but our observations turned out of less importance than I thought; yet if there had been one at Kew we should probably have used it &amp; might have found out something curious. It is impossible for me to predict whether or not we should ever want this or that instrument, for we are guided in our work by what turns up. Thus I am now observing something about geotropism, &amp; I had no idea a few weeks ago that this would have been necessary.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In a short time we might earnestly wish for a centrifugal apparatus or a heliostat. In all such cases it would make a great difference if a man knew that he could use a particular instrument without great loss of time. I have now given my opinion, which is very decided whether right or wrong &amp; Frank quite agrees with me. You can of course show this letter to Hooker<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Charles Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        
            
            
        
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">The Jodrell laboratory was completed in 1876 with funds for building and equipiment from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6529.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Jodrell Phillips-Jodrell</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9101.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thiselton-Dyer 1910</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9771.xml">letter from J. D. Hooker, 22 December 1874</ref>). Thiselton-Dyer was given responsibility for the laboratory and encouraged botanists to use its facilities (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1986.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1995</ref>, p. 250).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD was most familiar with the botanical laboratory of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref> in Würzburg (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10042.xml">letter from Julius Sachs, 4 July 1875</ref>); <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> worked there in the summer of 1878 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3">Kliment Arkadievich Timiryazev had visited CD at Down on 25 July 1877 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11072.xml">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 26 [July 1877]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4">A heliostat is a device containing a mirror that turns so as to direct sunlight to a fixed position; for its use in botany, see Sachs 1875, p. 683. CD refers to Francis and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f5">Geotropism (bending towards the centre of the earth) and related movements are discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, pp. 493–522.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>.</note>
            </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>