<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2347">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To T. H. Huxley   23 October [1858]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3227</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2347 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2347.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2347.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 180</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 110</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 175</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 243)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 243</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1858-10-23">23 Oct [1858]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD’s reasons for not signing the memorial requesting removal of natural history exhibits from British Museum. Less sure about moving botanical specimens to Kew. His notion of museum organisation.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Kew</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">British Museum collections</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Huxley</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>The names which you give as supporting your memorial make me quite distrust my own judgment.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But as I must say yea or nay, I am forced to say that I doubt the wisdom of the movement, &amp; am not willing at present to sign.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> My reasons, perhaps of very little value, are as follows. The governing classes are thoroughily unscientific, &amp; the men of art &amp; of archæology have much greater weight with government than we have. If we make a move to separate from Brit. Museum, I cannot but fear that we may go to the dogs. I think we owe our position in large part to the hundreds of thousands of people who visit the B. Mus. attracted by the heteregeous mixture of objects. If we lost this support, as I think we should, for a mere collection of animals does not seem very attractive to the masses (judging from Museum of Zoolog. Soc. formerly in Leicester Square &amp;c)<ref target="#foot.f4"/> then I do not think we sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. get nearly so much aid from government. Therefore I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be inclined to stick to the mummies &amp; Assyrian Gods, as long as we could. If we knew that Government was going to turn us out, then, &amp; not till then, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be inclined to make an energetic move.—</p>
<p>If we were to separate, I do not believe that we sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have funds granted for the many books required for occasional reference: each man must speak from his own experience, I have so repeatedly required to see old transactions &amp; old Travels &amp;c, that I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. regret extremely, when at work at Brit. Mus, to be separated from the <hi rend="underline">entire</hi> Library. The facilities for working at certain great classes, as Birds, larger fossils &amp;c are no doubt as bad as possible or rather impossible on the open days; but I have found the working rooms of the assistants very convenient for all other classes on all days.</p>
<p>In regard to the Botanical collections I am too ignorant to express any opinion: the point seems to be how far Botanists would object to journey to Kew; but there are evidently many great advantages in the transposition.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>If I had my own way, I would make the B. Mus. collection only a typical one for display, which would be quite as amusing &amp; far more instructive to the populace (&amp; I think to naturalists) than the present enormous display of Birds &amp; Mammals. I would save expence of stuffing &amp; would keep all skins, except a few “typicals”, in drawers. Thus much room would be saved, &amp; a little more space could be given to real workers, who could work all days. Rooms fitted up with thousands of drawers would cost but little. With this I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be contented. Until I had pretty sure information that we were going to be turned out, I would not stir in the matter.— With such opponents, as you name, I daresay I am <hi rend="underline">quite</hi> wrong, but this is my best though doubtful present judgment.—</p>
<p>My dear Huxley | Yours very sincerely | Ch Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. | The memorial does not strike me as very lucid. The number of Divisions &amp; Sub-divisions seem to me rather bothersome, &amp; destructive of force of the whole.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>It seems to me dangerous even to hint at a new Scientific Museum—a popular Museum &amp; to subsidise the Zoological Gardens; it would, I think, frighten any government.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.13 Gods] <hi rend="italic">before omitted point</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.13 as long] <hi rend="italic">after two omitted points</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.14 was] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘were’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.6 &amp;c] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.8 days.] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘other’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.2 ;] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> <hi rend="italic">full stop</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.2 but … transposition. 3.3] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">4.2 the populace 4.3] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘them’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">4.6 Rooms … but little. 4.7] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">4.10 though doubtful] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to a memorial presented to the British government concerning the natural history collections of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref>. A previous memorial had been circulated in June 1858 (see letters to R. I. Murchison, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2286.xml" resp="#automat">19 June [1858]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2292.xml" resp="#automat">24 [June 1858]</ref>); the second memorial was presented in November 1858 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.7, Appendix VI).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">A preliminary draft of this memorial to the chancellor of the exchequer is in the Huxley papers, Imperial College Archives. The final version (transcribed in Appendix VI) was signed by CD, Huxley, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_760.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Busk</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Benjamin Carpenter</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Harvey</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Henfrey</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2235.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Stevens Henslow</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had previously signed the memorial circulated by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3453.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roderick Impey Murchison</ref> in June 1858, protesting against the proposal that the natural history collections should be moved from the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.7, Appendix VI). The new memorial maintained that the collections could be re- arranged to best effect if they were removed from the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> site. CD presumably felt that having endorsed the need to keep the collections within the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref>, he should not support alternative plans.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The museum collections of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zoological Society of London</ref> had been closed in 1855 and sold to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Scherren 1905</ref>, p. 123).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The second memorial proposed that a new museum be established, comprising a ‘Typical or popular museum’ of zoology and a ‘Scientific zoological museum and library’. All the botanical collections, it suggested, could be sent to the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew and the ensuing repository turned into an equivalent ‘Scientific botanical museum and library’. See Appendix VI.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The first paragraph of the postscript (‘The memorial … force of the whole.—’) has been deleted.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>