<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13115">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Frithiof Holmgren   [14] April 1881<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8192</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13115 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13115.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13115.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="draft">
                <bibl>DAR 139.17: 24</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 226</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 205</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 23 (1881): 583</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Uppsala University Library (Frithiof Holmgren Collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_428.xml">Uppsala</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>139.17: 24</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 260 (fragile)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-14">[14] Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2343.xml">Holmgren, Frithiof</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD gives his opinion on vivisection with the understanding that the whole letter will be published. Worked for Act of Parliament, but disapproves of the one passed. CD convinced English physiologists do not perform cruel experiments.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">English physiologists</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Act of Parliament concerning vivisection</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-06" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-27" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-29" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down, Beckenham</placeName>
                    <date>April 1881</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>In answer to your courteous letter of April 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, I have no objection to express my opinion with respect to the right of experimenting on living animals.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I use this latter expression as more correct and comprehensive than that of vivisection.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You are at liberty to make any use of this letter which you may think fit; but if published, I should wish the whole to appear. I have all my life been a strong advocate for humanity to animals, and have done what I could in my works to enforce this duty. Several years ago when the agitation against physiologists commenced in England, it was asserted that inhumanity was here practiced, and useless suffering caused to animals; and I was led to think that it might be adviseable to have an Act of Parliament on the subject. I then took an active share in trying to get a bill passed, such as would have removed all just causes of complaint, and at the same time have left physiologists free to pursue their researches—a bill very different to the Act which has since been passed.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It is right to add that the investigation of the matter by a Royal Commission proved that the accusations made against our English physiologists were false. From all that I have heard, however, I fear that in some parts of Europe little regard is paid to the sufferings of animals; and if this be the case, I should be glad to hear of legislation against inhumanity in any such country. On the other hand, I know that physiology cannot possibly progress, except by means of experiments on living animals; and I feel the deepest conviction that he who retards the progress of Physiology commits a crime against mankind. Any one who remembers, as I can, the state of this Science half a century ago, must admit that it has made immense progress; and it is now progressing at an ever increasing rate  What improvements in medical practice may be directly attributed to physiological research, is a question which can be properly discussed only by those physiologists and medical practicioners who have studied the history of their subjects; but as far as I can learn, the benefits are already great. However this may be, no one, unless he is grossly ignorant of what science has done for mankind, can entertain any doubt of the incalculable benefits which will hereafter be derived from physiology, not only by man but by the lower animals. Look for instance at Pasteur’s results in modifying the germs of the most malignant diseases, from which, as it so happens, animals will in the first place receive more relief than man.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Let it be remembered how many lives and what a fearful amount of suffering have been saved by the knowledge gained of parasitic worms through the experiments of Virchow and others on living animals.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The future generation will be astonished at the ingratitude shown, at least in England, towards these benefactors of Mankind.</p>
<p>As for myself, permit me to assure you that I honour &amp; shall always honour every one who advances the noble science of Physiology.</p>
<p>I beg leave to remain | Dear Sir | Yours faithfully | Charles Darwin <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To | Professor Frithiof Holmgren | Upsala <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>P.S. <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>.—</p>
                    <p>I have written letters of the same tenour as the enclosed to several of the opponents of experiments on living animals, but they have all been suppressed. It now occurs to me that the publication in England of my answer to you might possibly influence some persons who are not bigoted.— I hope &amp; suppose that you will not object to my doing so, <hi rend="underline">that is if after further reflexion</hi> <hi rend="underline">I determine to make</hi> <hi rend="underline">the trial</hi>; but it is doubtful whether any leading newspaper would publish my letter which would be unpopular.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>C. D.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">5.1 P.S. … C. D.— 7.1] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">6.2 experiments] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘all’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">6.3 in England] ‘in’ <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘of’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">6.6 newspaper] ‘news’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The day is established by the date given in the published version of this letter (see n. 7, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13108.xml">7 April 1881</ref>, Holmgren had asked CD for his views on vivisection and laws forbidding or restraining its use.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Vivisection was often used to refer both to the opening and the dissecting of live animals; experimenting did not necessarily involve dissection. The committee that was set up to investigate in 1875 was formally called the Royal Commission on the practice of subjecting live animals to experiments for scientific purposes, but is often referred to as the Royal Commission on vivisection.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For CD’s earlier involvement in the drafting of a bill for the regulation of vivisection, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9923.xml">letter to J. S. Burdon Sanderson, [11 April 1875]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3707.xml">Louis Pasteur</ref> had discovered a vaccine for chicken cholera after experimentally infecting chickens with the disease; he published his results in December 1880 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11577.xml">Pasteur 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In 1859, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4897.xml">Rudolf Virchow</ref> had discovered the adult form of the nematode worm <hi rend="italic">Trichina spiralis</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Trichinella spiralis</hi>) in experiments with dogs (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11581.xml">Virchow 1859</ref>). The worm is responsible for the disease trichinosis in humans.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In the event, CD's letter, excluding the section marked ‘Private’, and dated 14 April 1881, was published in <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 18 April 1881, p. 10. The letter was also published in the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi>, 19 April 1881, p. 7.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>