<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7027">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. T. Moggridge   12 December 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">18041</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7027 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7027.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7027.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 214</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 214</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3353.xml">Moggridge, J. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Mentone</placeName>
                <date when="1869-12-12">12 Dec 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends seeds of <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus</hi> and suggests an advantage of climbing plants is to shed their seeds in places secure from animals.</p>  
<p>Contrary to F. Delpino, in JTM’s experience <hi rend="italic">Ophrys aranifera</hi> is not sterile. However, seed germination is poor.</p>  
<p>In a densely overgrown plot <hi rend="italic">Convolvulus sabatius</hi>, not normally a twiner, becomes one.</p>  
<p>Continues his extensive study on variability in <hi rend="italic">Arbutus</hi>, and speculates on selection in fruit shape.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Arbutus</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbing plants</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Convolvulus sabatius</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">fruit</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Lathyrus</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Ophrys aranifera</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">twiner</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1286">Delpino, Federico</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maison Gastaldy | Mentone | (<hi rend="print">Alpes Maritimes</hi>)</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 12 1869.</date>
                    <salute>Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have obained a few seeds of <hi rend="underline">Lathyrus Clymenum</hi> L. &amp; <hi rend="underline">Lath</hi>: <hi rend="underline">Ochrus</hi> DC. to send you, &amp; these I enclose.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I find that my botanical friends generally have never thought of collecting seed of such common plants as these for growing, so that I fear I shall not be likely to obtain more for you before next year.</p>
<p>I hope however that these may germinate. Some weeks ago I collected the small quantity of seed of <hi rend="underline">Lath: Clymenum</hi> L. which I send, by looking under the low bushes which were still covered with the dead haulm &amp; gaping pods of this plant. I was much struck by the scarcity of the seeds when compared with the abundance of the pods, &amp;, as the few seeds which I secured were obtained by searching in the thickest &amp; thorniest places, I feel sure that they have been eaten for the most part by birds &amp; mice.—</p>
<p>This fact serves to point out an additional advantage which climbing plants gain, beside support &amp; abundance of light, namely the opportunity of shedding their seeds, or some of them, in places secure from the depredation of animals.</p>
<p>I now remember that I obtained last year a good supply of fallen seed from the cruelly-spiny <hi rend="underline">Astragalus Tragacantha</hi> L. by searching underneath the matted branches, which act as protection from all ordinary intruders .... .... …</p>
<p>I have now, in my little plot of garden here, two seedling plants of <hi rend="underline">Ophrys aranifera</hi> Huds., which sprang the self-sown seed of capsules produced by the artificial fertilization of a plant which I had moved from the wild ground last spring.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I am much surprised to find that the seedlings are nearly as large as the thriving parent plant, thus indicating an extremely rapid growth— —.</p>
<p>I find some difficulty in reconciling M. Delphino’s statement as to the sterility of <hi rend="underline">Oph</hi>: <hi rend="underline">aranifera</hi> Huds. with the fact that it is abundant in all this region, the plant being one which can only be propagated by seed—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Moreover, whenever I have attempted the fertilization of this subspecies, fine capsules have been developed.</p>
<p>There are, no doubt, a great many obstacles to the <hi rend="underline">germination</hi> of the seed; &amp; this the example of my solitary pair of seedlings tends to shew, for I fertilized a considerable number of plants in the same plot of garden-ground; &amp; the two fine capsules of the successful plant must have furnished seed enough to sow the whole garden, yet only the two seedlings appeared—</p>
<p>My tiny plot of garden was left absolutely untouched during the months from May to October, &amp; I returned to find it a jungle of weeds. This may have injured the chances of the <hi rend="underline">Ophrys</hi> seeds; but, on the other hand, I find that very few plants have been materially injured, &amp; some have certainly gained by the shade which was afforded by the tall, much-branched intruders.</p>
<p>A plant of <hi rend="underline">Convolvulus sabatius</hi> Viv, a perennial of somewhat woody growth, &amp; which does not twine in its native habitat, was curiously affected, the branches being greatly lengthened &amp; ‘<hi rend="underline">drawn</hi>’, so that in several instances they twined round one another, one pair of stems making 8 complete turns—!</p>
<p>I have been able to carry on &amp; to extend my observations on <hi rend="underline">Arbutus</hi>, &amp; hope to get some good results from them…<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I have satisfied myself that the offspring do in some cases closely reproduce the details of the parents, but I still think that close resemblance is rare. I have obtained a curious record of the difference between the individuals in respect of their season of flowering, differences which, reckoned as they are by months, must expose the plants to very different conditions.</p>
<p>That these &amp; similar differences of condition are either secondary in their influence, or without influence, I have now gathered some evidence to shew.</p>
<p>I am now collecting the details of variation in seedling plants, &amp; in luxuriant shoots springing from trees which have suffered from cutting .... … My general observations lead to the conclusion that there is in <hi rend="underline">Arbutus Unedo</hi> L. a great amount of variability, but that among these variable forms a peculiar type of fruit—the globose-depressed—prevails— But as on the same tree the fruits do not always present the same shape, three forms being sometimes found together, I cannot avoid speculating whether there may not have been, or may not be, a selective process at work among the individual fruits, as there has been or may be among the individual trees; for these polymorphic individuals always have one predominant type of fruit, the three forms not being found together in equal or nearly equal numbers.</p>
<p>These differences among the fruits of one branch, are certainly not due to any circumstance such as position, crowding or the like, &amp; there is great reason to suppose that they are due to independant variation—</p>
<p>I must, however, apologise for the liberty I take in troubling you with details which are, I fear, too incomplete to be of interest   I hope, if my health continues to improve, to get my notes into order for publication before the summer; trusting that the Linnean Society will not reject them on account of the minute, &amp;, to some, perhaps tedious, details, &amp; the cost of reproducing a large series of illustrations.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Believe me | y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. very sincerely | J. Traherne Moggridge.</p>
<p>I hope that you will not scruple to give me any commissions which you think I can do for you— I esteem all such as favours recieved.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I have … intruders .... .... … 5.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>13.1 I have … conditions. 13.5] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6899.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. T. Moggridge, 18 September 1869</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Lathyrus ochrus</hi> is the cypress vetch; <hi rend="italic">L. clymenum</hi> the Spanish vetchling.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For Moggridge’s earlier work on <hi rend="italic">Ophrys aranifera</hi> (the spider orchid), and CD’s interest in it, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 13 and 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Moggridge evidently refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino’s</ref> statement in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>, part 1: 177, that in Liguria hardly one flower of <hi rend="italic">Ophrys aranifera</hi> out of 3000 set a capsule; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 50–1. See also Delpino 1867b, pp. 19–20, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 144 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 141).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">On Moggridge’s earlier observations of an <hi rend="italic">Arbutus</hi> (madrone) species, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6777.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. T. Moggridge, 7 June 1869</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6894.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. T. Moggridge, 16 September [1869]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> did not publish a paper by Moggridge on <hi rend="italic">Arbutus.</hi></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>