<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5454">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   22 March 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10654</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5454 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5454.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5454.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 75</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 75</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</persName>
                <placeName>Stuttgart</placeName>
                <date when="1867-03-22">22 Mar 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Agrees to publish German edition of <hi rend="italic">Variation</hi>.</p>  
<p>Discusses publication of third German ed. of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Thanks CD for portrait.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Variation</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>E. Schweizerbart, Commissions- und Verlagsbuchhandlung. Buchdruckerei Stuttgart</placeName>
                    <date>22 März 1867</date>
                    <salute>Verehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ihr freundliches Schreiben vom 19<hi rend="superscript">en</hi> veranlasst mich sofort Ihnen Antwort zu geben.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Empfangen Sie meinen aufrichtigen Dank für den neuen Beweis Ihrer Gewogenheit, die Sie für mich haben, indem Sie mir in uneigennützigster Weise die Aushänge Bogen Ihres grösseren Werkes, das Sie unter dem Titel: <hi rend="underline">The variation of animals</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Plants under Domestication</hi>” in diesem Augenblicke unter der Presse haben, Behufs einer deutschen Uebersetzung anbieten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Mit allem Vergnügen nehme ich diesen Antrag an und werde noch heute an Herrn Prof Carus<ref target="#foot.f4"/> schreiben, um ihn zu ersuchen, die deutsche Ausgabe davon zu besorgen; ich zweifle nicht daran, dass er sehr gerne diesem Auftrage sich unterziehen werde und wird er desshalb sich wohl selbst an Sie wenden.</p>
<p>Wegen der Holzschnitte werde ich mich demnächst an den Herrn Murray selbst wenden und möchte nur bitten dass Sie demselben gelegentlich sagen er möchte mir von den Holzschnitten zu Ihrem Werke <hi rend="doubleUnderline">gute</hi> Stereotypen machen lassen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Der Druck der neuen Auftrage von Origin deutsch, schreitet rasch vor und kann die erste Lieferung (12 Bog) in einigen Tagen verschickt werden, wenn das Ganze fertig, erhalten Sie nach Wunsch die Exemplare.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Für die liebenswürdige Uebersendung Ihrer Porträte habe ich Ihnen auch noch meinen Dank zu sagen; ich war nicht wenig überrascht statt des mir bekannten jüngeren Bildes in der anziehenden form einen älteren Herrn mit grauem Barte zu erhalten.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Ich sandte Herrn Carus eine hier gemachte Copie des grossen Bildes, worauf dieser mir schrieb, dass ihm das Kleinere das er von Ihnen erhalten (vermüthlich das mit der Stühllehne) fast besser gefalle, es ist das <hi rend="underline">ganz Profil.</hi></p>
<p>Es will uns scheinen dass das frühere Bild manchen besser zusagen würde; ich erlaube mir daher die Frage, ob Sie vielleicht Werth darauf legen, dass ein neueres Bild gegeben werde, woraus die mit Ihrem Aeusseren vorgegangene Veränderung ersichtlich ist; <hi rend="underline">das jenige Bild, das Sie mir bezeichnen, werde ich geben</hi>, bitte daher nur es mir zu bestimmen.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Mit gröster Hochachtung und Verehrung | Ihr ganz ergebenster | E Schweizerbart</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">Any Photographs</hi> | Murray— to make <hi rend="italic">good</hi> stereotypes’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>E. Schweizerbart, Commissions- und Verlagsbuchhandlung. Buchdruckerei Stuttgart</placeName>
                    <date>22 March 1867</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Your friendly letter of the 19th prompts me to answer immediately.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Please accept my sincere thanks for the new demonstration of your favour in most unselfishly offering me clean sheets of your larger work now in press, titled: <hi rend="underline">The variation of animals</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">plants under domestication</hi>”, for translation into German.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I am most pleased to accept your offer and I shall write to Prof. Carus<ref target="#foot.f4"/> today to ask him to deal with the German edition; I do not doubt that he will be happy to undertake this commission and therefore will contact you himself.</p>
<p>Concerning the woodcuts, I will contact Mr. Murray shortly myself and need only ask you to tell him, when the occasion arises, to kindly let me have <hi rend="doubleUnderline">good</hi> stereotypes of the woodcuts for your work.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>The printing of the new edition of the German Origin is progressing rapidly, and the first delivery (12 sheets) can be dispatched in a couple of days. When it is all ready you will receive copies as you wish.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I must also thank you for kindly sending me your portraits. I was not a little surprised to receive instead of the familiar fine figure of the earlier picture, that of a more elderly gentleman with grey beard.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I sent Herr Carus a copy of the large picture, made here, whereupon he wrote to me that the smaller one that he received from you (presumably the one with the chair-back) seems rather better to him, it is the <hi rend="underline">full profile.</hi></p>
<p>It strikes us that the earlier picture may appeal more to some; so I take the liberty of asking whether it perhaps matters to you that a newer picture is used in which the change in your appearance is evident. <hi rend="underline">I will use the picture you indicate to me</hi>, please just let me know your decision.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>With the highest esteem and admiration | your most devoted | E Schweizerbart</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, Appendix I. It was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, the head of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>, who used the signature E. Schweizerbart in business communications.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 157–8. It was written by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, the head fo <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref>, who used the signature E. Schweizertbart in business communications.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, [19 March 1867]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Schweizerbart refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, [19 March 1867]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Victor Carus</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">John Murray, CD’s publisher, provided Schweizerbart with electrotypes of the illustrations for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>; Murray’s ledger records a payment of £10 from Schweizerbart in September 1867 (John Murray Archive).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Carus had recently finished translating the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn and Carus trans. 1867; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5403.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. V. Carus, 17 February [1867]</ref>). No presentation list for Bronn and Carus trans. 1867 has been found. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The image used in the first two German editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1860 and Bronn trans. 1863) was a reproduction of a photograph taken around 1857 (DAR 225: 175; reproduced as the frontispiece to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD had sent Carus a photograph of himself with his letter of 10 November 1866 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14). The photograph Carus received was one made by CD’s son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Erasmus Darwin</ref> in 1864, reproduced as the frontispiece to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12 (Carus photograph album, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4438.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Smithsonian Institution</ref> Archives, Record Unit 7315). An engraving made from this photograph was used for the frontispiece to Bronn and Carus trans. 1867. CD may have sent Schweizerbart a later photograph, taken by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5315.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernest Edwards</ref> in 1865 or 1866 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4942.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from E. A. Darwin to Emma Darwin, 25 [November 1865]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>