<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3604F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. E. Darwin   14 June [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21670</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3604F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3604F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3604F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
                <relatedItem type="publication">
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 24: 448</bibl>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Cornford Family Papers (DAR 275: 2)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                        <collection>DAR</collection>
                        <idno>275: 2</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">Darwin, W. E.</persName>
                <placeName>Southampton</placeName>
                <date when="1862-06-14">14 June [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>WED’s travel plans; an insect he has observed on <hi rend="italic">Orchis maculata</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Southampton</placeName>
                    <date>June 14.</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very glad to hear they got home all safe, I dare say you were not sorry to get them, it is very unlucky about poor old Pouts just before the holidays begin.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I send off your watch some time today.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Do you know any reason why I should not offer myself for Sunday the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>, as D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker told me to write as soon as I had fixed my Sunday.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I shall come to Down on the Monday and go up for the ball on Tuesday, and back on Wednesday to the C. P. so to Down, and to Southampton on Thursday.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I dont know whether Etty told you of my seeing a <hi rend="underline">fly</hi>(?) sucking Orchis Maculata the wrong way standing above it, and peering over to suck and leaning over sideways to other flowers with out getting off first flower, so that the pollinia were glued unsymmetrically to its mouth and not to its trunk.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>You are reviewed in the Hampshire Advertizer but I have not seen it yet<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>your affect son | W E Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I am … Thursday. 2.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">pencil after illeg pencil del pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 13 [June 1862]</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Horace Darwin</ref> had returned to Down after staying with William in Southampton from 3 to 12 June 1862. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Darwin</ref>, known as Pouts or Pouter in the family, was sent home from school on 12 June because he had scarlet fever. (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242).)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had asked for his watch to be returned by registered post (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3601.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, 13 [June 1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">William had wanted to visit <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> at Kew for some time; see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3537.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [5 May 1862]</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3525.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. E. Darwin, [8 May 1862]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3541.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 9 May [1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The ball may have been associated with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Godfrey Wedgwood’s</ref> marriage; the wedding took place in Pimlico, London, on Tuesday 24 June (Bark ed. 2014, p. xxxv). William was probably planning to visit the Crystal Palace at Sydenham en route to Down before returning home to Southampton.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In a note dated 20 June 1862 (DAR 70: 13–14), CD recorded that William had seen a fly remove pollinia of <hi rend="italic">Orchis maculata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Dactylorhiza maculata</hi>, the heath spotted orchid) in Southampton; he also noted that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> had caught six flies (<hi rend="italic">Empis livida</hi>, a species of dance fly) with pollinia of <hi rend="italic">O. maculata</hi> attached to their eyes, as well as one specimen of <hi rend="italic">E. pennipes</hi> with pollinia attached to its thorax. CD added the information about George’s observations in <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed., p. 16, but did not mention William’s observation. Etty: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The <hi rend="italic">Hampshire Advertiser</hi>, 31 May 1862, p. 3, reprinted the review of <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> that had appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi>, 24 May 1862, pp. 683–5. This was a critical review that CD feared would hinder sales (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3609.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 18 [June 1862]</ref> and n. 5). Although the <hi rend="italic">Hampshire Advertiser</hi> omitted the sections from the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> criticising CD’s views on insect fertilisation of orchids, it did include the final paragraph stating that <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> did not fulfil CD’s aim of showing that all organic beings occasionally required cross-fertilisation.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>