<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5900">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Henty   20 February 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14334</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5900 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5900.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5900.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 181, 183</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 181, 183</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2239.xml">Henty, William</persName>
                <placeName>Brighton</placeName>
                <date when="1868-02-20">20 Feb 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has read CD’s inquiry about proportional numbers of males and females born to domestic animals [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">5863</hi>] and outlines his theory regarding the factors determining the sex of offspring.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">young, offspring</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>3 Montpelier Villas | Brighton</placeName>
                    <date>20 Feby 68</date>
                    <salute>Sir/</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In response to your letter in the Agricultural Gazette of the 15 Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> permit me to state that I have for some time had my attention drawn to a theory or principle on the balance of the sexes which bears on your enquiry &amp; which may perhaps tend to illustrate the subject<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I addressed a note to the Ag<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. Gazette a few weeks ago drawing attention of graziers &amp; farmers to what seems to be the law of nature, by which the sex of the progeny is determined, which if clearly understood &amp; confirmed will enable the breeder to arrange what proportion of either sex his stock shall produce<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>The principle is simply that nature which takes the utmost pains to secure the reproduction of her creations will cause the first products of generation to follow the sex of that one of the parents whose constitution is oldest (from age or infirmity) &amp; is therefore likely to die first</p>
<p>Having seen this principle stated above 30 years ago I have amused myself in tracing its results in man &amp; animals &amp; with almost invariable certainty.</p>
<p>For instance the known fact that males of the human species predominate in the proportion of 18 to 17 over females which is quoted by Paley &amp; others as a special arrangement by Providence to provide against the casualties of war &amp;c may by this rule be easily accounted for as on an average of marriages men largely exceed their wives in age<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Throughout the families of my acquaintance I can remember but one decided failure in its application. In others there have been apparent failures but explained by the after knowledge of facts in their physical condition e.g. one young wife of an elderly person produced a daughter but it turned out she had an open ulcer in her leg   In two similar cases the wife had a family of daughters, the cause being that whilst in childbearing she was in delicate health but after that period they recovered their former strength of constitution</p>
<p>When the folks on the Stock Exchange were betting about the sex of the expectant offspring of Louis Nap<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. I stated my opinion without hesitation that it would prove a son.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In my own case I applied this rule successfully when putting a favorite mare to a blood horse—&amp; I have known a friend exclaim—against his ill luck in always having a bull calf when he had permission to send a cow cost free to a very celebrated old bull—whereas if he had sent a cow older than the sire he would doubtless have had a heifer calf</p>
<p>One apparent exception was pointed out by a gentleman—a large breeder, in the fact that the first calf of a young heifer is generally a cow calf</p>
<p>This I attributed to the circumstance that, the cows running indiscriminately (in Australia) with the bulls the heifers took the bull before they had themselves arrived at full maturity &amp; whilst their constitution was therefore weaker than that of the male.</p>
<p>The authority in which I found the statement of this theory was a volume of lectures on Political Economy by J. Bryan Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi> delivered before the Royal Society of Dublin about 34 or more years since<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I have heard also that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Coombe<ref target="#foot.f6"/> has made allusion to it</p>
<p>I hope shortly to make fuller reference to these authorities when I am able to pay a visit to the British museum &amp; to communicate any further information if deemed by you of sufficient interest to the particular subject of your present enquiry</p>
<p>I remain | Sir | Faithfully yours | W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Henty <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Cha<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi> | &amp;c &amp;c</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 11 February [1868]. The full title of the journal is the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Henty’s letter has not been found in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3647.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Paley’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Principles of moral and political philosophy</hi>; the proportion of males to females is given by Paley as ‘nineteen to eighteen, or thereabouts … which excess provides for the greater consumption of males by war, seafaring, and other dangerous and unhealthy occupations’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paley 1785</ref>, p. 262).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Louis Napoleon’s son, Napoléon Eugène Louis John Joseph, was born in 1856.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The reference is to James Butler Bryan and Bryan 1831, pp. 317–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Combe</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>