<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-302">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Catherine Darwin   3 June 1836</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5071</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-302 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-302.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-302.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 154: 63</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi>: 140</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 1: 497</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 223</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>223: 35</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Cape of Good Hope</placeName>
                <date when="1836-06-03">3 June 1836</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1212.xml">Darwin, E. C.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Will call on Sir J. Herschel, then take short trip in the African desert.</p> 
<p>Horrified at the publication of "the little book of extracts" from his letters to Henslow ["Letters to Professor Henslow" (1835), <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 1: 3–16].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Collected papers</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2235">Henslow, J. S.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2259">Herschel, J. F. W.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cape of Good Hope.</placeName>
                    <date>June 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. 1836</date>
                    <salute>My dear Catherine,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>We arrived here the day before yesterday; the first part of our passage from Mauritius was very favourable, and the latter as execrably bad. We encountered a heavy gale of wind, which strongly reminded us of the old days, near Cape Horn; It is a lucky thing for me, that the voyage is drawing to its close, for I positively suffer more from sea sickness, now, than three years ago.— All hands, having been disappointed in letters at Sydney &amp; Mauritius made up their minds for a grand pile at this place.— The mountain of letters, alas, has dwindled into 〈a〉 small packet of about a dozen: amongs〈t〉 them I had the good fortune of receiving yours of Jan. <hi rend="underline">1836</hi>!.— Nine months’ letters are wandering over the wide ocean, which we shall not receive till some time after reaching England; But if you knew the glowing unspeakable delight, which I felt at being certain that my Father &amp; all of you were well, only four months ago, you would not grudge, the labor lost in keeping up the regular series of letters.—&amp; it has only happened by such order that I have received this last letter.—</p>
<p>When I wrote from Mauritius, I begged, that the Plymouth letter might contain a short abstract of the last 18 months; now it need only go back as far as January. Pray do not disappoint me this; for otherwise I shall be uncomfortable in my journey instead of enjoying, the sight of the most glorious &amp; the most beautiful of countries. I believe I have at home, a leathern Portmanteau, great coat, &amp; cloth leggings: if so, will you have them sent, by the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of September directed to “Lieut. Sulivan, to the care of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Elliot Royal Hotel, Devonport.—(to be kept till <hi rend="underline">H.M.S.</hi> Beagle arrives)”.— We go from hence to St Helena; between which place &amp; England, our stages are not yet determined.—</p>
<p>The Beagle is now lying at Simons Bay, more than 20 miles from Cape town, where I now am— This 〈is〉 a pretty &amp; singular town; it lies at the foot of an enormous wall, (the Table mountain), which reaches to the clouds, &amp; makes a most imposing barrier.— Cape town is a great inn, on the great highway to the east; an extraordinary number of houses are occupied as boarding houses, in one of which I am now settled: the first day I got amongst a set of Nabobs, who certainly, poor fellows, all together could not have produced a Liver as good as the hero in Beppo.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> They were heavy prosers. I was quite bewildered with Cawnpoor &amp; so many “poors,” &amp; with rushing from Calcutta to Bombay, backwards &amp; forwards.— in despair—I effected a most precipitate retreat; &amp; deliver me in future from the Nabobs.—</p>
<p>Tomorrow morning I am going to call with Capt. F.R. on the Sir J. Herschel. I have already seen the house which he has purchased; it is six miles from the town &amp; in a most retired charming situation. I have heard so much about his eccentric but very aimiable manners, that I have a high curiosity to see the great Man.—</p>
<p>The day after tomorrow, I hope to set out on a short ride of 3 or 4 days, to get a few glimpses of African landscape, or rather I should say, African deserts.— Having seen so much of that sort of country in Patagonia Chili &amp; Peru, I feel myself to a certain degree a connoiseur in a desert, &amp; am very anxious to see these. Every country has its peculiar character; &amp; every country is well worth seeing. But oh the country of countries; the nice undulating green fields &amp; shady lanes. Oh if you young ladies have been cutting down many of the trees (&amp; I shall recollect every one), I never will forgive you.—</p>
<p>I am quite delighted at hearing Erasmus is turned house holder; I hope I shall be able to get lodgings at no great distance, &amp; then London will be a very pleasant place. I often however think Cambridge would be better, I can not make myself cockney enough to give up thoughts of a quiet walks on an Autumnal morning, in the real country.—</p>
<p>I have been a good deal horrified by a sentence in your letter where you talk of “the little books with the extracts from your letters”. I can only suppose they refer to a few geological details. But I have always written to Henslow in the same careless manner as to you; &amp; to print what has been written without care &amp; accuracy, is indeed playing with edge tools.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But as the Spaniard says, “No hay remedio”.—</p>
<p>Farewell for the present &amp; God bless you all.— I have a strong suspicion that my Father will hear of me again before the time of sailing, which will happen in 10 days time.— Give my love to the young Miss Parker; for I hope I have a little niece, instead of a fifth nephew. My dear Catherine | Your affectionate Brother. C. D.</p>
<p>N.B. I find I am forced, after all to draw a Bill of 30£ at once.—it is not that I am at all sure I shall want the money here, but if on my return from the country my funds fail, I shall not at the moment not know what to do.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.8 dozen] ‘n’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘y’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">5.4 myself] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘much’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">5.7 young] ‘g’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘d’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">5.7 down] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">6.4 of a] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">8.3 for] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">9.3 not know] ‘not’ <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi>: 1.11 ‘knew’; 2.7 ‘directed to’; 3.3 ‘wall’; 5.6 ‘fields’; 5.7 ‘trees’; 6.4 ‘on’; 8.1 ‘suspicion’; 8.2 ‘time’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Nabob was a term applied to persons who returned from overseas, usually India, having acquired great wealth. CD refers to Beppo, the eponymous hero of Lord Byron’s satirical poem (1818).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Henslow had entered the following caveat in his prefatory remarks to the Cambridge Philosophical Society pamphlet of extracts: ‘The opinions here expressed must be viewed in no other light than as the first thoughts which occur to a traveller respecting what he sees, before he has had time to collate his Notes, and examine his Collections, with the attention necessary for scientific accuracy.’</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>