<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2855">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   3 July [1860]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3532</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2855 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2855.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2855.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="endorsement" subtype="letter">[1860]</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">10pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 178</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 27;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 1: 314</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 273</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Archives of the Gray Herbarium, Harvard University (41)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>41</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Sudbrook Park Down letterhead</placeName>
                <date when="1860-07-03">3 July [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> has "stirred up the mud with a vengeance"; AG and three or four others have saved CD from annihilation and are responsible for the attention now given to the subject. Reports events at Oxford BAAS meeting.</p> 
            <p>New evidence supports AG’s view of a warm post-glacial period.</p>
            <p>Discusses his recent orchid observations.</p>
            <p>Poses AG a question on design in nature.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchid</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">post-glacial warm period</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent [Sudbrook Park]</placeName>
                    <date>July 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My dear Gray</p>
<p>I received the mathematical papers,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> for which many thanks, but have not yet had time to try to understand them: Your letter of June 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> has been forwarded to me here (for I am at Water-Cure).<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have had an unhappy household of late: my eldest girl has had low fever, 9 weeks in bed, but at last we have moved her: &amp; my health quite broke down. We shall soon have to take her to sea-side &amp; I want a considerable change; for from anxiety &amp; consequent ill-health have done hardly anything for last six weeks.—   I am very sorry to hear how extremely hard you are pressed with work. It is a pity that you should spend more time over Reviews of my Book:<ref target="#foot.f3"/> you have done an immensity &amp; been of incalculable service. I feel very grateful; though I know well that this is not a personal affair: you wish that the subject sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be fairly treated &amp; discussed. Nevertheless I cannot help feeling deeply obliged to you.—   I can now very plainly see from many late Reviews, that I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have been fairly <hi rend="underline">annihilated</hi>, had it not been for 4 or 5 men, including yourself. The <hi rend="underline">early</hi> favourable reviews were highly important in preventing the subject from being “burked.”—</p>
<p>Yesterday I had letter from Hooker at B. Assoc<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. at Oxford;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; he tells me that there was one day a savage fight on my Book between Owen &amp; Huxley; &amp; subsequently a discussion of utmost warmth of 4 hours duration(!) on a paper by Draper of U. States on some subject,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> in which somehow (I know not how) my book became subject: Bishop of Oxford, one of most eloquent men in England, ridiculed me at great length &amp; with much spirit; &amp; Hooker answered him, I imagine, with wonderful spirit &amp; success.—</p>
<p>Owen will not prove right, when he said that the whole <hi rend="underline">subject</hi> would be forgotten in 10 years.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> My book has stirred up the mud with a vengeance; &amp; it will be a blessing to me if all my friends do not get to hate me. But I look at it as certain, if I had not stirred up the mud some one else would very soon; so that the sooner the battle is fought the sooner it will be settled,— not that the subject will be settled in our lives’ times. It will be an immense gain, if the question becomes a fairly open one; so that each man may try his new facts on it pro &amp; contra.—</p>
<p>Very many thanks about N.Y. Times;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I daresay you will be disappointed with the Article; &amp; I cannot for the life of me tell what it is that struck Lyell &amp; me on it—   I hope I may find it at home when I return there in 3 or 4 days.—   I will order the two numbers of the Atlantic when I know which months contain your Articles;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> as I shall be very anxious to see them.</p>
<p>I have just reread your letter: in truth I am myself quite conscious that my mind is in simple muddle about “designed laws” &amp; “undesigned consequences”.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Does not Kant say that there are several subjects on which directly opposite conclusions can be proved true?!<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I forgot to say that in Fraser’s Magazine for July, there is strong article by our great man W. Hopkins. It is written with very fair spirit &amp; with not more of the arrogance of a mathematician, than might have been expected. I have remonstrated with him for so coolly saying that I base my views on what I rank as great difficulties.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Anyone by taking these difficulties alone can make a most strong case against me. I could myself write a more damning Review than has as yet appeared! On question of Hybridity he passes over the insensibly fine gradation from utter sterility to complete fertility—,—the fertility (W. Herbert) of some hybrids,—&amp; the sterility of the vars. of Verbascum (Gärtner) &amp; of the vars. of Tobacco (Kölreuter), which latter facts you, by the way, never notice.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Your letters are great pleasure to me, but <hi rend="doubleUnderline">pray</hi> do not write whilst so overworked.—</p>
<p>I have this minute had letter from Lyell; who is just starting for continent; on his return he is going to investigate reported cases of Hippopotamus <hi rend="underline">subsequent</hi> to Glacial epoch: he finds Falconer &amp; Prestwich now believe in this remarkable fact; if so there has probably been in Europe a period subsequent to Glacial warmer.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Do you remember my saying that I hoped I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be proved wrong to punish me for disbelieving in you; &amp; it seems that my punishment is at hand!—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Not being able lately to work I have amused myself about Orchids. I have been struck with amazement at beauty of contrivances with respect to fertilisation by insects. The insects led me to find that two horns (I subsequently dissected out pollen-tube) in Gymnadenia conopsea are the stigmas &amp; you never saw anything so pretty as the contrivances are.</p>
<p>Do you know Hookers paper in Phil. Transact on Listera;<ref target="#foot.f15"/> he misapprehended meaning of his facts. I find the rostellum so delicate that the explosion takes place by touch of human-hair, &amp; the fluid sets hard in under two seconds. It was really beautiful to see a little Sphex licking the labellum, &amp; as soon as its head touched the rostellum the explosion took-place, &amp; the insect crawled out with the 2 pollen-masses cemented to its forehead, ready to impregnate next flower into which it crawled.</p>
<p>One word more on “designed laws” &amp; “undesigned results”. I see a bird which I want for food, take my gun &amp; kill it, I do this <hi rend="underline">designedly</hi>.—   An innocent &amp; good man stands under tree &amp; is killed by flash of lightning. Do you believe (&amp; I really sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> like to hear) that God <hi rend="underline">designedly</hi> killed this man? Many or most persons do believe this; I can’t &amp; don’t.—   If you believe so, do you believe that when a swallow snaps up a gnat that God designed that that particular swallow sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. snap up that particular gnat at that particular instant? I believe that the man &amp; the gnat are in same predicament.— If the death of neither man or gnat are designed, I see no good reason to believe that their <hi rend="underline">first</hi> birth or production sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be necessarily designed. Yet, as I said before, I cannot persuade myself that electricity acts, that the tree grows, that man aspires to loftiest conceptions all from blind, brute force.</p>
<p>Your <hi rend="underline">muddled</hi> &amp; affectionate friend | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 try to] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.11 Nevertheless] ‘l’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.2 a savage] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.2 on my Book] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.4 my] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘I’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.2 on] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘in’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">6.1 strong] <hi rend="italic">below del</hi> ‘strong’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">7.3 over the] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">8.4 probably] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">9.3 in] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">9.4 a] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">9.6 into which] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">9.7 crawled] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘into’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Gray had sent CD the June 1860 issue of a New York periodical, the <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Monthly</hi>. It contained an article by the mathematician <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5254.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Chauncey Wright</ref> entitled ‘The economy and symmetry of the honey-bees’ cells’ (Wright 1860). This issue of the <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Monthly</hi> is in DAR 48: 48–61; Wright’s paper was annotated by CD.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Gray’s letter has not been found. CD took the water-cure at Sudbrook Park, Richmond, Surrey, from 28 June to 7 July 1860 (‘Journal’; Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Gray was preparing an essay surveying the reviews of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2825.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 8 June [1860]</ref>). It was published as the last part of his anonymous three-part article in the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic</hi> <hi rend="italic">Monthly</hi> ([Gray] 1860b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2852.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 2 July 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2136.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Draper 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See preceding letter and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had asked Gray to procure a copy of the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, 28 March [1860], which contained a review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2767.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 25 April [1860]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">[Gray] 1860b comprised three articles that were published in the July, August, and October issues of the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>. Annotated copies of the articles are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In the third of his articles, Gray addressed this point ([Gray] 1860b, p. 414), stating that CD used: <quote type="quote"> expressions which seem to imply that the natural forms which surround us, because they have a history or natural sequence, could have been only generally, but not particularly designed,—a view at once superficial and contradictory; whereas his true line should be, that his hypothesis concerns the order and not the cause, the <hi rend="italic">how</hi> and not the <hi rend="italic">why</hi> of the phenomena, and so leaves the question of design just where it was before. </quote> The passage is marked in CD’s copy of the work.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In the <hi rend="italic">Critique of pure reason</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4288.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Kant 1781</ref>), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Immanuel Kant</ref> called certain transcendental ideas ‘antinomies of pure reason’, or pairs of contradictory metaphysical ideas, each of which could be conclusively proved. CD’s knowledge of Kant’s writings was probably drawn from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8326.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Whewell 1840</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3858.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hopkins 1860</ref>. CD’s letter to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hopkins</ref> has not been found, but see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2860.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 5 [July 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD discussed the work of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Herbert</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Friedrich von Gärtner</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2627.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Gottlieb Kölreuter</ref> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 246–50. Their respective investigations into hybridism were also extensively discussed in his ‘big book’ on species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell’s</ref> letter has not been found. He left England on 6 July 1860 for a tour in France, Belgium, and Germany. His purpose was to investigate the flint implements and fossils first discovered by Jacques Boucher de Crèvecoeur de Perthes. Before his departure, Lyell had discussed the possibility of a second post-glacial warm period with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1585.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Falconer</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3854.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Prestwich</ref> (see Wilson ed. 1970, pp. 452–5, 460). The subject had arisen after fossilised bones of the extant African elephant were found in association with those of extinct species in caves near Palermo. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2863.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter from Hugh Falconer, 9 July 1860</ref>, and K. M. Lyell ed. 1881, 2: 334–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2520.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">11 November [1859]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">24 December [1859]</ref>; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2645.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 7 January [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Hooker 1854b.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>