<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7425">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Francis Darwin   [after 21 January 1871]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20314</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7425 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7425.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7425.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete<ref target="#foot.f12"/></note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">** 5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Sotheby’s (dealers) (28 March 1983)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_395.xml">Sotheby’s</repository>
                    <collection>28 Mar 1983</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1871-01-22" notAfter="1882-12-31">[after 21 Jan 1871]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Responds to Mivart’s <hi rend="italic">Genesis of species</hi>. "I complain of his incessently speaking as if I trusted exclusively to natural selection … Mivart speaks in many places as if I entirely ignored the direct action of external conditions". Answers some of Mivart’s particular criticisms. Suggests FD read the letter to Marlborough Robert Pryor, as Pryor will never be able to read it himself.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Genesis of species</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3350">Mivart, St G. J.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Mivart, St G. J. 1871</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#conduct_of_debate">Conduct Of Debate</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>[letter written in response to the attack on him in St. George Mivart’s <hi rend="underline">Genesis of Species</hi>: Darwin confesses himself annoyed that he is accused of being dogmatic through the use of a quotation from <hi rend="underline">Variation under Domestication</hi> (Vol. II, p. 414), which Mivart does not give in its entirety:<ref target="#foot.f2"/> <quote type="quote"> … I complain of his incessantly speaking as if I trusted exclusively to natural selection (see <hi rend="underline">for instance</hi> Genesis p. 67):<ref target="#foot.f3"/> now I maintain that no one has taken such pains as I have to show what use and disuse have actually done …<ref target="#foot.f4"/> </quote></p>
<p rend="left">he then discusses in some detail supposed problems raised by Mivart, which he believes either do not exist, or are answered already in <hi rend="underline">The Origin of Species</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Variation under Domestication</hi>, or are answered in his “new book” (<hi rend="underline">The Descent of Man</hi>), for example the development of whale-bone<ref target="#foot.f5"/> <quote type="quote"> … In an isolated group with the gradations unknown it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be madness to pretend to indicate how any strange structure has been gained. But such cases as swim-bladders &amp; our lungs … &amp; scores of others ought to show anyone that he must be very cautious in saying what transformations are at least possible— Mivart cannot see how the lamina of whale-bone could have been started, but a ducks-beak w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> show how this is possible— The young fishes <hi rend="underline">believed</hi> to be nurtured in the abdominal sack of the marsupial Fishes by excreted mucus, shows how <hi rend="underline">possibly</hi> mammary glands might have been developed.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I indirectly &amp; by chance try to answer some points in my new book … </quote></p>
<p rend="left">he also expresses his astonishment that Mivart should raise the issue of the giraffe’s long neck<ref target="#foot.f7"/> (“ … It is extraordinary that Mivart in speaking of neck of Giraffe sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not have seen that when one of the already largest animals, in a country bearing nutritious leaf-bearing trees, had its neck elongated, it would be absolutely useless &amp; impossible for any other animal to acquire an elongated neck, for it could not reach so high as the already large animal with moderately elongated neck …”) and urges his son to discuss with Pryor the larynx of the kangaroo.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> <quote type="quote"> … At p. 60 Mivart says “I change my whole front.” which is hardly fair: he does not give my whole sentence from Origin 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Edit p. 105<ref target="#foot.f9"/>—nor does he allude to my having always insisted on monstrosities not being preserved, &amp; on importance of unconscious selection which implies selection of slight changes in many individuals … Mivart speaks in many places as if I entirely ignored the direct action of external conditions; &amp; in other places all the cases are taken from Dom. Animals under variation!<ref target="#foot.f10"/> … </quote></p>
<p rend="left">At the end Darwin writes: “But I shall weary Pryor &amp; yourself &amp; I have wearied myself … You must read this to Pryor if you can—he will never be able”.<ref target="#foot.f11"/>]</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7450A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to St G. J. Mivart, 21 January [1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In Mivart 1871a, pp. 23–4, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart</ref> discussed CD’s belief that natural selection worked on very slight variations; he wrote, ‘And again, after mentioning the frequent sudden appearances of domestic varieties, he speaks of “the false belief as to the similarity of natural species in this respect.’” See also Mivart 1871a, p. 102. What CD actually wrote in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 214 was: ‘The frequency of these cases is likely to lead to the false belief that natural species have often originated in the same abrupt manner.’ For Mivart’s accusation of dogmatism, see also the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7453A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to St G. J. Mivart, 23 January [1871]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In Mivart 1871a, p. 67, Mivart wrote, ‘The difficulty asserted applies, however, only to pure Darwinism, which makes use <hi rend="italic">only</hi> of indirect modifications through the survival of the fittest’, and contrasted Darwinism with ‘other theories’ that admitted the ‘<hi rend="italic">direct</hi> action of conditions upon animals and plants’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 293–318 (Laws of variation— use and disuse, etc.).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In Mivart 1871a, pp. 40–2, Mivart argued that the baleen sieve in the mouth of the whale could not have evolved by natural selection since an incipient sieve would not perform a useful function, and, moreover, existing animals that apparently had such incipient structures belonged to a different order from whales.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD refers to pipefishes (family Syngnathidae), a group in which the males incubate the eggs. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5912.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi></ref>, Notebook D, 169, CD wrote, ‘Notice the Syngnathus, or Pipe fish the male of which receives eggs in belly.— analogous to men having mammæ’; and in Notebook E, 57, ‘The Pipe-fish is instance of part of the hermaphrodite structure being retained in the male.—’ See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pauly 2004</ref>, pp. 159–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In Mivart 1871a, pp. 24–9, Mivart argued that if natural selection favoured the development of long necks in giraffes, many other ungulates in the same region should have developed long necks; also that the disadvantages of developing a long neck might outweigh the advantages.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In Mivart 1871a, p. 42, Mivart described how the elongation of the young kangaroo’s larynx prevented it from being choked when it suckled. CD referred to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3879.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Marlborough Robert Pryor</ref>, a friend of Francis.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In Mivart 1871a, p. 60, Mivart quoted CD’s comments from <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 104–5, on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Jenkin] 1867</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2552.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Charles Fleeming Jenkin</ref> had argued that in time favourable variations would be swamped as organisms with the variation bred with those without. Mivart quoted CD’s comment, ‘If, for instance, a bird of some kind could procure its food more easily by having its beak curved, and if one were born with its beak strongly curved, and which consequently flourished, nevertheless there would be a very poor chance of this one individual perpetuating its kind to the exclusion of the common form’, but omitted his continuation, ‘but there can hardly be a doubt, judging by what we see taking place under domestication, that this result would follow from the preservation during many generations of a large number of individuals with more or less curved beaks, and from the destruction of a still larger number with the straightest beaks.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Variation.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">According to the sale catalogue, this letter was written for Pryor’s benefit; ‘from the opening of the letter, it appears that he was seeking a refutation of Mivart from Darwin’. Pryor may have been planning to write a review of Mivart 1871a; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7765.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Francis Darwin, 21 May [1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">According to the sale catalogue, the original letter is complete and is five pages long.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>