<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13111">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Gaston de Saporta<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 April 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10616</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13111 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13111.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13111.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 38</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 38</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4181.xml">Saporta, L. C. J. G. de</persName>
                <placeName>Aix</placeName>
                <date when="1881-04-10">10 Apr 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends GdeS and A. F. Marion, <hi rend="italic">L’évolution du règne végétal. Les cryptogames</hi> [1881].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">L’Evolution du regne vegetal. Les cryptogames</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Marion, A. F. 1881</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-05" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-27" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-12-02" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00171_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00171_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="38:1r" xml:id="i171">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00171.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00171_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00171.dzi" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="38:1v" xml:id="i172">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00172.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00172_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00172.dzi" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="38:2r" xml:id="i173">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00173.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00173_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00173.dzi" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="38:2v" xml:id="i174">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00174.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00174_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00177-000-00174.dzi" width="3216px" height="5268px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aix (B. du Rh.)</placeName>
                    <date>le 10 Avril 81</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur et très honoré Confrère,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Nous avons eu soin, M. le professeur Marion et moi, de vous faire adresser par l’éditeur Germer–Baillière à Paris, un exemplaire de l’ouvrage que nous venons de publier sous le nom de <hi rend="underline">l’Evolution du règne végétal Les Cryptogames</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> C’est la première fois que l’on essaye en France et aussi ailleurs d’appliquer d’une manière rationnelle les principes que vous avez fondés à l’étude de la marche évolutive des végétaux—nous ne cherchons pas dans notre livre à prouver l’évolution du règne végétal, mais plutôt à exposer, le principe de l’évolution une fois admis, au moyen de quels procédés et par quelle filière d’organes le monde des plantes a marché du simple au composé, comment il a passé de la structure unicellulaire qu’il présentait à l’origine aux types les plus élevés et les plus complexes.</p>
                    <p>Nous avons voulu avant tout ne pas nous écarter des idées fondamentales posées par vous et qui ont été bien souvent méconnues ou appliquées à tort par les partisans aussi bien que par les adversaires de la doctrine transformiste.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>C’est à vous, très cher maître, dont nous nous proclamons les disciples, dans notre préface, à juger si nous avons compris et développé votre manière de voir, en interprétant avec justesse le sens des phénomènes de transformation organique dans les végétaux vivants ou fossiles nous ont gardé les vestiges.—</p>
                    <p>Votre approbation aurait pour nous un prix d’autant plus grand que nous avons divisé notre oeuvre en deux parties, la deuxième aura pour objet <hi rend="underline">les Phanérogames</hi> et nous travaillons en ce moment même à la mener à bonne fin.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>J’espère donc que vous avez notre volume entre les mains et que vous l’avez reçu exactement. S’il en était autrement veuillez me le faire savoir et je m’empresserai de réparer l’erreur en vous faisant parvenir cet ouvrage qui n’est pas bien long mais qui renferme un tableau abrégé des différents stades auxquels sont successivement arrivés les Cryptogames, à partir des inférieurs et des aquatiques, que nous nommons <hi rend="underline">protophytes</hi>, parceque nous pensons que les végétaux ne sont <hi rend="underline">devenues terrestre</hi> que par adaptation et que les plantes primitives ont du toutes être des Algues ou du moins être <hi rend="underline">assimilables aux algues</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je suis heureux, Monsieur et honoré confrère, de cette occasion de rendre témoinage de la fécondité de la doctrine fondée par vous et en vous présentant mes meilleurs souhaits et ceux de mon collaborateur le professeur Marion. je vous renouvelle l’expression de mon respectueux et sincère dévouement | M<hi rend="superscript">is</hi> de Saporta</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aix (B. du Rh.)</placeName>
                    <date>10 April 81</date>
                    <salute>Sir and highly honoured Colleague,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>We have taken care, Professor Marion and I, to arrange to send you through the publisher Germer-Baillière in Paris, a copy of the work which we have just published under the title <hi rend="underline">l’Evolution du règne végétal Les Cryptogames</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is the first time that anyone in France and also elsewhere has attempted to apply in a rational way the principles that you have established to the study of the evolutionary progression of plants—we do not seek in our book to prove the evolution of the plant kingdom, but rather to demonstrate, the principle of evolution having been accepted, by means of what processes and what lineage of organs the world of plants has advanced from simple to complex, how it has passed from the unicellular structure that it exhibited at the beginning to the highest and most complex types.</p>
<p>Above all we have wished not to deviate from the fundamental ideas posed by you and which have so often been misunderstood or applied incorrectly by supporters as well as opponents of the transformist doctrine.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>It is for you, very dear Master, whose disciples we proclaim ourselves, in our preface, to judge whether we have understood and developed your way of seeing, in interpreting accurately the direction of phenomena of organic transformation in living plants or fossils which have preserved traces for us.</p>
                    <p>Your approval would be such a great prize for us that we have divided our work into two parts, the second will have as its subject <hi rend="underline">the Phanerogams</hi> and we are working at this moment to bring it to a satisfactory conclusion.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>So I hope that you have our volume in your hands and that you have received it satisfactorily. If it was otherwise please let me know and I will hasten to correct the error by sending you this work, which is not very long but which includes a summary table of the different stages which the Cryptogams have successively reached, starting from lower ones and aquatic ones, which we call <hi rend="underline">protophytes</hi>, because we think that plants have only <hi rend="underline">become terrestrial</hi> by adaptation and that primitive plants must have all been Algaes or at least to have been <hi rend="underline">comparable to algaes</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I am happy, Sir and honoured colleague, to have this opportunity to present this token of the fruitfulness of the doctrine created by you and in offering you my best wishes and those of my colleague Professor Marion I renew the expression of my respectful and sincere devotion | Marquis de Saporta</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Saporta and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3162.xml">Antoine Fortuné Marion</ref> sent a copy of their work on cryptogams (non-flowering plants); CD’s copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11229.xml">Saporta and Marion 1881</ref> is in the Darwin Library–CUL. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the preface to their work, Saporta and Marion affirmed their belief in Darwinian evolution by natural selection (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11229.xml">Saporta and Marion 1881</ref>, pp. vii–xii).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The companion work, <hi rend="italic">L’évolution du règne végétal. Les phanérogames</hi> (Evolution of the plant kingdom. Phanerogams; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10381.xml">Saporta and Marion 1885</ref>) was published in 1885.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For the table, see Saporta and Marion 1885, p. 56. Included within the category of protophytes were lichens and fungi, as well as algae, but all the higher forms of cryptogams were shown as having been derived from algae. The table also indicated that, with the appearance of gymnosperms, there was a corresponding decline in cryptogams.</note>            
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>