<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12264">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   20 October 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5465</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12264 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12264.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12264.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B41–2</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B41–B42</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-10-20">20 Oct 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends corrections. Printing of German edition has not yet begun.</p>
            <p>Charles Reinwald wishes to print only CD’s sketch. French hostility to Germans the reason.</p> 
<p>Gustav Jäger and Robert Caspary no longer on title-page of <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Kosmos</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_852">Caspary, J. X. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2514">Jäger, Gustav</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3970">Reinwald, C.-F.</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-10-12" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2018-02-28" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-13" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2018-09-14" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-09-14" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2018-09-14" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
    <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00200_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00200_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
        <surface n="B:41r" xml:id="i200">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00200.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00200_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00200.dzi" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:41v" xml:id="i201">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00201.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00201_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00201.dzi" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:42r" xml:id="i202">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00202.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00202_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00202.dzi" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:42v" xml:id="i203">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00203.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00203_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00203.dzi" width="3681px" height="6237px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 20 October 1879.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Mit bestem Danke sende ich Ihnen hierbei unter Kreuzband die Correc〈tionen〉 zurück.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Von Fehlern habe ich nur noch bemerkt</p>
<p>p. 138 l. 8 offsprings for offspring</p>
                    <p>p. 170. l. 12 biogenetical for biological.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Der Letztere ist wahrscheinlich ein Schreibfehler im Manuscript; vielleicht lässt er sich noch unter den Erratis am Schlusse anführen.</p>
                    <p>Die deutsche Ausgabe ist im Drucke noch nicht begonnen obwohl der Verleger schon lange im Besitze des Manuscriptes ist, ich weiss nicht, woran die Verzögerung liegt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>M. Reinwald will, wie ich höre, nur Ihre biographische Skizze uebersetzen lassen, wobei aber wahrscheinlich nur ein Missverständniss unterliegt.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Derselbe hatte nämlich an meinen Verleg〈er〉 geschrieben, und dieser hatte, ohne dass zwischen uns die Sache besprochen worden war, in meinem Namen ein Honorar von 60 Mark pro Bogen verlangt. Obwohl das eigentlich keine hohe Summe ist, und es sich im Ganzen um eine Zahlung von 100 M. an mich handeln würde, hat M. Reinwald dies für exorbitant erklärt, und die Absicht ausgedrückt, er werde meinen Theil nicht mitabdrücken. Ich theile Ihnen diese Details nur mit, damit Sie nicht von Paris her in den Glauben versetzt werden, ich hätte eine irgendwie namhafte Summe verlangt. Mir liegt so wenig an dem Gelderwerb, dass ich ihm gern das Uebersetzungsrecht umsonst ertheilen würde, allein da es sich hierbei offenbar um eine Anim〈osi〉tät des Franzosen gegen den Deutschen handelt, so werde ich meinerseits nicht nachgeben, und eher das Doppelte verlangen.</p>
<p>Darf ich Sie wohl später, hochverehrter Herr, mit der Bitte belästigen, mir noch über einige in Ihrer Biographie auftretende Personen, von denen unsre biographischen Werke nichts wissen, und die ich Ihnen dann namhaft machen würde, einige ganz kurze Notizen für die Anmerkungen zu geben? Es werden nur 3 oder 4 Namen sein.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>In der Redaction des Kosmos ist eine Veränderung in sofern eingetreten als Prof. Jaeger und Caspari nicht mehr auf dem Titel erscheinen. Prof. Jaeger 〈ha〉tte durch sein lärmendes Auftreten in letzter Zeit eine so lebhafte Antipathie gegen sich hervorgerufen, dass sein Name den Fortbestand unseres Journals ernstlich gefährdet haben würde.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Da beide Herren sich gar nicht um die Redaction gekümmert haben, so ist durch ihren Austritt in technischer Richtung keine Veränderung entstanden, und wir hoffen sogar, dass dadurch das Journal nur gewinnen wird.</p>
<p>Mit dem herzlichen Wunsche, dass diese Zeilen Sie in erwünschtem Wohlsein antreffen mögen, zeichne ich, hochverehrter Herr | Ihr aufrichtig ergebener | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>20 October 1879.</date>
                    <salute>Most esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>With my best thanks I herewith return under wrapper the corrections.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Regarding errors I noticed only</p>
<p>p. 138 l. 8 offsprings for offspring</p>
<p>p. 170. l. 12 biogenetical for biological.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
<p>The latter probably is a misspelling in the manuscript; perhaps it is not too late for it to be listed among the errata at the end.</p>
<p>The German edition has not yet gone to print, although the publisher has had the manuscript for quite a while, I do not know the reason for the delay.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>I hear M. Reinwald will arrange for just your biographical sketch to be translated, but this is in all likelihood merely a misunderstanding.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> You see, he approached my publisher who, without the matter being discussed between us, demanded in my name royalties of 60 marks per sheet. While this is in itself not a large sum and would mean paying me 100 marks in total, M. Reinwald declared it excessive and expressed the intention not to print my contribution. I am informing you of these details merely so you will not be left with the impression from Paris that I had in any manner demanded the sum in question. I have so little interest in earning money that I would gladly give him the rights to the translation free of charge; however, as this is obviously a matter of the animosity of a Frenchman against a German, I for my part will not give in, but rather demand twice as much.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps I may trouble you, esteemed Sir, later on with the request to supply very brief notes for endnotes regarding a number of persons who come up in your biography and about whom our biographical works know nothing, and whom I would then identify? This would not be more than 3 or 4 names.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>In the editorial department of Kosmos a change has occurred insofar as Prof. Jaeger and Caspari no longer appear on the title-page. Prof. Jaeger’s clamorous behaviour in recent times created such heated antipathy towards him that his name would seriously have endangered the continued existence of the journal.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Since neither of these men bothered at all with the running of the journal, their departure has not caused any practical changes, and we even hope that the journal will only profit from it.</p>
<p>With the cordial wish that these lines will find you in a desirable state of health, I remain, most esteemed Sir | Yours sincerely devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
             
            
        </div>     
             
             
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Krause had evidently seen corrected proofs of the translation of his part of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> (see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12243.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 2 October 1879)</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Both these corrections were made in the printed book.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The German version of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> was published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_61.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Alberts</ref> of the publishing company Ernst Günther in April 1880 (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12583.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 19 April 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3970.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles-Ferdinand Reinwald</ref> published French translations of CD’s works; however, no French translation of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi> was published. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11978.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Krause, 5 [May] 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">For the list of names, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12316.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 14 November 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Jäger</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_851.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto Caspari</ref>. Jäger may have offended his co-editors by his efforts, from 1878 onwards, to publicise his sanitary woollen system (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9740.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Jaeger 1886</ref>), based on his theory that the odours of the human body had physical and psychological effects (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9743.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Jaeger 1880</ref>, a collection of reprints of essays originally published from 1876 onwards in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> and other periodicals). </note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>