<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1614">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Edward Hewitt   18 December 1857</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17618</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1614 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1614.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1614.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 166: 196</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 196</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2270.xml">Hewitt, Edward</persName>
                <placeName>Sparkbrook</placeName>
                <date when="1857-12-18">18 Dec 1857</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Hybrid varieties of pheasant and common fowl. Reply to CD queries.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fowl, common</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pheasant</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Eden Cottage, Spark Brook, | n<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Birm<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>.</placeName>
                    <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 18/57.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I am really sorry your very courteous letter has been so long without reply, but an <hi rend="underline">unusually severe</hi> personal illness, from family bereavement, was the only cause.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Thank God, I am now better!<anchor xml:id="ann.a2" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>As to Hybrids, the product of intermixture between the different varieties of Pheasants and domestic fowls, for years, and years, I admit it was alike my “hobby” and “my folly”. At one time I had 12 pairs of birds thus mated in my own possession, including attempts to cross the common English Pheasant, with the Chinese Silver Pencilled;—the English with the Chinese Golden, and also each variety of these Pheasants, with the Common Fowl. I obtained product from each “cross” in the Pheasants, inter se, but could never get even one solitary chick from either variety of <hi rend="underline">Chinese</hi> Pheasants and a fowl, though frequently in the case of the English bird. This appeared to me <hi rend="underline">very remarkable</hi> at the time, <anchor xml:id="ann.a3" type="annotationStart"/>as copulation was <hi rend="underline">quite</hi> as frequent in the one case as the other.<anchor xml:id="ann.a4" type="annotationEnd"/> <ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>In <hi rend="doubleUnderline">all</hi> these trials I admit the male bird was the Pheasant, were I to “try again”, I should reverse the sexes <hi rend="underline">also</hi>;—(why?) this year a friend of mine had a common English Pheasant, the survivor of a pair reared tamely, the cock having been lost by a mischance. <anchor xml:id="ann.a5" type="annotationStart"/>The owner begged the loan of a cock Silver Sebright Bantam—a beautiful bird, but <hi rend="underline">a notoriously bad</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">breeder</hi> <hi rend="underline">with his</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">own</hi> <hi rend="underline">hens</hi> —yet strange to say, they reared an Hybrid from him, and the hen Pheasant.<anchor xml:id="ann.a6" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>What is most curious, this offspring has both <hi rend="doubleUnderline">wattles</hi> <hi rend="underline">and</hi> a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">rosey</hi> -comb!!—not the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">slightest</hi> vestige of which, did I ever see before in any <hi rend="underline">Hybrid</hi>. <anchor xml:id="ann.a7" type="annotationStart"/>The formation of the nostrils is (as <hi rend="underline">always</hi> hitherto the case,) similar to the mother-pheasant’s,<anchor xml:id="ann.a8" type="annotationEnd"/> but to prove how strangely Nature confutes us, if we force her from her accustomed habits, this bird is not even so large as the Sebright. The plumage will be eventually quite as beautiful as eccentric, closely approximating that of a Chinese Silver <hi rend="underline">cock</hi> Pheasant, but the ground (particularly on the scapular feathers,) will show a clear (tho’ slight) guilding.</p>
<p>The above is decidedly the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">only</hi> instance <hi rend="underline">I ever knew</hi> of a male fowl, breeding with a hen Pheasant, <hi rend="underline">of any variety whatever</hi>. I purpose (if all goes on smoothly,) to write full particulars of this “curiosity,” for the general benefit of poultry friends, after its adult plumage is fully complete.</p>
<p>Hybrids are commonly very difficult “to tell” (as to the sex,) until <hi rend="underline">pretty well adult</hi>, but commonly, the superiority of size, where several are in rearing from the same nest, will be conclusive;<anchor xml:id="ann.a10" type="annotationEnd"/> I myself do not know any other test, whilst yet immature.</p>
<p>In reply to your remaining query, I have opened hundreds of eggs, containing the partially formed embryo of a Hybrid.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I once possessed a cock (english) pheasant, “netted” at “barley-time”, that became quite tame, and almost every egg laid to him was fructified, yet only very few <hi rend="underline">hatched</hi> comparatively. judging from appearances, they had progressed to the sixth or seventh day of incubation, but in only one instance, every egg (of eleven) hatched, although the foster-mother (a Game Hen) actually eat up in toto one of her chicks, (that showed a slight disposition to hemorrhage) even before it was well out of the shell; yet with that fatality <hi rend="underline">peculiar</hi> (<hi rend="underline">I</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">do</hi> believe) to <hi rend="underline">all</hi> “pets”, not one of the ten remaining ones came to maturity;—rats, cats, and (at last) some timber “blowing down”, all lending a helping hand.</p>
<p>In all instances within my own knowledge of <anchor xml:id="ann.a9" type="annotationStart"/>Hybrids, for the male Ph<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. and common Hen fowl (of any variety) the produce has been immensely in advance as to size, of <hi rend="underline">either</hi> parent; it is therefore worth reflection, that (as before narrated) the sexes opposed of the parents, a pigmy is the order of the day. There must be some occult cause for this, however indescribable, and such a result, I for one, <hi rend="underline">was not in anyway</hi> prepared for. Again there appears no obvious reason, why a Chinese Ph<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>., should <hi rend="underline">not</hi> breed with a fowl, when our common one <hi rend="underline">will</hi>; they copulate, yet <hi rend="underline">not</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">one</hi> egg fructifies. It proves a limit is placed to <hi rend="underline">our</hi> caprices, for they will very rarely breed a “cross” (if ever) at liberty.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> however carefully devised, in the animal world, otherwise most probably it would be pre-occupied by monsters, to the ruin and exclusion, of all others.</p>
<p>I am indeed, on reperusal, afraid you will think my letter tedious and far too prolix, it is also anything but carefully indited, still it expresses <hi rend="underline">my</hi> convictions, and with every good wish, it is freely rendered.</p>
<p><anchor xml:id="ann.a1" type="annotationStart"/>I am, My dear Sir, | Yours very faithfully, | Edward Hewitt.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note target="#ann.a1" targetEnd="#ann.a2"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a3" targetEnd="#ann.a4"><hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a5" targetEnd="#ann.a6"><hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note> 4.1 What … comb!!] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi> </note>
                <note target="#ann.a7" targetEnd="#ann.a8"><hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note target="#ann.a9" targetEnd="#ann.a10"><hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note> 7.1 In reply … eggs,] <hi rend="italic">double scored brown crayon</hi> </note>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Hewitt had suffered the sudden death of his only sister in February 1857, leaving him with an invalid mother to care for (<hi rend="italic">Cottage Gardener</hi> 17 (1856–7): 384–6). CD probably wrote to Hewitt soon after learning from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Bernhard Tegetmeier</ref> that Hewitt had made a number of crosses between pheasants and fowl (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 6 February [1857]</ref>). Tegetmeier drew upon Hewitt’s experiences in the relevant section of his <hi rend="italic">Poultry book</hi> (Tegetmeier ed. 1856–7, pp. 165–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD reported this information in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 435 n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD cited Hewitt on this point in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 422.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The passage ‘for they … liberty.’ was added at the bottom of the letter with a cross to indicate its position in the main text.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>