<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5034">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Benjamin Dann Walsh   13 March 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8748</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5034 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5034.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5034.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Walsten (1974): 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_133.xml">Field Museum</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4944.xml">Walsh, B. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Rock Island, Ill.</placeName>
                <date when="1866-03-13">13 Mar 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>On the "bullae" as constant, regular generic characters in Hymenoptera. Disagrees with Louis Jurine ["Observations sur les ailes des hyménoptères", <hi rend="italic">Mem. Accad. Sci. Torino</hi> 24 (1820): 177–214].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Hymenoptera</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">hymenopteres</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Mem. Accad. Sci. Torino</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Jurine, Louis 1820</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rock Island. Illinois. U.S.</placeName>
                    <date>March 13. 1866</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas. Darwin Esq.</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I send you herewith a copy of a recent Paper for yourself, &amp; another for M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wallace, which I must beg you to forward to him. I do not know &amp; cannot find out his address, or I would not put you to this trouble.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> He was kind enough to send me a copy of his Memoir on the <hi rend="underline">Malayan Papilionidæ</hi>, which I am highly delighted with.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Since my Paper was printed, I have had forwarded to me an extract from Jurine’s “Nouvelle Methode &amp;c” (Tome 1. Introd. p. 19), in which he notices the “bullæ” I have written about as occurring in certain Aculeate Hymenoptera, e.g. <hi rend="underline">Andrena</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Nomada</hi> among the Bees, though he says Hymenoptera “des deux premièrs ordres n’ont pas de bulles aux ailes, ou s’ils en ont, ce n’est qu’un petit nombre, et elles y sont très-irregulièrement placées.”<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Whereas, after examining hundreds of Eureopean species, belonging to scores of different genera of <hi rend="underline">Ichneumonidæ</hi>, besides the N.A. genera already examined, I find that the “bullæ” in any given genus are just as constant &amp; regular as any other generic character, &amp; that the species on the two sides of the Atlantic follow precisely the same laws in this respect.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Jurine says he was at first inclined to suppose that the ‘bullæ” were apertures through which the air contained in the veins (which he considered as air-tubes) penetrated the membrane of the wing; but that, on reflecting that a very great number of Hymenoptera had no “bullæ” at all, he came to the conclusion that they were caused by the foldings of the wing (les plis de l’aile.)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> But in the first place the wings of Hymenoptera are not folded, in the sense in which the wings of Coleoptera may be said to be folded, &amp; in the second place it is impossible to fold up the wing of an <hi rend="underline">Ichneumon</hi>, so as to make a fold wherever there is a “bullæ”, without making additional folds in certain veins which never have any bullæ.</p>
<p>As I find these singular “bullæ” are far more general in Hymenoptera than I had supposed, &amp; wherever they appear are homologous, I partly incline now to believe that they must be connected in some unknown manner with the circulatory system.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> At all events in certain genera, e.g. <hi rend="underline">Metopius</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Xylonomus</hi>, very fine fibres seem to issue cross-wise from them into the membrane of the wing. But even if we make this assumption, I do not see that this explains the colorational phenomena, i.e. that in a black wing the bullæ &amp; the adjacent membrane should be uniformly white or whitish. It is a very puzzling subject certainly. Singularly enough, Jurine has entirely overlooked what I have called the spots F &amp; G, which are just as plain &amp; constant in the Bee as in the Ichneumon.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Yours very truly | Benj. D. Walsh</p>
<p>P.S. Do you know anything of a Quaker gentleman, “M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wilson Armistead, Virginia House, Leeds?” He sent me a circular &amp; a letter, stating that he was about to publish an illustrated Book on the Galls of the whole world &amp; soliciting assistance.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I answered him by Mail last autumn, &amp; afterwards on Oct. 13. 1865 sent him through the Smithsonian Institution a large Box containing specimens of Galls. Since then I have not heard a word from him, which does not strike me as particularly polite. But perhaps he is sick or dead. He stated that he was recommended by Prof. Westwood to apply to me.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Left of signature</hi>: ‘Wallace | 9 S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Marks Crescent | Regents Park | N. W’<ref target="#foot.f10"/></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Walsh refers to the second part of his essay ‘On phytophagic varieties and phytophagic species’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walsh 1864–5</ref>). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref> leased a house at 9 St Mark’s Crescent, London, in April 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6492.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raby 2001</ref>, p. 182; see also CD’s annotation).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Walsh refers to Wallace 1864b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle méthode de classer les hyménoptères et les diptères</hi>, by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2622.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Jurine</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jurine 1807</ref>, p. 20). The quotation may be translated as follows: Hymenoptera ‘of the two first orders do not have bullae on their wings, or if they do have them, they are but few in number, and are positioned very irregularly’. Walsh had observed that ‘blister-like spots’ or ‘bullae’ appeared in identical number and pattern on the wings of different species of parasitic wasps in the family Ichneumonidae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walsh 1864–5</ref>, pp. 209–15). Jurine did not class the Ichneumonidae among the two first orders of Hymenoptera, however (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jurine 1807</ref>, p. (1)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Walsh’s further observations on bullae in the Ichneumonidae are reported in Walsh 1866b, pp. 241–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4277.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jurine 1807</ref>, p. 20, and Walsh 1866b, p. 245.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In Walsh 1866b, pp. 246–8, Walsh remarked that the bullae were located along wing-veins, which were blood-conducting tubes, but that their connection with the circulatory system was uncertain.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Walsh identified five bullae (A to E), and two additional minute spots (F and G) on the wings of species of <hi rend="italic">Ichneumon</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8150.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walsh 1864–5</ref>, pp. 209–15, and Walsh 1866b, pp. 241–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Armistead published several papers on gall insects, but his book on the subject was unfinished at the time of his death in 1868 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6763.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Royal Society catalogue of scientific papers</hi></ref>, <hi rend="italic">Entomologist</hi> 4 (1868): 49).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Walsh refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Obadiah Westwood</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See n. 1, above.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>