<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9125">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alfred Moschkau<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   2 [December] 1873<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10112</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9125 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9125.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9125.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 249</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 249</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3421.xml">Moschkau, O. C. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Niederoderwitz (Zittau)</placeName>
                <date when="1873-12-02">2 [Dec] 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses variation and selection in Harz canaries.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">canaries</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Harz</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Nied. Oderwitz,</placeName>
                    <date>d. 2. Nov. 1873.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Hochverehrter Meister!</seg>
                    <salute>Sehr geehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Besten Dank für Ihren freundl. Brief u. die Mittheilung, dass ich meine Aufzeichnungen über die Transmutationslehre doch nicht wagen darf<ref target="#foot.f3"/>—der Henne das Ei—Ihnen zu ubersenden, zumal ich in der Häckel’schen Schöpfungsgeschichte Alles viel besser fand.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Doch eines muss ich Ihnen nennen. Es betrifft die Züchtung der Canarienvögel im Harz, dieser Vogel existirt doch fast gar nicht mehr in seinen ursprünglichen Sein, ja ich glaube die jetzt lebende Art eignet sich garnicht mehr für ein Leben in der freien Natur— dies sind nur Umwandlungserfolge, der Schlag der wilden (im Freien lebenden—unveredelten) Canarienvögel kann sich nimmer vergleichen mit dem der echten Harzer, was doch wohl auf eine im Laufe der Zeit peu à peu gewordene Umänderung der Sangesorgane schliessen lässt. Auch das Gefieder ist ein viel weicheres, mehr wolliges bei den edleren als den Wilden, die in Deutschland rar werden.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Auch hier ist deutlich erkennbar der “Kampf um’s Dasein”. Die milden-melodiösen Schläger züchtet man, sie mehren sich in Menge, die Wilden sucht man der Veredelung theilhaftig zu machen oder überlässt sie ihrem Schicksal— in einer Spanne Zeit verschwinden sie ganz u. spätere Zoologen kennen sie nur vom Hörensagen.</p>
<p>Beweise für die Wahrheit Ihrer ruhmeswürdigen Lehre—wie oben mitgetheilter lassen sich zu Tausenden aufzahlen. Wer, der sich eines gesunden Verstandes rühmt, könnte dagegen sprechen?</p>
<p>Wenn ich schliesslich die Bitte auszusprechen wage, dass Sie eines <hi rend="underline">armen</hi> Geistesverwandten Lernlust durch <hi rend="underline">Gratis</hi> uberlassung eines Exemplars Ihrer epochemachenden Werke “Ueber die Entstehung der Arten” oder “die Abstammung des Menschen” fördern möchten, hoffe ich Sie werden mir dieselbe, sowie die abermalige Belästigung mit einem Briefe verzeihen und mich eines gütigen Bescheides werth halten.</p>
<p>Ew. Wohlgeboren | ergebenster | Alfred Moschkau, Phil. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Pro.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Nied. Oderwitz,</placeName>
                    <date>2. Nov. 1873.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Most respected master!</seg>
                    <salute>Highly honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many thanks for your kind letter and for your advice that I should after all not venture to send you my notes on the Transmutation theory<ref target="#foot.f3"/>— giving eggs to a hen—especially as I found everything expressed much better in Häckel’s Schöpfungsgeschichte.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>But I must tell you one thing. It has to do with the breeding of Canary birds in the Harz; this bird hardly exists any more in its original form, indeed I believe that the present day form is no longer adapted to life in the wild— they are only successful variants; the song of the wild (living in the open—undomesticated) canary birds can not compare any more with that of the true Harz variety, from which a progressive change in the vocal organs over the course of time can surely be inferred. The feathers are also much softer, and more woolly in the domesticated variety than in the wild birds, which are becoming rare in Germany.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Here too the “struggle for existence” is clearly recognisable. Softly melodious warblers are bred, their numbers increase prolifically, one may attempt to improve the wild ones or leave them to their fate— in time they will disappear altogether and future zoologists will only know them from hearsay.</p>
<p>Proofs of the truth of your praiseworthy theory—as that cited above, can be counted in their thousands. How could anyone claiming to be of sound mind oppose it?</p>
<p>If I venture, in closing, to ask you to foster a <hi rend="underline">poor</hi> kindred spirit’s thirst for knowledge by sending me a <hi rend="underline">free</hi> copy of your epoch-making works “On the origin of species” or “The Descent of Man”, I hope you will forgive me for this as well as for bothering you again with a letter, and I hope that you will regard me worthy of a favourable reply.</p>
<p>Yours | most devoted | Alfred Moschkau | Phil. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Pro.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 527–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The month is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9137.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alfred Moschkau, 10 November 1873</ref>. Moschkau evidently wrote ‘November’ in error.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s letter has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9137.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Alfred Moschkau, 10 November 1873</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Haeckel 1868b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The Harz mountains in northern Germany extend between the Elbe and Leine rivers for about sixty miles (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>). The Harz mountain roller canary is a variety of <hi rend="italic">Serinus canaria domesticus</hi>, bred in the upper Harz mountains. Moschkau evidently believed that wild canaries were found in the Harz mountains, but canaries are only found in the wild in the Canary Islands, Madeira, and the Azores. Moschkau may have observed a close relative, the European serin (<hi rend="italic">Serinus serinus</hi>), which is a summer migrant in Germany. CD had discussed variation in domestic canary birds in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 295.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>