<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-330">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Anthony Carlisle   [19 December 1836]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1864A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1985">1985</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-330 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-330.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-330.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="01">1</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The Royal College of Surgeons of England (Minute book of Board of Curators MUS/2/1/4)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_349.xml">RCS London</repository>
                    <idno>Archives</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1836-12-19">[19 Dec 1836]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received" subtype="personGrp">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_829.xml">Carlisle, Anthony</persName>
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4102.xml">Royal College of Surgeons</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>"Read a letter [to AC] of the 19th Instant from Mr Charles Darwin of Christs College, Cambridge stating that understanding from the Conservators that a Series of fossil Bones collected during the voyage of H: M: Surveying Vessel Beagle possesses a peculiar Interest as connected with Specimens already in the Museum of this College that it had always been his intention to present such Bones to some public collection on the condition that Casts thereof should be given to the leading Public Bodies for the sake of making them more generally useful, specifying the British Museum the Geological Society and the Universities of Cambridge and Oxford, and one set for himself: and that under such Conditions he should be most happy to present the entire series to the Museum of this College."</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">conservators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Christ’s College Cambridge, museum</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>[Cambridge]</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>[Read a Letter of the 19th Instant from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles Darwin of Christs College, Cambridge stating that understanding from the Conservators that a Series of fossil Bones collected during the voyage of H:M: Surveying Vessel Beagle possesses a peculiar Interest as connected with Specimens already in the Museum of this College that it had always been his intention to present such Bones to some public collection on the condition that Casts thereof should be given to the leading Public Bodies for the sake of making them more generally useful, specifying the British Museum the Geological Society and the Univer- sities of Cambridge and Oxford, and one set for himself: and that under such Conditions he should be most happy to present the entire series to the Museum of this College.]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The minute continues: <quote type="quote"> ‘And M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Owen stating that such fossil remains (which were found in the Pampas to the Southward of Rio de la Plata) are highly desirable for the Collection more especially the Cranium of a hitherto unknown gigantic rodent Animal and parts of the skeleton of a Gigantic Armadillo which would be a most important addition to the Series of Osteology which already enriches the Museum of this College. Resolved: That this Board recommend to the Council the acceptance of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin’s liberal offer upon the conditions proposed.’ </quote> CD’s specimens remained at the Royal College of Surgeons until it was damaged by bombing in World War II. Specimens that survived were later removed to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref> (Natural History).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>