<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10538">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To A. R. Wallace   17 June 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1792</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10538 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10538.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10538.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS(A)</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS(A)">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 275</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 185;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Marchant (1916) 1: 289;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">The British Library (Add MS 46434)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_43.xml">The British Library</repository>
                    <idno>Add 46434</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1876-06-17">17 June 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Further detailed comments on <hi rend="italic">Geographical distribution</hi>.</p>  
<p>Base treatment [of George Darwin] by Mivart in <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi> [137 (1874): 40–77].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Quarterly Review</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1224">Darwin, G. H.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Mivart, St G. J. 1874</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Wallace, A. R. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham</placeName>
                    <date>June 17. 1876</date>
                    <salute>My dear Wallace</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have now finished the whole of Vol I, with the same interest &amp; admiration as before; and I am convinced that my judgement was right and that it is a memorable book, the basis of all future work on the subject.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have nothing particular to say, but perhaps you would like to hear my impressions on two or three points. Nothing has struck me more than the admirable &amp; convincing manner in which you treat Java.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> To allude to a very trifling point, it is capital about the unadorned head of the Argus-pheasant<ref target="#foot.f3"/>   How plain a thing is, when it is once pointed out! What a wonderful case is that of Celebes: I am glad that you have slightly modified your views with respect to Africa.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> And this leads me to say that I cannot swallow, the so-called continent of Lemuria, i.e. the direct connection of Africa &amp; Ceylon. The facts do not seem to me many and strong enough to justify so immense a change of level. Moreover Mauritius and the other islands appear to me oceanic in character.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> But do not suppose that I place my judgement on this subject on a level with yours. A wonderfully good paper was published about a year ago on India in the Geolog: J,—I <hi rend="underline">think</hi> by Blandford. Ramsay agreed with me that it was one of the best published for a long time. The author shows that India has been a continent with enormous fresh water lakes from the Permian period to the present day. If I remember right he believes in a former connection with S. Africa.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I am sure that I read, some 20 to 30 years ago, in a French Journal an account of teeth of mastodon found in Timor; but the statement may have been an error.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>With respect to what you say about the colonising of N. Zealand, I somewhere have an account of a frog frozen in the ice of a Swiss glacier, and which revived when thawed.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I may add that there is an Indian toad which can resist salt water &amp; haunts the sea side.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Nothing ever astonished me more than the case of the Galaxias; but it does not seem known whether it may not be a migratory fish like the salmon.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> It seems to me that you complicate rather too much the successive colonisations into N. Zealand. I should prefer believing that the Galaxias was a species, like the Emys of the Sevalik Hills, which has long retained the same form.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Your remarks on the insects &amp; flowers of N.Z: have greatly interested me; but aromatic leaves I have always looked at as a protection against their being eaten by insects or other animals; and as insects are there rare such protection would not be much needed.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I have written more than I intended; &amp; I must again say how profoundly your book has interested me.</p>
<p>Now let me turn to a very different subject. I have only just heard of &amp; procured your two articles in the Academy. I thank you most cordially for your generous defence of me against M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mivart.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> In the Origin I did not discuss the derivation of any one species; but that I might not be accused of concealing my opinion I went out of my way &amp; inserted a sentence which seemed to me (&amp; still so seems) to declare plainly my belief. This was quoted in my Descent of Man. Therefore it is very unjust, not to say dishonest, of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mivart to accuse me of base fraudulent concealment.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I care little about myself; but M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mivart in an article in the Q. Review (which I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> was written by him) accused my son George of encouraging profligacy, &amp; this without the least foundation   I can assert this positively as I laid George’s article &amp; the Q. Review, before Hooker, Huxley &amp; others, &amp; all agreed that the accusation was a deliberate falsification.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Huxley wrote to him on the subject &amp; has almost or quite cut him in consequence; &amp; so would Hooker, but he was advised not to do so as Pres. of the Royal Soc.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Well he has gained his object in giving me pain, &amp; good God to think of the flattering almost fawning speeches which he has made to me. I wrote of course to him to say that I would never speak to him again.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I ought, however, to be contented, as he is the one man who has ever, as far as I know, treated me basely. Forgive me for writing at such length &amp; believe me | Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. I am very sorry that you have given up Sexual Selection.— I am not at all shaken &amp; stick to my colours like a true Briton.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> When I think about the unadorned head of the Argus pheasant, I might exclaim, “et tu Brute”!<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.2 June 17. 1876] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.1 in … Journal] <hi rend="italic">interl in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.1 Now … Brute”! 5.3] <hi rend="italic">in CD’s hand</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">4.3 derivation] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘origin’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.4 might not] ‘not’ <hi rend="italic">over del illeg</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.4 went … &amp; 4.5] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">4.11 before] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n8">4.14 has gained] ‘has’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n9">4.14 his object] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘in’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n10">5.1 at all] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD was reading Wallace’s <hi rend="italic">Geographical distribution of animals</hi> (Wallace 1876a; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10531.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 5 June 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 349–60</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In Wallace 1876a, 1: 340, Wallace pointed out that the male argus pheasant’s head, which was unadorned, was completely concealed from the view of a spectator at the front by his ornamented wings; he added that this was a remarkable confirmation of CD’s view that coloured plumes were developed in the male bird for the purpose of display during the breeding season.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 426–38, especially pp. 437–8. Wallace suggested that there had formerly been a land link between Celebes and Asia; previously he had speculated on a former continent in the area of the Indian Ocean linking Celebes with Africa (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8075.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1859</ref>, p. 178). Celebes is now Sulawesi.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 76–7. Lemuria was the name proposed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4251.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Philip Lutley Sclater</ref> for a hypothetical former continent stretching from Madagascar to Ceylon (Sri Lanka) and Sumatra (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9328.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sclater 1864</ref>). Wallace called it a ‘legitimate and highly probable supposition’. Oceanic islands: i.e. those formed without a foundation of continental rock, for instance as a result of volcanic action (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref> s.v. Islands). Mauritius is part of the Mascarene islands group. For CD’s views on Mauritius, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Volcanic islands</hi></ref>, pp. 28–31. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9518.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ramaswamy 2004</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Andrew Crombie Ramsay</ref> was present at the meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref> when <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_484.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Francis Blanford’s</ref> paper was read, and agreed with his suggestion of a junction of Africa, India, and Australia in geological time (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8940.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Blanford 1874</ref>, p. 540). However, no correspondence with CD on the subject has been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In Wallace 1876a, 1: 426, Wallace concluded that the Timorese islands had not acquired their animal life from an actual union with any other large island. Wallace had himself given CD information about <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4226.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Friedrich Adolph Schneider</ref>, who claimed to have found teeth of <hi rend="italic">Mastodon</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Mammut</hi>) in Timor (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3334.xml" resp="#automat">letter from A. R. Wallace, 30 November 1861</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schneider 1863</ref>). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3915.xml" resp="#automat">letter from A. R. Wallace, 14 January [1863]</ref> and n. 6. Schneider’s article was in a Dutch journal and was in Dutch.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 459–62. The account of the frog has not been found. Some species of frog are able to survive freezing, including <hi rend="italic">Rana arvalis</hi>, the moor frog, which is found in Switzerland.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Fejervarya cancrivora</hi> (the Asian brackish frog).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 400–2. In Origin 6th ed., p. 343, CD wrote that <hi rend="italic">Galaxias attenuatus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">G. maculatus</hi>, the inanga) inhabited Tasmania, New Zealand, the Falkland Islands, and mainland South America, and suggested that this indicated dispersal from an Antarctic centre during a former warm period. He added that species of the genus had the power of crossing ‘by some unknown means’ considerable distances of open ocean. Wallace had suggested that fish eggs and amphibians might be transported on icebergs.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Wallace described <hi rend="italic">Emys tecta</hi> as ‘the sole survivor of the strange Siwalik fauna of the Miocene epoch’. <hi rend="italic">Emys tecta</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Pangshura tecta</hi>, the Indian roofed turtle. The Siwalik Hills are in the Punjab region of India, near Saharanpur.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See Wallace 1876a, 1: 462–4. Wallace noted that insects and plants with conspicuous flowers were comparatively scarce in New Zealand, which he took to confirm the theory that conspicuous flowers had developed because they attracted insects that aided in pollination. He added that scented flowers and leaves were also scarce, which suggested that they also served to attract insects.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Wallace had reviewed <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3350.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">St George Jackson Mivart’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Lessons from nature</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mivart 1876</ref>) in the <hi rend="italic">Academy</hi> on 10 and 17 June 1875 (Wallace 1876b). CD’s copy is in DAR 140.1: 6 and 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mivart 1876</ref>, p. 144, Mivart wrote that CD had ‘at first studiously disguised his views as to the bestiality of man’. In the conclusion to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, CD had written, ‘Light will be thrown on the origin of man and his history’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 488). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 1, he wrote: ‘During many years I collected notes on the origin or descent of man, without any intention of publishing on the subject, but rather with the determination not to publish, as I thought that I should thus only add to the prejudices against my views. It seemed to me sufficient to indicate, in the first edition of my “Origin of Species,” that by this work “light would be thrown on the origin of man and his history;” and this implies that man must be included with other organic beings in any general conclusion respecting his manner of appearance on this earth.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">For the controversy over Mivart’s remarks about <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref>, and the involvement of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, Appendix V. Mivart’s anonymous article in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi> was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5508.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Mivart] 1874</ref>; George’s article was ‘Beneficial restrictions to liberty of marriage’ in the <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Review</hi> (G. H. Darwin 1873).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9773.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from T. H. Huxley, 23 December 1874</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9807.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 7 January 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9812.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to St G. J. Mivart, 12 January 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">In the second part of his review (Wallace 1876b), Wallace noted that he did not believe that CD’s theory of sexual selection could account for the bright plumage of male birds. Wallace thought that intensity of colour was correlated with general vigour and sexual excitability, aided by sexual selection insofar as vigour and ardour were attractive to females. CD and Wallace had discussed the subject at length; see especially <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4308.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Shakespeare</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Julius Caesar</hi>, 3.1.85</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>