<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3061">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>   [before 9 February 1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15628</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3061 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3061.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3061.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 38</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 26</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 9 February 1861, p. 122 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Gard. Chron. 1861: 122</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1861-02-08">[before 9 Feb 1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1808.xml">Gardeners’ Chronicle</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses the possible explanation of why fly-orchid plants in a correspondent’s garden had no pollen-masses removed while <hi rend="italic">Orchis maculata</hi> had all of its pollen-masses removed. CD points out that different orchids are fertilised by different insects. The insects needed to fertilise the fly-orchid may not have inhabited the site of the correspondent’s garden.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">fly-orchid</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Orchis maculata</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pollen</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[Down]</placeName>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much obliged to Mr. Marshall, of Ely, for his statement that the 15 plants of Fly Orchis (Ophrys muscifera) which does not grow in his neighbourhood, but which flourished in his garden, had not one of their pollen masses removed.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The Orchis maculata, on the other hand, which likewise does not grow in the neighbourhood, had all its pollen masses removed. Mr. Marshall is not perhaps aware that different insects haunt different Orchids, and are necessary for their fertilisation.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> From the wide difference in shape of the flower of Orchis and Ophrys, I should have anticipated that they would be visited and fertilised by different insects. In Listera, for instance, it is chiefly Ichneumonidæ, and sometimes flies, which by day perform the marriage ceremony. In the case of most Orchids it is nocturnal moths. Orchis pyramidalis, however, is visited by Zygæna, and I have examined one of these day-sphinxes with three pair of pollen-masses firmly attached to its proboscis. There can hardly be a doubt that the Butterfly Orchis is visited by different moths from most of the smaller Orchids; and I have recognised its peculiar pollen masses attached to the sides of the face of certain moths. It is probable that the same kind of moths would visit all the species of true Orchis, which closely resemble each other in structure. Thus the Orchis conopsea, planted in a garden some miles from where any native plant grew, had its pollen masses removed; so this is a parallel case with that of O. maculata given by Mr. Marshall. I have also transplanted the rare Malaxis to a place about two miles from its native bog, and it was immediately visited by some insect, and its pollen-masses were removed. On the other hand, the Epipactis latifolia, growing in my garden and flowering well, had not its pollen-masses removed; though in its own home, several miles distant, the flowers are regularly visited and thus fertilised. We thus see that the seeds of an Orchid might be carried by the wind to some distant place, and there germinate, but that the species would not be perpetuated unless the proper insects inhabited the site. I have now Goodyera repens growing in my garden, and I shall be curious to see next summer whether our southern insects discover or appreciate the nectar of this Highland Orchid.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">C. Darwin</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is given by the publication of the letter in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 9 February 1861. It was headed: ‘<hi rend="italic">Fertilisation of British Orchids by Insect Agency</hi>’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to a letter by William Marshall of Ely published in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> on 20 January 1861 under the heading ‘Fertilisation of British orchids by insect agency’. Marshall was responding to CD’s notice, printed in the issue of 9 June 1860, in which CD requested readers to observe the bee or fly orchis, <hi rend="italic">Ophrys apifera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">O. muscifera</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">O. insectifera</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">insectifera</hi>), to see whether the pollen-masses of the flowers had been removed by insects, ‘for it seems a strange fact that a plant should grow pretty well, as it does in this part of Kent, and yet during several years seldom be fertilised.’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [4–5 June 1860]; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 34).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD identified various insects that pollinated different species of orchids in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 36–8. He mentioned Marshall’s case on page 38. <hi rend="italic">Orchis maculata</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Dactylorhiza maculata</hi>, the heath spotted orchid.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 112–16.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>