<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10757">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   [before 17 January 1877]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7912</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10757 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10757.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10757.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp inc †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 111: B55–8r</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>111: B55–8r</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1877-01-16">[before 17 Jan 1877]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Remarks on the difference between the sexes in <hi rend="italic">Restionaceae</hi> and other subjects – occasioned by reading the introduction [to <hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Restionaceae</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Forms of flowers</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex differences</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-09-14" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2016-09-14" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="left">message as I received it.</p>
<p>A few things occurred to me in reading the Introduction.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> No doubt they have all occurred to you and I merely offer them on the remote chance of their proving useful. The nos: refer to the paragraphs</p>
<p>II. The difference between ♀ &amp; ♂ in some plants is really surprising. In <hi rend="underline">Restiaceæ</hi> which are locally abundant in individuals, species, &amp; genera in Australia and at the Cape of Good Hope the sexual differentiation has so far affected the whole plant that D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Masters and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bentham who have recently studied them—the former as regards Africa the latter as regards Australia—consider it practically impossible to match one ♂ &amp; ♀ of at any rate many species amongst Herbarium specimens<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>There is something curious about the “domestic economy” of Petasites vulgaris. I see you have Sir J. Smith’s English Flora and you will find the account of it in vol. iii pp. 426, 427. The species is if one may so put it both monœcious and diœcious. The two Linnean species <hi rend="underline">Tussilago Petasites</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Tussilago hybrida</hi> are regarded now as the <hi rend="underline">predominantly</hi> male and female forms respectively<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>By the way you have <hi rend="doubleUnderline">two</hi> Thirdly’s<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>iv. There are many hermaphrodite plants which frequently suppress their petals. <hi rend="underline">Ranunculus auricomus</hi> is one. This species is often sterile which I find Masters Journ. of Bot. 1867 p. 159, attributes to a tendency found in other Ranunculaceæ to become diœcious.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>vii. It hardly comes within your plan probably to mention the numerous cases in which flowers hang out ‘flags of distress’ without apparently paying any very heavy price for it.— In many Cruciferæ the external flowers of the corymbs are developed in a way comparable with that in Compositæ and Umbelliferæ. In <hi rend="underline">Iberis</hi> there are certainly the proper proportion of stamens in the enlarged flowers though it is possible they may not be up to much.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width20">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_10757_1.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                    <p>But the most singular arrangement I know is in <hi rend="underline">Mussænda</hi> a genus of <hi rend="underline">Rubiaceæ</hi> where <hi rend="underline">one tooth</hi> of the calyx in a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">few</hi> flowers of an inflorescence is developed into a large leafy expansion<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Something (I am drawing from memory like this)  I am not prepared to say without disturbing herbarium specimens what effect this may have had on the sexual organs</p>
                    <figure type="diagram" rend="blockCentred width25">
                        <graphic url="../images/dcp_lett_10757_2.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
<p>As you mention the singular arrangement in <hi rend="underline">Muscari</hi> one calls also to mind cases like <hi rend="underline">Salvia Horminum</hi> where the upper bracts are enlarged and brightly coloured and the flower suppressed. The same arrangement obtains also in <hi rend="underline">Lavandula</hi> and other Labiates<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very truly | W. T. Thiselton Dyer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 message … it.] <hi rend="italic">del pencil</hi></note>
                <note>2.1 A few … paragraphs 2.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 In … specimens 3.6] ‘Bentham c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> tell me whether rudiments of sexual organs’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 There is … Labiates 9.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.3 The two … respectively 4.5] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 iv. … is one. 6.2] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>7.4 Cruciferæ] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi></note>
                <note>9.2 <hi rend="italic">Salvia Horminum</hi>] ‘&amp; <hi rend="italic">[</hi>Masters<hi rend="italic">]</hi> case of’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>9.2 <hi rend="italic">Salvia</hi> … suppressed. 9.4] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi>; ‘Ballardia is next genus to muscari &amp; Hyanthus’ <hi rend="italic">added ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘p 3 gradation of dioiceous Plant Tussilago’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘[‘Umb’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] Iberis | Mussænda— | Your praise of my book pleases me much, though I fear it is greatly too strong.— [‘My object’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] I am particularly obliged for your notes,— my object I feared that I might have fallen into the grossest errors— I’<ref target="#foot.f10"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil del blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10798.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 17 January 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD evidently sent a manuscript copy of the introduction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref> to Thiselton-Dyer for his comments; the manuscript has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Restiaceae (a synonym of Restionaceae) is a large family of rush-like flowering plants of the southern hemisphere. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3217.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maxwell Tylden Masters</ref>, in his ‘Synopsis of the South African Restiaceæ’, had noted that considerable confusion had been caused by authors describing as distinct species what proved to be the opposite sex of some previously described genus or species (Masters 1867a, pp. 209–10). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_398.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Bentham</ref> had similarly stated that the great dissimilarity in habit and inflorescence between the males and females of some species made even their generic determination very difficult (Bentham and Mueller 1863–78, 7: 209). In the published version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 11, CD added Thiselton-Dyer’s observation in discussing dioecious plants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his description of <hi rend="italic">Petasites</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4415.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Edward Smith</ref> synonymised <hi rend="italic">Tussilago petasites</hi> L. with <hi rend="italic">Petasites vulgaris </hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. hybridus</hi>subsp. <hi rend="italic">hybridus</hi>, butterbur) and described the moneocious form as a casual variety. The species is usually dioecious, but sometimes monoecious. CD’s annotated copies of the first four volumes of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7288.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. E. Smith 1824–36</ref> are in the Darwin Library–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the published version of the introduction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, CD does not use the term; rather, he refers to the first to fourth classes of polygamous plants.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Ranunculus auricomus</hi> (goldilocks buttercup) has imperfect or frequently absent petals. Masters had noted the frequent sterility of this and similar species in a discussion of the morphology of the ovules of <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus</hi> (Masters 1867b).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Iberis</hi> is the genus of candytuft in Cruciferae (a synonym of Brassicaceae), the mustard and cabbage family. Compositae is a synonym of Asteraceae, the daisy and sunflower family. Umbelliferae is a synonym of Apiaceae, the carrot and parsley family.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Mussaenda</hi> is a genus of tropical Indian and African plants in the family Rubiaceae (coffee and madder). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 5, CD described the flowers as characterised by a single modified sepal with large petal-like expansion.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In the published version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 8, CD cited Thiselton-Dyer for his information on <hi rend="italic">Salvia horminum</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">S. viridis</hi>, annual clary). CD had also described the modified bud-like flowers of <hi rend="italic">Muscari</hi> or feather hyacinth (now more commonly referred to as grape hyacinth).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD’s annotations are notes for his reply; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10798.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 17 January 1877</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>