<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13700">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Wilhelm Breitenbach<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   22 February 1882</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14082</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13700 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13700.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13700.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160: 296</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 296</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_607.xml">Breitenbach, Wilhelm</persName>
                <placeName>Porto Alegre, Rio Grande do Sul</placeName>
                <date when="1882-02-22">22 Feb 1882</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes his collections and research on Brazilian insects, especially Orthoptera. Comments on insect phylogeny.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Orthoptera</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Brazil</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2021-02-02" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-09" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-17" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2022-01-05" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-01-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01278_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01278_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
        <surface n="296:1r" xml:id="i1278">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01278.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01278_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01278.dzi" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="296:1v" xml:id="i1279">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01279.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01279_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01279.dzi" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="296:2r" xml:id="i1280">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01280.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01280_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01280.dzi" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="296:2v" xml:id="i1281">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01281.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01281_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-01281.dzi" width="3545px" height="5838px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Verehrtester Herr Darwin!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Als ich vor einiger Zeit meine bis jetzt in unserer Provinz gesammelten Insecten musterte, war es mir sofort klar, dass ich zuerst den Orthopteren meine besondere Aufmerksamkeit schenken müsse.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Gestatten Sie mir, dass ich Ihnen heute wenigstens zwei der mir am interessantesten scheinenden Beobachtungen mittheile. Einen ausführlicheren Bericht über diese und andere Punkte werde ich in kurzer Zeit für “Katter’s Entomologische Nachrichten” ausarbeiten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Jene langgestreckten, grünen, flügellosen Mantiden sind Ihnen bekannt. Ich habe eine Art (oder ist es nur zufällig ein Exemplar?) gefunden, bei der ganz deutliche Flügelrudimente vorhanden sind. In den mir augenblicklich zugänglichen Werken finde ich Nichts darüber, ich vermuthe daher dass diese Beobachtung neu ist.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Zahlreich sind hier die einem durren Holzstengel ähnlichen Stabheuschrecken. Die Bestimmung der Gattungen ist mir nach der vorhandenen Literatur noch nicht gelungen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Wenn man als Hauptmerkmale dieser Thiere den kegelförmig verlängerten Kopf mit den weit vorgerückten Augen, und die dürre, langgestreckte Gestalt betrachtet, so glaube ich auf dem Wege zu sein, die phyletische Entwicklung dieser sonderbaren Formen ermitteln zu können. Ich habe neulich eine ganze Anzahl Acridier gefunden, bei denen man eine allmälige Verlängerung des Kopfes über die Augen hinaus, ein allmaliges Vorrücken der Augen (vom Hinterende des Kopfes nach vorn) und ein allmäliges Dünnerwerden der ganzen Gestalt, verbunden mit Längsstreckung, deutlich erkennen kann.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Sollte es mir gelingen, noch mehr solcher Zwischenglieder zu finden, so dürfte es nicht schwer sein, eine vollständige Stufenleiter aufzustellen von typischen Acridiern, einerseits bis zu den typischen Stabheuschrecken. Ich glaube, dass der Gegenstand volle Aufmerksamkeit verdient.</p>
<p>Sonst habe ich noc〈h v〉iele interessante Orthopteren gefunden, zahlreiche geflügelte Mantis-Arten, eine sehr hübsche Pterochroza, mehrere Phylloptera und Verwandte 〈un〉d eine sehr grosse Anzahl anderer Locustinen und Acridier.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Eine Heuschrecke habe ich, von der die Leute auf den Colonien behaupten, dass sie wie die Wanderheuschrecke Europa’s grosse Züge mache.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Bestätigen kann ich diese Angabe vorläufig allerdings nicht.</p>
<p>Indem ich hoffe, dass es Ihnen recht gut geht, begrüsse ich Sie als | Ihr | hochachtungsvoll ergebener | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. W. Breitenbach <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Porto Alegre. 22.II.82. | Rio Grande do Sul. | Brazil.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
           
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
       <opener>
           <salute> Most esteemed Mr Darwin!</salute>
       </opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>Some time ago, when examining the insects that I have collected so far in our province, it was immediately clear to me that first I had to pay special attention to the Orthoptera.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Allow me to communicate to you today at least two observations that strike me as the most interesting. I will soon prepare a detailed report on this and other issues for “Katter’s Entomologische Nachrichten”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You are familiar with these elongated, green, wingless mantids. I found a species (or is it perchance just a specimen?) in which rudimentary wings are quite clearly present. In the works currently at my disposal I find nothing about this, and hence I suspect that this observation is new.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
       <p>Stick insects that resemble a dry wooden stalk are numerous here. I have not yet succeeded in identifying the genus with the aid of the literature at my disposal.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> If one considers the conically elongated head with eyes that are moved far forward and the thin, elongated body as the defining feature, then I believe I am on the way to establishing the phyletic evolution of these peculiar forms. I recently came across a considerable number of acridians among which the gradual elongation of the head beyond the eyes, a gradual forward-moving of the eyes (from the back of the head to the front) and a gradual slimming of the entire body combined with elongation can be clearly distinguished.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Should I succeed in finding yet more such intermediate forms it will not be difficult to draw up a complete scale from the typical Acridae, on the one hand, to the typical stick insects. I believe that this subject deserves particular attention.</p>
        <p>Other than that I came across many other interesting Orthoptera, numerous winged species of Mantis, a very pretty Pterochroza, several Phylloptera and related species and a very large number of other Locustidae and Acridae.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have got a grasshopper that people claim undertakes extensive migrations like the migratory locust of Europe.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> However, for the time being I cannot confirm this claim.</p>
           <p> In the hope that you are thriving I remain | Yours | respectfully devoted | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. W. Breitenbach</p>
          
            <p rend="left">Porto Alegre. 22.II.82. | Rio Grande do Sul. | Brazil.</p>
        </div>
                
        
                  
                
              
    </div>
    
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Orthoptera is the order of grasshoppers, locusts, and crickets. At this time, it included several families which have since been reclassified into their own orders, among which are mantids (Mantidae; order Mantodea) and stick insects (Phasmatidae; order Phasmida or Phasmatodea).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Breitenbach’s paper ‘Entomologische Skizzen aus der Provinz Rio Grande do Sul Brasilien’ (Entomological sketches from the province of Rio Grande do Sul Brazil; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11598.xml">Breitenbach 1882</ref>) appeared in the June 1882 issue of <hi rend="italic">Entomologische Nachrichten</hi>. The journal was edited by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9461.xml">Friedrich Ketter</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Mantises have two pairs of wings; in most species, only males have fully developed wings while females have rudimentary ones or are wingless. Earlier descriptions of mantis species had noted differences in wing-size in males and females (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1103.xml">Burmeister 1832–55</ref>, 2: 540). In his article, Breitenbach speculated on whether these rudimentary wings were hereditary or a mere atavism (Breitenbach 1882, pp. 159–60).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">On the classification of stick insects, see n. 2, above. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Breitenbach refers to members of the Acrididae (the family of short-horned grasshoppers). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Pterochroza</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phylloptera</hi> are genera of katydids (family Tettigoniidae, order Orthoptera). Locustidae is the former family of locusts (now subsumed within Acrididae). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The main swarming species of locust in the Rio Grande do Sul region is the South American locust (<hi rend="italic">Schistocerca cancellata</hi>), which ranges from Argentina into the southern parts of Brazil. (Rio Grande do Sul is in the south of Brazil.) </note>
        </div>
               
    
               
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>