<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6542">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From James Orton   4 January 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10296</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6542 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6542.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6542.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 173: 37</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>173: 37</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3599.xml">Orton, James</persName>
                <placeName>Rochester, N.Y.</placeName>
                <date when="1869-01-04">4 Jan 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes the novelties found on his recent expedition to South America sponsored by the Smithsonian Institution.</p> 
<p>Wants to dedicate to CD book [<hi rend="italic">The Andes and the Amazon</hi> (1870)] which is modelled on <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Journal of researches</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">The Andes and the Amazon</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, South</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Orton, James 1870</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Smithsonian Institution</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rochester, New York, U.S.</placeName>
                    <date>Jan. 4. 1869.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Charles Darwin, Esq</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I take the liberty to make a request.</p>
<p>I have lately returned from a Scientific Expedition, under the auspices of the Smithsonian Institution, across equatorial America, via Quito, the Napo and the Amazons.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> My party made collections in every department of Natural History, to which I added a continuous series of barometrical and other physical observations across the continent, an account of which was published in Silliman’s Journal for last September.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I made a special study of the geology of the Ecuadorian volcanoes and the Amazonian valley. Of fossils, I found at Paita on the coast three forms additional to those described by D’Orbigny in your ‘Observations’,— Cinthium laeviuscula, Ostrea gallus and a new sp. of Ampullina.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In the high valley of Quito near Riobamba, I discovered a vast deposit of mammalian bones, chiefly of the mastodon, horse, tapir and llamas.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In the valley of the Amazons at Pebas, 2200 miles above Pará, I discovered a bed of fossil shells in the peculiar clay formation which overspreads the whole valley. Those determined are Neritina pupa (a familiar West Indian sp.), new sp. of Turbonilla, Mesalia and Tellina, and representatives of a new genus related to Isocardia.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> You will recollect that Bates, Wallace and Agassiz found no fossils in the Valley, and the glacial theory of the last rests somewhat on that “negative evidence”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> You may be interested also, in the fact that on a little lake on the slope of Antisana, 13,300 ft. above the Pacific, I found a grebe-like bird with undeveloped wings and scarcely able to walk, but at home on the water.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Associated with it were Penguins (in appearance): they were so shy we failed to secure one.</p>
<p>I will also state that I met a peccari, a “cock of the rock” and fine reptilian sp. common to both sides of the Andes,—Esmeraldas and Napo.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>The collections are in the hands of eminent naturalists, and will be reported on at an early day.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I am myself preparing, and have nearly ready for the press, a Narrative of the Expedition, modeled after your charming Voyage of the Beagle,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> weaving in the most important scientific results.</p>
<p>And now, my dear Sir, this is the burden of this letter,—I desire the high honor and privilege of dedicating this work on “The Andes and the Amazons” to one whose name is so pleasantly associated with our southern continent.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>With the very highest respect I am, dear Sir, | Your obedient Servant | James Orton.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 In the … valley. 3.2] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Orton led an expedition to the Andes from 1867 to 1868; the expedition was sponsored by Williams College, Massachusetts, and the Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2316.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Elliott 1979</ref>). Quito, the capital city of Ecuador, is in Pichincha province in the north central part of the country. The Napo river flows through north-eastern Ecuador and Peru into the upper Amazon river.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Orton refers to his paper ‘Physical observations on the Andes and the Amazons’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1868</ref>). The <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> was popularly known as ‘Silliman’s Journal’ after its founder, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4352.xml">Benjamin Silliman</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7343.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">South America</hi></ref>, p. 130, CD referred to fossil gastropods from Paita (a province in north-western Peru) that had been described by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3593.xml">Alcide Charles Victor Dessalines d’Orbigny</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1868</ref>, p. 116 n., Orton mentions <hi rend="italic">Cerithium laeviuscula</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ostrea gallus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">O. megadon</hi>), and <hi rend="italic">Ampullina ortoni.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Riobamba is a city in Chimborazo province in central Ecuador. The deposit of bones is mentioned in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1870</ref>, p. 154.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Pebas is a town in north-eastern Peru on the banks of the upper Amazon; Pará is a region (now state) in northern Brazil. The species <hi rend="italic">Neritina pupa</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Puperita pupa</hi>, the zebra nerite), <hi rend="italic">Turbonilla minuscula</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Tryonia minuscula</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Mesalia ortoni</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Dyris ortoni</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Tellina amazonensis</hi> (asynonym of <hi rend="italic">Pachydon amazonensis</hi>), as well as two others are mentioned in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1870</ref>, p. 283. The passage is scored in CD’s copy (see n. 11, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Orton refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Walter Bates</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1870</ref>, p. 282 n., Orton refers to <hi rend="italic">A journey in Brazil</hi> for Agassiz’s view that the sandstone deposits in the area had resulted from glacial drift and showed no sign of marine origin (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_80.xml">J. L. R. Agassiz and Agassiz 1868</ref>, pp. 250, 411, and 424).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Antisana is a volcano in north central Ecuador near Quito. The grebe was later identified as <hi rend="italic">Podiceps occipitalis</hi> (the silvery grebe; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1870</ref>, p. 146). CD had collected specimens of this bird (identified as <hi rend="italic">P. kalipareus</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8579.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi></ref> pt. 3, p. 136) during the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Esmeraldas and Napo are provinces in northern Ecuador on the western and eastern sides respectively of the Andes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">For a list of the naturalists who identified and catalogued the specimens collected, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1870</ref>, pp. xii–xiii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches.</hi></ref></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Orton refers to <hi rend="italic">The Andes and the Amazon</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6027.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Orton 1870</ref>). The dedication reads, ‘To <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Darwin</ref>, M.A., F.R.S., F.L.S., F.G.S., whose profound researches have thrown so much light upon every department of science, and whose charming “Voyage of the Beagle” has so pleasantly associated his name with our southern continent, these sketches of the Andes and the Amazon are, by permission most respectfully dedicated.’ CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 644–5).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>