<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7752">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From V. O. Kovalevsky   10 May 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17788</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7752 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7752.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7752.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 169: 89</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>169: 89</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2751.xml">Kovalevsky, V. O.</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1871-05-10">10 May 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Paris is in the hands of "brigands and socialists", but one grows accustomed to sporadic bombardment,</p>
            <p>and VOK is peacefully studying invertebrate palaeontology collections.</p> 
<p>Reports on Paul Gervais’ successful cross between a <hi rend="italic">Triton</hi> and an axolotl.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">axolotl</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">invertebrate</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Triton</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1853">Gervais, Paul</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Paris</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">"brigands and socialists"</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>10 May— 71.—</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Six weeks ago seeing by all German papers that Paris is “à feu et à sang” and having the Zwischensemester before me I got here with my wife and stayed the whole time studying the eocene and miocene vertebrate fauna of France in the collections of the Jardin des Plantes and Ecole des Mines.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The confusion in this part of Palaeontology is really lamentable; genera and subgenera spring every day, founded on the most slight differences, and I have seen many of the Creators of genera, not excepting M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gervais himself,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> who could on no account show reason why they did rise such and such forms into a genus. It is really high time that some good comparative anatomist with a critical and destructive turn of mind should go to work and bring some light into this confusion. Yesterday I have seen in the laboratoire of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gervais a fact that shall certainly interest You; his son, a young medical man,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> succeeded in fertilizing artificially the eggs of Axolotls (Amblystoma) by the sperm of common Triton; his first experiments were done the last year and he got some bastards Axolotlo-Triton which unhapilly did not live more than six weeks; the young are alike distinct from both parents externally, but till now no minute investigation was undertaken to see the differences in the dental system and so on. This spring he succeded a second time in pairing male Tritons with female Axolotl ant the larvae are swimming merilly, there is a hope that they will live, as the first experiment has given some hints as to the best manner of their food and exposition to light. Such distinct animals giving (fertile) offspings, that should be a really remarkable fact.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Seeing that Paris is now in hands of “brigands”, assasins, socialists” and so on, one is astonished at the quiet mode of life it is still possible to have here; unhappily M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thier persist in saving us from the fictitious brigands and introducing “order”, so the cannon is booming without interruption day and night, but we are so acustomed to the sound that it seems quite natural.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Having taken a walk in the Champs Elysèes I have seen two shells at ten yards, happily they did not burst, but some days ago while walking with my wife and sister a shell exploded some fifty yards from us without doing us any harm.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I dont think the Versaillais will ever get into Paris, even if an assault should succeed under cover of the Mont Valerien and the large batteries of St. Cloud, the troops could not advance in the streets covered now by solid earth fortifications and armed with mitrailleuises; it seems however that under the pression of the newly elected municipalities Versailles shall make peace.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Have You seen the brief description in the new <hi rend="underline">Paleontologie</hi> <hi rend="underline">generale</hi> of Gervais, of the Typotericum; there is nearly a complete skeleton in the museum of this remarkable animal found in Your pampean mud of South America<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Please to remember me to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Darwin and the ladies<ref target="#foot.f9"/> | Yours very truly | W. Kowalevksy</p>
<p>P.S. I hope to return to Berlin in some days, so my adress in th same, Anatomical Museum.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.1 Seeing that] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket, pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘(Write to him &amp; say I wrote) about German Book’<ref target="#foot.f10"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil, crossed pencil</hi>; ‘(Answered)’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘Post Restante’ <hi rend="italic">pencil, crossed pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><hi rend="italic">À feu et à sang</hi>: in fire and blood (French). Civil war had broken out in France following its defeat in January 1871 by Germany in the Franco-Prussian war. Much of the violence was concentrated in Paris from March until the end of May 1871, culminating in a battle between the army of the provisional government, and the national guard and radical republicans led by the Paris Commune (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Annual register</hi></ref> 1871, pp. 175–201, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tombs 1981</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Zwischensemester</hi>: between semesters, that is, a university vacation (German). Kovalevsky had previously been in Berlin (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-7583.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from V. O. Kovalevsky, 14 March 1871</ref>); he was working on his doctoral dissertation at Jena University, while his wife, Sofia Vasilyevna Kovalevskaya, was studying mathematics in Berlin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koblitz 1983</ref>, pp. 100–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paul Gervais</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5742.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Frédéric Paul Gervais</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The axolotl (<hi rend="italic">Ambystoma mexicanum</hi>) is a large neotenic salamander in the family Ambystomatidae. Triton is a former genus name for some salamanders that are in the family Salamandridae. No publications by Henri Gervais reporting on this research have been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6859.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Adolphe Thiers</ref> was head of the French provisional government during the conflict with republican forces in Paris (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tombs 1981</ref>, pp. 2–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Sofia Kovalevskaya’s sister was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6085.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anna Vasilyevna Korvin-Krukovskaya</ref>. The Champs-Elysées is an avenue in Paris. For details on the Kovalevskys’ stay in Paris and their political involvement, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Koblitz 1983</ref>, pp. 104–11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The army of the provisional government was based at Versailles. Mont Valérien and Saint Cloud were fortifications to the west of Paris (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7777.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tombs 1981</ref>, p. 72). A <hi rend="italic">mitrailleuse</hi> was an early machine gun, with a multiple barrel that was turned and reloaded manually (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wawro 2003</ref>, p. 53).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2826.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gervais 1867–9</ref>, 1: 134–7, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Paul Gervais</ref> described <hi rend="italic">Typotherium</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">Mesotherium</hi>) an extinct South American mammal. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi></ref>, pp. 81–4, CD described ‘a great Pampian formation’ of reddish mud and clay, where he found the fossil remains of large extinct mammals, including <hi rend="italic">Megatherium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Megalonyx</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Scelidotherium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Toxodon</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Kovalevsky refers to Emma, Henrietta Emma, and Elizabeth Darwin; he last visited Down in late August or early September 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7735.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to V. O. Kovalevsky, 3 May 1871</ref>; CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Körte 1829</ref>. His annotations are notes for his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7762.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Kovalevsky of 17 May [1871]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>