<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6305">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ludwig Molendo and Alexander Walther   5 August 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10136</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6305 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6305.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6305.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">2pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 229</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 229</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent" subtype="personGrp">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3357.xml">Molendo, Ludwig</persName>
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4948.xml">Walther, Alexander</persName>
                <placeName>Bayreuth</placeName>
                <date when="1868-08-05">5 Aug 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Send their work [<hi rend="italic">Die Laubmoose Oberfrankens</hi> (1868)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die Laubmoose Oberfrankens</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Walther, Alexander 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Bayreuth,</placeName>
                    <date>August 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It is a slight tribute paid by gratitude to instruction, when we send a trifling essay to the Reformator of Natural Philosophy, not without the hope that it may find a kind reception.</p>
<p>The inclosed book contains in its third part a slight investigation in your great theory, as far as we tried to apply its principles to the spreading about of the different species of moss.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>You yourself, most honoured Sir, have repeatedly encouraged to such investigations.</p>
<p>Until now no greater trial has, at least in Germany, been made to apply these principles to Kryptogames;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> and this one is also only a precursor; for Mr Molendo’s next work is devoted to the so-called law of migration, in which we do not see a new principle and, as to the long isolation—not one which is every where valid.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>We think that this first fruit of a branch of Botany, which until now was steril, may not be altogether unworthy of coming into your hands; as the study of your ideas has riprened it. But whether the fruit is indeed already ripe authors seldom know.</p>
<p>Also the Polygamic species were particularly taken into consideration and shall, in future, be subjected to more particular investigations.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> They seem to explain in a natural way certain cases of near affinity.</p>
<p>Our German Bryologians will, withhout doubt, attack this our way of considering the matter, and they are welcome to do so.</p>
<p>With the assurance of the highest consideration we are, most honoured Sir, yours very obedient servants | L. Molendo. | A. Walther</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The book was Walther and Molendo 1868. There is a lightly annotated copy in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 843). The third part of the book (pp. 207–79) was headed ‘Pflanzengeographische Betrachtungen’ (phytogeographical considerations). In a note at the back of the book referring to page 224, CD wrote: ‘Even close species of moss do not live close together; the Struggle for Life, being severest between nearest forms—good!’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Kryptogames: i.e. cryptogams.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The ‘law of migration’ (<hi rend="italic">Migrationgesetz</hi>) was developed by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moritz Wagner</ref> (Wagner 1868a and 1868b); his view was that a new species could appear only from a geographically isolated population of the parent species. Molendo’s work on the law of migration was apparently never published. See also Walther and Molendo 1868, pp. 263–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For the discussion of polygamic species in relation to natural selection, see Walther and Molendo 1868, pp. 272–7.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>