<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13673">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Anton Dohrn   9 February 1882</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16360</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13673 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13673.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13673.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Groeben (1982): 78</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 222</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 222</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml">Dohrn, F. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Stazione Zoologica di Napoli</placeName>
                <date when="1882-02-09">9 Feb 1882</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Birthday congratulations from the Naples Zoological Station. A new physiological department will be constructed. Describes work in progress at the Station.</p>
            <p>Sends his paper on teleosteans.</p>
            <p>Heard R. Owen read a paper at York [meeting of BAAS]. Owen had views similar to AD’s, but seemed not to be aware of work of others.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">teleosteans</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3629">Owen, Richard</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">York</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">birthday congratulations</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">meeting</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">BAAS</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Naples Zoological Station</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2021-02-18" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-09" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-16" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2022-01-05" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2022-01-26" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01000_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01000_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="222:1r" xml:id="i1000">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01000.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01000_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01000.dzi" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="222:1v" xml:id="i1001">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01001.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01001_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01001.dzi" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="222:2r" xml:id="i1002">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01002.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01002_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01002.dzi" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="222:2v" xml:id="i1003">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01003.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01003_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-01003.dzi" width="3091px" height="5367px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Stazione Zoologica | di | Napoli</hi></placeName>
                    <date>February 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1882.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. Darwin!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Permit me to confer once more the Zoolog. Station’s and my own kindest congratulations for the return of Your birthday, and to tell You, that the Zool. Station is steadily growing in all its different departments.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>It has been my desire from the very beginning to erect a physiological Department along with the manifold arrangements to favour the progress of morphological Science,—but it is only now, that I can really say, this desire is going to be fulfilled.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> A very fine locality has been got, outside the great building of the Station, which has no more room enough for all the different branches of the whole undertaking. It will be connected by two tubes for conducting seawater with the main building and offer thus every facility for experiments both chemical and physical. I hope to be able thus to offer to Physiologists a new opportunity for the special study of Torpedo, and to receive in exchange their cooperation in many questions, which interest Morphologists more specially.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The other fields of our activity are well progressing. Four volumes of the Fauna &amp; Flora of the Gulf of Naples are in course of execution in print and plates, and new ones are begun in study.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The Zool. Jahresbericht has had its second year, and though I have failed to gain the cooperation and amalgamation of the Brit. Record Association I have succeeded in getting support from Continental Academies, Societie’s and Governments.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am sorry, that the animosity against this literary Enterprise of ours has moved a critic in the Annals and Magazine to overstep largely the boundaries of fair criticism, but I am afraid, he will regret that himself much more, than the Zool. Station.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I take the liberty to send You a small paper of mine with statements regarding the formation of the Mouth and Hypophysis in Teleostians.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> You recollect perhaps that in a former pamphlet I tried to explain the Origin of Vertebrates in another way, than it was generally understood.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I always felt bound to give statements of fact for the support of my views, but could not find among other occupations time and energy enough to follow them up. Even now I have had to postpone studies in this direction, but I hope, what I have published may lead to a new inspection by others of the facts, which I believe to have ascertained in Fishes.</p>
                    <p>It was very curious, that when I happened to assist the Meeting at York Professor Owen should have read a paper, whereby he gave his assent to similar views. He seemed not to be aware, that they had already formed the object of continued discussions, and that since Cuvier and Geoffroy de St Hilaire several important attempts had been made to state and solve the problem, whose importance he most distinctly pointed out.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> It is even sometimes comical, to see how every involution on the back of invertebrates is suspected by some people to be homologous with the supposed ancient or the present Vertebrate mouth, as if this question could be treated with any chance of success, if not only the mouth but the whole of the organization were to be taken in account and to be reduced or derived to and from the supposed ancestor.</p>
<p>I have heard to my sincerest regret, that by the fault of my Publisher You have after all paid the subscription for the first year of the Fauna &amp; Flora, whilst I had asked it as a privilege from Your side to accept the Volumes from the Zool. Station as a gift. I hope, that now my orders are better respected, and that You will accept my excuse.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I was glad to have met Your Sons George and Horace at York, and to hear both from them and from Mr. Balfour, who lately visited us here, that your health was comparatively good.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Please accept my kindest wishes and regards which I present to Yourself Mrs. Darwin and all Your family, and which I would gladly have offered orally last year, had I not been afraid of disturbing You.</p>
<p>Yours | most respectful | Anton Dohrn <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">To | Charles Darwin Esq. | Down.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s 73d birthday was on 12 February 1882.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The main building of the Zoological Station housed the morphology department and, from 1876, a botanical department. The physiology department, opened in 1882, was housed in a rented building nearby. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11707.xml">Groeben 1985</ref>, p. 10.)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Torpedo</hi>, a genus of elasmobranch (cartilaginous) fishes, was popular as a research subject. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_258.xml">Francis Maitland Balfour</ref> had studied the development of its spinal nerves during a visit to the station in 1875  (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9401.xml">Balfour 1875</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The monograph series <hi rend="italic">Fauna und Flora des Golfes von Neapel und der angrenzenden Meeres-Abschnitte</hi> began publication in 1880 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10939.xml">Chun 1880</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10940.xml">Emery 1880</ref>). In 1881, three monographs were planned, but only two were published (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11708.xml">Dohrn 1881a</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11709.xml">Solms-Laubach 1881</ref>); the next monograph appeared out of sequence in 1883 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11710.xml">Grassi 1883</ref>, p. [v]). The volumes published in 1882 were <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11711.xml">Mayer 1882</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11712.xml">Berthold 1882</ref>. Two other volumes had been planned for publication in 1882, but appeared later (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11708.xml">Dohrn 1881a</ref>, p. [v]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The <hi rend="italic">Zoologischer Jahresbericht</hi>, initially edited by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml">Julius Victor Carus</ref>, was intended to provide an annual overview of work in zoology. The <hi rend="italic">Zoological Record</hi> was a British publication jointly sponsored by the British Association for the Advancement of Science and the Zoological Society of London, and was primarily devoted to taxonomy. Dohrn’s attempt to combine the publications was unsuccessful (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3608.xml">Heuss 1991</ref>, pp. 170–1). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The criticism in <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of Natural History</hi> has not been identified. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Dohrn’s paper, ‘Studien zur Urgeschichte des Wirbelthierkörpers’ (Studies on the prehistory of the vertebrate body; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11713.xml">Dohrn 1881b</ref>), focused on the development of the mouth and pituitary gland in teleost (bony) fishes. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Dohrn had proposed that vertebrates originated from annelids in his paper ‘Der Ursprung der Wirbelthiere und das Princip des Functionswechsels. Genealogische Skizzen’ (The origin of vertebrates and the principle of functional change. Genealogical sketches; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml">Dohrn 1875</ref>). CD’s copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. For more on the controversy surrounding Dohrn’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5158.xml">Maienschein 1994</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9845.xml">letter from Anton Dohrn, 7 February 1875</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9991.xml">letter to Anton Dohrn, 24 May 1875</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml">Richard Owen</ref> had delivered a paper, ‘On the homology of the conario-hypophysial tract, or of the so-called “pineal” and “pituitary glands”’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11714.xml">Owen 1881a</ref>), to the biology section of the annual meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science held at York from 31 August to 7 September 1881. Owen had referred only to the work of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1170.xml">Georges Cuvier</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1840.xml">Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Dohrn refers to the monograph series <hi rend="italic">Fauna und Flora des Golfes von Neapel und der angrenzenden Meeres-Abschnitte</hi> (see n. 4, above).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">George Howard Darwin</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1226.xml">Horace Darwin</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_258.xml">Francis Maitland Balfour</ref>.</note>     
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>