<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10835">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel   9 February 1877<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5306</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10835 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10835.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10835.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 70</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 70</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1877-02-09">9 Feb 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends birthday wishes. Album of photographs from German admirers has been sent.</p>
            <p>Plans trip to Mediterranean.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">German admirers</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Mediterranean</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">birthday</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>9 Februar 1877</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Zu Ihrem bevorstehenden 69sten Geburtstage sende ich Ihnen meine herzlichsten Grüsse und wärmsten Glückwünsche.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Möge Ihnen dieser Tag noch oft in voller geistiger und körperlicher Frische wiederkehren und Ihnen Gelegenheit geben, die ungeheuren Fortschritte der biologischen Wissenschaften zu überschauen, zu denen Sie durch Ihre epochemachenden Werke den ersten Anstoss gegeben haben.</p>
<p>Sie werden an diesem Tage das Album mit Photographien von einer Anzahl Ihrer deutschen Verehrer erhalten, von dessen Vorbereitung Sie leider schon vorzeitig durch die Zeitungen gehört hatten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Sie werden also nicht überrascht sein durch das Album selbst, vielleicht aber dadurch, dass die Zahl der Beitragenden nicht grösser und die Ausstattung nicht glänzender geworden ist. Zu unserem grossen Bedauern haben eine Anzahl von hervorragenden Naturforschern, welche zu Ihren Verehrern gehören, sich nicht am Album betheiligt. Namentlich fehlen manche Professoren, die ich gern in der Gesellschaft gesehen hätte. Immerhin werden Sie finden, dass Viele unserer bedeutendsten Männer Ihrer huldigen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Hier in Jena wird Ihr Geburtstag durch eine besondere Feier verherrlicht werden, welche ich mit meinen Schülern veranstaltet habe. Als Beilage sende ich Ihnen die gesammelten “Studien zur Gastraea-Theorie”, deren einzelne Theile Sie bereits besitzten.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Am 24. Februar werde ich Jena verlassen und nach Triest (von dort wahrscheinlich nach Lesina) reisen, um 6–7 Wochen am Mittelmeer zu arbeiten (hauptsächlich über Medusen).<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Mit grösstem Vergnügen denke ich noch oft an den September-Besuch in Down zurück, den Ihre Güte mir erlaubte.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Indem ich Sie bitte, Ihre liebe Familie freundlichst von mir zu grüssen, bleibe ich | mit unveränderlicher | Liebe und Verehrung | Ihr treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>9 February 1877</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I send my most cordial greetings and my warmest congratulations for your approaching 69th birthday.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> May you have many more days of full mental and physical vigour, and have the opportunity to survey the vast advances of the biological sciences that you have initiated with your epoch-making work.</p>
<p>On this day you will receive the album with photographs of a number of your German admirers, the preparation of which you will have unfortunately heard about earlier through the newspapers.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You will not be surprised, then, by the album itself, but what will perhaps astonish you is that the number of contributors is not larger and the production is not more splendid. To our great disappointment a number of outstanding naturalists, who count among your admirers, have not contributed to the album. In particular certain professors are missing, whom I would have liked to have seen in this company. At least you will find that many of our most important men show their respect for you.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Here in Jena your birthday will be distinguished with a special celebration that I organised with my students. I enclose the collected “Studien zur Gastraea-Theorie”, whose separate parts you already possess.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>On 24th February I shall leave Jena for Triest (and thence probably for Lesina), to work on the Mediterranean for 6–7 weeks (chiefly on Medusae.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I often recall with the greatest pleasure my visit to Down last September, which your kindness made possible.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Asking you to give my friendliest regards to your dear family, I remain | with unchangeable love and admiration | Yours truly devoted | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD was in fact 68 on 12 February 1877.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The photograph album was sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3907.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emil Rade</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10826.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Emil Rade, [before 16] February 1877</ref> and n. 3). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5291.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Otto Zacharias</ref> had sent CD a printed notice about the album, and later informed him by letter (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 24, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10628.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Otto Zacharias, 2 October 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">165 German and Austrian scientists appeared in the album, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10178.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gries 2006</ref>. Haeckel’s portrait appears first in the album and is full-page in size; the other photographs are grouped according to university. Haeckel also appears at the centre of a group portrait of zoology students at the University of Jena.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The final part of Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Biologische Studien: Studien zur Gastraea-Theorie</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3274.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1870–7</ref>) was published in 1877; all the parts are in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. A copy of the single-volume edition (Haeckel 1877) is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Trieste and Lesina are both on the Adriatic Sea. The University of Vienna maintained a marine zoological station at Trieste (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1898.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dean 1893</ref>, pp. 703–5). Lesina was the Italian name for the Croatian city of Hvar on the island of Hvar (or Lesina); Haeckel had spent a month there in 1871 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 21 December 1871</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Haeckel visited Down on 26 September 1876 (<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>