<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12055">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles Moore   15 May 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10177</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12055 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12055.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12055.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp &amp; ADraft 3pp &amp; ADraft 8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 233</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 233</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_147.xml">Geological Society</repository>
                    <collection>Charles Moore correspondence</collection>
                    <idno>LDGSL/802/DARWIN/1,  LDGSL/802/DARWIN/2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3379.xml">Moore, Charles (a)</persName>
                <placeName>Bath</placeName>
                <date when="1879-05-15">15 May 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends an ammonite from the Upper Lias, which has <hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi>-like bodies on surface. He wants CD’s interpretation. Discusses possible function of aptychi, siphuncular tube, and operculum in ammonites.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ammonite</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Balanus</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">Lias, Upper</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">parasites</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-14" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-16" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-20" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-30" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by Alison Pearn. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2018-08-30" status="copyedited">Copyedited by Samantha Evans. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cambridge Place. Bath</placeName>
                    <date>May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1879</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental"><hi rend="italic">Ammonites, Aptychi, Balani</hi>?</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have sent you a fragment of an ammonite from the Upper Lias attached to which are some Barnacle-like bodies—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In the midst of your other scientific work I would not have troubled you but that they are part of a very interesting study not yet exhausted, some particulars of which I think you may like to know— Some of these little bodies are <hi rend="underline">slightly</hi> larger, others still smaller. They do not appear to have the true shell structure of Balanus and in every instance the opercular valves are ancylosed and without a slit— Possibly they are young forms, but, although I have had 40 years experience of these beds I have never found them in a more advanced condition.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>In the Upper Lias there is a wonderfully <hi rend="underline">conservative</hi> bed, a few inches thick, containing saurians, fish, Ammonites, &amp;c, &amp;c From this I have a slab 18 inches long with a piece of wood with many <hi rend="underline">Mytilidæ</hi> and above them a colony of <hi rend="underline">Pollicipes</hi>, but without trace of their peduncles— (I have Pollicipes also in the Rhætic Beds.)<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>The same bed contains numerous Ammonites with their Aptychi in position often far back in their outer chambers some of them being almost microscopic. Years ago I wrote a short paper pointing out that there was never more than one Aptychus to an Ammonite, &amp; that being too small for an outer operculum I thought it might perform some office connected with the siphuncular tube—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>When Ammonites of 4 to 8 in. in diameter are found in the above bed they usually lie on the surface, or rather the shell has been very gradually denuded, or dissolved away, leaving clear &amp; sharp impressions or moulds of where they lay.— The small ostraea &amp; other shells that were attached to the exterior of the ammonite still lie in the stone below but above these is to be traced the original internal smooth surface of the shell to which they were attached<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Curiously enough, the Aptychus, sometimes very perfect still lies in the impression of the outer chamber, and in addition to this portions of the siphuncular tube still remain</p>
                    <p>But the remarkable fact is this that the tube, or the hollow that represents it appears to have been surrounded by thick membranous layers, in one instance passing round the various whorls for nearly 18 inches in length, the largest part being half as big round as my little finger— Seemingly like the peduncle of cirripedia it was an ovæ-bearing tube, &amp; it had even suggested itself to me, Why might not Aptychus be a parasitic male to the Ammonite?!!<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>But these Balani? now bother me— A few days ago on examining more closely one of these ammonite impressions I found to my great surprise that the surface was covered with very small globular ovæ, but becoming larger &amp; more disc like towards the outer chamber— Then I found strings of them lying together—like little Nodosarian shells— Next bivalve-looking entomostracan-like bodies presented themselves, sometimes hollow, sometimes pointed at one end, undistinguishable from the horn sheaths containing the antennæ you have referred to in connexion with some of the larvae of the cirripedes<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>There appear to be several stages of development before they pass into the pyramidal barnacle like forms I have now sent, but I need not now refer to them minutely If these are Cirripedes it will be wonderful to find on a single Ammonite so many points of interest which it took you so much labour &amp; research to determine—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I have these points shewn more or less on about 12 ammonites— If I could brush off from the surface of one specimen, all the ovæ carapaces, &amp;c &amp;c they would about half fill a tumbler!</p>
                    <p>Some of my Aptychi are in very perfect condition &amp; there is something more to be said of them. Whatever they may be there is no doubt D’Orbingy was mistaken when he figured his specimen, making the cirripedal antennae project through a membrane which united the two valves together<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I remain My dear Sir | Yours faithfully | Ch<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Moore</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The fragment of the ammonite has not been found. In stratigraphy, the Lias is the lower Jurassic period. Ammonites are an extinct group of marine cephalopods of the Triassic, Jurassic, and Cretaceous periods; their closest living relative is the nautilus.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Balanus</hi> is a genus of sessile cirripedes commonly known as acorn barnacles; in adults, the opercular valves or terga open like hinged doors to reveal a thick opercular membrane through which cirri can be extended and withdrawn. Anchylosed valves are those which have fused together.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Mytilidae is a family of mussels (marine bivalve molluscs); <hi rend="italic">Pollicipes</hi> is a genus of pedunculate cirripedes, known as goose-neck barnacles. The Rhaetic was a geological stage in the late Triassic period.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Aptychi are calcitic plates, occurring singly or in pairs in the body chamber of ammonites; in the mid nineteenth century, some naturalists believed they were separate animals while others argued they were ammonite valves. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3593.xml">Alcide d’Orbigny</ref> maintained that <hi rend="italic">Aptychus</hi> was a pedunculate cirripede (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6008.xml">Orbigny 1849–52</ref>, 1: 254–7), but CD had argued against this (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1314.xml">letter to S. P. Woodward, 21 March [1850]</ref> and n. 2, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2621.xml"><hi rend="italic">Fossil Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, pp. 3–5). In ‘On the Aptychus’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10920.xml">C. Moore 1851</ref>), Moore argued that the Aptychus was part of the body of the ammonite rather than a parasite and further suggested that its attachment to the siphuncular tube indicated that it had some connection with the function of that organ. The siphuncle is a small tube that fills the chambers of the ammonite with gas and water to control buoyancy.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Ostraea</hi> is a genus of oysters (bivalve molluscs); one valve of their shell is slightly concave where the shell attaches to a substrate. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In 1848, while working on cirripedes, CD discovered that some species had developed what he later termed ‘complemental males’ attached to hermaphrodite individuals (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1174.xml">letter to J. D. Hooker, 10 May 1848</ref> and n. 12; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851)</ref>, pp. 281–93, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854)</ref>, pp. 23–30). Moore probably speculated that ammonites could be analogous.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Nodosaria</hi> is a genus of Foraminifera characterised by shells composed of globular chambers. The name Entomostraca was formerly used to refer to all crustaceans other than Malacostraca (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4661.xml">Leftwich 1973</ref>). CD wrote that the antennae of larval <hi rend="italic">Scalpellum vulgare</hi> first appeared within an envelope or horn (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854)</ref>, p. 105).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Cirripede larvae have up to six naupliar stages plus a cyprid stage before becoming adults. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6008.xml">Orbigny 1849–52</ref>, 1: 255; Orbigny figured side by side images of the largest valve of the pedunculate barnacle <hi rend="italic">Anatifa laevigata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Lepas anatifera</hi>, the pelagic goose-neck barnacle) and the valve of what he termed <hi rend="italic">Aptychus sublaevis</hi>, together with images of what he imagined the <hi rend="italic">Aptychus</hi> would have looked like when living, complete with projecting cirri. Orbigny supposed that the valves of <hi rend="italic">Aptychus</hi> were analogous to the largest of the five valves of the <hi rend="italic">Anatifa</hi>.</note>     
        </div> 
     
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>