<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11839">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   21 January 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15563</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11839 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11839.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11839.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 20 March 1879, pp. 463–4</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature 19 (1879): 463–4</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Santa Catharina, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1879-01-21">21 Jan 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Has lately found frog that has eggs on its back.</p>
            <p>Pupae of caddis-flies living on rocks have lost fringe of hairs on their feet. In species that live in the water these are used for swimming.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">caddis-flies</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">frog</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">eggs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pupae</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-07-11" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-14" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-09-04" status="editorResponseCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-05-24" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-24" status="copyedited">Copy-edited by <name sameAs="#sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
    <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Blumenau, St. Catharina, Brazil,</hi></placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="print">January</hi> 21, 1879</date>
                    <salute>M<hi rend="smallCaps">y</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">ear</hi> S<hi rend="smallCaps">ir</hi>,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>If I remember well, I have already told you of the curious fauna which is to be met with between the leaves of our Bromeliæ.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Lately I found, in a large Bromelia, a little frog (<hi rend="underline">Hylodes</hi>?), bearing its eggs on the back. The eggs were very large, so that nine of them covered the whole back from the shoulders to the hind end, as you will see on the photograph accompanying this letter, Fig. I (the little animal was so restless that only after many fruitless trials a tolerable photograph could be obtained). The tadpoles, on emerging from the eggs, were already provided with hind-legs; and one of them lived with me about a fortnight, when the fore-legs also had made their appearance. During this time I saw no external branchiæ, nor did I find any opening which might lead to internal branchiæ.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p> 
    <figure rend="blockCentred width20">
        <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_11839_1.png"/>
    </figure>
<p>There is here another locality in which a peculiar fauna lives, viz., the rocks of waterfalls, which are of very frequent occurrence in almost all our mountain rivulets. On these rocks, along which the water is slowly trickling down, or which are continually wetted by the spray of the waterfall, there live various beetles not to be met with anywhere else, larvæ of diptera and caddis-flies, and a tadpole remarkable for its unusually long tail.</p>
<p>The pupæ of caddis-flies living on the rocks of waterfalls (I examined three species belonging to the <hi rend="underline">Hydropsychidæ, Hydroptilidæ</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Sericostomatidæ</hi> (<hi rend="underline">Helicopsyche</hi>)), as well as those living in the Bromeliæ (a species belonging to the <hi rend="underline">Leptoceridæ</hi>), are distinguished by a very interesting feature.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> In other caddis-flies the feet of the second pair of legs (and in some species those of the first pair also) are fringed in the pupæ with long hairs, which serve the pupa, after leaving its case, to swim to the surface of the water for its final transformation. Now neither on the surface of bare or moss-covered rocks, nor in the narrow space between the leaves of Bromeliæ, the pupæ have any necessity, nor would even be able, to swim, and in the four species living on such localities which I examined, and which belong to as many different families, the feet of the pupæ are quite hairless, or nearly so, while in allied species of the same families or even genera (<hi rend="underline">Helicopsyche</hi>) the fringes of the legs, used for swimming, are well developed.</p>
                    <figure rend="blockCentred width15">
                        <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_11839_2.png"/>
                    </figure>                    
<p>This abortion of the useless fringes in the caddis-flies inhabiting the Bromeliæ and waterfalls appears to me to be of considerable interest, because it cannot be considered, as in many other cases, as a direct consequence of disuse; for at the time when the pupæ leave their cases and when the fringes of their feet are proving either useful or useless, these fringes as well as the whole skin of the pupa, ready to be shed, have no connection whatever with the body of the insect; it is therefore impossible that the circumstance of the fringes being used or not for swimming, should have any influence on their being developed or not developed in the descendants of these insects. As far as I can see, the fringes, though useless, would do no harm to the species, in which they have disappeared, and the material saved by their not being developed appears to be quite insignificant, so that natural selection can hardly have come into play in this case. The fringes might disappear casually in some individuals; but, without selection, this casual variation would have no chance to prevail. There must be some constant cause leading to this rapid abortion of the fringes on the feet of the pupæ in all those species in which they have become useless, and I think this may be atavism. For caddis-flies, no doubt, are descended from ancestors which did not live in the water, and the pupæ of which had no fringes on their feet. Thus there may even now exist in all caddis-flies an ancestral tendency to the production of hairless feet in the pupæ, which tendency in the common species is victoriously counteracted by natural selection, for any pupa, unable to swim, would be mercilessly drowned. But as soon as swimming is not required and the fringes consequently become useless, this ancestral tendency, not counterbalanced by natural selection, will prevail, and lead to the abortion of the fringes.</p>
<p>I do not remember having seen, in any list of cleistogamic plants, the Podostemaceæ. These curious little aquatic plants, which Lindley placed near the Piperaceæ, Kunth between the Juncagineæ and Alismaceæ, and which Sachs considers as being of quite dubious affinity, cover densely the stones in the rapids of our rivers;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> on the branches which come above the surface of the water, there are pedunculated, open, fertile flowers; but there are numerous sessile flower-buds also on the branches, which probably remain submerged for ever; I have not yet ascertained whether these submerged flowers are fertile; if they are so, they can hardly fail to be cleistogamic.</p>
<p>F<hi rend="smallCaps">ritz</hi> M<hi rend="smallCaps">üller</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
<note xml:id="foot.f1">No previous letter from Müller on animals living in Bromeliae (now Bromeliaceae, or bromeliads) has been found. The original of this letter and the accompanying photograph and diagrams has not been found; the transcription here is from the published version in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Müller collected specimens of the egg-bearing frog; these are now
                    in the Museu Nacional do Rio de Janeiro; for an image of one, see the plate in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27, reproduced at 250 per cent of the original size. <hi rend="italic">Hylodes</hi> is a genus of tree frogs endemic to south-eastern Brazil;
                    frogs of this genus are not egg-bearing. The frog that Müller photographed was a
                    then unnamed species of <hi rend="italic">Fritziana</hi> (the species has now
                    been given the name <hi rend="italic">Fritziana mitus</hi>; see M. Walker <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2018), in the egg-bearing frog family
                    Hemiphractidae, in which eggs develop into free-living non-feeding tadpoles or
                    directly into froglets, bypassing the typical tadpole stage (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10662.xml">Duellman and Trueb
                    2015</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Hydropsychidae: the family of net-spinning caddisflies. Hydroptilidae: micro-caddisflies. <hi rend="italic">Helicopsyche</hi> (the word was probably added by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3274.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert McLachlan</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11930.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Robert McLachlan, 13 March 1879</ref>) is now a genus in the family Helicopsychidae (snail-case caddisflies), but was previously tentatively associated with the family Sericostomatidae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9704.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">McLachlan 1873</ref>, p. 40). Square brackets are used around <hi rend="italic">Helicopsyche</hi> in the printed text.  Leptoceridae: long-horn caddisflies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Podostemaceae is the riverweed family; Piperaceae is the pepper family; Juncagineae (now Juncaginaceae) is the arrow-grass family; Alismaceae (now Alismataceae) is the water plantain family. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2932.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lindley</ref> recognised the family Podostemaceae as dicotyledonous and placed it next to the Elatinaceae, which he called water-peppers and which are now more usually referred to as waterworts (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4772.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Lindley 1846</ref>, pp. 482–3). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2764.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Sigismund Kunth</ref> mistakenly wrote that Lindley placed it near the Piperaceae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9712.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Kunth 1831</ref>, p. 243) and Müller evidently followed Kunth in this error. Kunth himself, believing the family Podostemeae to be monocotyledonous, placed it next to the Juncagineae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9712.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Kunth 1831</ref>, pp. 242–3). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref> recognised the family Podostemoneae as dicotyledonous but recorded its placement as doubtful (Sachs 1874, p. 634). See also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 6, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1974.xml">letter to J. D. Hooker, [early December 1856]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1966.xml">letter from J. D. Hooker, [early December 1856].</ref></note>
       </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>