<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4831">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Bartholomew James Sulivan   8 May [1865]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10816</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4831 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4831.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4831.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 284</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 284</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml">Sulivan, B. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Board of Trade</placeName>
                <date when="1865-05-08">8 May [1865]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on the funeral of Robert FitzRoy.</p>
            <p>His own health has deteriorated and he must give up his work.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1650">FitzRoy, Robert</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">funeral</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Board of Trade. S.W.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>May 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was going to write to you today thinking you would like to know that I saw the remains of poor FitzRoy laid in their last resting place on Saturday.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I was in Cornwall when I heard of it, having read a letter from him <hi rend="underline">the day before.</hi> I had resigned my appointment a week before that—as three Doctors—consulted separately—told me I must give up, &amp; ought to have done so sooner.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>FitzRoy wrote to me saying he thought I was right, and that he was anxious about what he ought to do. We have been urging him here for some time to take a long rest—&amp; I have told him over &amp; over again that he ought to do so, or give up entirely: but he wanted the strength of mind to decide, and I fear the idea of losing the Income for his family had much to do with it—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> In his note he said he had been very ill but his wife<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; a skilful Doctor, had—under god—saved his life, &amp; he also remarked on never really feeling the value of blessings &amp; particularly of health—until losing them. Though he trusted in his case it was only temporary— This I think shows he had no previous idea of taking away his own life, and that it could only have been done through the sudden impulse of insanity.</p>
<p>I came back Thursday night hoping to be in time for the funeral. I found a note from Mellersh<ref target="#foot.f6"/> at Brighton asking me to tell him when it was to be—but I found no one knew any thing about it at the Board or Adm<hi rend="superscript">ty</hi> and I should not have known had not M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. FitzRoys brothers<ref target="#foot.f7"/> come to his office to lock up his papers &amp;c &amp; they told me it was early on Saturday at the Norwood Church, close to his house,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; they had told no one but relatives as they thought under the circumstances it ought to be very private—but they were sure it would be gratifying to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. FitzRoy if we were present. A French officer Capt Pigeard—of the Embassy—came to me afterwards to know when it was as he wished to attend on behalf of the French Navy, as they all thought so highly of him &amp; many had recieved much kindness from him.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Mellersh came up in time &amp; he &amp; I—Capt Pegeard, &amp; Babbington—FitzRoy’s assistant,<ref target="#foot.f10"/>—were the only strangers. His brother,<ref target="#foot.f11"/> two of M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> FitzRoy’s brothers<ref target="#foot.f12"/>—Lord Campden<ref target="#foot.f13"/> and Genl Wood &amp; his brother<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I think made up the old party. It was a very quiet and plain funeral, just what I think all funerals should be. Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. FitzRoy would go, &amp; the two daughters were with her.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> we all waited outside and walked after her carriage—&amp; the same back the brothers only going into the house. It was a trying scene at the grave. Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. F and the girls looked dreadfully ill, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. F gave way very much. The coffin was plain black wood with “Robert FitzRoy, born — — died — —” on a brass plate. You may suppose what a trial it was for me, and the thought of old times and scenes that would be mixed up with it all. The relatives were much pleased at the French Captain—showing such a desire to be present. I have no doubt many would have been there if they had known it, but no answer could be given to numerous letters to the office asking when it was to be, even from distant ports.</p>
<p>&amp; Now about my own case. I remained abroad four months,<ref target="#foot.f16"/> was not much better for two months while moving about in France &amp; Italy—but after six weeks quiet rest at Vevey I got so well that when we went up to a mountain Pension for three weeks I was able to walk up mountains for hours without any return of pain or weakness in leg, or headache, &amp; I returned as well as I ever felt but as I got to work again the symptoms soon returned, and by January I was very unwell. at one time I was a fortnight at home with severe shooting pains in back of head every few seconds, and afterwards for six weeks my leg gave way so in knee &amp; below it that I could not walk from the station to office—&amp; latterly—for the first time,—I feel my work a burthen to me. About a month since, the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> at Brighton, who sent me abroad, told me I must have perfect rest for my head: to make sure I consulted two others without their knowing what others said, and they all agreed, &amp; said I ought to have given up before, &amp; that if I went beyond the turning point I should go rapidly down hill, but that avoiding brain work &amp; excitement I might live to a good age, as there was no disease of the heart, but only weakness of action so that the small vessels of head were congested— After the weather got warmer I got better, but with these opinions I felt I ought at once to give up— I go on till end of this month, and then go on half pay as a private gent. again. We mean to sell the house as I cannot afford to live near London, and also my girls are better by the sea; so we go to Bournemouth where we shall settle.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>I should like to run down to you for one night before I leave, to see you before we go. I am sorry to hear such a poor account of you. Why do you not give up all work and try a Summer in the Swiss Mountain air? My eldest boy<ref target="#foot.f18"/> passed last July and is now Sub Lieut &amp; Assist Surveyor of Firefly in Mediterranean. The second is now passing at Portsmouth.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> The youngest<ref target="#foot.f20"/> asked me to let him try the Cambridge local examination last December   he was 15 &amp; of course in the Junior batch.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> out of 675 he was bracketed 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. in the Mathematical Honors only 12 getting them; and of the 8 above him, 7 were so much older that they had gone up for the previous exam<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> a year before, which also gave them a great advantage in experience. I hope therefore he will be able to win an open Scholarship at Cambridge if he lives to try. I always wished one boy to do that.</p>
<p>With very kind regards to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Darwin &amp; your Daughters | Believe me dear Darwin | Yours most sincerely | B. J. Sulivan</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to the death of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1650.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert FitzRoy</ref>; he committed suicide on 30 April 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">FitzRoy was buried in the cemetery at St Luke’s Church, Norwood, on 6 May 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4826.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 2 May 1865</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4827.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 4 May [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Sulivan had been suffering from health problems (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, letters from B. J. Sulivan, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4431.xml" resp="#automat">18 March [1864]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4622.xml" resp="#automat">23 September [1864]</ref>, and Sulivan ed. 1896, p. 378). He had been working as chief naval officer of the Marine Department at the Board of Trade (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">FitzRoy had been head of the Meteorological Department at the Board of Trade (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). On FitzRoy’s financial difficulties, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_157.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anderson 1999</ref>, pp. 201–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1649.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maria Isabella FitzRoy</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Mellersh</ref> and Sulivan had both served under FitzRoy on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> during the 1831–6 voyage (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1), Mellersh as a midshipman and Sulivan as second lieutenant (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1978</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6770.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John George Smyth</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6769.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Smyth</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1095.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Burke’s landed gentry</hi></ref> 1846, s.v. Smyth of Heath Hall).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4826.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 2 May 1865</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6532.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Pigeard</ref> was naval attaché at the French Embassy, London (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1865). Elements of FitzRoy’s weather-forecast service were based on work in France; FitzRoy had also been elected a corresponding member of the Académie des sciences in Paris in 1863 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1115.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burton 1986</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Thomas H. Babington was a senior clerk at the Board of Trade, where he worked as FitzRoy’s assistant in the Meteorological Department (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">British imperial calendar</hi></ref> 1865, p. 100; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5367.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mellersh 1968</ref>, pp. 288–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Sulivan refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George FitzRoy</ref> of Grafton Regis, Northamptonshire (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1096.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Burke’s peerage</hi></ref> 1970, s.v. Grafton, duke of).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See n. 7, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6442.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles George Noel</ref>, Viscount Campden (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1096.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Burke’s peerage</hi></ref> 1865).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Sulivan refers to Lieutenant-general <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5230.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Wood</ref>. Wood had two brothers, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7038.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Edward Wood</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5220.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Alexander Wood</ref>; the Woods were cousins of FitzRoy (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1596.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">County families</hi></ref> 1865; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1096.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Burke’s peerage</hi></ref> 1878 s.v. Londonderry, Marquis of; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>, s.v. FitzRoy, Robert, and Wood, David Edward).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">For FitzRoy’s surviving daughters see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4826.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 2 May 1865</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Sulivan had taken six months’ leave in 1864 because of poor health (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, letters from B. J. Sulivan, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4431.xml" resp="#automat">18 March [1864]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4622.xml" resp="#automat">23 September [1864]</ref>). See also Sulivan ed. 1896, p. 378.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">The Sulivans retired to Bournemouth in Hampshire (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1596.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">County families</hi></ref> 1872–90; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4844.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 31 May [1865]</ref>). Only two of Sulivan’s daughters have been identified, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6822.xml">Sophia Henrietta</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6890.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Catherine Sabine Sulivan</ref>. There was also <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8177.xml">Frances Emma Georgina Sulivan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4615.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Young Falkland Sulivan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4618.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Edward Sulivan</ref>. Sulivan refers to the Royal Naval College in Portsmouth, Hampshire.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Norton Sulivan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">The University of Cambridge established the Local Examination Syndicate in 1858. The aim was to use the authority of the University to promote a standardised measure of educational attainment. At centres throughout the country two examinations were held in December every year, one for boys under 16 and one for boys under 18. Papers relating to the syndicate are in the University Archives–CUL (Cambridge University Register (Local Examinations) 57.1: 1–46).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>