<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10259">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. H. Scott   13 November 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10697</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10259 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10259.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10259.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 123</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 123</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4260.xml">Scott, W. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Wanderers’ Club</placeName>
                <date when="1875-11-13">13 Nov 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Gives an example of the power of reasoning shown by dogs.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">dogs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Wanderers’ Club, | Pall Mall.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Nov 1875</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas Darwin Esq MA. FRS &amp;c &amp;c</seg>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Upon the several occasions of my reading your admirable work on “The Descent of Man”, I was always much struck with your remarks on the Powers of Reasoning in animals, yet, I always thought that the instance you gave in which such powers had been demonstrated in <hi rend="underline">dogs</hi> were not quite as startling as one would have imagined.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I have often since first reading your interesting work, intended writing you of a clear case of reasoning which took place with a Dog, which I knew well, belonging to a very old friend of my father (D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Scott of Exeter),<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but I have delayed doing so, thinking, I should only be taking up your time which I know is so exeedingly valuable, without doing a corresponding amount of good.</p>
<p>To make quite sure of the facts I wrote my friend, (Mr Wentworth of Beckhampton Wilts)<ref target="#foot.f3"/> the owner of the dog, a short time since, setting out the circumstances as I remembered them, &amp; he replied stating they were correct as related by me.</p>
<p>They are as follows; To begin with I should state, that the dog was a cross between a Retriever &amp; Newfoundland, taking after, in appearance, more of the latter than the former. He was an exceedingly intelligent animal and had been taught by his owner to do several tricks &amp; also make himself useful and among other things would ring the Bell, which was one of the old fashioned ones having a pulley &amp; tassel; shut the door, take the slippers put them into the cupboard &amp; bring back the Boots etc etc. The dog had however one bad habit, as a sporting dog, &amp; that was he would persist in chasing a hare when he saw one. The day when my friend was going out shooting &amp; not wishing to take “Shot” as the dog was called with him, he shut him up in the Dining room giving strict injunctions to the Housemaid not to let him out. My friend had not however gone very far on his road before “Shot” overtook him. When M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wentworth returned home in the evening he naturally made enquiries as to who had let the dog out, when the Housemaid stated that <hi rend="underline">hearing the Dining room </hi> <hi rend="underline">Bell ring she answered it &amp; on her opening the door “Shot” jumped</hi> <hi rend="underline">out over her shoulder &amp; made his escape</hi>.</p>
<p>That this was a clear case of reasoning I think cannot be questioned, and as to its truth I have not the least particle of doubt, as my friend M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wentworth is a gentleman well known in Wiltshire having resided there for a large number of years. Furthermore I knew the dog myself &amp; can testify as to the great amount of intelligence he always displayed.</p>
<p>I trust you will excuse the liberty I have taking in writing to you, but, I thought the above an interesting illustration of Reasoning in a dog &amp; one you would like to be acquainted with. Believe me Sir | Yours obed<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi> | W H Scott</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD discussed the mental powers of dogs in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 40–2, 44–7, 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Robson Scott</ref> had supplied CD with information on sign language and had assisted <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref> with his research on cousin marriage (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from W. R. Scott to E. B. Tylor, 28 June 1870</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9417.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from G. H. Darwin, 18 April 1874</ref> and n. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7567.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Wentworth</ref> was a farmer in Beckhampton, Avebury, Wiltshire (Census returns of England and Wales 1851 (The National Archives: Public Record Office RG10/1904/20/31)).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>