<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8595">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From S. H. Haliburton   3 November [1872]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14314</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8595 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8595.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8595.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 85</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 85</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2059.xml">Haliburton, Sarah</persName>
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
                <date when="1872-11-03">3 Nov [1872]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for copy of <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Reminiscences of their youth.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Bridge House | Richmond | S. W.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Charles Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>If I was to try &amp; express to you, the extreme pleasure your letter had given me, to say nothing of the Book that accompanied it, I might be accused of flattery, or “soft Sawder”—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Still, I may, (&amp; <hi rend="underline">I will</hi>) with truth declare that few letters, &amp; few gifts have afforded me the gratification of yours yesterday— To know that I was still remembered by you, after such a lapse of years, is in itself a satisfaction</p>
<p>That remembrance has indeed been reciprocal, &amp; often &amp; often have I lamented that I never had a chance of seeing you— I have made enquiries from various friends of your’s, &amp; have always been told, that even the excitement of meeting an old friend, was usually more than you could bear— Spite of this, I will still indulge the hope of once more shaking hands with one of the best &amp; most valued friends of my youth—</p>
<p>How many sad changes have befallen us both, since we met, &amp; how many of those we most loved, have been taken from us,—to me, especially Life is but a shadow, a remembrance, of happy bygone days—</p>
<p>I have, like you, a most vivid remembrance of the bright old Woodhouse times, in which you stand first &amp; foremost<ref target="#foot.f3"/>   I can recall the Beetle, &amp; the Fungus hunting, &amp; above all, the glee with which “Charles Darwin” used to be descried, cantering up to the house, it being a received opinion, that any frowns of the poor governor<ref target="#foot.f4"/> would be at once dispelled, you being always the most influential favourite— I have now in my possession a letter you wrote to me from “Terra del Fuego”, at my particular request, &amp; I can often laugh at your boyish assertion, that the highest pitch of your ambition would be to be favourably alluded to, in Eddowe’s Journal!—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I think that ambition has been attained, &amp; <hi rend="underline">something more</hi>—</p>
<p>I live a very quiet, solitary life, only associating with a few old, &amp; kind friends, my house is pretty enough, actually <hi rend="underline">on</hi> Richmond Bridge, with small garden sloping down to the River— My old passion for Animals still continues, but alas, I have no room for Poultry here, I have tried Pigeons, but they &amp; the Cats were incompatible, so my live stock is now reduced to two tiny Maltese dogs, two very large persian Cats, &amp; an old Cockatoo that I have had since 1848— I am certain your book will very much interest &amp; amuse me— When one lives as I do, alone with Animals, their habits &amp; manners become doubly interesting &amp; familiar— My health is but indifferent, I fancy there is something amiss with my heart &amp; the famed “Owen Constitution” is not what it was, in days of Yore. Time, &amp; Sorrow, have much tried me—</p>
<p>You ask after the Family, poor Fanny, as you perhaps know, became a Widow 6 months ago, &amp; now lives in London, with two unmarried daughters—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Caroline Lister is settled in Yorkshire, Sobie lives alone at Cirencester, Arthur now reigns at poor old Woodhouse, Francis lives on his small property near Overton, &amp; Charles is Chief Constable of Oxfordshire,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> with a Wife &amp; 5 Children— Of your Children, I have from time to time heard, that many of them inherit the Family talents, &amp; I think you have one Daughter married,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> if not more—</p>
<p>When Summer returns, if we live till then, may I look forward to our meeting somehow &amp; somewhere, I often go to London, &amp; would meet you anywhere you might appoint though I must not run the risk of affecting your health—</p>
<p>Once more, thanking you from my heart, for the pleasure you have given me, believe me, always, most truly &amp; affectionately Yours | S. H. Haliburton</p>
<p>Why did you address me so formally?—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8591.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to S. H. Haliburton, 1 November [1872]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had sent Haliburton a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8591.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to S. H. Haliburton, 1 November [1872]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8591.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to S. H. Haliburton, 1 November [1872]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">William Mostyn Owen Sr, Haliburton’s father.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The letter has not been found; Haliburton probably made the request before CD left on the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 1, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-183.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Sarah Williams, 26[–31] August 1832</ref>; Williams was Haliburton’s first married name). <hi rend="italic">Eddowes’s Journal</hi> was a weekly regional newspaper (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">North 1997</ref>, s.v. <hi rend="italic">Salopian Journal and Courier of Wales</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3619.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fanny Myddelton Biddulph</ref> was Haliburton’s sister and an intimate correspondent of CD’s before the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage; her husband, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_440.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Myddelton Biddulph</ref>, died in 1872. Her unmarried daughters were Fanny Charlotte and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alice Myddelton Biddulph</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Caroline Lister</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sobieski Mostyn Owen</ref> were Haliburton’s sisters. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3612.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Mostyn Owen</ref>, Haliburton’s brother, was the eldest surviving son of William Mostyn Owen Sr, and had inherited the family property at Woodhouse. Haliburton also refers to Francis and Charles Mostyn Owen.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Darwin</ref> married <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Buckley Litchfield</ref> in 1871 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>