<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5490">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Robert Trail   5 April 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10988</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5490 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5490.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5490.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 175</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 175</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4789.xml">Trail, Robert</persName>
                <placeName>Drem</placeName>
                <date when="1867-04-05">5 Apr 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on an experiment in crossing potato varieties.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">potato</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Aberlady Lodge | Drem</placeName>
                    <date>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April 1867</date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I received yours of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Instant last night and in reply beg to say that in listening to the very interesting and instructive paper by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Anderson Henry on the subject of Hybridization of Plants it brought to my recollection the experiment which I had made on the Potato a great many years before.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am afraid however that all I have to say on the subject will be very meagre and of very little use in a scientific point of view.—</p>
<p>The experiment was made with two sorts which are now supposed to have perished with the Potato disease.— They were at the period extensively cultivated in Forfarshire where I then was and were called the old Blue and the large American the latter a very coarse potato   The sets were cut with a very sharp knife and only one eye was left which was divided as near as possible through the middle and carefully joined to the eye of the other and kept in its place by a piece of bass.— There might be about Sixty sets so treated.— The results were very various. Some produced Potatoes all white, some all blue; Some with part all white and part all blue and a few probably four or five had the produce regularly mottled.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The only difference that I observed from the rest of the crop was that the Potatoes were much smaller in size though not less numerous</p>
<p>The two sorts experimented on, regularly produced the one white and the other blue flowers. Not having then any idea that the subject was of any interest I did not pay any attention to the colours of the flowers where the varieties seem to have united and in consequence of removal from the house and garden the experiments were not repeated as I had no opportunity at that time of continuing them and I had totally lost sight of the subject till I heard M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Henrys valuable Paper</p>
<p>The foliage of the blue Potato was of a much darker green than the other.— If there are any further particulars which you would wish to know it will give me great pleasure to supply them.— I am scarcely a Botanist but have often amused myself producing new varieties of florists flowers by crossing</p>
<p>I am | Sir | Yours Faithfully | Robert Trail</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Trail of 1 April 1867</ref> has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_115.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isaac Anderson</ref>-Henry had read a paper on hybridisation before the Botanical Society of Edinburgh on 14 March (Anderson-Henry 1867a). CD had read of Trail’s remarks in a report in the <hi rend="italic">Farmer</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5484.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Isaac Anderson-Henry, 3 April 1867</ref>, n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD reported Trail’s remarks in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 395–6, commenting that the potatoes that turned out part white and part blue, or mottled, afforded ‘clear evidence of the intimate commingling of the two varieties’. This was an example of one of the types of reproductive phenomena that he hoped his provisional hypothesis of pangenesis would account for (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 357–404).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>