<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1967">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. D. Fox   3 October [1856]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7100</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1967 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1967.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1967.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">10pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 240</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 84</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 6: 237</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Christ’s College Library, Cambridge (MS 53 Fox 100)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_83.xml">CCLC</repository>
                    <collection>MS 53</collection>
                    <idno>Fox 100</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1856-10-03">3 Oct [1856]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1730.xml">Fox, W. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Finds his grief over his daughter Anne’s death still strong.</p>
            <p>Is following Lyell’s advice about publishing his species doctrine. It is not to be a sketch, however, but as perfect as his 19 years of work will allow. His work on pigeons has been invaluable on many points. "No subject gives me so much trouble as means of dispersal of terrestrial production in the oceanic islands."</p>
            <p>Finds "most remarkable differences" in skeletons of rabbits.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Natural selection</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1203">Darwin, A. E.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3051">Lyell, Charles</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dispersion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear old Friend</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I am very sorry to hear how much you have been ailing. I had not heard of this affection of the leg. I do most sincerely hope that the water-cure will complete the good work which it has begun: the loss of locomotion to a man so active &amp; energetic as yourself would be grievous. No one can wish more truly for your recovery than I do.—</p>
<p>Thank you for telling me about our poor dear child’s grave.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The thought of that time is yet most painful to me. Poor dear happy little thing. I will show your letter tonight to Emma.— About a month ago I felt overdone with my work, &amp; had almost made up my mind to go for a fortnight to Malvern; but I got to feel that old thoughts would revive so vividly that it would not have answered; but I have often wished to see the grave, &amp; I thank you for telling me about it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. not be surprised if I went for a fortnight to Moor Park Hydropathic establishment for a fortnight, some time;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> for I have great faith in treatment, &amp; no faith whatever in ordinary Doctoring. It was <hi rend="underline">very</hi> kind in D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gully to speak so of me: if you go there again, pray remember me <hi rend="underline">most</hi> kindly to him, &amp; say that never (or almost never) the vomiting returns, but that I am a good way from being a strong man. Do not mention Moor Park; but sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. I ever go there, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. <hi rend="underline">certainly</hi> inform him.—</p>
<p>My poor wife has been having a bad summer; for poor soul, we shall have another Baby this autumn! Our second Boy, George (an enthusiastic <hi rend="underline">Herald</hi>! &amp; Entomologist)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> has been for the last six weeks, at his first School; the Revd. C. Pritchard at Clapham,—a school which has been much patronised by scientific men, Herschel, Airy, Grove &amp; Gassiott:<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I like it very well, &amp; we can have him home monthly for a day.—</p>
<p>You know that our Aunt M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> S Wedgwood lives here: a month ago she slipped on the road &amp; fractured the head of thigh-bone &amp; is utterly crippled,— —a grievous accident for her with all her peculiarities,—far worse than death.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I remember you protested against Lyells advice of writing a <hi rend="underline">sketch</hi> of my species doctrines; well when I begun, I found it such unsatisfactory work that I have desisted &amp; am now drawing up my work as perfect as my materials of 19 years collecting suffice, but do not intend to stop to perfect any line of investigation, beyond current work. Thus far &amp; no farther I shall follow Lyell’s urgent advice.— Your remarks weighed with me considerably. I find to my sorrow it will run to quite a big Book.—</p>
<p>I have found my careful work at Pigeons really invaluable, as enlightening me on many points on variation under domestication. The copious old literature, by which I can trace the gradual changes in the Breeds of Pigeons has been extraordinarily useful to me.— I have just had Pigeons &amp; Fowls <hi rend="underline">alive</hi> from the Gambia! Rabbits &amp; Ducks I am attending pretty carefully, but less so than Pigeons. I find most remarkable differences in skeletons of Rabbits— Have you ever kept any odd breeds of Rabbits &amp; can you give me any details? Your Call Drake is quite hearty: I have not watched it much, but have not noticed its loquacity; the beak seems short &amp; breast very protuberant. If at any time you could spare time, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. very much like to hear any particulars about habits of Call Ducks.— Do they show any migratory restleness in Autumn?—</p>
<p>One other question, you used to keep Hawks, do you at all know, after eating a Bird, how soon after they throw up the pellet? No subject gives me so much trouble &amp; doubt &amp; difficulty, as means of dispersal of the same species of terrestrial productions on to oceanic islands.— Land Mollusca drive me mad, &amp; I cannot anyhow get their eggs to experimentise on their power of floating &amp; resistance to injurious action of salt-water.—</p>
<p>I will not apologise for writing so much about my own doings, as I believe you will like to hear.— Do sometime, I beg you, let me hear how you get on in health; &amp; <hi rend="underline">if so inclined</hi> let me have some words on Call Ducks.</p>
<p>My dear Fox | Yours affectionately | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.4 to Malvern] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.3 School;] <hi rend="italic">semicolon altered from colon</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">6.2 on] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘in’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">6.2 variation] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">6.6 Rabbits] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Pigeons’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">6.8 it much] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘them’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">7.2 how] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘w’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to CD’s aunt, Sarah Elizabeth (Sarah) Wedgwood, who suffered a bad fall in September 1856 (see n. 7, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Anne Elizabeth Darwin had died at <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Manby Gully’s</ref> hydropathic establishment in Malvern, Worcestershire, on 23 April 1851 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had left Malvern before Anne’s burial, which was arranged by Frances Mackintosh Wedgwood.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Moor Park, in Surrey, was run by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2802.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Wickstead Lane</ref>. CD paid his first visit there in April 1857 (‘Journal’; Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Howard Darwin</ref>, aged 11, had developed an interest in collecting moths and butterflies, as well as continuing his earlier love of drawing soldiers and coats-of-arms. CD preserved several of his detailed coloured drawings (DAR 210.7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Frederick William Herschel</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_50.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Biddell Airy</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2007.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Robert Grove</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1826.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Peter Gassiot</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3871.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Pritchard</ref>, astronomer and educational reformer, had founded the Clapham Grammar School and instituted a curriculum that included the sciences. He later became Savilian professor of astronomy at Oxford. For the care taken by CD in the education of his sons, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5563.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. R. Moore 1977</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Sarah Wedgwood lived at Petleys, near Down House. On 3 September 1856, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> recorded in her diary: ‘Aunt S. fall’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>