<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2930">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   26 September [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3523</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2930 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2930.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2930.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 182</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 31;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 344, 3: 318</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 388</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Gray Herbarium of Harvard University (28)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>28</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Eastbourne Down letterhead</placeName>
                <date when="1860-09-26">26 Sept [1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Has read sheets of AG’s third <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> article [Oct 1860] and praises it and AG’s other reviews and articles highly.</p> 
            <p>Is surprised at the inability of others to grasp the meaning of natural selection.</p> 
<p>Has been testing the sensitivity of <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi>, which he finds remarkable.</p> 
            <p>Asks if AG will be able to make some observations on orchids for him.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Drosera</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Atlantic Monthly</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1860a</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">exclamations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">instructions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent [Eastbourne]</placeName>
                    <date>Sept. 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My dear Gray</p>
<p>I have a multitude of things to thank you for; &amp; hardly know how to begin. I forward &amp; stamped letter to Grisebach in yours of Sept. 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Always use me this way, when convenient; as a scrap from you, I consider very good payment. With respect to Von Baer’s statement about Guinea-pig; I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. much like to know where it is;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but it can hardly be trusted unless he has brought forward some quite new evidence with respect to the unknown wild type of Guinea-pig. I have seen some of the Hybrids of Rabbit &amp; Hare;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; believe case is to be trusted; but I do not know that the exact <hi rend="underline">half</hi>-bloods are <hi rend="underline">perfectly</hi> fertile <hi rend="underline">inter se</hi>: it is a particularly curious case, because many have perseverinly tried &amp; utterly failed even to unite these 2 species.</p>
<p>Your letter of the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. was very pleasant, &amp; so was that to Hooker, (just received from Lady Hooker)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> which made us all (ie my family) laugh heartily. I have received the Dialogue from Silliman’s October no<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Also the Proofs of the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Atlantic Article.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> These both seem to me <hi rend="underline">very</hi> good; but if forced to choose, I think I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> pick out the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> article as best.— (I don’t know though)    I do not pretend to be a good judge, as I have never attended to Logic, Philosophy &amp;c; but it is my opinion that you are best reasoner, of any man, let him who he may, that I ever read. As for your metaphors &amp; similes, they make me envious: I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> like to steal a few: yet you never are tempted to use them prodigally. The two last essays are <hi rend="underline">far</hi> the best Theistic essays I ever read. But I must return to the metaphors— I like specially that of the woman &amp; the cloth;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> and that of the rain-drops on the ocean.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I believe my chief difference with you, is that I (unfortunately) think more of the rain-drops on the ocean than on those on the land. All your arguments about Design seem to me excellent; but I must hereafter read all again. I have a feeling that the existence of the multitude of Stars &amp; the motion of the planetary system &amp;c are equally good with living beings to prove a First Cause; &amp; yet if there were no living things, there could hardly be design.— But I well know that I am muddled-headed on this subject.—</p>
<p>I have sent the August no<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> of Atlantic to Annals &amp; Mag. of N. History; &amp; offered to pay for its printing, if its length prevented its insertion: I have affixed your name, as Lyell agreed that it so greatly added to its value:<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I do most sincerely hope that I have not done wrong. The Saturday Review has lately been discussing Design; so I will send the Dialogue to it, of course without your name; whether they will print, I doubt.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I wish I could think of any Journal to print the October number.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I have had a letter of 14 folio pages from Harvey against my Book, with some ingenious &amp; new remarks; but it is an extraordinary fact that he does not understand at all what I mean by Nat. Selection.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I have begged him to read the Dialogue in next Silliman, as you never touch the subject without making it clearer.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I look at it as even more extraordinary that you never say a word or use an epithet which does not express fully my meaning. Now Lyell, Hooker &amp; others, who perfectly understand my book, yet sometimes use expressions to which I demur. If I had to write my book again I would use “Natural Preservation” &amp; drop “Selection”, but it is too late now. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gray of B. Museum says to me “it is, you know, obviously impossible that there can be any <hi rend="underline">Selection</hi> in case of Plants”.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> I made no answer; for it is hopeless. Well, your extraordinary labour is over; if there is any fair amount of truth in my views, I am well assured that your great labour has not been thrown away. I am perfectly convinced that had it not been for yourself, Hooker, Huxley &amp; Lyell; my Book would Scientifically have been a complete failure. You have been most generous &amp; disinterested in your exertions; &amp; I thank you from my heart.</p>
<p>Farewell, my dear Gray | Yours most truly | C. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. Please observe that if the Appletons lose by the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Edition never selling, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. <hi rend="doubleUnderline">prefer</hi> repaying the money they have paid me.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>I am writing this at Eastbourne, where we have come to sea-side for my girls health, &amp; she has certainly profited by it.—   Consequently I shall not see Clark (Agassiz’s man).<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>I have been infinitely amused by working at Drosera: the movements are really curious; &amp; the manner in which the leaves detect <hi rend="underline">certain</hi> nitrogenous compounds is marvellous.—   You will laugh; but it is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">at present</hi>, my full belief (after endless experiment) that they detect (&amp; move in consequence of) the <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2880</mn></mfrac></math></formula> part of a single grain of Nitrate of Ammonia; but the Muriate &amp; Sulphate of Ammonia bother their chemical skill, &amp; they cannot make anything of the nitrogen in these salts!<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>I began this work on Drosera in relation to <hi rend="underline">gradation</hi> as throwing light on Dionæa.—<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>Does Spiranthes (or any odd genus of Orchids) grow near you; if so, I would ask you next summer to make a few observations, which would not take 10 minutes for me. There is very curious contrivance in our S. autumnalis for insect fertilisation; viz a decked boat-full of viscid matter &amp; on a touch the deck splits &amp; leaves viscid matter exposed. But I would explain if you have a Spiranthes.—</p>
<p>I yet hope, &amp; almost believe, that the time will come when you will go further in believing a very large amnt of modification of species, than you did at first or do now. Can you tell me whether you believe further or more firmly than you did at first? I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> really like to know this. I can perceive in my immense correspondence with Lyell, who objected to much at first, that he has, perhaps unconsciously to himself converted himself very much during last six months.— &amp; I think this is case even with Hooker.—   This fact gives me far more confidence than any other fact.—</p>
<p>P.S. 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> | How does Dana get on? I wrote to him, a month or two ago.—<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.7 the Hybrids] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.9 unite] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘cross’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.1 (just … Hooker) 2.2] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.5 (I don’t know though)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.9 <hi rend="italic">far</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.13 on those] ‘on’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.1 Annals &amp;] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.6 October] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘Augus’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">4.5 use an] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">4.12 great] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">4.13 away.] <hi rend="italic">before omitted point</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">7.1 sea-side] ‘-side’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">8.4 consequence of] ‘of’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">8.5 of Ammonia] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">9.1 on Drosera] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">9.1 throwing] <hi rend="italic">before omitted point</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">10.2 next summer] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">10.4 decked] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">10.5 But … Spiranthes.—-] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">11.3 now] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘know’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">11.6 during] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘more’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">11.6 &amp;] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is given by the reference to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3016.xml">[Gray] 1860c</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The letter from Gray mentioned by CD has not been found. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2001.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Heinrich Rudolf Grisebach</ref> was professor of botany at Göttingen University. CD had used his flora of the Balkans in 1856 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Ernst von Baer</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 28 [September 1860]</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2860.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 5 [July 1860]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2927A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 25 September 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2361.xml">Maria Hooker</ref> had apparently sent CD a letter that Gray had written to her son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2910.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 10 September [1860]</ref>). Hooker had just left for Syria (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3990.xml">L. Huxley ed. 1918</ref>, 1: 528).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD refers to the article entitled ‘Discussion between two readers of Darwin’s treatise on the origin of species, upon its natural theology’, published in the September issue of the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> ([Gray] 1860c). There is a copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL, on which CD wrote: ‘<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>(?)’. Gray’s authorship is confirmed by his biographer, A. Hunter Dupree (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, pp. 288–9). According to Dupree, the ‘Discussion’ was a record of an actual debate that took place between Gray and his friend <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4795.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Treadwell</ref>, formerly Rumford professor at Harvard University. Gray described Treadwell as a ‘skeptical neighbor of mine, a man who hangs doubtfully on the skirts of atheism, and thinks Darwin’s book will give him a firmer hold’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, p. 289). In the debate, the first reader was Treadwell and the second Gray.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The third and final part of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3018.xml">[Gray] 1860b</ref> was published in the October issue of the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>. The article was entitled ‘Darwin and his reviewers’. There is an annotated copy of Gray’s articles for the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The passage occurs in [Gray] 1860c, p. 239. It describes the way that a ‘woman of a past generation’ would believe the wool or cotton forming a piece of cloth was carded, spun, and woven by hand rather than by machine. <quote type="quote"> If you patiently explained to her the theory of carding machines, spinning jennys, and powerlooms, would her reception of your explanation weaken her conviction that the cloth was the result of design? It is certain that she would believe in design as firmly as before, and that this belief would be attended by a higher conception and reverent admiration of a wisdom, skill, and power so greatly beyond anything she had previously conceived possible. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The passage occurs in the third part of [Gray] 1860b, p. 417: <quote type="quote"> The whole animate life of a country depends absolutely upon the vegetation; the vegetation upon the rain. The moisture is furnished by the ocean, is raised by the sun’s heat from the ocean’s surface, and is wafted inland by the winds. But what multitudes of rain-drops fall back into the ocean, are as much without a final cause as the incipient varieties which come to nothing! </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2927A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 25 September 1860</ref>. The paper was reprinted in the November issue of <hi rend="italic">Annals and Magazine of</hi> <hi rend="italic">Natural History</hi>, pp. 373–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 3 October [1860]</ref>. The article was not published in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD refers to the third part of [Gray] 1860b. It was not reprinted in an English journal.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-2898.xml" resp="#automat">Letter from W. H. Harvey, 24 August 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See n. 6, above. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Harvey</ref> and Gray corresponded about CD’s theory. After reading Gray’s ‘Dialogue’ ([Gray] 1860c) and the articles in the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> ([Gray] 1860b), Harvey wrote to Gray on 3 November 1860: ‘“Almost thou persuadest me to be a Darwinite“—not <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> so, but thou persuadest me to be a <hi rend="italic">Grayite</hi>.‘ (Gray Herbarium, Harvard University).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Edward Gray’s</ref> response to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> was negative. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2583.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 14 December [1859]</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3216.xml">Gunther 1975</ref>, pp. 454–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2706.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 20 February 1860</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 22 May [1860]</ref>. In May 1860, CD recorded in his journal the sum of <hi rend="italic">£</hi>21 17<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 6<hi rend="italic">d</hi>., which represented CD’s share of the profits of the American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic"> Origin</hi></ref>. See ‘Journal’ (Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry James Clark</ref> was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz’s</ref> personal assistant at the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard, and a contributor to Agassiz’s <hi rend="italic">Contributions to the natural</hi> <hi rend="italic">history of the United States of America</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_66.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Agassiz 1857–62</ref>). In June 1860, he was appointed assistant professor of zoology in the Scientific School of Harvard University. Following his appointment, he travelled for his health’s sake in England, France, Germany, and Switzerland. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1991</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">CD continued his experiments on <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> throughout his stay in Eastbourne. His notes on these experiments are in DAR 60.1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> is a member of the Droseraceae. In <hi rend="italic"> Insectivorous</hi> <hi rend="italic">plants</hi>, CD stated of <hi rend="italic">D. muscipula</hi>: ‘This plant, commonly called Venus’ fly-trap, from the rapidity and force of its movements, is one of the most wonderful in the world‘ and ’is one of the most beautifully adapted plants in the vegetable kingdom‘ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref>, pp. 286, 358).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana</ref> returned to the United States in August 1860, having spent over a year in Europe recuperating from a breakdown in his health (<hi rend="italic">American Journal of Science and Arts</hi> 30 (1860): 308). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2882.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. D. Dana, 30 July [1860]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>