<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13208F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   17 June 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21545</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13208F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13208F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13208F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 73</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>271.1: 73</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>
                <date when="1881-06-17">17 June 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Glad CD approves of diaheliotropic paper. Reports on experiments with <hi rend="italic">Carex</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Yucca</hi>. Discusses translation of ‘Växtbook’ from Swedish. Heard some excellent music the previous night.</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-13" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-03" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-05-29" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>
                    <date>17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 81</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Many thanks for yr letter   I am awfully glad you approve of the Diaheliotropic paper.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have written for extra copies— I have been working pretty hard— I had a good go at the developement of Carex embryo in reference to the architecture of the very young root.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It is awfully difficult as the little beasts must be free of the endosperm so that you can roll them over &amp; see both sides; the rolling is done very cutely by putting a very fine spun glass filament under the cover glass; then they are always getting lost; it is good practice for accurate focussing as you have to avoid the upper &amp; lower surfaces &amp; look at the middle set of cells— I have also been doing Yucca root which turns out to be interesting because it isnt of the true Monocotyledon type.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Since then I have been doing cambium in various plants— D<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Bary is simply splendid in the way he helps one; it makes one envy the men who work 4 or 5 years under him<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>The Swedish Växt book is nothing to do with wax, it = “Gewächse” &amp; is about Plant-forms   a sort of “Grisebach en miniature” as de Bary says<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I heard from Schmiedeberg the Prof of Pharmacology that Hensen’s book is very good but otherwise I couldn’t hear much of him; there will be a full notice of it by Strassburger in the Bot Zeitung.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I am going tonight with de B to the Naturfor: Gesell to hear the Petrolog Professor talk chiefly about old Hahn &amp; his <hi rend="underline">Hahnia meteorica</hi> &amp; I must go this minute<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>I heard some excellent music lastnight by 3 students P.F. V &amp; V<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> of Schubert extremely well played by all; it is a small Musical &amp; Literary Soc &amp; the men seem very pleasant.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Neitzel also played a Beet Sonata 106 very well, &amp; gave a little lecture on the meaning of it it being the life of a hero<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>Yours affec | F. D.</p>
<p>I got a very nice letter from old W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> which I will answer very soon<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I am very glad about G. &amp; Ball—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Isnt the review in Nature on the Salt Book rather Romanesque; it amused me<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter has not been found; CD’s letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13206.xml">[16 June 1881]</ref> must have crossed in the mail with this letter. Francis’s paper ‘On the power possessed by leaves of placing themselves at right angles to the direction of incident light’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10623.xml">F. Darwin 1880a</ref>) had recently been published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>). CD had defined diaheliotropism as the taking of a position more or less transverse to the light and induced by it (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>, p. 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Carex</hi> is the genus of true sedges in the family Cyperaceae; some sedges develop distinct dauciform (carrot-like) roots, which are short with dense root hairs, as a response to nutrient deficiency.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The roots of most monocotyledons are composed of a fibrous network, known as adventitious roots, that arise from the stem. Plants of the genus <hi rend="italic">Yucca</hi> have long fleshy taproots (typical of dicotyledons) as well as a shallow radial root system.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Francis was working for the summer in the laboratory of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1268.xml">Anton de Bary</ref> in Straßburg (Strasbourg). De Bary was known for his close supervision of practical work with his students and his accessibility (see, for example <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11442.xml">Bower 1938</ref>, pp. 17, 24–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13206.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, [16 June 1881]</ref> and n. 6; the work was ‘Försök bis analytisk behandling af växtformationerna’ (Attempt at an analytical approach to plant formations; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11414.xml">Hult 1881</ref>). The German ‘Gewächs’ and Swedish ‘växt’ are cognates; they derive from the verb ‘wachsen’ (växa): to grow. CD associated  ‘väx’ with English ‘wax‘ and initially thought the title might refer to bloom, the waxy coating on some leaves and fruit. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2001.xml">August Heinrich Rudolf Grisebach</ref> had been a professor of botany at Göttingen and travelled widely studying plant geography (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5820.xml"><hi rend="italic">NDB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9306.xml">Oswald Schmiedeberg</ref> commented on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2226.xml">Victor Hensen</ref>’s recent work, <hi rend="italic">Physiologie der Zeugung</hi> (Physiology of reproduction; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11415.xml">Hensen 1881</ref>). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13179.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, 27 May 1881</ref>. It was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9307.xml">Adolf Engler</ref>, rather than <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4587.xml">Eduard Strasburger</ref>, who reviewed <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11415.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Hensen 1881</ref> in <hi rend="italic">Botanische Zeitung</hi>, 17 June 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11443.xml">Engler 1881</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2051.xml">Otto Hahn</ref> had sent CD a copy of his work <hi rend="italic">Die Meteorite (Chondrite) und ihre Organismen</hi> (Meteorites (chondrites) and their organisms; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11186.xml">Hahn 1880</ref>) in December 1880 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 28, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12917.xml">letter from Otto Hahn, 16 December 1880</ref>). Hahn sent his collection to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5046.xml">David Friedrich Weinland</ref>, who named one of the coral-like forms <hi rend="italic">Hahnia meteorica</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10055.xml">Burke 1986</ref>, p. 172). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9308.xml">Emil Cohen</ref> was professor extraordinarius of petrography at Straßburg.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9304.xml">Franz Schubert</ref> wrote two piano trios for piano (pianoforte), violin, and cello (violoncello) (D. 898 and D. 929). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6336.xml">Ludwig van Beethoven</ref>’s Piano Sonata no. 29, op. 106, was played by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9305.xml">Otto Neitzel</ref>, a former director of the <hi rend="italic">Musikverein</hi> (music society) in Straßburg and the music director of the Straßburger Stadttheater.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1245.xml">William Erasmus Darwin</ref> has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_262.xml">Robert Stawell Ball</ref>; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13197.xml">letter to G. H. Darwin, 8 June [1881]</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">The history of salt</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11440.xml">Boddy 1881</ref>) was anonymously reviewed in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 9 June 1881, pp. 123–4. The reviewer supposed that the book was written as ‘an elaborate joke’ and the tone of the review is very tongue-in-cheek. ‘Romanesque’: Francis implies that the anonymous reviewer might have been <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">George John Romanes</ref>.</note>  
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>