<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10815">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Hermann Müller   25 January 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7859</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10815 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10815.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10815.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp ††</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 110: A26–7</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>110: A26–7</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml">Müller, H. L. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Lippstadt</placeName>
                <date when="1877-01-25">25 Jan 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for calling attention to a "considerable error" in his observations on <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi> fertility [in <hi rend="italic">Die Befruchtung der Blumen</hi> (1873)]. [See <hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi>, p. 52.]</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Hottonia</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Die Befruchtung der Blumen</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Müller, H. L. H. 1873</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-09-15" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2016-09-15" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lippstadt,</placeName>
                    <date>Jan 25. 77.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am glad of being reminded by you of a considerable error of my book “Die Befruchtung”.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>When trying on Hottonia, I was not aware of the necessity of calculating the whole-average-numbers of seeds contained in a capsule from the average-numbers on the single plants in observation; but I was of opinion that I must not consider the fertility of the long-styled flowers legitimately fertilised, as greater than the fertility of the long-styled flowers illegitimately fertilised, unless every single long-styled plant legitimately fertilised yielded a greater average-number of seeds than every single long-styled plant illegitimately fertilised. Hence, the first of the former yielding a greater average-number than the first of the latter, the other of the former, on the contrary, yielding a smaller (although but little smaller) number than the other of the latter, I thought that any remarkable difference of their fertility was not proved by my observations.</p>
<p>The figures p. 351 are quite right, but the conclusion of “eben so hohe Fruchtbarkeit” p. 352 is to be corrected, and I will be very much obliged to you if you will be good enough and correct it in your review on the observations on heterostyled plants.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Nothwithstanding this error, it is striking that the difference of fertility between legitimately and illegitimately fertilised plants is much smaller in the long-styled than in the short-styled form; and, as far as the small number of my observations permits any generalisation, the conclusion which I have drawn from the supposed equal fertility of legitimately and illegitimately fertilised long-styled plants of Hottonia, will, I think, be appliable to their, in comparison with the short-styled form, less differing fertility.</p>
<p>I have to return to you my hearty thanks for your kindly sending to me the second edition of your Work on Orchids, which always will remain the standard-work for every one who will explain structures of flowers.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> If any success has rewarded Hildebrand’s, Delpino’s etc., my brothers and my own attempts in this department of research, it is essentialy owing to the incitation and to the splendid model given to us by your work on Orchids.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> It has been with great delight that I have reviewed the many new observations made since the first edition.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very sincerely | H. Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>5.1 I have … edition. 5.7] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘I think I must say something about his view— | supported by Lythrum, but contradicted by *short-sty [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] Primula, in above the short-styled form is most likely to receive own pollen is the more sterile—whilst in Pulmonaria the long-styled is the most likely to receive it is the more sterile &amp; with Linum grandiflorum the long-styled always receives own pollen &amp; is absolutely barren.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> | Would it be worth while to give Table of relative [<hi rend="italic">interl</hi>] fertility of the [<hi rend="italic">illeg del</hi>] illegitimate union of each dimorphic species.— taking fert of short-styled as 100— that of Linum w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be 0— that of Hottonia w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be <hi rend="italic">180</hi>?<ref target="#foot.f7"/> | (Read letter)’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></p> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The letter from CD concerning Müller’s error in <hi rend="italic">Die Befruchtung der Blumen durch Insekten</hi> (Fertilisation of flowers through insect agency; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>) has not been found; CD evidently pointed out a flaw in Müller’s experimental method (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had referred to the crosses of plants of the same form as ‘homomorphic’ unions and later as ‘illegitimate’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, p. 87 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 55), and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>, p. 187 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 121)). In his description of experiments with <hi rend="italic">Hottonia palustris</hi> (water violet), Müller had concluded, ‘illegitime Kreuzung zwischen verschiedenen Stöcken der langgrifflegen Form bei Hottonia eben so hohe Fruchtbarkeit ergibt als legitime Kreuzungen’ (an illegitimate cross between different plants of the long-styled form in <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi> results in just as great fertility as legitimate crosses; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>, p. 352). CD double-scored the passage in his copy. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 52, CD used Müller’s data on <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi>, but followed his own practice of deriving mean numbers of seeds and included a table showing that the proportion of seeds legitimately produced to those illegitimately produced was as 100 to 85. In the English translation of Müller’s book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5700.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1883</ref>, p. 388), Müller added a footnote to his statement, noting the correctness of CD’s approach and giving the proportion of seed from the two types as CD had done. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Müller’s name is on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref> (Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Hildebrand</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> had written many works on aspects of floral morphology that promoted cross-fertilisation; all had acknowledged CD’s pioneering role (see, for example, Hildebrand 1867, pp. 4–5, Delpino 1867, p. 4, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> 1868).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had added many further observations based on information received from Fritz and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Müller</ref>, Hildebrand, and Delpino among others. CD listed relevant works published since the first edition in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. vii–x.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 263–8, CD discussed Müller’s suggestion (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. Müller 1873</ref>, p. 352) that homostyled plants might have been rendered heterostyled from the effects of habit (Müller observed flies frequently carrying pollen from the long-styled form of <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi> to the stigma of the same form), since some illegitimate unions were highly fertile, as in the case of long-styled <hi rend="italic">Hottonia</hi>. CD concluded that differences in the degree of sterility of illegitimate unions in various species were incidental, following from changes gradually effected in their reproductive systems, in order that the sexual elements of the distinct forms should act perfectly on one another.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, pp. 188–243, CD did provide tables showing the fertility of illegitimate offspring of heterostyled plants.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>