<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13213">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   21 June 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5313</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13213 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13213.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13213.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 78</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 78</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1881-06-21">21 June 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Plans visit to Ceylon.</p>
            <p>Describes rejection of his application for funds by Berlin Academy. Asks about possibility of obtaining support in England. Is writing to Lubbock and Huxley about it.</p>
            <p>Hopes that new microscope from Zeiss is satisfactory. Ernst Abbe selected lenses.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_5">Abbe, Ernst</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2486">Huxley, T. H.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3026">Lubbock, John</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_5294">Zeiss, Carl</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Ceylon</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">England</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">visiting</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Berlin Academy</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-01" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-03" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-05-29" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2021-03-31" status="copyedited">by Samantha Evans and entered by Shelley Innes</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00329_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00329_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="78:1r" xml:id="i329">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00329.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00329_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00329.dzi" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="78:1v" xml:id="i330">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00330.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00330_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00330.dzi" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="78:2r" xml:id="i331">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00331.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00331_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00331.dzi" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="78:2v" xml:id="i332">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00332.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00332_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00166-000-00332.dzi" width="3911px" height="6348px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>21. Juni 81.</date>
                    <salute>Theurer und hochverehrter Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>In Erfüllung eines sehnlichen Wunsches, welchen ich seit 30 Jahren hege, einmal die Wunder der Tropen-Natur zu sehen, beabsichtige ich nächsten Winter in <hi rend="underline">Ceylon</hi> zuzubringen. Ich denke, Ende <hi rend="underline">September</hi> direct (via Suez, Bombay) nach Colombo zu gehen, 4 Monate (theils in Pt. Galle, theils in Trincomalee) zu arbeiten, und April 1882 zurückzukehren.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich will hauptsächlich Medusen und Radiolarien untersuchen, daneben tüchtig zeichnen und malen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Ich habe kürzlich auch Öl-Malen und Photographiren gelernt, und bin zu Allem wohl vorbereitet.</p>
                    <p>Um die bedeutenden Kosten der Reise zu decken, (besonders auch um Viel dredgen und sammeln zu können) hatte ich gehofft, von der Berliner Academie das “Humboldt-Stipendium” zu bekommen, und meine dortigen Freunde hatten mir letzten Ostern <hi rend="doubleUnderline">bestimmt</hi> <hi rend="underline">versprochen</hi>, daraus 15,000 Mk (= 750 £ Strl). für diesen Zweck zu erhalten. In der entscheidenden Sitzung, in voriger Woche, hat jedoch die Academie (mit wenig Stimmen Majorität) beschlossen, diesen Antrag <hi rend="underline">abzulehnen</hi>, weil “Professor Haeckel der eifrigste und gefährlichste Apostel der <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Darwinschen Irrlehren</hi> ist, und weil seine zoologischen Arbeiten ohne <hi rend="underline">wahren Werth</hi> sind. (!!)<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Ich habe nun heute an Sir John <hi rend="underline">Lubbock</hi> und an Prof. <hi rend="underline">Huxley</hi> gleichlautende Briefe gerichtet, mit der Bitte, ob sie vielleicht ein Reise-Stipendium (womöglich 400–500 £ Strl) von irgend einer gelehrten britischen Societät (vielleich <hi rend="underline">Royal Society</hi> oder <hi rend="underline">British Association</hi>) für mich erlangen können.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Zur Motivirung könnte angeführt werden, dass ich seit 5 Jahren für den “<hi rend="underline">Challenger</hi>” gratis arbeite (Die “Deep-Sea-Medusae”, mit 32 Tafeln, sind jetzt fertig; die Radiolaria (mit 120 Tafeln) halb fertig).<ref target="#foot.f6"/> An Sir Wyville Thomson, welcher mir Empfehlungen an den Gouverneur von Ceylon versprochen hat, habe ich ebenfalls geschrieben.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>An Sie, mein hochverehrter Freund, möchte ich nun die freundliche Bitte richten, mein Gesuch womöglich bei Gelegenheit zu unterstützen. Vielleicht können Sie mit Sir John Lubbock darüber conferiren.</p>
                    <p>Ihr Microscop von Zeiss ist hoffentlich nach Wunsch ausgefallen. Mein Freund, Prof. <hi rend="underline">Abbe</hi>, welcher bei Zeiss die feineren optischen Arbeiten beaufsichtigt, hatte mir versprochen, die <hi rend="underline">besten Linsen</hi> für Sie auszusuchen, und Mr. Zeiss selbst hat dafür gesorgt.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Sie sagten Beide selbst, dass für den Namen “<hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi>” <hi rend="underline">meine</hi> Empfehlung <hi rend="underline">überflüssig</hi> sei.</p>
                    <p>Wenn ich in Ceylon Etwas für Sie sammeln oder besorgen kann, wird es mein grösstes Vergnügen sein!</p>
                    <p>Hoffentlich geht es Ihnen gut! Mit herzlichsten Grüssen an Sie und an Ihre Familie Ihr | treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
                        
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>21. June 81.</date>
                    <salute>Dear and highly esteemed friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>In fulfilment of an ardent wish of mine, which I have entertained for 30 years, to one day see the wonders of tropical nature, I plan to spend next winter in <hi rend="underline">Ceylon</hi>. At the end of <hi rend="underline">September</hi>, I intend to go directly (via Suez, Bombay) to Colombo  to work for 4 months (partly in Point de Galle, partly in Trincomalee) and to return in April 1882.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I will study mainly Medusae and Radiolaria, besides drawing and painting a lot.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have recently learned oil-painting and photography, and I am well prepared for everything.</p>
                    <p>To cover the considerable costs of the trip, (in particular, to be able to do a lot of dredging and collecting) I had hoped to receive the “Humboldt-Stipendium” of the Berlin Academy, and my friends there had <hi rend="underline">firmly</hi> promised me last Easter that I would receive 15,000 Mark (= 750 £ Strl) from it for this purpose. At the crucial session last week, however, the academy decided (with a bare majority) to <hi rend="underline">turn down</hi> this proposal, on the grounds that “Professor Haeckel is the most ardent and most dangerous apostle of the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Darwinian heresy</hi>, and because his zoological work has no <hi rend="underline">true merit</hi>. (!!)<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
                    <p>Now I have today sent identical letters to Sir John <hi rend="underline">Lubbock</hi> and to Prof. <hi rend="underline">Huxley</hi>, with the request that perhaps they might be able to secure me a travel grant (if possible 400–500 £ Strl) from some learned British society (perhaps <hi rend="underline">Royal Society</hi> or <hi rend="underline">British Association</hi>).<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In justification, it could be stated that over the past 5 years I have been working free of charge for the “<hi rend="underline">Challenger</hi>” (the “Deep-Sea Medusae”, with 32 plates, are now complete; the Radiolaria (with 120 plates) are half-done).<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have written to Sir Wyville Thomson, who promised me a letter of recommendation to the governor of Ceylon, as well.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    <p>To you, my highly esteemed friend, I would kindly direct my request for your support, should the opportunity arise. Perhaps you could discuss it with Sir John Lubbock.</p>
                    <p>I hope your microscope from Zeiss has turned out as you wished. My friend, Prof. <hi rend="underline">Abbe</hi>, who is supervising the finer optical work at Zeiss, promised me to choose the <hi rend="underline">best lenses</hi> for you, and Mr Zeiss has taken care of it personally.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> They both told me that for the name “<hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi>” <hi rend="underline">my</hi> recommendation was <hi rend="underline">superfluous</hi>.</p>
                    <p>If there is anything that I could collect or get for you in Ceylon, it would be my greatest pleasure!</p>
                    <p>I hope you are well! With my most cordial greetings to you and to your family Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Haeckel</p>
                        
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Haeckel began his voyage to Ceylon (Sri Lanka) on 8 October 1881 and arrived back in Jena on 21 April 1882 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9852.xml">Haeckel 1883b</ref>, pp. 11, 337). Point de Galle (now Galle) is on the southernmost tip of the island; Trincomalee is a port city on the east coast. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Medusae are the free-swimming sexual forms of animals of the phylum Cnidaria; Haeckel published extensively on these (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10582.xml">Haeckel 1879–81</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11358.xml">Haeckel 1882</ref>). The order Radiolaria of the phylum Protozoa is composed of a diverse group of unicellular protozoans with siliceous skeletons; Haeckel proposed one of the earliest classification schemes for Radiolaria (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10225.xml">Haeckel 1887</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The Humboldt-Stiftung für Naturforschung und Reisen (Humboldt Foundation for Scientific Research and Travel) was administered by a group of trustees; for more on the rejection of his application and the supporters and opponents of Haeckel among the trustees, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11452.xml">Richards 2008</ref>, p. 345.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The letter of 21 June 1881 from Haeckel to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> and Huxley’s reply of 1 July 1881 are reproduced  in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7940.xml">Uschmann and Jahn 1959–60</ref>, pp. 26–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The scientific results of the dredging expedition of HMS <hi rend="italic">Challenger</hi> (1872–6) were published between 1880 and 1895. For Haeckel’s reports on Medusae and Radiolaria, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11358.xml">Haeckel 1882</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10225.xml">Haeckel 1887</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4730.xml">Charles Wyville Thomson</ref> was chief of the civilian scientific staff of the <hi rend="italic">Challenger</hi> expedition. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9313.xml">James Robert Longden</ref> was governor of Ceylon at this time.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-13044.xml">letter to Ernst Haeckel, 9 February 1881</ref>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5.xml">Ernst Abbe</ref> was a partner of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5294.xml">Carl Zeiss</ref> in his optical firm at Jena. The microscope was Stativ IV no. 3650, with condenser (manufactured on 11 November 1880) and included the objectives BB, DD, F, and K (ZEISS Archives). The microscope was for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Francis Darwin</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>