<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12464">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. J. Romanes   6 February 1880</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15522</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12464 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12464.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12464.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="28">28</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">E. D. Romanes 1896, p. 95</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Romanes, E. D. 1896: 95</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1880-02-06">6 Feb 1880</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thinks Herbert Spencer has done little service to science but a great service to thinking.</p>
            <p>Thinks importance of mathematics overestimated [by J. F. Moulton] in criticising Spencer.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3429">Moulton, J. F.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4495">Spencer, Herbert</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number, increase and decrease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-06" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-12-06" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2019-01-07" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2019-05-24" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2019-05-24" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-01-11" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>February 6, 1880.</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have to thank you very much for your two letters, and also for the enclosures from [Moulton], which I now return.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The latter convey exactly the criticism that I should have expected from [Moulton], for while writing my essay on Theism I had several conversations with him upon the subject of Spencer’s writings, and so know exactly what he thinks of them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> But in none of these conversations could I get at anything more definite than is conveyed by the returned letters. In no point of any importance did he make it clear to me that Spencer was wrong, and the only result of our conversation was to show me that in [Moulton’s] opinion it was only my ignorance of mathematics that prevented me from seeing that Mr. Spencer is merely a ‘word philosopher.’ Upon which opinion I reflected, and still reflect, that the mathematicians must be a singularly happy race, seeing that they alone of men are competent to think about the facts of the cosmos. And this reflection becomes still more startling when supplemented by another, viz. that although one may not know any mathematics, everybody knows what mathematics are: they are the sciences of number and measurement, and as such, one is at a loss to perceive why they should be so essentially necessary to enable a man to think fairly and well upon other subjects. But it is, as you once said, that when a man is to be killed by the sword mathematical, he must not have the satisfaction of even knowing how he is killed. Of course, in a general way I quite understand and agree with [Moulton] that Spencer has done but little service to science. But I believe that he has done great service to thinking, and all the mathematicians in the world would not convince me to the contrary, even though they should all deliver their judgment with the magnificent authority of a [Moulton].</p>
                    <p>Coming now to the diagram, I am much obliged to you for your suggestions. The ‘Descent of Man,’ with all its references upon the subject, and also your paper on the ‘Baby,’ were read, and the results embodied in the diagram, so I am very glad you did not take the needless trouble of consulting these works.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> By ‘Love’ I intend to denote the complex emotion (dependent on the representative faculties) which, having been so lately smitten myself, I am perhaps inclined to place in too exalted a position. But you did not observe that I placed ‘Parental Affection’ and ‘Social Feeling’ very much lower down.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In my essay I carefully explain the two cases of Drosera and Dionæa as being the best hitherto observed for my purpose in establishing the principle of discrimination among stimuli, as a principle displayed by non-nervous tissues.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See letters to G. J. Romanes, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12454.xml">3 February 1880</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12461.xml">5 February 1880</ref>. With the first of these letters, CD had enclosed letters to him from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3429.xml">John Fletcher Moulton</ref> of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12350.xml">10 December 1879</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12356.xml">13 December 1879</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 27). Moulton’s letters contained his comments on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2029.xml">Malcolm Guthrie</ref>’s critique of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml">Herbert Spencer</ref>’s views on CD’s theory of natural selection in <hi rend="italic">On Mr. Spencer’s formula of evolution</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9746.xml">Guthrie 1879</ref>). In the printed source of this letter, Moulton’s name has been replaced by dashes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10630.xml">[G. J. Romanes] 1878</ref>, Romanes had discussed ideas presented by Spencer in <hi rend="italic">First principles</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7366.xml">Spencer 1860–2</ref>), notably Spencer’s concept of ‘persistence of force’ ([G. J. Romanes] 1878, p. 88 and passim). See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12454.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 3 February 1880</ref> and n. 3. Moulton’s criticism of both Spencer and Guthrie centred on their apparent failure to understand many of the scientific terms and concepts they employed in their writing. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12461.xml">5 February 1880</ref>, CD had told Romanes that he would need to consult <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8641.xml">‘Biographical sketch of an infant’</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> before venturing to say anything on babies or animals.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Commenting on a diagram that later appeared in <hi rend="italic">Mental evolution in animals</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10553.xml">G. J. Romanes 1883</ref>, facing title page), CD expressed surprise that Romanes had not put the development of ‘love’ at an earlier stage (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12461.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 5 February 1880</ref> and n. 2). Romanes alludes to his marriage in February 1879 to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8371.xml">Ethel Duncan</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See G. J. Romanes 1883, pp. 49–51. Romanes had evidently mentioned a different case illustrating plant sensitivity in a now missing letter to CD; CD suggested that the types of sensitivity shown by <hi rend="italic">Drosera</hi> (sundew) and <hi rend="italic">Dionaea</hi> (Venus fly trap) were better examples (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12461.xml">letter to G. J. Romanes, 5 February 1880</ref> and n. 3).</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>