<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9611">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Henryk Stecki<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   29 August 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10791</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9611 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9611.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9611.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 252</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 252</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4540.xml">Stecki, Henryk</persName>
                <placeName>Zhitomir</placeName>
                <date when="1874-08-29">29 Aug 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports observations on a chicken with a human face.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">chicken</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Tros’cianica</placeName>
                    <date><formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>29</mn><mn>17</mn></mfrac></math></formula> Août 1874.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></date>
                    <salute>Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>La bienveillance avec laquelle vous avez bien voulu agréer la lettre que je vous ai écrite au commencement de cette année, m’enhardit à vous en écrire une autre pour soumettre à vos méditations scientifiques un fait extrêmement curieux et presque incroyable, qui s’est produit dans ma famille.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Dans mon enfance et ma jeunesse, j’ai toujours entendu parler d’une poule qui se trouvait chez une tante à moi, qui vit encore quoique fort âgée. C’etait une poule formée comme toutes les autres de corps, mais qui avait un visage humain. Ma tante l’a eue après sa grand’mère, pendant près de 10. ans; toute la contrée l’a connue, quant à moi, j’étais enfant alors, et ne l’ai vue que sur une portrait fait d’après nature.</p>
<p>Etant dernièrement en visite chez ma vieille tante, l’idée m’est venue de faire copier ce portrait pour vous l’envoyer. Il a si bien réussi, qu’il est difficile de distinguer la copie de l’original. Ce fait, tellement extraordinaire, peut paraître invraisemblable, et bien qu’aujourd’hui, il soit déjà assez difficile de trouver des personnes qui aient vu de leurs yeux ce monstre, je suis parvenu à me procurer trois signatures, que vous trouverez sur le revers du portrait ci-joint. Les signatures sont celles: de ma tante, d’une voisine à elle Madame Skorupska, et du curé de l’endroit, le Chanoine Wielobycki, prêtre respectable, qui ne connaissant pas les langues étrangères, a écrit son attestation en latin. J’espère que cette pièce curieuse ne déparera pas vos collections.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Voici les données que j’ai pu rassembler: La grand’mère de ma tante aimait beaucoup les oiseaux. Après sa mort, survenue, je crois, en 1822. ou 23. Madame Podhorodenska née Wilga,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> a hérité après elle de sa collection d’oiseaux différents, au nombre desquels se trouvait la poule en question. Cette dernière avait un nez très bien conformé, ainsi qu’une bouche garnie de six petites dents blanches, dont quatre en haut et deux en bas. Les yeux étaient ronds comme ceux d’une poule ordinaire. Comme elle n’avait pas de bec, on lui donnait des graines de froment et autres, pures et proprement nétoyées, qu’elle prenait avec ses lèvres et qu’elle croquait avec ses petites dents. Elle vecu à Holoby dans le Gouvernement de Volhynie,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> et comme je vous l’ai dit, Monsieur, toute la contrée l’a connue, et j’ai passé ma jeunesse à en entendre parler dans ma famille. On a voulu avoir de la postérité après elle, et elle est morte ne pouvant pas pondre ses oeufs, en 1832. Ma tante était alors abssente, et à son retour à Holoby, la poule n’existait plus; on avait enterré ce curieux phénomène de l〈a〉 nature, qu’il aurait fallu empailler. Je me suis informé après sa voix. Ma tante ne se souvient pas de l’avoir jamais entendue; mais le prêtre prétend, qu’elle produisait quelquefois un petit son habituel aux poules ordinaires. Sur le menton, elle avait quelques petites plumes en guise de poil. Voilà tout ce que j’ai pu apprendre sur le compte de cet être phénoménal.</p>
<p>Je vous prie, Monsieur, de vouloir bien accepter avec bienveillance ces détails, bien qu’incomplèts peut-être, ainsi que la photographie coloriée ci-jointe,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> et agréer l’expression des sentiments distingués de | Votre très humble serviteur | Henri Stecki</p>
<p>Je vous serai très reconnaissant, Monsieur, si vous vouliez me faire part de la réception de cet envoi, à l’adresse: Monsieur Henri Stecki, par Varsovie, Zytomir<ref target="#foot.f8"/> à Romanow, Gouvernement de Volhynie (Russie).</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Tros’cianica</placeName>
                    <date><formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>29</mn><mn>17</mn></mfrac></math></formula> August 1874.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></date>
                    <salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The benevolence with which you were so good as to accept the letter I wrote you at the beginning of this year, emboldens me to write you another in order to submit an extremely curious and almost incredible fact, which occurred in my family, to your scientific meditations.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Throughout my childhood and youth, I often heard tell of a hen belonging to an aunt of mine, who is still alive although very old. It was a hen shaped like any other in body, but which had a human face. My aunt had it from her grandmother, for nearly 10. years; the whole countryside knew it, as for me, I was then just a child, and only saw it in a portrait drawn from nature.</p>
<p>Being lately on a visit to my elderly aunt, the idea came to me to have this portrait copied in order to send it to you. It was so successful, that it is hard to distinguish the copy from the original. This fact is so extraordinary as perhaps to seem implausible, and even though it is already difficult to find people nowadays who saw this monster with their own eyes, I have managed to procure three signatures, which you will find on the reverse of the enclosed portrait. The signatures are those: of my aunt, of her neighbour Madame Skorupska, and of the local curé, Canon Wielobycki, a respectable priest, who, not knowing foreign languages, has written his attestation in Latin. I hope that this curious piece will not spoil the beauty of your collections.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Here are the facts I was able to collect: My aunt’s grandmother greatly loved birds. After her death, which, I believe, occurred in 1822. or 23. Madame Podhorodenska, née Wilga,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> inherited her collection of different birds, among which was to be found the hen in question. The latter had a very well-formed nose, as well as a mouth garnished with six small white teeth, four of which were at the top and two at the bottom. The eyes were round, like any ordinary chicken. As it had no beak, it was given grains of wheat and so on, pure and properly cleaned, which it took with its lips and chewed with its little teeth. It lived at Holoby in the Government of Volhynia,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> and as I told you, Sir, the whole countryside knew of it, and I heard about it all through my youth from my family. They wanted to obtain offspring from it, but it died egg-bound, in 1832. My aunt was absent at the time, and on her return to Holoby, the hen was no longer in existence; that curious phenomenon of nature had been buried, when it ought to have been stuffed. I enquired about its voice. My aunt could not remember ever having heard it; but the priest claimed, that it sometimes made a little noise common to ordinary fowl. On its chin it had a few small feathers of a hair-like sort. There you have all that I have been able to learn about this phenomenal being.</p>
<p>Please be so kind as to accept these details, though perhaps incomplete, with goodwill, Sir, as well as the coloured photograph enclosed,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and I remain | Your very humble servant | Henri Stecki</p>
<p>I should be most grateful, Sir, if you could inform me when you have received this letter, at the following address: Monsieur Henri Stecki, via Warsaw, Zytomir<ref target="#foot.f8"/> at Romanow, Government of Volhynia (Russia).</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Stecki gives both the Gregorian (29 August) and Julian (17 August) calendar dates. Troscianica: probably now Trostyanets’, L’viv oblast (district), Ukraine.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9366.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henryk Stecki, 18 March 1874</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Madame Skorupska and Canon Wielobycki have not been identified. The picture has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Madame Podhorodenska has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Holoby, central Volyn’ oblast, is now in north-west Ukraine. Volhynia was at the time a guberniya (province) of Russia (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The photograph has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Presumably Zhytomyr, a city now in north-west Ukraine.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>