<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4094F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Armand de Quatrefages<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   [14 April 1863]<ref target="#foot.f2"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20940</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4094F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4094F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4094F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete<ref target="#foot.f10"/></note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 11: 313–14 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"> <hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 378–9 </bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">BSAP 4 1863: 378–9</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date when="1863-04-14">[14 Apr 1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3892.xml">Quatrefages de Bréau, J. L. A. de</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>The niata is a very good case because the race is well established and must originate in South America. There is a description of the head by [Richard] Owen in the <hi rend="italic">Descriptive catalogue of the osteological collection of the College of Surgeons</hi>.</p>  
<p>Has observed modifications in the skeletons of rabbits, ducks, poultry, and pigeons. There is an extract about modifications in pigeons in the first chapter of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>. Encloses a woodcut of crested or polish fowls; there is a change in the brain as well as in the exterior bones.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">ducks</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">niata cow</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">pigeons</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">poultry</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descriptive catalogue of the osteological collection of the College of Surgeons</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, South</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Owen, Richard 1853</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ce nâta est pour vous, un cas excellent car la race est bien établie et doit tirer son origine de l’Amérique du Sud.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> C’est une race très-singulière. Une courte description de la tête a été faite par le professeur Owen dans le <hi rend="underline">Catalogue descriptif de la collection ostéologique du collège des chirurgiens</hi>, 1853 page 624. Vous y verrez que <hi rend="underline">la connexion des os</hi> est modifiée, car le maxillaire ne s’unit pas aux os du nez.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>En examinant un grand nombre de squelettes de lapins, de canards, de poulets et de pigeons, j’ai rencontré plusieurs modifications remarquables dans les squelettes; mais comme elles ne sont pas encore publiées, vous ne pourriez en tirer aucun parti.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Le pigeon Powter (grosse-gorge ou boulans) descendant certainement du <hi rend="underline">Columba Livia</hi>, est un cas intéressant car il a l’œsophage très-amplifié et modifié.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Dans le premier chapitre de mon <hi rend="underline">Origine de l’Espèce</hi>, vous trouverez un extrait des modifications remarquables chez les pigeons.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Les poulets ‘a crête, ou, comme nous les appelons, <hi rend="underline">polish fowls</hi>, sont un excellent cas;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> ils produisent parfaitement bien; autrefois, il n’y avait qu’un sexe dont le crâne fût affecté, maintenant les deux sexes sont affectés. J’insère ici une gravure sur bois très-bien faite.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> J’ai examiné beaucoup de crânes. Il y a un changement étonnant de forme dans le <hi rend="underline">cerveau lui-même</hi>, et dans <hi rend="underline">l’intérieur</hi> du crâne, en outre du changement des os extérieurs.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>This nãta is an excellent case for you because the race is well established and must derive its origin from South America.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It is a very singular race. A short description of the head was made by Professor Owen in the <hi rend="underline">Descriptive catalogue of the osteological collection of the College of Surgeons</hi>, 1853 page 624. You will see there that the <hi rend="underline">connection of the bones</hi> is modified, since the maxillary is not fused to the bones of the nose.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In examining a great number of skeletons of rabbits, ducks, poultry, and pigeons, I have observed several remarkable modifications in the skeletons, but since these are not yet published, they would not be of any use to you.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The Powter pigeon (inflated gullet or boulans) which undoubtedly descends from <hi rend="underline">Columba Livia</hi>, is an interesting case since it has a very enlarged and modified oesophagus.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>In the first chapter of my <hi rend="underline">Origin of species</hi> you will find a section about remarkable modifications in pigeons.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>The crested fowls, or, as we call them, <hi rend="underline">polish fowls</hi> are an excellent case;<ref target="#foot.f8"/> they reproduce perfectly well; in the past there was only one sex in which the skull was affected; now both sexes are affected. I am enclosing a very well drawn woodcut.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I have examined a great many skulls. There is an astonishing change of form in the <hi rend="underline">brain itself</hi> and in the <hi rend="underline">interior</hi> of the skull, besides the change in the external bones.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s original letter has not been found. For a translation of this text, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.11, Appendix I. The extant portion of the letter-text was published in the <hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 378–9. Quatrefages probably translated this portion for his presentation to the Société d’Anthropologie (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">CD’s original letter has not been found. For a transcription of this letter in French see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.11, p. 313. The extant portion of the letter-text was published in the <hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 378–9. Quatrefages probably translated this portion for his presentation to the Société d’Anthropologie (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The date was given by Quatrefages when he introduced the letter in a discussion at the Société d’Anthropologie on 16 July 1863 (<hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 378).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, [28 March –] 11 April 1863</ref> and nn. 7, 8, and 9. CD thought that niata were a useful example of the environment’s effect on anatomical form; the breed had been selected from cattle imported from Europe (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 88–91).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Niata were described in Owen [1853], 2: 3832 (see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 89–91). For Quatrefages’s presentation of photographs of the niata skull at discussions of the Société d’Anthropologie de Paris, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4171.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 19 May [1863]</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD published this material in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 103–304. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> was not published until 1868; Quatrefages read this letter of CD’s to the Société d’Anthropologie on 16 July 1863, and a report of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Bernhard Tegetmeier’s</ref> presentation of a Polish or crested breed of fowl to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Zoological Society of London</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863), pp. 378–80; see <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London</hi>, 25 November 1856, pp. 366–8). CD may have mentioned this Zoological Society report to Quatrefages in the missing portion of this letter; he cited his reliance on Tegetmeier’s information on poultry in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 225 (see nn. 8 and 9, below). Quatrefages briefly mentioned examples of variation in poultry to the Société d’Anthropologie on 7 May and 2 July (see <hi rend="italic">Bulletins de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris</hi> 4 (1863): 273, 350–1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">An engraving and description of the Pouter pigeon is provided in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 137–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 20–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The Polish or crested breed of fowl and its sub-breeds are described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 227–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The enclosure has not been found, but a woodcut of the Polish fowl appears in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 229.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The letter is considered incomplete since it does not include a salutation or valediction. In addition, Quatrefages probably translated only a portion of the letter from CD for his reading to the Société d’Anthropologie, and some further text may be missing (see n. 1, above).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>