<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5439">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Benjamin Clarke   12 March 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16427</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5439 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5439.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5439.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp encl 4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 157/1, 158</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 157/1, 158</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_944.xml">Clarke, Benjamin</persName>
                <placeName>Hampstead</placeName>
                <date when="1867-03-12">12 Mar 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Requests CD’s subscription to his <hi rend="italic">On systematic botany and zoology</hi> [1870]. "Progressive development" is a leading principle of his work.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">On systematic botany and zoology</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Clarke, Benjamin 1870</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00591_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00591_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="158:1r" xml:id="i591">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00591.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00591_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00591.dzi" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="158:1v" xml:id="i592">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00592.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00592_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00592.dzi" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="158:2r" xml:id="i593">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00593.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00593_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00593.dzi" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="158:2v" xml:id="i594">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00594.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00594_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00594.dzi" width="3135px" height="5308px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>2 Mount Vernon | Hampstead | N.W.</placeName>
                    <date>March 12 67.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have for a long time had in view the addition, to my work on the Natural System of Botany,<ref target="#foot.f1"/> of a new arrangement of the Classes of Zoology on principles closely analogous to those of the botanical Tables of that work, so as to combine the two systems into one system of Botany &amp; Zoology.</p>
<p>By this combination I hope &amp; even expect that they will materially assist in proving each other correct &amp; also explain each other &amp; so facilitate to students the study of both, there being many students in the present time who are initiated in Botany &amp; Zoology nearly at the same time.</p>
<p>The Table of the new arrangement of the Classes of Zoology is now ready for the press &amp; I write to request the favour of your subscription for the work with the zoological addition the price of which to those who have subscribed for the botanical work, &amp; therefore to you, will be only <hi rend="superscript">s</hi>10/– &amp; you will receive it carriage free.</p>
<p>The botanical part of the work is the same as that you have already received but the book will have a different title i.e. On Systematic Botany &amp; Zoology &amp; will contain 2 or 3 pages of letterpress or possibly more explanatory of the Zoological Table &amp; also 1 or 2 pages of botanical Addenda.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The botanical Addenda will I believe materially assist in proving the botanical arrangement, especially as regards the flowering plants, to be correct.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gray of the British Museum<ref target="#foot.f3"/> &amp; other Zoologists will favour me with their opinions of the Zoological Table before it is printed off.</p>
<p>The botanical arrangement I have every reason to believe is quite successful, especially in its principles, &amp; I have not heard of a single objection to it, so I am encouraged to proceed.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I beg to enclose a notice of progressive development believing it will interest you. It is presented as an addendum to the Tables in which progressive development is the leading principle, although there is no notice of that subject in the letterpress of the work.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I remain dear Sir | truly yours | Benj<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. Clarke. <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>On a mode of producing Varieties by Pruning.</p>
<p>About eight years since I commenced two experiments one on red wheat &amp; the other on white for the purpose of producing a six-set variety, i.e. six grains in a spikelet, three or four being the usual number in cornfields.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Before the plants flowered all the stems were cut away except one &amp; as soon as the ear was protruded the upper half was cut off, &amp; all the fresh shoots at the base of the stems were removed about once a week or fortnight till the ears were ripened.</p>
<p>The result was that the six-set was produced &amp; in the third year a seven-set spikelet, which as far as I know has not been observed by agriculturists &amp; it seemed very probable that eight-set could be produced.</p>
<p>The experiment which had only economical purposes in view was then discontinued because it was found that cutting off the upper half of the ear for only three years had the very singular effect of occasioning the upper half of the ear in the red wheat to be nearly barren &amp; shrivelled, &amp; of converting the upper half of that in the white into an unnaturally dense spike approaching that of Phalaris Canariensis;<ref target="#foot.f7"/> it was in this that the seven-set was produced. Would not this account for varieties with short spikes? A plant growing in barren ground would have unusually short spikes which in time might perhaps become a permanent variety.</p>
<p>One suggestion may be interesting. If the central bud of a Sun-flower were cut off when the plant was about a foot high, &amp; those of the lateral branches which sprouted afterwards when they became a few inches long &amp; the plant was then left to flower, I quite expect that a corymbous<ref target="#foot.f8"/> variety of the Sun-flower would be produced having many small heads in the place of one, which could be propagated by seed, &amp; the corymbs increased in density by continuing the pruning.</p>
<p>This leads to the inference that progressive development depends in great measure on the condition of the parents at the time of fertilization;— whatever that condition may be it is unalterably stamped on the offspring. But it appears to me that this is not the only cause of progressive development. Spontaneous generation although it has been regarded as unphilosophical is nevertheless it appears to me rendered most probable by Dactylium oogenum,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> &amp; if so it is in all probability a very common occurrence. This being the case, spontaneous alteration at the time of generation, not depending on the condition of the parents, would perhaps be a phenomenon not so unlikely to occur as otherwise might be supposed. The production of a nectarine on a peach tree I regard as an instance of this spontaneous alteration,<ref target="#foot.f10"/> &amp; at Hampstead there is an Elm tree one arm of which has an apparently different leaf, I think considerably smaller, &amp; much denser branches than the rest of the tree, which I suppose to arise from one of the buds having spontaneously a new mode of growth.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>If then buds at the time of generation can take on a new mode of growth, of course embryos can do the same, &amp; here we should have a prolific source of new varieties.</p>
<p>I therefore attribute progressive development to two causes which act either separately, or, not improbably, sometimes in conjunction.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Clarke refers to <hi rend="italic">A new arrangement of phanerogamous plants</hi> (Clarke 1866), a taxonomic work in which Clarke presented a natural system of botanical classification based on the position of the ovaries. Although CD’s name does not appear on the list of original subscribers to the privately published work (see Clarke 1866), he evidently bought a copy; he recorded a payment in his Account books–cash account (Down House MS) of £1 under the heading ‘Botanical book Clarke’ for 26 December 1866. CD’s copy has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Clarke’s new work, <hi rend="italic">On systematic botany and zoology</hi>, was published in 1870 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clarke 1870</ref>); CD recorded a payment in his Account books–cash account (Down House MS) of 10<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> under the heading ‘Syst. Bot. &amp; Zool<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> B. Clarke’ for 20 October 1870. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Clarke refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Edward Gray</ref>, who was the keeper of the zoological collections at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For CD’s view on the lack of criticism of Clarke 1866, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5445.xml" resp="#automat">letter to J. D. Hooker 17 March [1867]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The tables in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1425.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clarke 1870</ref> are arranged to show a genealogical relationship among the different classes, but this relationship is not noted in the accompanying text.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Red and white wheat are varieties of <hi rend="italic">Triticum aestivum</hi>, common bread-wheat (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Peterson 1965</ref>, p. 15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The reference is to <hi rend="italic">Phalaris canariensis</hi> or canary grass, which has spike-like panicles that resemble those of club wheat (<hi rend="italic">Triticum compactum</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Corymbous: i.e. corymbose.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Dactylium oogenum</hi> is a species of anamorphic fungus (that is, a fungus persisting in an asexual state). Clarke evidently believed its occurrence was the result of spontaneous generation. On the Victorian debates over spontaneous generation, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Strick 2000</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD noted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 340 that there was considerable evidence of peach trees producing nectarines by bud-variation. CD defined bud-variation as including ‘all those sudden changes in structure or appearance’ that occasionally occurred ‘in full-grown plants in their flower-buds or leaf-buds’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 373).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 390–4, CD considered certain cases of bud-variations that gave rise to different forms of growth on a single plant as consequences of reversion.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>