<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10548">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Bruno Schreiber<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   24 June 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10642</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10548 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10548.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10548.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German) †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 63</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 63</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4236.xml">Schreiber, Bruno</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1876-06-24">24 June 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes cosmological ideas of Christian Radenhausen.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3908">Radenhausen, Christian</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Leipzig | Windmühlenstr. 33. 1. Etg.</placeName>
                    <date>d. 24. Juni 1876.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrtester Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Verzeihen Sie, wenn ich mir erlaube, mit einer Bitte mich Ihnen zu nähern.</p>
<p>Ich bin der Verzeihung gewiß, denn ich vertraue auf Ihre unendliche Güte. Ich möchte gern Ihre Ansicht hören, über meine Meinung, daß zwei hervorragende Männer zu einer gewissen Zeit, sich immer gegenseitig ergänzen.</p>
<p>Schon in den frühesten Zeiten finde ich es, bei Jesus und Johannes dem Täufer, später dann bei Wolfram v. Eschenbach und Walther von der Vogelweide, Leibnitz und Newton, Schiller und Göthe und in der Gegenwart, erlauben Sie mir zu sagen Darwin und Radenhausen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Gestatten Sie mir, dies etwas näher zu beleuchten.</p>
<p>C. Radenhausen, dessen persönliche Bekanntschaft zu machen, ich die Gelegenheit hatte, unternimmt in seinem neuesten Werke Osiris (Weltgesetze in der Erdgeschichte),<ref target="#foot.f3"/> eine Kosmogenie zu begründen, und zwar eine Kosmogenie, welche mit Ihrer Lehre, sehr geehrter Herr, trefflich harmonirt.</p>
<p>C. Radenhausen ist der Ansicht, dass sich die Erde durch anschliessen angezogener Weltkörperchen und Weltgasen gebildet habe. Er theilt die Geschichte der Erde in eine:</p>
<p>Kältezeit, die Verbindung “Wasser” noch starr gefroren.</p>
<p>Hierauf folgt nach ihm:</p>
<p>Feuer- und Frostzeit.</p>
<p>Wasserzeit.</p>
<p>Warmzeit, Wasserbereich über die ganze Erdoberfläche verbreitet.</p>
<p>Endlich wird der Wolkenbereich erweitert und das Leben auf Erden geht zu Grunde.</p>
<p>Ich bin nicht wenig gespannt, zu hören, was Sie dazu sagen werden.</p>
<p>Nochmals um Verzeihung bittend | verbleibe ich | Mit aller Hochachtung | Ihr ergebenster | Bruno Schreiber | stud. pharm.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Leipzig | Windmühlenstr. 33. 1. Floor.</placeName>
                    <date>June 24 1876.</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Forgive me for taking the liberty of approaching you with a request.</p>
<p>I am certain of forgiveness, for I trust in your endless benevolence. I should like to hear your view of my opinion that two outstanding men of a certain time always complement one another.</p>
<p>I find this already in the most ancient times, with Jesus and St John the Baptist, later with Wolfram von Eschenbach and Walther von der Vogelweide, Leibnitz and Newton, Schiller and Göthe and in the present, permit me to say, Darwin and Radenhausen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Allow me to clarify this somewhat. C. Radenhausen who I had the opportunity to become personally acquainted with, in his latest work Osiris (Weltgesetze der Erdgeschichte),<ref target="#foot.f3"/> attempts to lay the foundations for a cosmogeny, namely a cosmogeny that is in perfect harmony with your doctrine, most honoured Sir.</p>
<p>C. Radenhausen takes the view that the earth developed through the linking of world corpuscules and world gases that attract one another. He divides the history of the earth into an:</p>
<p>Ice age, the compound “water” still frozen stiff.</p>
<p>According to him then follow:</p>
<p>Age of fire and of frost</p>
<p>Water period</p>
<p>Warm period, water zone over the whole surface of the earth.</p>
<p>Finally the cloud zone expands and life on earth becomes extinct.</p>
<p>I am not a little anxious to hear what you have to say about this.</p>
<p>Once more begging your forgiveness | I remain | With the profoundest respect | Yours most devoted | Bruno Schreiber | stud. pharm.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 219–20.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7677.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wolfram von Eschenbach</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7678.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Walter von der Vogelweide</ref> were the foremost German epic and lyric poets, respectively, of their time. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2872.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3519.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Isaac Newton</ref> developed calculus independently. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7679.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich von Schiller</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref> were poets, philosophers, and friends. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Radenhausen</ref> was an engineer and philosophical writer.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">There is a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9303.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Radenhausen 1874–6</ref> (Osiris: world laws in the history of the earth) in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>