<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2703">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   18 [and 19 February 1860]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">199</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2703 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2703.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2703.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">10pp</note>
            <note type="postmark">FE 20 60</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 232</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 140</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 92</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.199)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>199</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1860-02-18">18 [Feb 1860]</date>
                <date when="1860-02-19">[19 Feb 1860]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Encloses reviews by Asa Gray and Bronn. Comments on Bronn review. Mentions review by Wollaston.</p> 
<p>Comments on paper by W. H. Harvey in <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi> [(1860): 145–6]. Discusses Harvey’s belief in the permanence of monsters.</p> 
            <p>Discusses CL’s objection that still-living primitive forms failed to develop.</p> 
<p>The survival of <hi rend="italic">Lepidosiren</hi> and other primitive types of fish and mammals.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Lepidosiren</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Gardeners’ Chronicle</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1860a</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Harvey, W. H. 1860</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">monstrosity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I send by this Post, Asa Gray which seems to me very good, with the stamp of originality on it.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> Also Bronn’s out Jahrbuch fur Mineralogie.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The united intellect of my family has vainly tried to make it out.—   I never tried such confoundedly hard German: nor does it seem worth the labour.—   He sticks to Priestley’s green matter &amp; seems to think that till it can be shown how life arises, it is no good showing how the forms of life arise.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> This seems to me about as logical (comparing very great things with little) as to say it was no use in Newton showing laws of attraction of gravity &amp; consequent movements of the Planets, because he could not show what the attration of Gravity is.—</p>
<p>The expression “wahl der lebensweise” makes me doubt whether B. understands what I mean by natural selection,—as I have told him.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> He says (<hi rend="underline">if I understand him</hi>) that you ought to be on same side with me.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Ever yours affec<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi> | C. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. | Sunday afternoon | I have kept back this to thank you for your letter with much news received this morning.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> My conscience is uneasy at the time you waste in amusing &amp; interesting me.—   I was very curious to hear about Phillips.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The Review in Annals <hi rend="underline">is</hi>, as I was convinced, by Wollaston; for I have had very cordial letter from him this morning.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I send by this Post an attack in G. Chroni. by Harvey (a first-rate Botanist as you probably know).<ref target="#foot.f9"/> It seems to me rather strange: he assumes the permanence of monsters, whereas monsters are generally sterile &amp; not often inheritable. But grant his case it comes that I have been too cautious in not admitting great &amp; sudden variations. Here again comes in the mischief of my <hi rend="underline">Abstract</hi>: in fuller M.S. I have discussed parallel case of a normal fish like a monstrous Gold-fish: I end my discussion by <hi rend="underline">doubting</hi>, because all cases of monstrosities which resemble normal structures, which I could find were not in allied groups.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Trees like Aspicarpa with flowers of two kinds, (in the Origin) led me also to speculate on same subject;<ref target="#foot.f11"/> but I could find only one doubtfully analogous case of species having flowers like the degraded or monstrous flowers.— Harvey does not see that if only a few (as he supposes) of the seedlings inherited his monstrosity natural selection would be necessary to select &amp; preserve them.— You had better return G. Chron. &amp;c &amp;c to my Brother’s.—</p>
<p>The case of Begonia in itself is very curious: I am tempted to answer the notice, but I will refrain for there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be no end to answers.</p>
<p>With respect to your objection of multitude of still living simple forms, I have not discussed it anywhere in the Origin, though I have often thought it over.— What you say about “progress being only occasional &amp; retrogression not uncommon” I agree to; only that in animal kingdom I greatly doubt about retrogression being <hi rend="underline">common</hi>.—   I have always put it to myself what advantage can we see in an infusory animal, or an intestinal worm—or coral-polyps—or earth-worm being highly developed? If no advantage, they would not become highly developed,— not but what all these animals have very complex structures (except infusoria) &amp; they may well be higher than the animals which occupied similar places in the economy of nature before the Silurian Epoch.—   There is a blind snake, with appearance &amp; in some respects (Perhaps falsely appearing so) habits of worm, but this blind snake does not tend, as far as we can see, to replace &amp; drive out worms. I think I must in any future Edit. discuss a few more such points— &amp; will introduce this &amp; H. C. Watson’s objection about infinite number of species—&amp; the general rise in organisation.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> But there is a directly opposite objection to yours, which is very difficult to answer, viz how at first start of life, when there were only simplest organisms, how did any complication of organisation profit them? I can only answer that we have not facts enough to guide any speculation on the subject.—</p>
<p>With respect to Lepidosiren Ganoid Fishes, perhaps Ornithorhynchus I suspect, as stated in Origin, that they have been preserved from inhabiting F. Water &amp; isolated parts of world, in which there has been less competition &amp; less rapid progress in Nat. Selection, owing to the fewness of individuals which can inhabit small areas. &amp;c &amp;c—&amp; where there are few individuals, variation almost must be slower.—<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>There are several allusions to this notion in the Origin— as under Amblyopsis the blind cave fish. &amp; under Heer about Madeira plants resembling fossil &amp; extinct plants of Europe.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>With hearty thanks for all your kindness—</p>
<p>Yours affect<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.8 the Planets] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.1 lebensweise’] <hi rend="italic">before omitted quotation marks</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.2 My] ‘M’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">5.8 groups] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘cases’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">6.1 with flowers of two kinds] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">6.3 of species … flowers.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">6.4 (as he supposes)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">7.1 is] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">7.2 I will] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘per’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">8.4 agree] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘qui’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">8.6 an intestinal] ‘an’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">8.6 worm] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘work’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">8.7 highly developed,—-] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘so;—-’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">8.11 (Perhaps … so)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">8.12 any future] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">8.13 such] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">8.13 H.] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">8.14 about infinite … species] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">8.17 ?] <hi rend="italic">over full stop</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">9.3 &amp; less … Nat. Selection, 9.4] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">9.5 &amp; where … be slower.—- 9.6] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>


            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">[Gray] 1860a. See preceding letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Bronn 1860a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn’s</ref> assertion that CD’s theory of evolution was incomplete until it could account for the initial creation of organic matter from inorganic elements. He referred to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3866.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Priestley’s</ref> report of having isolated in a sealed glass jar ‘green matter’ that was neither animal nor vegetable in nature ‘but a thing <hi rend="italic">sui generis</hi>’ (Priestley 1779–86, 1: 342). Bronn also discussed the recent debate in France over <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3833.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Félix Archimède Pouchet’s</ref> claim to have produced unicellular organisms through spontaneous generation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6384.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pouchet 1859</ref>). This passage is scored in CD’s copy of Bronn 1860a, p. 114, which is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. For a translation of Bronn 1860a, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hull 1973</ref>, pp. 120–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2698.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. G. Bronn, 14 February [1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The passage to which CD refers follows a discussion of the evidence for metamorphic processes in some of the oldest geological formations, which bears on the question of the existence of life before the Silurian period. The passage contains an element of ambiguity (Bronn 1860a, p. 115): <quote type="quote"> Ja Lyell nimmt bekanntlich einen endlosen Wechsel-Prozess dieser Art an; daher wir kürzlich nicht ohne einige Überraschung fanden, dass er die Darwin’sche Schrift denjenigen Geologen entgegenhält, welche an eine progressive Entwickelung der organischen Welt glauben. [Indeed Lyell assumes, as is well known, a continual process of change of this sort [metamorphic processes]; therefore it is not without some surprise that we have recently found that he contrasts Darwin’s writing with those geologists who believe in a progressive development of the organic world.] </quote> Bronn believed that CD’s theory necessarily entailed a tendency toward progression of organisms, a principle that Lyell vehemently rejected (Bronn 1860a, p. 115). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hull 1973</ref>, p. 123.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Lyell’s letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">John Phillips discussed <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in his presidential address to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2696.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 14 February [1860]</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Vernon Wollaston</ref> has not been found. CD refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Wollaston] 1860</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">A letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Harvey</ref>, professor of botany at Trinity College, Dublin, was published in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle and</hi> <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Gazette</hi>, 18 February 1860, pp. 145–6. Harvey gave the example of <hi rend="italic">Begonia frigida</hi>, in which it appeared that a new species had originated through the abnormal development of the existing form. If this proved to be the case, he stated, CD’s ‘theory would receive a serious damage’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 145). Lyell included in his scientific journal a brief memorandum about Harvey’s article (Wilson ed. 1970, p. 353).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD discussed his belief that monstrosities could not give rise to new specific forms in his unpublished ‘big species book’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 318–21).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 417. Lyell recorded CD’s statement in his scientific journal (Wilson ed. 1970, p. 353).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4975.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hewett Cottrell Watson</ref> discussed this objection in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2636.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of [3? January 1860]</ref>. CD had sent the letter to Lyell and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (see letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">4 [January 1860]</ref>, and to T. H. Huxley, 11 January [1860]). CD discussed these and other objections to his theory in the third edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, in a new section entitled ‘On the degree to which organisation tends to advance.—’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed.</ref>, pp. 133–43).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 130.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 139, 107.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>