<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-440">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Emma Wedgwood   [21 November 1838]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7421</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-440 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-440.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-440.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 210.8:5</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>210.8:5</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gt Marlborough St, 36</placeName>
                <date when="1838-11-21">[21 Nov 1838]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml">Wedgwood, Emma</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Recounts his misadventures on the train journey back to London. Tells of a visit to the FitzRoys and a friendly letter from Lyell. Whether CD and Emma should live in central London or in the suburbs is a perplexing problem, much discussed by relatives and friends.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">London</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, domestic life</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">train journey</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>[36 Great Marlborough Street]</placeName>
                    <date>Wednesday Morning 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> <ref target="#foot.f1"/></date>
                    <salute>My dear Emma</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been writing letters all morning, &amp; before I go to the Geolog Soc. I shall amuse myself by giving you an account of my travels.— The train was retarded by the high winds, &amp; a rumour passed from one carriage to the other, that we possibly should miss the London train.— Accordingly as we entered the station-yard at Bermingham, we saw the London train start, &amp; they would not wait even the five minutes necessary just to jump into the carriages.— The indignation of all us unfortunates was immense.— I can laugh now, though I could not then, at the expression of all faces, as each group turned out of its carriage, like bees out of a hive.— nothing could be heard, but “infamous, scandalous conducts.— directors, parliament rascals.” &amp;c.— One high-minded passenger avenged himself, there being nobody to abuse excepting porters, by going to London in a night horse coach, much to his inconvenience.—</p>
<p>I took another line, &amp; comforted myself with a beef steak &amp; tea, &amp; then went to bed at 5 oclock with orders, which greatly amused the chamber maids, to be called at <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> before eleven to go by <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> past 11 night train. I did [not] sleep, but enjoyed a nice quiet cogitation over the few last days, &amp; the prospect of the long future &amp; the realization of my day dreams.— At the proper time I got into the London train, with my temper somewhat soured by the cold &amp; wet night, &amp; found for my companions three Manchester hogs, who passed the whole night in playing whist on one of the cushions, drinking huge quantities of brandy &amp; water &amp; singing half-blasphemous songs. I was right glad to escape out of such a hogsty &amp; reach my lodging at half past six in the morning.—</p>
<p>After having settled &amp; sorted divers papers I started to tell the news to the Captain.— You see I am treating you, as if you were my actual wife, &amp; giving you an account of all my doings as I hope to do for many a long year my own dear Emma.— The Captain &amp; Madam were most cordial, &amp; both, especially the former highly approved of my conduct: he says we shall not know, what real happiness there is in man &amp; woman living together, till we have tried it for at least six months.— I dare say there may be some truth in this, though I suspect the time of probation will be a good deal shorter with us.— I wish it began rather earlier,—though I humbly beg pardon for saying so, &amp; will not again.— But when I think of those few hours, when we sat together in the Library, hope deferred does make my heart quite sick to call you in truth my wife.— M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> FitzRoy &amp; the Captain gave me sundry good hints about houses,—the more I hear on this subject, the more I perceive that it is really a very perplexing one.— In three or four days I shall commence taking systematic walks, to settle as far as the general situation is concerned.— I believe you are right in choosing a central region, at least for the first year or two. Erasmus highly approves of this choice,—though FitzRoy was so strong against it, that he almost staggered me. I will report progress, as I go on acquiring hints &amp; knowledge.—</p>
<p>I have received a letter from Lyell, forwarded from Shrewsbury, which has pleased me extremely.— it is most cordial &amp; almost affectionate as if from a relation.— M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Lyell added a postscript, in which she says, “your letter caused us some <hi rend="underline">surprise</hi>”. I do not know whether this is meant as a gentle scold,—but it looks like it.—</p>
<p>Erasmus met mother-in law<ref target="#foot.f2"/> at M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Warren’s, &amp; he says he could not help looking guilty, as if he was speaking to an ill-used woman.— Mother in law exclaimed, “oh this is the reason he would not come near us of late.”— I dined with Erasmus in the evening &amp; Robert came in.— I have not room to give an account of his affairs, nor indeed do I clearly understand them,—but he seems bent, on prosecuting the Brighton Paper. he also said, he thought it not impossible, that L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Palmerston intended to deprive the country of his diplomatic services.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But I trust from what he afterwards said, this will not be the the case.— Alderson<ref target="#foot.f4"/> has been very goodnatured in consulting over his affair. It appears that Robert is afraid the Public will never believe that any man would give 500£ to free a man, without some motive, such as wishing to prevent the disclosing some secret.</p>
<p>This appears to me not an improbable &amp; most odious interpretation which will be put on the affair if it gets into the newspaper.—</p>
<p>Good bye my dearest good girl | C. D.</p>
<p>I have not space to say half I wish to say.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.8 turned out] ‘out’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.8 a] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.11 horse] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.9 escape] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.10 six] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.14 the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.15 a] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.16 Erasmus] ‘E’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘&amp;’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">4.1 a letter] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">5.3 he would] ‘he’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘she’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">5.6 bent,] <hi rend="italic">before del</hi> ‘&amp; I suspect against’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">5.11 prevent] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">5.11 disclosing] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘criminal’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14"><hi rend="italic">point omitted after</hi> : 3.17 ‘progress’; 5.8 ‘from’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Misdated by CD. 21 November 1838, the date of the postmark, was a Wednesday.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Anne <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2389.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Susan Horner</ref>, Mrs <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2392.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Leonard Horner</ref>, Lyell’s mother-in-law.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Robert Mackintosh had returned from a consulship in America in June 1838 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wedgwood 1980</ref>, p. 232) and was waiting for another appointment. Palmerston was Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs at the time.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_66.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Hall Alderson</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>