<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2861F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">To <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4883.xml">Queen Victoria</ref>   [2 July 1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">22065</idno>
                
                
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2861F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2861F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2861F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt> 
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="30">30-Supplement</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="description">Memorial</note>
                <note type="physdesc" n="Mem"/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10989.xml">National Sunday League [1860]</ref></bibl>
                <bibl type="printedSource">National Sunday League [1860]</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                    <date when="1860-07-02">[2 July 1860]</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4883.xml">Victoria, queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and empress of India</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc><abstract>
                <p>With 942 others petitions Queen Victoria for museums, art galleries and libraries to open on Sunday afternoons for the benefit of those who work during the week.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-09-23" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="raclarkson">Rosy Clarkson</name></change>
            <change when="2020-11-18" status="sup-footnoted">Footnoted <name xml:id="sevans">Sam Evans</name></change>
            <change when="2021-05-13" status="sup-reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
            <change when="2021-06-18" status="initialProofCompleted">Proofread by <name xml:id="elsmith">Liz Smith</name></change>
        <change when="2021-08-11" status="sup-finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread for vol. 30 supplement by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <salute><hi rend="print">TO HER MOST GRACIOUS MAJESTY VICTORIA, BY THE GRACE OF GOD OF THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND IRELAND, QUEEN, DEFENDER OF THE FAITH.</hi></salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        <p><hi rend="print">The Memorial of the undersigned connected with Literature, Science, and the Fine Arts, Professors of divers Universities, &amp;c., &amp;c.,</hi></p>
                        <p rend="left"><hi rend="print">HUMBLY SHEWETH,</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="print">That your Memorialists take it for granted that Museums and other collections of a similar character are established for the instruction and moral improvement of the people; and that in proportion as such Institutions are made available for popular education do they fulfil the purposes of their origin.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="print">That the labors and necessary avocations of the great body of the community leave little or no opportunity of visiting such Institutions during the week, when they are open to the public, and hence that the main object of their formation is lost to those whom they are intended to benefit.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="print">The Sunday, as a day of rest and leisure, when the thoughts of men, released from the engrossing labor of mere existence, turn naturally to the beauties of the Universe, and to its Creator, is the time most fitted for the exercise of the reflective faculties; and your Memorialists being firmly convinced that all true education must tend to the reverence and love of the Deity, believe that if such Institutions as above enumerated were open to the people on Sunday Afternoon, it would be an inestimable boon to the laboring population, would raise up an opposing principle to intemperance and immorality, and in every way advance the condition of the people.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="print">YOUR MEMORIALISTS therefore pray your Majesty to lend your Royal countenance to remove all restrictions and impediments, so that the National Museums, Picture Galleries, Botanical Gardens, and similar collections, as well as those of parochial or municipal foundation throughout the United Kingdom, may be opened to the public on Sunday Afternoon.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></hi></p>
                      <p><hi rend="print">Charles Darwen, M.A., F.R.S., F.G.S.</hi> [and 942 others]<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                
                
                
                
            </div>
            
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is provided in the pamphlet from which the text of this memorial has been transcribed.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">The National Sunday League was founded in 1855, at first with the aim of securing the opening of museums and other institutions on a Sunday, and later with the aim of permitting Sunday excursions, musical performances, and lectures. In London, the campaign to secure Sunday opening of national museums and art galleries did not succeed until 1896, although some municipal institutions introduced Sunday opening earlier. (See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9905.xml">Stoddard 1896</ref>, pp. 477–8.) For more on the League’s anti-Sabbatarian objectives and promotion of ‘rational recreation’, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11743.xml">McVeigh 2019</ref>, pp. 41–2.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s name (spelled Darwen) appears in the Appendix to the pamphlet, with nine other names, introduced as follows: ‘The sheets with the following names appended were lost in the transmission’.</note>
            </div>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>