<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9126">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From T. H. Huxley   3 November 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3429A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9126 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9126.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9126.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Huxley (1900) 1: 403</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 329</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 329</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Athenaeum Club</placeName>
                <date when="1873-11-03">3 Nov 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>W. H. Flower is ill and obliged to go off for six months. Wants to return the money Flower contributed to fund for his holiday, asks the amount.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1670">Flower, W. H.</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">holiday</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Athenæum Club | Pall Mall</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. 1873</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You will have heard, (in fact I think I mentioned the matter when I paid you my pleasant visit the other day) that Flower is ill &amp; obliged to go away for six months to a warm climate—<ref target="#foot.f1"/> It is a great grief to me as he is a man for whom I have great esteem &amp; affection apart from his high scientific merits—and his symptoms are such as to cause very grave anxiety— I shall be happily disappointed if that accursed consumption has not got hold of him—</p>
<p>The College Authorities have behaved as well as they possibly could to him and I do not suppose that his enforced retirement, for a while, gives him the least pecuniary anxiety as his people are all well off—&amp; he himself has an income apart from his College pay— Nevertheless, under such circumstances a man with half a dozen children always wants all the money he can lay hands on; and whether he does or no, he ought not to be allowed to deprive himself of any—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Which leads me to the gist of my letter— His name was on your list as one of those hearty friends who came to my rescue last year; and it was the only name which made me a little uneasy—for I doubted whether it was right for a man with his responsibilities, to make sacrifices of this sort<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>However, I stifled that feeling not seeing what else I could do without wounding him— But now my conscience won’t let me be; and I do not think that any consideration ought to deter me from getting his contribution back to him some how or other— There is no one to whose judgment on a point of honour I would defer more readily than yours—and I am quite sure you will agree with me— I really am quite unhappy &amp; ashamed to think of myself as vigorous &amp; well at the expense of his denying himself any rich man’s caprice he might take a fancy to—</p>
<p>So my dear good friend let me know what his contribution was that I may get it back to him somehow or other—even if I go like Nicodemus privily &amp; by night to his bankers—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Ever | Yours faithfully | T. H. Huxley</p>
<p>Not one solitary moment have I had to devote to <hi rend="underline">Nitella</hi> yet<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Huxley refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1670.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Flower</ref>. Huxley visited Down on 25 and 26 October 1873 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 26 October [1873]</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin’s</ref> diary (DAR 242)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In 1870, Flower had replaced Huxley as Hunterian Professor of comparative anatomy and physiology at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4102.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal College of Surgeons of England</ref>. He had three sons and three daughters; his father founded Flower’s brewery in Stratford-upon-Avon in 1831 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Flower contributed to the subscription fund raised by Huxley’s personal friends in April 1873 to relieve his financial problems (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8876.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to subscribers to T. H. Huxley’s gift, [25 April 1873]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Huxley alludes to the biblical story of Nicodemus’s coming to prepare Jesus’s body by night (John 19: 39).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Nitella</hi> is a genus of branched, multicellular algae, commonly known as stoneworts.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>