<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-1480">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To T. H. Huxley   23 April [1853]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3204</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-1480 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1480.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-1480.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="05">5</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 145: 151</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 73</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 5: 133</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 4)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 4</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1853-04-23">23 Apr [1853]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>On THH’s paper on cephalous Mollusca [<hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond.</hi> 143 (1853) pt 1: 29–66]. Discovery of the type or "idea" (in THH’s sense, not Owen’s or Agassiz’s) is one of the highest ends of natural history.</p> 
            <p>Discusses anamorphism;</p> 
<p>position of heart in <hi rend="italic">Cleodora</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Variability within species;</p>
            <p>cementing process in cirripedes.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cirripedes</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Cleodora</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Mollusca, cephalous</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Huxley, T. H. 1853</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">archetypes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cirripedes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Farnborough Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Ap. 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>I have got out all the specimens, which I have thought could by any possibility be of any use to you;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but I have not looked at them, &amp; know not what state they are in, but sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be much pleased if they are of the smallest use to you. I enclose a catalogue of Habitats: I thought my notes w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have turned out of more use: I have copied out such few points as perhaps w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. not be apparent in preserved specimens.— The Bottle shall go to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gray<ref target="#foot.f3"/> on Thursday next by our weekly carrier.—</p>
<p>I am very much obliged for your Paper on the mollusca;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I have read it all with much interest; but it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be ridiculous in me to make any remarks on a subject on which I am so utterly ignorant; but I can see its high importance. The discovery of the type or “idea” (in <hi rend="underline">your</hi> sense, for I detest the word as used by Owen, Agassiz &amp; Co) of each great class, I cannot doubt is one of the very highest ends of Natural History:<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; certainly most interesting to the worker out. Several of your remarks have interested me; I am, however, surprised at what you say versus “anamorphism”: I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have thought that the archetype in imagination was always in some degree embryonic, &amp; therefore capable &amp; <hi rend="underline">generally undergoing</hi> further development.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Is it not an extraordinary fact, the great difference in position of the heart in different species of Cleodora?<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I am a believer that when any part usually constant differs considerably in different <hi rend="underline">allied</hi> species; that it will be found in some degree <hi rend="underline">variable</hi>, within the limits of the same species:—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Thus, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. expect that if great numbers of specimens of some of the species of Cleodora had been examined with this object in view, the position of the heart in some of the species, w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have been found variable.— Can you aid me with any analogous facts?</p>
<p>I am very much pleased to hear that you have not given up the idea of noticing my Cirripedia volume.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> All that I have seen since confirms everything of any importance stated in that volume. More especially I have been able rigorously to confirm, in an anomalous species, by the clearest evidence, that the actual cellular contents of the ovarian tubes, by the gland-like action of a modified portion of the <hi rend="underline">continuous</hi> tube, passes into the cementing stuff:<ref target="#foot.f10"/> in fact cirripedes make glue out of their own unformed eggs!.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Pray believe me | Yours sincerely | C. Darwin</p>
<p>I told the above case to Milne Edwards &amp; I saw he did not place the smallest belief in it.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">3.2 usually constant] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi>; <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>‘t’ <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">3.6 the heart] <hi rend="italic">after illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">4.2 Cirripedia] <hi rend="italic">interl and altered from</hi> ‘Cirripedial’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">4.4 confirm,] <hi rend="italic">before omitted comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.4 in an] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the by’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 11 April [1853]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s collection of ascidians from the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 11 April [1853]</ref>). He also enclosed notes extracted from his zoological diary of the voyage (DAR 30.2: 167–73).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1959.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Edward Gray</ref>, keeper of the zoological department, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8646.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">British Museum</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3995.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">T. H. Huxley 1853b</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3995.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">T. H. Huxley 1853b</ref> was primarily concerned with establishing an archetype for the cephalous Mollusca. Huxley, although using the term ‘archetype’ coined by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref>, expressly distanced his particular usage from any idealistic connotations, stating (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 50): <quote> I make no reference to any real or imaginary ‘ideas’ upon which animal forms are modelled. All that I mean is the conception of a form embodying the most general propositions that be affirmed respecting the Cephalous Mollusca, standing in the same relation to them as the diagram to a geometrical theorem, and like it at once imaginary and true. For both Huxley and CD, the archetype of a class was suggested by comparative embryology and was a hypothetical structure representing general anatomical uniformities (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix II and di Gregorio 1984, pp. 22–35). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3629.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Owen</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>, on the other hand, believed in a Platonic archetype (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1982</ref>, pp. 42–4).</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Huxley denied the existence of transitional forms between archetypes. ‘Anamorphism’, as he used the term, denoted a progression from a lower to a higher type, which he doubted ever occurred: ‘It may indeed be a matter of very grave consideration whether true anamorphosis ever occurs in the whole animal kingdom. If it do, then the doctrine that every natural group is organized after a definite archetype, a doctrine which seems to me as important for zoology as the theory of definite proportions for chemistry, must be given up.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3995.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">T. H. Huxley 1853b</ref>, p. 63). See di Gregorio 1984, p. 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3995.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1853</ref>, p. 42 and Plate IV.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD repeated this rule in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 307, where he attributed it to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4972.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Robert Waterhouse</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8192.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Waterhouse 1846–8</ref>, 2: 452 n. 1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1514.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to T. H. Huxley, 11 April [1853]</ref>, and n. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Proteolepas bivincta</hi>, which CD classified as the sole species of a new order, Apoda. <hi rend="italic">Proteolepas</hi> is now known not to be a cirripede. The observations on the cementing apparatus and process mentioned in this letter are described in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>599–600. In T. H. Huxley 1857, Huxley stated that while he had not been able to trace the connection between the peduncular tubes and the cement gland, he nonetheless rather favoured ‘the conclusion that they are thus connected.’ (p. 239).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1481.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Dana, 8 May [1852]</ref>, n. 5. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>38 n. and in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4838.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1854): </ref>151 n., CD cited cases from the Crustacea of genera in which organs of the ovaria secrete a substance which served to attach the eggs to the parent’s body, but he pointed out that these were only analogous to the situation he described in cirripedes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD is referring to the 1849 meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science at which he commented on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2091.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Albany Hancock’s</ref> paper and which <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3335.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henri Milne-Edwards</ref> also attended. In his report on Hancock’s paper, published in the <hi rend="italic">Athenæum</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 250–1), CD remarked that the cementing substance of Cirripedia was ‘certainly secreted from glands which are actually continuous portions of the branching ovarian tubes or caeca’. To this Milne-Edwards ‘suggested that the secretion … was produced by a gland at the base of the antennae, similar to that which occurs in some species of macrourous Crustacea.’ CD ‘in reply stated that the gland in the cirripedes was truly ovarial.’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 1: 251).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>