<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5389A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller   2 February 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20483</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5389A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5389A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5389A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Draft, incomplete<ref target="#foot.f18"/></note>
            <note type="physdesc">inc</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 109–11; DAR 70: 146</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>Möller, Alfred 1915–21 2: 109–11; 70: 146</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Desterro, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1867-02-02">2 Feb 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for CD’s letter inquiring about capsules produced by the <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria</hi> with larger pods [see <hi rend="doubleUnderline">5331</hi>]. Gives descriptions of <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria</hi> and of the other Vandeae.</p>  
<p>Describes <hi rend="italic">Oncidium flexuosum</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Tells of botanical results of recent excursion to the German colony Theresopolis. Brought home fine collection of living orchids.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">5331</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oncidium flexuosum</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Vandeae</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Maxillaria</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">German colony</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Theresopolis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro,</placeName>
                    <date>Febr. 2. 1867.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am much obliged to you for your kind letter (without date)<ref target="#foot.f1"/> in which you ask about the number of capsules produced by the Maxillaria with the larger pods.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am told by a french collector M. Gautier that it is the Maxillaria tetragona; however his names are not always to be relied upon.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> On large plants growing on rocks and covering often more than a square-foot you may sometimes find half a dozen or more, whilst smaller plants growing on trees yield rarely more than one or two. I think that hardly 20% of the flowers produce seed-capsules.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The species is interesting in some other respects also. The bifid pedicelli of the pollinia execute the same movement, you have described in Maxillaria ornithorhyncha, the right and left pollen masses are connected by an elastic tissue like that of the caudicle.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Whereas in all other Vandeae, I examined (Notylia, Cirrhaea, Ornithocephalus, Polystachya, Aëranthus, Oncidium, Cyrtopodium and several other species of Maxillaria), the margins of the valves of the seed-capsules are beset with hygroscopic hairs, I could not find them in the ripe pods of this species; but there are some scattered and rudimentary hairs in the young capsules.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I send you pollen-tubes taken out of a young pod of this Maxillaria showing the fringes which from the six longitudinal ribbons extend between the ovula. On comparing these pollen-tubes with those of Cattleya Leopoldi<ref target="#foot.f7"/> you will be struck by a remarkable difference.</p>
<p>In Maxillaria (and with a single exception in all our Vandeae) the pollen-tubes remain fresh in their whole length; in Cattleya (as well as in all our Epidendreae) the upper part of the pollen-tubes soon becomes dry and black; this evidently is a consequence of the stigmatic chamber being shut in Vandeae, whilst it remains open and the pollen exposed to air in Epidendreae.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I already told you in my last letter, that in Notylia and in Oncidium flexuosum, pollen and stigma of the same plant act, as it were, as a poison on each other; this is also the case with the curious Oncidium unicorne and with another species which seems to be nearly related to Oncidium pubes.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I have had numerous racemes of a second species of Cirrhaea (perhaps the C. dependens Rchb. f.) interesting by the extreme variability of the colours of its flowers. I could not fertilize this species with fresh pollinia whilst it might be done easily after they had dried half an hour or an hour.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> This probably will prevent the flowers being fertilized with the same plants pollen. The disk in this species is provided with a hook facilitating its being taken away.</p>
<p>There begins now to flower here a curious small Orchid, viz. Ornithocephalus.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>The anther-bed has a small transverse ridge on the anterior margin; the pedicellus of the pollinium passing over this ridge forms an obtuse angle; as soon as the pollinium is removed by an elastic binding of the pedicellus, this obtuse angle is transformed into a very acute one and subsequently by an hygroscopic movement, the pedicellus is curved in a very singular and elegant manner. In water the pedicellus returns to the former form.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The two pods of Monachanthus which I fertilized (Dec. 25) with pollen of Catasetum mentosum are now already 7 cm long and as much in circumference.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>The plant of Oncidium flex., on which I had fertilized some flowers simultaneously with pollen from a distinct plant of the species and with pollen of Epidendrum Zebra, having perished by an accident I have repeated the experiment on another plant; the result has been the same and I have satisfied myself that it is indeed the side of the Epidendrum-pollen which grows less and that of the Oncidium-pollen which grows more rapidly.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>I have made in the first weeks of January a pleasant excursion on the continent, up the river Cubatão to the German colony Theresopolis;<ref target="#foot.f14"/> and have brought home a fine collection of living Orchids, among which a large plant probably belonging to the Catasetidae<ref target="#foot.f15"/>   You state in your Orchis-book that there are flourishing in your neighbourhood 13 species of Orchids; now on the Cubatão you may collect on the branches of a single old Cedrela-tree even a larger number of species: half a dozen Maxillariae, four or five small Pleurothallidae, a couple of Oncidia, the Leptotes bicolor etc. The beautiful Miltonia cereola was very abundant.—<ref target="#foot.f16"/> The most striking feature of the Orchid-flora of Theresopolis was the abundance and variety of Maxillariae and the entire absence (as far I have seen) of the Cattleyae, the Amphiglott Epidendra,<ref target="#foot.f17"/> the Brassavola, which are the dominant littoral forms. Epidendra in general seem to be much more rare than here, where I already know 13 species....</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-5261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to Fritz Müller, [before 10 December 1866]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5226.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to CD of 1 and 3 October 1866</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14), Müller had estimated that there were 1,756,440 seeds in one <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria</hi> capsule. CD told him he wanted to publish this fact and asked how many capsules were produced (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, [before 10 December 1866]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Maxillaria tetragona</hi>, native to Santa Catarina state, is now usually known as <hi rend="italic">Bifrenaria tetragona</hi> and less often as <hi rend="italic">Cydoniorchis tetragona.</hi> An old synonym was <hi rend="italic">Lycaste tetragona.</hi> <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5734.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hippolyte Gautier</ref> has not been further identified; Müller also mentioned him in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5264.xml">letter of 2 November 1866</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 379 n. 34, CD mentioned that the <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria</hi> described by Müller sometimes produced six capsules; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 158 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 155), and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 278.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For CD’s description of the pollination mechanism in <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria ornithorhyncha</hi> (an unpublished name), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 191. For definitions of CD’s terms for orchid structures, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 5–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Müller had earlier mentioned hairs on the capsules of some orchids (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5344A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 January 1867</ref> and n. 19).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Cattleya leopoldii.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD did not mention the varying conditions of the pollen-tubes in Epidendreae and Vandeae in the second edition of <hi rend="italic">Orchids.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5292A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 December 1866</ref>, and this volume, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5344A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 January 1867</ref>, for Müller’s descriptions of the poisonous effect of same-plant pollen in <hi rend="italic">Oncidium flexuosum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Notylia.</hi> CD reported Müller’s finding in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 134–5. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. 330, 341. Müller published his observations on the effects of same-plant pollen in F. Müller 1868a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">For Müller’s earlier observation on an unnamed species of <hi rend="italic">Cirrhaea</hi>, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5344A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 January 1867</ref> and n. 17. CD mentioned Müller’s observation of the second species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 172. Müller’s published account of <hi rend="italic">Cirrhaea</hi> is in F. Müller 1868b and was cited by CD in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 150).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">‘Anther-bed’: that portion of the column under, or surrounding, the anther (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2145.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1981</ref>, p. 308 s.v. ‘clinandrium’). CD included Müller’s account of the movement of the <hi rend="italic">Ornithocephalus</hi> pedicel (now stipe) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 159–60. Figure 14 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 160) was taken from Müller’s enclosed sketch of this movement.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5344A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 January 1867</ref> and nn. 13–17.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5344A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 1 January 1867</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Müller lived in Destêrro (now Florianópolis) on Santa Catarina Island. Rio Cubatâo flows into the Atlantic off the south end of the island. Theresopolis, on the Rio Cubatâo, is now Queçaba (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">West 2003</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">CD and Müller considered the Catasetidae a subfamily within the tribe Vandeae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 178); for a recent classification, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2146.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dressler 1993</ref>, pp. 168–70.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 345. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 279, CD added that Müller found more than thirteen species of orchid on a single <hi rend="italic">Cedrela</hi> tree.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><hi rend="italic">Amphiglottis</hi> is a synonym (no longer accepted) for some species of <hi rend="italic">Epidendrum.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">This letter was found by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref> and published in <hi rend="italic">Fritz Müller: Werke, Briefe und Leben</hi> (Möller ed. 1915–21). According to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_9163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Möller</ref>, all of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller’s</ref> letters to CD were written in English (see Möller ed. 1915–21, 2: 72 n.); most of them have not been found. Many of the letters were later sent by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> to Möller, who translated them into German for his book. Möller also found final drafts of some letters (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 72 n.) and published these in their original English version. The present letter is one of these. Müller’s drawings of the pollinium of <hi rend="italic">Ornithocephalus</hi> were excised from the original letter and are in DAR 70: 146. They are included as part of the letter.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>