<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11287">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Gaston de Saporta   24 December 1877</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15002</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11287 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11287.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11287.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">L</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="L">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 147: 423</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Conry (1972): 109; <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 284</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Archives Gaston de Saporta (private collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_376.xml">Archives Gaston de Saporta</repository>
                    <collection>(private collection)</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1877-12-24">24 Dec 1877</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4181.xml">Saporta, L. C. J. G. de</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Such honours as proposal for election to Institut affect CD very little.</p>
            <p>GdeS’s idea that dicotyledonous plants were not developed until sucking insects evolved is a splendid one. The suggestion that fertilisation of the surviving members of the most ancient dicotyledons should be studied is a good one. CD hopes GdeS will keep it in mind.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">dicotyledonous plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">foreign membership</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Institut</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-09-07" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name> </change>
        <change when="2016-10-24" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2016-10-26" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2016-12-02" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2016-12-02" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Dec 24. 1877</date>
                    <salute>Mr dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I thank you sincerely for your long &amp; most interesting letter, which I should have answered sooner had it not been delayed in London.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I had not heard before that I was to be proposed as a Corr: Member of the Institute.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Living so retired a life as I do, such honours affect me very little; &amp; I can say with entire truth that your kind expression of sympathy has given, &amp; will give me much more pleasure than the election itself, should I be elected.</p>
                    <p>Your idea that dicotyledonous plants were not developed in force until sucking insects had been evolved seems to me a splendid one.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am surprised that the idea never occurred to me, but this is always the case when one first hears a new &amp; simple explanation of some mysterious phenomenon. It’s the old story of Columbus &amp; the egg.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I formerly showed that we might fairly assume that the beauty of flowers, their sweet odour &amp; copious nectar, may be attributed to the existence of flower-haunting insects but your idea, which I hope you will publish, goes much further &amp; is much more important.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> With respect to the great development of mammifers in the later Geological periods following from the development of dicotyledons, I think it ought to be proved that such animals as deer, cows, horses &amp;c could not flourish if fed exclusively on the gramineæ &amp; other anemophilous monocotyledons; &amp; I do not suppose that any evidence on this head exists.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>Your suggestion of studying the manner of fertilisation of the surviving members of the most ancient forms of the dicotyledons is a very good one, &amp; I hope that you will keep it in mind yourself, for I have turned my attention to other subjects. Delpino I think says that Magnolia is fertilised by insects which <hi rend="underline">gnaw</hi> the petals, &amp; I should not be surprised if the same fact holds good with Nymphaea.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> When ever I have looked at the flowers of these latter plants, I have felt inclined to admit the view that petals are modified stamens &amp; not modified leaves; though Pointsettia seems to show that true leaves might be converted into coloured petals.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I grieve to say that I have never been properly grounded in Botany &amp; have studied only special points: therefore I cannot pretend to express any opinion on your remarks on the origin of the flowers of the Coniferæ, Gnetaceæ &amp;c; but I have been delighted with what you say on the conversion of a monœcous species into a hermaphrodite one by the condensations of the verticels on a branch bearing female flowers near the summit &amp; male flowers below. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thiselton Dyer, in a review of my book in Nature, objected on morphological grounds to a somewhat similar notion; but did not explain what these grounds were.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
                    <p>With respect to persistent types your cases are curiously analogous to those which occur in many groups of the animal kingdom &amp; have been commented on by Huxley.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
                    <p>I expect Hooker to come here before long, &amp; I will then show him your drawing &amp; if he makes any important remarks I will communicate with you.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> He is very busy at present in clearing off arrears after his American expedition, so that I do not like to trouble him even with the briefest note.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
                    <p>I am at present working with my son at some physiological subjects &amp; we are arriving at very curious results, but they are not as yet sufficiently certain to be worth communicating to you.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I do not know whether you feel any interest about insectivorous plants: my son Francis fed with meat last summer a large number of plants of <hi rend="underline">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> &amp; left others unfed by excluding insects; &amp; the difference between the two sets of plants in growth, &amp; especially in the number &amp; weight of the seeds was truly wonderful. He has sent a paper on this subject to the Linnean Soc a copy of which he will hereafter send to you.<ref target="#foot.f14"/></p>
<p>With my best thanks &amp; the greatest respect, I remain, my dear Sir | Yours faithfully</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Gaston de Saporta, 16 December 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had been nominated for membership of the botanical section of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_15.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Académie des sciences</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Gaston de Saporta, 16 December 1877</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Dicotyledons are flowering seed-plants, or angiosperms, characterised by the presence of two embryonic seed-leaves or cotyledons; CD had remarked that the sudden appearance of so many dicotyledons was ‘most perplexing’, and conjectured that the plants had first developed in an isolated region and then spread quickly when geographical conditions became favourable (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Oswald Heer, 8 March [1875]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD refers to the apocryphal story about <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5423.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christopher Columbus’s</ref> challenge to a group of men to make an egg stand on end; when none was successful, Columbus tapped the end, cracking the egg slightly to flatten the tip, after which it stood easily. The story illustrates the fact that a brilliant idea often seems obvious or simple in retrospect.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD discussed beauty in flowers and its relation to insect visitors in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 239–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 16 December 1877</ref>, Saporta argued that the evolution of plant-eating mammals was linked to development in the plant kingdom.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref> discussed the fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Magnolia</hi> species aided by beetles of the genus <hi rend="italic">Cetonia</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>, 2: 234–5. He discussed the beetle’s gnawing of another flower, <hi rend="italic">Paeonia moutan</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. suffruticosa</hi>), which he included as a flower type like <hi rend="italic">Magnolia</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 236. <hi rend="italic">Nymphaea</hi> is the genus of waterlilies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Poinsettia is the common name of <hi rend="italic">Euphorbia pulcherrima</hi>; its bright red bracts, or modified leaves, are often mistaken for petals.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 16 December 1877</ref>, Saporta had argued that the verticils or whorls of the corolla were converging spiral turns. He also suggested that the contraction of sexual branches bearing what he termed androphylls and carpophylls (male and female parts of modified leaves) resulted in the formation of hermaphrodite flowers. In his review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10159.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thiselton-Dyer 1877</ref>, p. 331), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Turner Thiselton-Dyer</ref> had discussed CD’s view that a monoecious condition was the first step to hermaphroditism and offered an opposing explanation that the earliest angiosperms were hermaphrodites.  </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Gaston de Saporta, 16 December 1877</ref> and n. 11. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> had discussed the persistence of animal types in his anniversary address to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1841.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Geological Society of London</ref> (T. H. Huxley 1862; for a discussion of Huxley’s views on this point, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Desmond 1982</ref>, pp. 85–112). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Saporta had sent CD a tracing of a fossil leaf and asked whether <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> could examine it and suggest a comparison (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11281.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Gaston de Saporta, 16 December 1877</ref> and n. 26).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Hooker had spent July and August 1877 travelling in the United States (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 19 October 1877</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> were studying the physiology of plant movement; their findings were published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref> in 1880. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><hi rend="italic">Drosera rotundifolia</hi> is the common or round-leaved sundew. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin’s</ref> paper (F. Darwin 1878a) was read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 17 January 1878 and published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>).</note>
        </div>
            
    
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>