<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3095">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. B. Tegetmeier   22 March [1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1344</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3095 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3095.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3095.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 19</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 180</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 63</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Archives of the New York Botanical Garden (Charles Finney Cox Collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_302.xml">NYBG</repository>
                    <collection>Charles Finney Cox</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1861-03-22">22 Mar [1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4682.xml">Tegetmeier, W. B.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Asks whether WBT will read over his MS sketch on poultry when done.</p>
            <p>Wants rabbit specimens.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">poultry</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbit</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>March 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I ought to have answered your last note sooner; but I have been very busy.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> How wonderfully successful you have been in breeding Pouters! you have good right to be proud of your accuracy of eye &amp; judgment. I am in the thick of Poultry; having just commenced &amp; shall be truly grateful for the skulls, if you can send them by any conveyance to the Nag’s Head next Thursday.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> If too busy, will you send them whenever you can, addressed, thus</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>C. Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi></p>
<p>care of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mitchell</p>
<p>Per S.E Railway Postman</p>
<p>Bromley, Kent</p> </figure> 
<p>You ask about Vermilion wax: positively it was not in state of comb, but in solid bits &amp; cakes, which were thrown with other rubbish not far from my Hives.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> You can make any use of fact, you like.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Combs could be concentrically &amp; variously coloured &amp; dates recorded by giving for few days wax darkly coloured with vermilion &amp; indigo, &amp; I daresay other substances.</p>
<p>You ask about my crossed Fowls; &amp; this leads me to make a proposition to you, which I hope cannot be offensive to you.— I trust you know me too well to think that I would propose anything objectionable to the best of my judgment. The case is this. For my object of treating Poultry, I must give sketch of several breeds with remarks on various points. I do not feel strong on subject. Now when my M.S. is fairly copied in an excellent hand-writing; would you read it over, which would take you at most an hour or two, &amp; make comments in pencil on it; &amp; accept, like a Barrister, a fee, we will say of a couple of guineas.— This would be a great assistance to me; specially if you would allow me to put note, stating that you, a distinguished judge &amp; Fancier, had read it over. I would state that you doubted or concurred as each case might be: of course striking out what you were sure was incorrect. There would be little new in my M.S. to you; but if by chance you used any of my facts or conclusions, before I published, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> wish you to state that they were on my authority; otherwise I shall be accused of stealing from you.— There will be little new except that perhaps I have consulted some out of the way books, &amp; have corresponded with some good authorities.</p>
<p>Tell me frankly what you think of this; but unless you will oblige me by accepting remuneration, I cannot &amp; will not give you such trouble.— I have little that several points will arise which will require investigation, as I care for many points disregarded by Fanciers; &amp; according to any time thus spent you will, I trust, allow me to make remuneration. I hope that you will grant me this favour.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>There is one assistance which I will <hi rend="underline">now</hi> venture to beg of you, viz to get me, if you can, another specimen of <hi rend="underline">old</hi>  <hi rend="underline">white</hi> Angora Rabbit. I want it dead for Skeleton; &amp; <hi rend="underline">not</hi> knocked on Head.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Secondly I see in Cottage Gardener (March 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. p. 375) there are (impure) Half-lops with one ear quite upright &amp; shorter than the other lopped ear. I much want a dead one.— Baker cannot get one.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Baily is looking out;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> but I want two specimens. Can you assist me, if you meet any Rabbit fancier? I have had rabbit with one ear more lopped than the other; but I want one with one ear quite upright &amp; shorter, &amp; the other quite long &amp; lopped.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>My dear Sir | Yours sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.9 S. E] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.3 &amp; variously 2.4] ‘&amp;’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.4 darkly] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.7 in pencil 3.8] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.11 each] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.12 in my M.S.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.16 have corresponded] ‘have’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">5.1 , if you can, 5.2] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">5.2 <hi rend="italic">old</hi>] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">5.4 the other] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">5.6 specimens.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">5.7 the other] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">5.8 shorter] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘short’</note>
                </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is provided by the reference to CD’s study of fowl for his work on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> (see ‘Journal’; Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Tegetmeier’s letter has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Tegetmeier had agreed to lend his extensive collection of the skulls of various breeds of fowl for CD’s study of the osteological differences between domesticated and wild poultry. The carrier that operated between Down and London used the Nag’s Head Inn, Borough, as the point of collection.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3075.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 1 March [1861]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Tegetmeier had previously conducted experiments on the construction of bees’ cells in which bees were provided with various colours of wax (see Tegetmeier 1858). His intention to carry out further experiments was mentioned in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7654.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tegetmeier 1859</ref>, p. 35, but he does not appear subsequently to have published the results of any systematic experiments on bee-cell construction.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">There is an entry in CD’s Account book (Down House MS) on 31 March 1861 that reads: ‘Tegetmeier 10<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> Science.’ This probably pertains to specimens Tegetmeier sent to CD (see n. 7, below). A further entry on 13 June records that CD paid him the sum of £5 5<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. ‘for scientific assistance’. Tegetmeier’s assistance in reading CD’s manuscript is acknowledged in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 225 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Tegetmeier sent CD the rabbit as requested. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3103.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Tegetmeier, 28 March [1861]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Either Samuel C. or Charles N. Baker, poultry dealers in Chelsea. Over the past few years, CD had obtained different varieties of fowls from them.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_236.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Baily</ref> was a poulterer and dealer in live birds with a shop in Berkeley Square, London.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 119, CD stated that he had examined the skulls of three half-lop rabbits. He was interested in learning whether differences in the size and musculature of the ear had any influence on the structure of the skull. He found this to be so, calling the case ‘a remarkable case of correlation of growth’. He went on to state (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 119): <quote type="quote"> Who would have surmised that by keeping an animal during many generations under confinement, and so leading to the disuse of the muscles of the ears, and by continually selecting individuals with the longest and largest ears, he would thus indirectly have affected almost every suture in the skull and the form of the lower jaw! </quote></note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>