<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11772">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To James Torbitt   [1]4 December 1878<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13724</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11772 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11772.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11772.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Copy</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="C">1p</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 148: 106</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>148: 106</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1878-12-14">[1]4 Dec 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4777.xml">Torbitt, James</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Congratulates JT on success in breeding potato varieties.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">potato</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">varieties</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down,</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 4, 1878.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I heartily congratulate you on your gigantic labours of comparison being for the present finished and at the apparent great success of your later trials.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Would it not lighten your labours to throw away all the earliest and less sound varieties? I admire your energy greatly. Energy carries everything before it. That was a very good plan of yours selecting the heaviest and largest seeds, of which I did not think, yet since the publication of my Cross-Fertilization I have received additional evidence of the advantage from selecting large seeds.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I shall read your abstract with pleasure. I should be unwilling to give you the trouble to copy all the details but besides this I have little strength and am much overworked by my present investigations and endless letters. But pray do not think that I am not interested in your results. Would it not be well to get your abstract published in some good Agricultural or Horticultural Journal?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> When I receive your abstract I will send it to Messrs Farrer &amp; Caird.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am sorry that business is still bad.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p> With all good wishes | Yours very faithfully | Ch. Darwin.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
 
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The day is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11787.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 12 December 1878</ref>. The day on the copy was evidently a copyist’s error; a note at the top of the copy records that it was made from another copy, not from the original letter. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Torbitt had sent his report of experiments in growing disease-resistant varieties of potato; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11787.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 12 December 1878</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11787.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 12 December 1878</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, CD had included measurements of the weight of the capsules and seed produced by cross- and self-fertilised plants (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 74–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his letter of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11787.xml">12 December 1878</ref>, Torbitt had asked CD whether he wanted a full report or a summary of his results. No abstract of the results of Torbitt’s potato-crossing experiments has been found; some results were later published in a letter in <hi rend="italic">Field</hi>, 8 March 1879, p. 272. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had enlisted the help of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_788.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Caird</ref> to secure government funding for Torbitt’s potato-crossing experiments (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11387.xml">letter to James Torbitt, 1 March 1878</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11787.xml">letter from James Torbitt, 12 December 1878</ref> and n. 3.</note>
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>