<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9478">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   31 May 1874</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10956</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9478 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9478.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9478.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 93</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 93</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
                <placeName>London, Gloucester Rd, Kew, 10</placeName>
                <date when="1874-05-31">31 May 1874</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Movement in plants; effect of syringing on <hi rend="italic">Opuntia</hi> plants that capture insects with their flowers.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Opuntia</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">vibration, including sound</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>10 Gloucester Road, Kew</placeName>
                    <date>May 31. 1874</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Some time ago you asked me to try the effect of syringing plants with sensitive flowers.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> <hi rend="underline">Opuntia</hi> is one of these and as there are a good many in flower in the Cactus house I got M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Smith the Curator to go with me this morning and experiment upon them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In its so to speak virgin state the flower has the stamens spread out with a greater or less divergence from the style—</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p rend="left">They do not use syringes with a nose at Kew but produce a spray by placing a finger over the nozzle. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Smith who is an adept at this and who was much interested in trying the flowers, syringed them successively.</p>
<p>I confess I was astonished at the readines with which the lightest syringing we could give them elicited movement. The contraction was not instantaneous but there was always a perceptible interval of time—not more than a second or so perhaps—and then the stamens gradually moved towards the style.</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>We tried two species in particular O. polyacantha and O. monacantha<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>You asked me about Stapelias—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I cannot find anything about movement in their flowers. I should expect the parts to be quite stationary. Probably there is some provision for cross fertilization by the removal of the pollen masses which is not yet worked out. Asclepiadaceæ are a kind of analogue amongst Dicotyledons of Orchideæ amongst Monocotyledons.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Prof. Oliver<ref target="#foot.f6"/> called my 〈a〉ttention the other day to the way in which plants capture insects sometimes by means of their flowers. He had an idea that the nectar poisoned them, mentioning the Oleander as one case in point.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> <hi rend="underline">Ledum palustre</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> a specimen of which I inclose, he thought was another instance. Here however it seems to me that the insects are caught by the viscidity of the ovary and according to Weale, Linn. Journ. xiii pp. 48, 49 Gomphocarpus physocarpus capture〈d〉 insects which “got attached to the stigmatic glands and appeared unable to release themselves”<ref target="#foot.f9"/>   Of course in this way the soil above the plant would get enriched with nitrogenous matters. But I suppose that the destruction of the insects is merely an accidental concomitant of the glutinousness which is brought about in connection with some other purpose</p>
<p>Meehan appears to have noticed the closing of the expanded lobes of the stigma in many Scrophulariaceæ and Bignoniaceæ—. He has lately observed it in <hi rend="underline">Catalpa</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> If I can keep it in my recollection when Catalpa comes into flower I will try the effects of syringing</p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very truly | W. T. Thiselton Dyer</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>4.1 I cannot … themselves” 5.8] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9387.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 4 April 1874</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Opuntia</hi> is the genus of paddle cacti. Thiselton-Dyer refers to John Smith (1821–88).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Opuntia polyacantha</hi> is the hairspine cactus or panhandle prickly pear; <hi rend="italic">O. monacantha</hi> is the drooping prickly pear or Barbary fig.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See letter to W. H. Thiselton-Dyer, 4 April 1874 and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Asclepiadaceae is now subsumed within the family Apocynaceae (milkweed). Orchideae is the largest tribe in the orchid subfamily, Orchidoideae. In milkweed and orchids the pollen is grouped into complex structures called pollinia. Dicotyledons have seeds with two embryonic leaves, and monocotyledons have one.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3589.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Daniel Oliver</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Nerium oleander</hi> has poisonous flowers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><hi rend="italic">Ledum palustre</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Rhododendron tomentosum</hi>) is marsh Labrador tea.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Gomphocarpus physocarpus</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Asclepias physocarpa</hi>, the balloonplant or swan plant) is described in <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4989.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Philip Mansel Weale’s</ref> paper on fertilisation in the Asclepiadeae, published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> (Weale 1870).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Meehan’s</ref> observations on Scrophulariaceae and Bignoniaceae were reported in the <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia</hi> 25 (1873): 277. <hi rend="italic">Catalpa</hi> is a genus of spreading deciduous trees in the Bignoniaceae family, including <hi rend="italic">C. bignonioides</hi> (Indian bean tree).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>