<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11213">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. H. Darwin   [28 October 1877]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">7583</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11213 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11213.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11213.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 210.2: 60–1</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>210.2: 60–1</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">Darwin, G. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Trinity College, Cambridge</placeName>
                <date when="1877-10-28">[28 Oct 1877]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Writes again about arrangements for the honorary degree ceremony.</p>
            <p>Has been working on tides, which he is almost certain have altered the obliquity of the ecliptic.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">obliquity of the ecliptic</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">tides</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sea, sea-currents</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">LL.D. ceremony</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-08-26" status="editorResponseCompleted"><name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <date>Sunday</date>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I suppose you will have heard from the Vice Chancellor consulting you as to what time you will like to take your degree.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I gather from Hughes &amp; D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Phear that they would like you to fix on three or four days on which you could come up, out of which they c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. take their choice.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I told you that there were only stated days on which you c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. take the degree, but I hear now that there is some talk of an extra-congregation but of which no date is fixed &amp; that is why I ask you to name a space of several days— if it included a Thursday I think they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be able to have their choice of the ordinary day or the extra day. I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. suggest the week from Nov 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.–23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. I don’t kno’ whether there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be any degree besides yr’s on the extra day but perhaps there might be   The special day w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be a much shorter job than the other because there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be no ordinary business &amp; w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be over in 20 min. The master of Emman D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Phear is very anxious for a special day, but I don’t yet know what the Vice C. thinks<ref target="#foot.f4"/>   There might be a few other degrees conferred on the Special day, but I don’t much think there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be. However I dare say you will have settled it all before you get this.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>I am afraid I have been working rather too hard lately &amp; I did an act of great courage yesterday in putting aside my work, but I don’t feel as if I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. take an interest in anything else.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I was working a good deal when I really was’nt up to it &amp; was very seedy yesterday &amp; today I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. hardly work if I would.</p>
                    <p>I will <hi rend="underline">try</hi> to work a little easier when I start again, but you can’t think what a pang it cost me to lay it aside (The rest is the fag end of a letter I wrote last night in consequence of some bother about y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> degree but which is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">all</hi> removed by what I heard afterwards) even for a day, for I am just bearing down on the most interesting point.</p>
                    <p>However I went on till I had finished the most difficult point, &amp; I shall be able to take up the thread again now that that is down in black &amp; white. I feel almost confident now that tides in the body of the Earth will have altered the obliquity of the Ecliptic—&amp; there’s a grand result for the geologists to play with. How much &amp; which way I hav’nt the least idea but I suspect it would take a million years even with a very perceptible earth tide to make a considerable change in the obliquity. But we’ve got a good bank of time to draw on &amp; surely even a few degrees of change in geological history wd be very important.</p>
<p>I think it is <hi rend="underline">just</hi> on the cards that it may turn out to be an inequality of enormous period say a million years decreasing &amp; then a million increasing but I don’t quite see my way to that yet.</p>
                    <p>I am so very glad to hear poor Hen. is about again<ref target="#foot.f7"/>   I hadn’t the least idea that you were going to pay a visit to London. I hope you will find Uncle Ras tol. Perhaps I will run up for a night— how long do you stay. perhaps tomorrow<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I wonder whether you c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. persuade Frank to come up to Cambridge for your L.LD— Newton Clark &amp; others w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be so very glad to see him. Is Bessy in London with you?<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Your affectionate son | G. H. Darwin</p>
<p>I’ve left off tee-totalling for I don’t think it suited &amp; I must say like my wine very much</p>
<p>Will you send me a telegram if there is not room for me— I think a day or two’s change may get me up again</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
           
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the references to the vice-chancellor’s letter and to CD’s visit to London (see n. 8, below). In 1877, 28 October was a Sunday.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11209A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Atkinson, 25 October 1877</ref>, concerning the honorary LLD (doctor of laws) that was to be conferred on CD.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas McKenny Hughes</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7975.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel George Phear</ref> served on the Senate of the University of Cambridge.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Phear was the master of Emmanuel College, Cambridge; the vice-chancellor of the university was Atkinson.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had written to Atkinson on 27 October 1877, expressing his preference for the degree ceremony to take place on 6 December.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">George Darwin was continuing to work on his paper on the supposition that that the earth was composed of a viscous or imperfectly elastic matter, and thus subject to tides in its interior (G. H. Darwin 1878; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. H. Darwin, 18 [October 1877]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henrietta Emma Litchfield</ref> had fallen ill with a fever in Switzerland while caring for her husband, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Buckley Litchfield</ref>, who was recovering from an appendectomy (<ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Horace Darwin to G. H. Darwin, 24–5 October 1877</ref> (DAR 258: 864)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> visited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1211.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Erasmus Alvey Darwin</ref> in London from 26 to 29 October 1877 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> had become friends with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3517.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Newton</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Willis Clark</ref> while he was a student at Cambridge. It is not known whether Elizabeth (Bessy) Darwin visited London.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>