<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5966">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From A. R. Wallace   1 March 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8846</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5966 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5966.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5966.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †, encl 7pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 148: 417, DAR 148: 418</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> Marchant (1916) 1: 199; <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 289, 301 </bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 106: B49–50, B53–5</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>106: B49–B50, B53–B55</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml">Wallace, A. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Hurstpierpoint</placeName>
                <date when="1868-03-01">1 Mar 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Offers enclosure demonstrating that natural selection could produce sterility of hybrids.</p>
            <p>More on Pangenesis and the inadequacy of H. Spencer’s approach.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4495">Spencer, Herbert</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pangenesis</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00128_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00128_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
        <surface n="B:49r" xml:id="i128">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00128.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00128_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00128.dzi" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:49v" xml:id="i129">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00129.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00129_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00129.dzi" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:50r" xml:id="i130">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00130.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00130_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00130.dzi" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:50v" xml:id="i131">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00131.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00131_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00106-000-00131.dzi" width="2971px" height="5183px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Hurstpierpoint,</placeName>
                    <date>March 1st. 1868</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I beg to enclose what appears to me a demonstration, <hi rend="underline">on your own principles</hi>, that Nat. Select. <hi rend="underline">could</hi> produce <hi rend="underline">sterility of hybrids</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>If it does not convince you I shall be glad if you will point out <hi rend="underline">where</hi> the <hi rend="underline">fallacy lies</hi>. I have taken the two cases of a <hi rend="underline">slight</hi> <hi rend="underline">sterility</hi> overcoming a <hi rend="underline">perfect fertility</hi>, and of a <hi rend="underline">perfect sterility</hi> overcoming a <hi rend="underline">partial fertility</hi>,—the beginning and end of the process. You admit that variations in <hi rend="underline">fertility</hi> and <hi rend="underline">sterility</hi> occur, and I think you will also admit that if I demonstrate that a <hi rend="underline">considerable amount of sterility</hi> would be advantageous to a variety, that is sufficient proof that the <hi rend="underline">slightest variation</hi> in that direction would be useful also, and would go on accumulating.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Sir C. Lyell spoke to me as if he greatly admired “Pangenesis”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am very glad H. Spencer at once acknowledges that his view was something quite distinct from yours.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Although, as you know, I am a great admirer of his, I feel how completely his view failed to go to the root of the matter, as yours does. His explained nothing, though he was evidently struggling hard to find an explanation. Yours as far as I can see explains everything in <hi rend="underline">growth</hi> and <hi rend="underline">reproduction</hi>, though of course the mystery of <hi rend="underline">life</hi> and <hi rend="underline">consciousness</hi> remains as great as ever.</p>
<p>Parts of the chapter on Pangenesis I found <hi rend="underline">hard reading</hi> and have not quite mastered yet,—and there are also throughout the discussions in Vol. 2. many bits of <hi rend="underline">hard reading</hi>, on minute points which we, who have not worked experimentally at cultivation and crossing as you have done, can hardly see the importance of, or their bearing on the general question.</p>
<p>If I am asked, I may perhaps write an article on <hi rend="underline">the book</hi> for some Periodical, &amp; if so shall do what I can to make “Pangenesis” appreciated.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I suppose Mrs. Darwin thinks you <hi rend="underline">must</hi> have a holiday, after the enormous labour of bringing out such a book as that.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I am sorry I am not now staying in town. I shall however be up for two days on Thursday &amp; shall hope to see you at the <hi rend="underline">Linnæan</hi> when Mr. Trimen has a paper on some of his wonderful S. African Mimetic Butterflies.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I hope this will reach you before you leave.</p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very faithfully | Alfred R. Wallace—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other" xml:id="encl.1">
            <ab><ref target="#foot.f8"/></ab>
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre"><hi rend="underline">Sterility of Hybrids produced by Natural Selection</hi></p> 
<p>1. Let there be a species which has varied into <hi rend="underline">two forms</hi>, each adapted to existing conditions better than the parent form, which they supplant.</p>
<p>2. If these <hi rend="underline">two forms</hi>, which are supposed to co-exist in the same district, do not intercross, Nat. Select. will accumulate favourable variations, till they become sufficiently well adapted to their conditions of life and form <hi rend="underline">two allied species</hi>.</p>
<p>3. But if these <hi rend="underline">two forms</hi> freely intercross with each other and produce hybrids which are also quite fertile <hi rend="underline">inter-se</hi>, then the formation of the two distinct races or species will be retarded or perhaps entirely prevented; for the offspring of the crossed unions will be <hi rend="underline">more vigorous</hi> owing to the cross, although <hi rend="underline">less adapted to their conditions of life</hi> than either of the pure breeds.</p>
<p>4. Now let a <hi rend="underline">partial sterility</hi> of some individuals of these two forms arise when they intercross; and as this would probably be due to some special conditions of life, we may fairly suppose it to arise in <hi rend="underline">some definite portion of the area</hi> occupied by the two forms.</p>
<p>5. The result is, that in this area <hi rend="underline">hybrids</hi> will not increase so rapidly as before; and as by the terms of the problem the two pure forms are better suited to the conditions of life than the hybrids, they will tend to supplant the latter altogether whenever the struggle for existence becomes severe.</p>
<p>6. We may fairly suppose also, that as soon as any <hi rend="underline">sterility</hi> appears under natural conditions, it will be accompanied by <hi rend="underline">some disinclination to cross unions</hi>; and this will further diminish the production of hybrids.</p>
<p>7. In the other part of the area, however, where hybridism occurs unchecked, hybrids of various degrees will soon <hi rend="underline">far outnumber</hi> the parent or pure forms.</p>
<p>8. The first result then of a <hi rend="underline">partial sterility</hi> of crosses appearing in one part of the area occupied by the two forms, will be,—that the <hi rend="underline">great majority</hi> of the individuals will there consist of the pure forms only, while in the rest of the area these will be in a <hi rend="underline">minority</hi>;—which is the same as saying, that the new sterile or <hi rend="underline">physiological variety</hi> <ref target="#foot.f9"/> of the two forms, will be better suited to the conditions of existence than the remaining portion which has not varied physiologically.</p>
<p>9. But when the struggle for existence becomes severe, that variety which is best adapted to the conditions of existence always supplants that which is imperfectly adapted;— therefore <hi rend="underline">by Natural Selection</hi> the <hi rend="underline">sterile varieties</hi> of the two forms will become established as the only ones.</p>
<p>10. Now let a fresh series of variations in the <hi rend="underline">amount of sterility</hi> and in the <hi rend="underline">disinclination to crossed unions</hi>, occur,—also in certain parts of the area: exactly the same result must recur, and the progeny of this new physiological variety again in time occupy the whole area.</p>
<p>11. There is yet another consideration that supports this view. It seems probable that the <hi rend="underline">variations</hi> in <hi rend="underline">amount of sterility</hi> would to some extent concur with and perhaps depend upon the <hi rend="underline">structural variations</hi>; so that just in proportion as the two forms diverged and became <hi rend="underline">better adapted to the conditions of existence</hi>, <hi rend="underline">their sterility would increase</hi>. If this were the case then Natural Selection would act with double strength, and those varieties which were better adapted to survive both structurally and physiologically, would certainly do so.</p>
<p>12. Let us now consider the more difficult case of two allied species A. B. in the same area, half the individuals of each (A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>.) being absolutely <hi rend="underline">sterile</hi>, the other half (A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>.) being <hi rend="underline">partially fertile</hi>. Will A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. ultimately exterminate A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>.?</p>
<p>13. To avoid complication it must be granted, that between A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. no cross unions take place, while between A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. cross unions are as frequent as direct unions, though much less fertile. We must also leave out of consideration crosses between A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>., B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. with their various approaches to sterility, as I believe they will not affect the final result although they will greatly complicate the problem.</p>
<p>14. In the first generation there will result; 1st. The pure progeny of A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and of B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. 2nd. The pure progeny of A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and of B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and 3rd. The hybrid progeny of A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>.</p>
<p>15. Supposing that, <hi rend="underline">in ordinary years</hi>, the increased constitutional vigour of the hybrids exactly counterbalances <hi rend="underline">their imperfect adaptation to conditions</hi>, there will be in the 2nd. generation, besides these three classes, hybrids of the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. degree between the first hybrids and A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. respectively. In succeeding generations there will be hybrids of all degrees, varying between the first hybrids and the almost pure types of A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>.</p>
<p>16. Now if at first the number of individuals of A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. were equal, and year after year the <hi rend="underline">total number</hi> continues stationary, I think it can be proved, that while one half will be the pure progeny of A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>., the other half will become more and more hybridised, until the whole will be hybrids of various degress.</p>
<p>17. Now this <hi rend="underline">hybrid</hi> and somewhat <hi rend="underline">intermediate race</hi>, cannot be so well adapted to the <hi rend="underline">conditions of life</hi> as the two <hi rend="underline">pure species</hi>, which have been formed by the minute <hi rend="underline">adaptation to conditions</hi> through Nat. Select.;— therefore, in a severe struggle for existence, the hybrids must succomb, especially as, by hypothesis, their fertility would not be so great as that of the two pure species.</p>
<p>18. If we were to take into consideration the unions of A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. with A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. with B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>., the results would become very complicated, but it must still lead to there being a number of <hi rend="underline">pure forms</hi> entirely derived from A<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and of <hi rend="underline">hybrid forms</hi> mainly derived from A<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>. and B<hi rend="superscript">F</hi>.; and the result of the struggle of these two sets of individuals can not be doubtful.</p>
<p>19. If these arguments are sound, it follows—that sterility may be accumulated and increased, and finally made complete by Natural Selection whether the sterile varieties originate together in a definite portion of the area occupied by the two species, or occur scattered over the whole area.</p>
<p>Alfred R. Wallace—</p>
<p>P.S. In answer to the objection as to the unequal Sterility of <hi rend="underline">reciprocal crosses</hi> (“Variation &amp;c.” Vol. 2. p. 186) I reply, that, as far as it went, the sterility of <hi rend="underline">one cross</hi> would be advantageous even if the other cross was fertile: and just as characters now coordinated may have been <hi rend="underline">separately</hi> accumulated by Nat. Select., so the <hi rend="underline">reciprocal crosses</hi> may have become sterile one at a time.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter:</hi> ‘76<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></formula> | Westbourne | Grove’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter:</hi> ‘Your collections— <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> E. Museum | About Pieridæ—number of sexes—’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; ‘Linn Soc.— Your Book’<ref target="#foot.f10"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Enclosure:</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 We … hybrids. 6.3] <hi rend="italic">reverse question marks, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>9.3 therefore … ones. 9.4] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.1 It … <hi rend="italic">increase.</hi> 11.4] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi>; ‘No’ <hi rend="italic">in margin pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.3 depend … <hi rend="italic">variations</hi>;] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi></note>
                <note>13.3 unions,] ‘this, from experience, excessively improbable’ <hi rend="italic">interl pencil</hi></note>
                <note>13.4 as … problem. 13.5] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>21.2 the sterility … fertile: 21.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of enclosure:</hi> ‘inhabit different areas’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 185–9, CD discussed the question of whether sterility of hybrids could be produced through natural selection, and concluded that, in general, it could not. For CD’s changing views on the subject of the sterility of hybrids as a selected quality, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4765A.xml" resp="#automat">letter to M. E. Wichura, 3 February [1865]</ref> and n. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had argued that degrees of lessened fertility could not have been slowly accumulated by means of natural selection because an individual would not gain any advantage by its lessened fertility when crossed with another variety, since it would leave fewer offspring and not be ‘selected’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 186–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD discussed pangenesis, his theory of hereditary transmission, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 357–404. CD had sent <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Lyell</ref> proof-sheets of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> and had been particularly pleased with Lyell’s appreciation of pangenesis (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5612.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 22 August [1867]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In a letter of 8 February 1868, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer</ref> had commented on pangenesis, noting that the hypothesis differed from his own theory of hereditary transmission. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5940.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 27 February [1868]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Wallace did not publish a review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emma Darwin</ref> were in London from 3 March to 1 April 1868 (see ‘Journal’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4806.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Roland Trimen</ref> read his paper (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7825.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Trimen 1868</ref>) at the 5 March 1868 meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>. Wallace attended, but CD did not (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6030.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Roland Trimen, 20 March [1868]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The enclosure was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref> 1: 289–93, together with footnotes written by Wallace and dated 1899. The manuscript version of the footnotes is in DAR 106: B56. Wallace published the first eleven paragraphs of the enclosure in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8125.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. R. Wallace 1889</ref>, pp. 179–80.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">The term ‘physiological species’ had been coined by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> to describe animals or plants that exhibited cross or hybrid sterility (T. H. Huxley 1863b, pp. 106–8). CD had been challenged by Huxley to demonstrate a case of artificial selection producing varieties of a species that were cross sterile, that is, new ‘physiological species’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[T. H. Huxley] 1860</ref>, T. H. Huxley 1862, pp. 108–13, 146–50, and T. H. Huxley 1863b, pp. 107–8). CD’s interest in cases of intra-specific sterility was in part prompted by this challenge. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix VI, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3852.xml" resp="#automat">letter to T. H. Huxley, 10 [January 1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD’s annotations are notes for his reply to Wallace; the reply has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6012.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 15 March [1868]</ref>, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to A. R. Wallace, 17 [March 1868]</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>