<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7396">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Edouard van Beneden<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   17 December 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14033</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7396 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7396.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7396.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 160: 132</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>160: 132</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_385.xml">Beneden, Edouard van</persName>
                <placeName>Liège</placeName>
                <date when="1870-12-17">17 Dec 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>CD has been nominated as a <hi rend="italic">Membre Associé</hi> of the Belgian Royal Academy.</p> 
            <p>Discusses crustacean embryology; EvB is at variance with Dohrn.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">crustaceans</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1346">Dohrn, F. A.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">embryology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">associate membership</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Belgian Royal Academy</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00538_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00538_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
        <surface n="132:1r" xml:id="i538">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00538.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00538_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00538.dzi" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="132:1v" xml:id="i539">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00539.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00539_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00539.dzi" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="132:2r" xml:id="i540">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00540.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00540_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00540.dzi" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="132:2v" xml:id="i541">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00541.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00541_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00160-000-00541.dzi" width="3561px" height="5944px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Liège</placeName>
                    <date>17 X<hi rend="superscript">bre</hi>. 1870</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur et illustre Confrère,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai éprouvé un véritable joie en apprenant votre nomination comme membre Associé de l’Académie royale de Belgique et je ne puis m’empêcher de vous dire combien je suis heureux de voir qu’en cette circonstance les Belges aient fait la leçon aux membres de l’Institut de France.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Puissent tous les corps savants du monde protester comme l’Académie de Belgique contre la discussion qu’ils ont osé entamer sur la question de vos mérites scientifiques. Votre nom résume tout le mouvement scientifique de ces dernières années et vos immortals travaux sont au dessus de toutes les attaques du cléricalisme et de l’ignorance.— J’ai été indigné comme doivent l’être tous ceux qui ont connaissance de vos travaux, en lisant cette discussion qui est une flétrissure pour cette institution, à ajouter à toutes celles que la science française a éprouvé dans ces dernières années.—</p>
<p>En Belgique la jeune génération a arboré le drapeau de l’indépendance intellectuelle et a jeté au loin les préjugés et les idées préconcues. Et si parmi les hommes d’un âge bien mur il en est qui n’ont pas accepté vos idées, au moins ils ont su mettre vos mérites au dessus de leurs convictions personnelles.—</p>
<p>Je suis heureux et fier d’avoir été nommé correspondant de l’Académie, le jour où vous avez été Élu comme associé.—</p>
<p>Je vous envoie un exemplaire de quelques uns de mes travaux.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Veuillez les recevoir comme un témoignage de mon profond respect. Vous verrez que je travaille la même question que Dohrn: l’embryogénie des Crustacés.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Je crois être arrivé à un joli résultat: c’est la démonstration par l’embryogénie de la dérivation des articulés d’un forme de Vers. (Embr. des Sacculins.—id des Lernéens)<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je continue ces recherches et les publications et j’espère arriver bientôt à construire l’arbre généalogique de ce groupe.— Je ne suis pas arrivé aux mêmes conclusions que Dohrn.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> J’espère pouvoir vous envoyer très prochainement le développement des Nebalia.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>J’ai eu l’occasion d’étudier récemment l’organisation du <hi rend="underline">Anelasma squalicola</hi>. Je crois avec Dohrn que nous avons là le passage aux Peltogaster.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> J’ai retrouvé parfaitement les racines plongées dans les chairs, telles que vous les avez figurées.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Les pièces de la bouche existent à l’état rudimentaire.</p>
<p>Excusez la liberté que j’ai pris de vous écrire et reçevez, Monsieur et illustre confrère l’expression de mon profond respect. | Prof. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Edouard Van Beneden | rue Vinave d’Ile à <hi rend="underline">Liége</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Liège</placeName>
                    <date>17 December 1870</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir and illustrious Colleague,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I felt a real joy on learning of your nomination as an Associate member of the Académie royale de Belgique and I cannot prevent myself from telling you how happy I am to see that in this matter the Belgians have taught the members of the Institut de France a lesson.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> May all the learned bodies of the world protest, like the Academy of Belgium, against the debate they dared instigate on the question of your scientific merits. Your name summarises the whole scientific movement of recent years and your immortal work is above all attacks by clericalism or ignorance.— I was indignant, as must all be who know your work, on reading this discussion, which is another blot on the record for this institution, to add to all those that French science has experienced in recent years.—</p>
<p>In Belgium the younger generation has hoisted the standard of intellectual independence and has thrown off prejudice and preconceived ideas. And if among men of a riper age there are some who have not accepted your ideas, at least they have been able to place your merits above their personal convictions.—</p>
<p>I am happy and proud to have been named a correspondent of the Academy on the same day that you were Elected as an associate.—</p>
<p>I am sending you copies of some of my work.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Please receive them as a demonstration of my profound respect. As you will see, I am working on the same question as Dohrn: the embryogeny of the Crustaceans.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I think I have reached a fine result: the demonstration through embryogeny of the derivation of the articulates from a sort of Worm. (Embr. of Sacculina.—id. of the Lernaeans)<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I am continuing these researches and publications and I hope soon to be able to construct the genealogical tree for this group.— I have not come to the same conclusions as Dohrn.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I hope to be able to send you the development of Nebalia very soon.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Recently I had the opportunity to study the organisation of <hi rend="underline">Anelasma squalicola</hi>. I hold, with Dohrn, that this is the transition to the Peltagastes.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I was perfectly able to find the roots plunged into the flesh, just as you depicted them.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> The mouthparts exist in a rudimentary state.</p>
<p>Excuse the liberty I have taken in writing to you and accept, dear Sir and illustrious colleague, my profoundest respects. | Prof. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Edouard Van Beneden | rue Vinave d’Ile, <hi rend="underline">Liège</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 315–16.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7390.xml" resp="#automat">letter from L. A. J. Quetelet, 15 December 1870</ref>. CD had been nominated for the zoological section of the Académie des Sciences on 27 June 1870 (<hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus de l’Académie des Sciences</hi> 70 (1870): 1418). The Institut de France includes five academies, one of which is the Académie de Sciences. CD was nominated a further five times without success, until he was finally elected to the botanical section in 1878 (Corsi and Weindling 1985, p. 699). For more on the controversy over CD’s election, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7283.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 18 July 1870</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">There are offprints of Beneden 1868, 1869a, 1869b, 1870a, 1870b, 1870c, and 1870d, and Beneden and Bessels 1868, in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL; Beneden 1868 and 1870b are lightly annotated.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1346.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anton Dohrn</ref> had written several articles, later collected into a book (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1870</ref>), on the morphology and development of crustaceans.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See Beneden 1870a, pp. 105–6. Beneden suggested that the early development in embryos of <hi rend="italic">Sacculina</hi> (a genus of Rhizocephala) resembled that of many annelid worms. Beneden had earlier described the embryonic development of <hi rend="italic">Lernaea</hi>, a genus of parasitic copepods, commonly known as anchor worms (Beneden and Bessels 1868, pp. 440–1).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Dohrn outlined some of his differences with Beneden concerning the genealogy of Crustacea in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2083.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1870</ref>, pp. 159–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Beneden did not publish on <hi rend="italic">Nebalia</hi>, a genus of sea fleas, now in the order Leptostraca. <hi rend="italic">Nebalia</hi> had been considered by some to be a divergent form of Phyllopoda, but by 1872 <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_955.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Friedrich Claus</ref> had reclassified it as a primitive form of Malacostraca (see Claus 1872, pp. 329–30).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The barnacle species <hi rend="italic">Anelasma squalicola</hi> lives on some species of sharks with its peduncle embedded in the shark’s skin. <hi rend="italic">Peltogaster</hi> is a genus of Rhizocephala that parasitises hermit crabs. CD had suggested <hi rend="italic">A. squalicola</hi> might be a link to Rhizocephala after reading F. Müller 1864 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter to Fritz Müller, 10 August 1865</ref> and n. 7). For Dohrn’s views on the relationship between <hi rend="italic">A. squalicola</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Peltogaster</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2093.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dohrn 1875</ref>, p. 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4837.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi> (1851): </ref>380–1 and plate IV, figure 3.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>