<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2252">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   4 April [1858]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3510</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2252 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2252.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2252.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 156</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 13;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 154</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 62</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Archives of the Gray Herbarium, Harvard University (25)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>25</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1858-04-04">4 Apr [1858]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses the variation of species in large and small genera.</p>
            <p>Thanks AG for his list of close species.</p> 
<p>Laments the slow progress he makes with his book [<hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Natural selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">close species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number of species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Ap. 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Gray</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Your kindness to me is really beyond thanks. Believe me that I feel it. By an odd chance yesterday morning, before I got your letter, I had just written down what I had to say on closely allied species in large genera; &amp; I thought that you had forgotten all about your list, &amp; knowing how hard you were worked, to my credit be it said, I <hi rend="underline">firmly</hi> resolved that nothing sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. induce me to remind you. Therefore you may believe how delighted I was to get your list, which is now being tabulated.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I am, also, particularly obliged for the answer to my question:<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Hooker &amp; several (not all) other Botanists differ from you &amp; think there would be a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">strong</hi> tendency to omit recording actually existing varieties in the smaller genera. None of them pretend they ever thought of this before I asked the question. From what <hi rend="doubleUnderline">little</hi> systematic work I have done myself, I cannot realise their view; &amp; my tables of several local Floras in several respects contradict them in my opinion, &amp; show that Botanists have worked rather more systematically &amp; regularly in recording varieties than could have been anticipated. This is my view, but what Hooker will say, when he reads, as I hope he will, my discussion on this subject I know not. Taking Books as a guide, I find in local Floras &amp; in the only 2 Entomological works, which I have tried, that the rule is almost universal, that the larger genera have more species with varieties (&amp; a greater average number of varieties to the varying species) than the smaller genera.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>You ask to see my sheets as printed off; I assure you that it will be the <hi rend="underline">highest</hi> satisfaction to me to do so: I look at the request as a high compliment. I shall not, you may depend, forget a request, which I look at as a favour.— But (&amp; it is a heavy “but” to me) it will be long before I go to press: I can truly say I am <hi rend="underline">never</hi> idle; indeed I work too hard for my much weakened health; yet I can do only 3 hours of work daily, &amp; I cannot at all see, when I shall have finished: I have done eleven long chapters; but I have got some other very difficult ones, as palæontology, classification &amp; embryology &amp;c, &amp; I have to correct &amp; add largely to all those done. I find, alas, each chapter takes me on average three months, so slow I am. There is no end to the necessary digressions. I have just finished a chapter on Instincts, &amp; here I found grappling with such a subject as Bees cells &amp; comparing all my notes made during 20 years took up a despairing length of time.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>But I am running on about myself in a most egotistical style. Yet I must just say how useful I have again &amp; again found your letters, which I have lately been looking over &amp; quoting; but you need not fear that I shall quote anything you would dislike, for I try to be very cautious on this head.— I most heartily hope you may succeed in getting your “incubus” of old work off your hands &amp; be in some degree a free man.</p>
<p>Agassiz has most kindly sent me his Introduction two first Part; but I confess I am disappointed: I cannot realise his rules on the value of the higher groups, &amp; all his prophetic &amp;c &amp;c types.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Again let me say that I do indeed feel grateful to you &amp; believe me | My dear Gray | Yours most truly | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">2.2 (not all)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.6 of several local Floras] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.12 average] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.3 forget] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘to’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.9 on average] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.10 slow] ‘l’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘h’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.11 on] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘if’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.11 Instincts] ‘I’ <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘i’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">5.1 Introduction] <hi rend="italic">altered from</hi> ‘Introductory’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 21 February [1858]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See CD’s annotations on the preceding letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD refers to his question about the likelihood of botanists recording varieties in larger genera more frequently than in small (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-2218.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 21 February [1858]</ref>). Gray’s response, which CD sent to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2254.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 10 April [1858]</ref>), has not been found. However, CD cited Gray on the point in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 161: <quote> Dr. A. Gray, whose opinion will be considered by all as of the greatest weight, after deliberation does not believe that he has himself so acted: he at first thought that he might have unfairly recorded a greater number of varieties in the smaller genera…</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s results are summarised in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 134–67.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD recorded having completed chapter 10, on the ‘Mental powers and the instincts of animals’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, pp. 466–527), on 9 March 1858 (‘Journal’; Appendix II).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The first volume of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_66.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Agassiz 1857–62</ref> was presented to CD by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2217.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Louis Agassiz, 21 February [1858]</ref>). The work is in the Darwin Library–CUL and contains annotations and an abstract by CD. CD presumably refers to Agassiz’s discussion of ‘The gradation of structure among animals’ and ‘Prophetic types among animals’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_66.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Agassiz 1857–62</ref>, 1: 26–30, 116–18). The ‘prophetic type’ was the first-appearing representative of a group that reached its full development at a later period.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>