<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11785">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Raphael Meldola   11 December 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">2675A</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11785 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11785.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11785.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 171: 133</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>171: 133</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3289.xml">Meldola, Raphael</persName>
                <placeName>Atlas Works, Hackney</placeName>
                <date when="1878-12-11">11 Dec 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Is making progress with the Weismann translation.</p>
            <p>Wonders whether Francis Darwin would give a botanical lecture at a Bayswater school.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Studien</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1222">Darwin, Francis</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Bayswater</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Weismann, A. F. L. 1882</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin family</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">school</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Offices, | 50 Old Broad Street. | E.C. | Atlas Works, Hackney Wick, | London, N.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1878</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am much obliged for your last letter, the justice of which I perfectly see; but I am afraid I must have expressed myself too strongly as I had no wish for you to claim so much from your own works as you appear to have inferred.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> However your Preface shall remain unaltered &amp; <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi> I may take upon myself (of course with your approval) to claim a little more for you than appears <hi rend="underline">directly</hi> from the work in hand.</p>
                    <p>I have made considerable progress with the translation— the first Essay (“Seasonal Dimorphism”) is nearly completed &amp; a specimen is now with Messrs. Sampson Low &amp; Marston for their approval before getting the affair finally settled with them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Dr. Weismann has been so good as to look up another lithographer for me at Würzburg who will do the plates (under Weismann’s supervision) at a much lower price.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Might I so far trespass on your time as to ask your opinion whether the German word “phyletische” so frequently used by Weismann might be Anglicised into “phyletic” without “treading on the corns” of the philologists. I like it better than “innate” or “inherent”— The German word is new so far as the dictionaries are concerned.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>There is one other matter which I wished to ask you about &amp; which is really the chief “raison d’être” of the present letter.</p>
                    <p>A friend of mine, the Principal of a School at Bayswater, is getting up a course of lectures to which I &amp; several gentlemen are going to contribute, but we have a preponderance of physical science &amp; I am anxious to secure a biological lecture— does your son Mr. Francis Darwin care about this kind of thing?<ref target="#foot.f5"/> One lecture of about an hour’s duration is all that is required— “Self-defense among plants” would do admirably. The lectures are on Tuesday evenings at 8 o’clock. I can promise an appreciative audience &amp; a fee of two guineas, &amp; I shall be happy to give any personal assistance that may be required. Seeing the vast state of ignorance that still prevails among “the people” such a concession on the part of your son would be conferring a great benefit. I should be grateful if you would kindly lay the matter before him.</p>
<p>I trust the severity of the weather has not influenced your health.</p>
<p>Yours faithfully, | R. Meldola.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
             
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11759.xml">letter to Raphael Meldola, 26 November [1878]</ref> and n. 1. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5050.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Weismann’s</ref> essay on seasonal dimorphism in butterflies (Weismann 1875a) was the first part of Meldola’s translation, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the theory of descent</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10041.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1882</ref>, 1: 1–160). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Six colour lithographic plates made by the firm J. A. Hofmann, Würzburg, appeared in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10041.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Weismann 1882</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The term ‘phyletische’ had been coined in 1866 by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>, 2: 45, 299, and passim) to refer to a genealogical connection between one species and others. It had been translated as ‘phyletic’ by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml">Edwin Ray Lankester</ref> in <hi rend="italic">The history of creation</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3282.xml">Haeckel 1876</ref>, 2: 95 and passim).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Neither Meldola’s friend nor the lecture series has been identified.</note>            
        </div>     
         
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>