<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10375">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   31 January and 1 February 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5304</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10375 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10375.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10375.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 67</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 67</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1876-01-31">31 Jan 1876</date>
                <date when="1876-02-01">1 Feb 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for comments on <hi rend="italic">Arabische Korallen</hi> [1876].</p>  
<p>Comments on <hi rend="italic">Monoenia darwinii</hi> [?] as a primitive sponge.</p>  
<p>Discusses criticisms of CD’s theory by K. E. von Baer ["Über Darwin’s Lehre", in <hi rend="italic">Reden</hi> 2 (1876): 235–480].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Monoenia darwinii</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">sponge</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Arabische Korallen</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Reden</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Baer, K. E. von 1876</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">aboriginal forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>31. Jan 76</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter theurer Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Für Ihre beiden lieben und überaus freundlichen Briefe danke ich Ihnen herzlich. Es ist mir die grösste Freude und Genugthuung, dass Sie, als einer der genauesten Kenner und der beste Beurtheiler der Korallenbänke, mit den “Arabischen Korallen” so sehr zufrieden sind.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Ich habe mir die möglichste Mühe gegeben, den wunderbaren Effect der herrlichen Korallenbänke und ihrer bunten Bewohner so getreu als möglich wiederzugeben.</p>
<p>Ich hatte Anfangs die Absicht, die prächtige Crambactis (in Fig. 2) C. <hi rend="underline">Darwinii</hi> und die kleine Monoxenia (in Fig. 11) M. <hi rend="underline">arabica</hi> zu nennen.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Nachher glaubte ich aber, es würde Ihnen mehr Freude machen, wenn die letztere Ihren Namen trüge. Sie ist offenbar eine von den ältesten und primitivsten Korallen-Formen und steht (beim Mangel aller Kalktheile) wohl der hypothetischen Stammform der Octocorallen oder Alcyonarien sehr nahe (näher als Haimea und Hartea, die Spicula besitzen).<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Für den Reformator der Descendenz-Theorie ist gewiss eine solche uralte Stammform, wie Monoxenia, besonders interessant. Auch dass die ursprüngliche Gastrula-Form (Archigastrula) in ihrer Ontogenie noch heute conservirt ist, spricht für ihr sehr hohes Alter (wie bei Amphioxus).—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Gegenwärtig arbeite ich an der III. Aufl. der “Anthropogenie”, die wesentlich verbessert wird.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen | Ihr treu ergebener | Ernst Haeckel.</p>
<p>P. S. 1. Febr 76.</p>
<p>So eben erhalte ich ein neues Buch vom alten Baer in Dorpat, welches zum grössten Theile der Darwin schen Theorie gewidmet ist.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Soweit ich eben, nach flüchtigem Durchblättern, gesehen habe, ist dasselbe <hi rend="doubleUnderline">sehr schwach</hi> und zeigt, dass der gute Baer (jetzt <hi rend="underline">84 Jahre alt</hi>!) <hi rend="underline">nicht mehr</hi> das nöthige Urtheil und die philosophische Kritik besitzt, Ihre Theorie richtig zu verstehen und zu würdigen. Ich verehre den alten Baer ausserordentlich. Um so mehr bedaure ich, dass er jetzt noch so schlechte Sachen schreibt und seine früheren hohen Verdienste in den Schatten stellt. Ich erkläre mir das daraus, dass er seit 40 Jahren der Biologie, speciell aber der Morphologie, ganz entfremdet ist, und deren Fortschritte und neue Aufgaben nicht mehr versteht. Durch seine grosse Autoritaet wird er unserer Lehre immerhin manchen Schaden zufügen.</p>
<p>E. Hkl.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>31. Jan 76</date>
                    <salute>Most honoured, dear friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>For both your good and exceedingly kind letters I thank you cordially. It gives me the greatest joy and satisfaction that you, as one of the most painstaking experts and the best judge of coral reefs, are so very content with the “Arabische Korallen”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have tried my utmost to capture the wonderful effect of the magnificent coral reefs and of their colourful inhabitants.</p>
<p>At first I intended to name the splendid Crambactis (in fig. 2) C. <hi rend="underline">Darwinii</hi> and the little Monoxenia (in fig. 11) M. <hi rend="underline">arabica</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But then it occurred to me that you would like it better if the latter bore your name. It is obviously one of the oldest and most primitive coral-forms (because of its lack of calcareous parts) probably very near the hypothetical ancestral form of octocorals or Alcyonaria (closer than either Haimea or Hartea, which have spicules).<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Such an ancient ancestral form as Monoxenia surely must be of particular interest for the reformer of the theory of descent. That the ancestral gastrula form (archigastrula) is still preserved today in its ontogeny also speaks for its very great age (as in the case of Amphioxus).—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Currently I am working on the III. ed. of “Anthropogenie”, which will be substantially improved.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>With my most cordial greetings | Yours faithfully | Ernst Haeckel.</p>
<p>P.S. 1 Febr 76.</p>
<p>Just now I received a new book from old Baer of Dorpat, which chiefly deals with the Darwinian theory.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> As far as I can see from a quick leaf through, it is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">very weak</hi> and shows that the good Baer (now <hi rend="underline">84 years old</hi>!) <hi rend="underline">no longer</hi> has the requisite judgment and philosophical acumen properly to comprehend and appreciate your theory. I admire old Baer extremely. So I regret all the more that he now writes such a poor thing, and puts his previous high merit in the shade. I imagine this is because he has entirely lost touch with biology and especially morphology these past 40 years, and no longer understands its progress and new problems. With his great authority he will still cause our theory considerable harm. | E. Hkl.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 35–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Haeckel</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10358.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">15 January [1876]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10363.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 January [1876]</ref>. CD had praised Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Arabische Korallen</hi> (Arabian corals; Haeckel 1876b), a profusely illustrated book based on popular lectures with scientific explanations.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Fig. 2 in Haeckel 1876b, p. 4, is <hi rend="italic">Crambactis arabica</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Entacmaea quadricolor</hi>, the bulb-tentacle sea anemone); fig. 11, p. 12, is <hi rend="italic">Monoxenia darwinii</hi>; the taxon is no longer recognised. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, p. 439.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Octocorallia is a subclass of Anthozoa (corals and sea anemones); Alcyonaria was an earlier name given to this group. <hi rend="italic">Haimea</hi> is no longer used as a genus name in Octocorallia because of an earlier use of the name for a genus in the class Echinoidea (heart urchins, sand dollars, and sea urchins). <hi rend="italic">Hartea</hi> is no longer recognised. Haeckel had grouped corals into three main divisions, of which two survived to the present day, the Hexacorallia and the Octocorallia. According to Haeckel, <hi rend="italic">Monoxenia</hi> was the earliest genus of Octocorallia, dating back to the Cambrian period (see Haeckel 1876b, pp. 77–8 and plate VI).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Haeckel had hypothesised that early forms of organisms were conserved in the developmental stages of their descendents (recapitulation); he proposed that two primary cell types or germ layers were differentiated in the early embryonic development of all multicellular organisms and that the ancestral mode of germ-layer formation was by invagination to produce a functional gut. This stage in development was called gastrulation and represented the recapitulation in ontogeny of an ancient organism. Haeckel also supported the theory that <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus</hi> (the lancelet; now <hi rend="italic">Branchiostoma lanceolatum</hi>) was the earliest ancestral form of vertebrate (for more on the development of this theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5158.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Maienschein 1994</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The third edition of Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic"> Anthropogenie oder Entwickelungsgeschichte des Menschen</hi> (Anthropogeny, or the developmental history of humans; Haeckel 1877a) appeared in 1877. CD’s copy is in the Darwin Library–Down.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Ernst von Baer</ref> had recently published the second part of his collected addresses, <hi rend="italic">Studien aus dem Gebiete der Naturwissenschaften</hi> (Studies in the field of science); one of the essays included was ‘Ueber Darwin’s Lehre’ (On Darwin’s theory; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9124.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Baer 1864–76</ref>, 2: 235–480). For more on Baer’s objections to CD’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Vucinich 1988</ref>, pp. 92–9; for a contemporary response to Baer’s critique, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9125.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Seidlitz 1876</ref>, pp. 39–170.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>