<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11650">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alphonse de Candolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   10 August 1878</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14135</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11650 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11650.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11650.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Baehni (1955): 151</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 24</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 24</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml">Candolle, Alphonse de</persName>
                <placeName>Samaden</placeName>
                <date when="1878-08-10">10 Aug 1878</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Congratulations on CD’s long-overdue election to the French Academy of Sciences.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">French Academy election</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-01-18" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-03-29" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2017-04-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-07-27" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2017-07-27" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-01-26" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00091_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00091_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="24:1r" xml:id="i91">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00091.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00091_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00091.dzi" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="24:1v" xml:id="i92">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00092.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00092_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00092.dzi" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="24:2r" xml:id="i93">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00093.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00093_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00093.dzi" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="24:2v" xml:id="i94">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00094.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00094_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00094.dzi" width="3576px" height="5932px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="24 foldout" xml:id="i95">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00095.jpg" width="6811px" height="5862px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00095_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="6811px" height="5862px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00161-000-00095.dzi" width="6811px" height="5862px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Samaden (Engadine)</placeName>
                    <date>10 aout 1878</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Les nouvelles arrivent tard et incompletement dans l’extrémité orientale de la Suisse et à 1724<hi rend="superscript">mets</hi>. d’élévation, à douze heures des chemins de fer; cependant un journal m’a appris votre nomination par l’Académie des Sciences de l’Institut, comme correspondant.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Permettez moi de vous dire à quel degré j’en ai été satisfait. Chose singulière! dans le cas actuel ce n’est pas lélu qu’il faut le plus féliciter—car votre position est si élevée dans la science qu’un titre de plus est assez indifférent— Mais c’est l’Académie à la quelle je m’interesse et qui tardait beaucoup trop à reconnaître vos mérites. Le systeme de presentation par sections vous a nui parcequ’on vous renvoyait de la zoologie à la botanique ou vice versa.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Malheureusement il y avait aussi des preventions ridicules par des motifs non scientifiques. J’ai craint quelquefois qu’on ne vous traitat comme jadis le D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Priestley qui avait découvert l’oxygène—c’est vrai—mais qui était républicain, de sorte que les Académies <hi rend="underline">royales</hi> de Paris et de Berlin ne le voulaient pas sur leurs listes.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Enfin vous avez survécu aux objections fausses et hors de place qu’on suscitait contre vous! Elles ne venaient pas des membres de l’Académie que je connais le plus et auxquels je parlais souvent de vous, mais plutot de mathématiciens, physiciens etc, avec lesquels j’ai moins de rapports. Même M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Quatrefages, qui combat vos opinions en histoire naturelle, m’a dit avoir voté pour vous dans une autre occasion où la discussion sur votre compte fut très vive.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> La jeunesse francaise vous est plus favorable, surtout en provinces, et la renouvellement du personnel de l’Académie vous aurait fait nommer tot ou tard, mais il vaut mieux que cela soit arrivé maintenant.</p>
                    <p>Vous aurez recu le 1<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> volume de nos <hi rend="underline">Monographiæ Phanerogamarum</hi> que j’ai dit au libraire de vous envoyer.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> C’est un livre à consulter dans l’occasion, voila tout. A peine une page ou deux dans les généralitées sur les Smilax valent-elles la peine d’attirer votre regard.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Par parenthese en comparent les Smilax fossiles avec les vivants j’ai pris une triste opinion des prétendues espèces végétales fossiles. Les charactères génériques ne peuvent pas du tout être devinés par les feuilles, qui sont ici la seule chose connue, et encore les feuilles sont reduites à des limbes sans petioles qui ne permettent pas de distinguer des espèces. Je n’ai jamais vu une donnée paléontologique aussi vague.</p>
                    <p>Mes compliments à Messieurs vos fils.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Je voudrais les rencontrer une fois dans cette curieuse vallée de l’Engadine où les courses de montagne ont un attrait tout particulier, surtout pour la jeunesse.</p>
<p>Agréez, je vous prie, mon cher Monsieur, l’assurance de me mes sentiments les plus dévoués | Alph. de Candolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Samedan (Engadine)</placeName>
                    <date>10 August 1878</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>News arrives late and incomplete in the eastern extremity of Switzerland and at 1724<hi rend="superscript">mts</hi> of elevation, twelve hours away by rail; nevertheless a newspaper informed me of your nomination by the Académie des Sciences de L’Institut, as a correspondent.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Allow me to tell you just how pleased this made me. How odd! in the current case it is not the one elected who deserves more congratulations—for your position is so elevated in science that one more title is a matter of indifference—Rather it is the Académie that interests me, and that delayed much too long in recognising your merits. The system of induction by section harmed you because it passed you on from the zoological to the botanical or vice versa.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Sadly there were also ridiculous prejudices from unscientific motives. I sometimes feared lest we treated you as we formerly did D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Priestley, who had discovered oxygen—it’s true—but who was a republican, so that the <hi rend="underline">royal</hi> Academies of Paris and Berlin did not want him on their lists.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Finally you have survived the false and out-of-place objections that were stirred up against you! They did not come from members of the Académie that I know best and with whom I speak often of you, but more from mathematicians, physicians etc, with whom I have less contact. Even M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Quatrefages, who fought your opinions in natural history, told me that he had voted for you on another occasion when the discussion on your account was very lively.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> French youth is more favourable to you, especially in the provinces, and the replacement of personnel in the Académie would have allowed your appointment sooner or later, but it is better that this should have happened now.</p>
                    <p>You will have received the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> volume of our <hi rend="underline">Monographiæ Phanerogamarum</hi>, which I instructed the bookseller to send you.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> It is a book to consult on occasion, that’s all. At most one or two pages in the generalizations on <hi rend="underline">Smilax</hi> are worth the effort to hold your attention.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> As an aside, in comparing the fossil <hi rend="underline">Smilax</hi> with living, I gained a sad opinion of the so-called plant fossil species. Generic characteristics can not at all be determined by the leaves, which are here the only thing known, and moreover the leaves are reduced to blades without petioles, which make it impossible to distinguish species. I have never seen so vague a palaeontological fact.</p>
                    <p>My compliments to your sons.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I would like to meet them some time in this curious valley of the Engadine where the mountain paths have a special attraction, particularly for the young.</p>
<p>Please be assured, my dear Sir, of my most devoted regards | Alph. de Candolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>  
          
          
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 341–2. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Candolle was at the Swiss health resort Samaden (Samedan is the usual English spelling of the name) in the upper Engadine. CD was elected a corresponding member of the botanical section of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_15.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Académie des sciences</ref> of the Institut de France on 5 August 1878 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11640A.xml">letter from J.-B. Dumas and Joseph Bertrand, 5 August 1878</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD was nominated six times between 1870 and 1878 for membership of the zoological section of the Académie (Corsi and Weindling 1985, p. 699; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 18, 20, and 21). For more on the controversy surrounding the nominations, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stebbins 1988</ref>, pp. 147–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3866.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Priestley</ref>, a polemical republican and Unitarian, became a foreign member of the Académie royale des sciences on 26 February 1784 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10490.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schofield 2004</ref>, p. 151). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Armand de Quatrefages had promoted CD’s nomination for membership of the zoological section of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_15.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Académie des sciences</ref> in July 1870; some of the attacks against CD at this time were reported at length in <hi rend="italic">Revue des cours scientifiques</hi> (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7283.xml">letter from Armand de Quatrefages, 18 July 1870</ref> and n. 6). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">A. de Candolle and Candolle eds. 1878–96. The first three volumes of this work are in the Darwin Library–Down. Candolle worked on the publication with his son <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_811.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Casimir de Candolle</ref>. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Smilax</hi> is the genus of greenbrier; for more of Candolle’s observations on fertilisation in <hi rend="italic">Smilax</hi>, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11084.xml">letter from Alphonse de Candolle, 31 July 1877</ref>. See also  A. de Candolle and Candolle eds. 1878–96, 1: 26–7. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">It is not known which of CD’s sons are referred to, but Candolle mentioned <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> by name in his letter of January 1877 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25), and Francis and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_811.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Casimir de Candolle</ref> shared some of the same research interests. </note>
        </div>   
       
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>