<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4646">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Haeckel   26 October 1864<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5276</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4646 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4646.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4646.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="12">12</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp (German) damaged †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 39</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 39</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2048.xml">Haeckel, E. P. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                <date when="1864-10-26">26 Oct 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks CD for notes concerning the development of his ideas about the origin of species. Says August Schleicher and Carl Gegenbaur also interested.</p>
            <p>Names new supporters of CD’s theory, including Max Schultze, Rudolf Leuckart, and Alexander Braun. Zoologists have been more interested than botanists.</p> 
<p>He is writing a general work on the relationships among animals [<hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie der Organismen</hi> (1866)].</p>  
<p>Comments on Fritz Müller’s <hi rend="italic">Für Darwin</hi> [1864].</p>  
<p>Gegenbaur is revising his <hi rend="italic">Grundzüge der vergleichenden Anatomie</hi> [2d ed. (1870)] to accord with evolution.</p>  
<p>Thanks CD for copy of book on balanids [<hi rend="italic">Living Cirripedia</hi>, vol. 2].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">balanids</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Fur Darwin</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Generelle Morphologie der Organismen</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Grundzuge der vergleichenden Anatomie</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Living Cirripedia</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_595">Braun, A. C. H.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2908">Leuckart, K. G. F. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4240">Schultze, M. J. S.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gegenbaur, Carl 1870</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Haeckel, E. P. A. 1866</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Müller, J. F. T. 1864</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>26. October 1864.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr und Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Die vielen Arbeiten, welche jedesmal der Anfang des Wintersemesters und die Einrichtung der neuen Vorlesungen mit sich bringen,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> haben mich bisher verhindert, Ihnen für Ihren sehr willkommenen letzten Brief zu danken. Die wichtigen Notizen, welche Sie die Güte hatten, mir über den Entstehungsgang Ihrer grossen und so höchst wichtigen Anschauungen vom Ursprung der Arten mitzutheilen, haben mich im höchsten Masse interessirt, und i〈ch〉 sage Ihnen dafür ganz besonderen Dan〈k,〉 ebenso auch meine Freunde <hi rend="underline">Schleic〈her</hi> und〉 <hi rend="underline">Gegenbaur</hi>, denen ich Ihren Brief mi〈tgeteilt〉 habe.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Für uns Biologen ist 〈diese Mitteilung〉 zur Entwicklungs-Geschichte 〈ihrer Lehre〉 vom höchsten Werth, um so m〈ehr als Ihre Anschauungen〉 zur Entstehungs-Geschichte 〈der Arten〉 die Grundlage aller unserer 〈Erkenntniss bilden.〉 Ich spreche hier mit Gegen〈baur und Schlei〉cher jeden Tag von Ihnen u〈nd Ihrer Theorie〉 und jeden Tag finden wir neue Beweise für die Wahrheit derselben und entdecken darin neue fruchtbare Anregungen für unsere Arbeiten. Wohin ich in irgend einem Zweige der Zoologie mein Auge wende, überall ist est das Princip der gemeinsamen Abstammung, welches Licht und Verständniss in die am meisten verwickelten Puncte bringt und die schwierigsten Räthsel löst. Ganz besondere Freude empfinde ich aber zu sehen, wie Ihre Lehre allerwärts und mit jedem Tage neue Fortschritte macht und jetzt selbst 〈v〉ielfach von denen anerkannt wird, die 〈an〉fangs Ihre heftigsten Gegner waren.</p>
<p>〈In d〉en Monaten August und September habe ich 〈eine längere〉 Reise durch Süd-Deutschland und die 〈Schweiz gema〉cht, dabei mehrere Universitäten 〈besucht, wobei ich〉 mich selbst von der fortschreiten 〈den Verbrei〉tung der Descendenz-Theorie 〈überzeugen konnte.〉 Ein fast eben so eifrigen An〈hänger wie i〉ch selbst, ist mein Freund Édouard 〈Claparède〉 in Genf, ein ausgezeichneter Zoolog, der aber leider durch schwere und unheilbare Krankheit am Arbeiten gehindert wird.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Auch Prof. Max <hi rend="underline">Schultze</hi> in Bonn, unser erster Histolog, und Prof. <hi rend="underline">Leuckart</hi> in Giessen, einer der besten Zoologen, haben sich jetzt zu Ihrer Anschauung bekehrt.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Mehrere sehr für mich belehrende Gespräche über die verschiedenen fruchtbaren Seiten Ihrer Theorie hatte ich vor wenigen Wochen in Berlin mit Prof. Alexander <hi rend="underline">Braun</hi>, einem der ausgezeichnetsten deutschen Botaniker, der trotz seiner ziemlich hohen Jahre fast in allen Stücken mit Ihnen übereinstimt.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Im Übrigen finde ich, dass die Botaniker weit weniger von Ihrer Theorie wissen und auch weit weniger Interesse und Nutzen daran zu finden behaupten, als die Zoologen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Zum Theil liegt dies wohl in der Natur der Sache, da die vergleichende Anatomie und Entwicklungsgeschichte der Thiere, welche uns auf jedem Schritte neue Beweise für die volle Wahrheit der Abstammungslehre liefert, bei den Pflanzen noch nicht entfernt so weit bekannt ist.</p>
<p>Die genealogischen Stammbäume der grossen Gruppen sind im Pflanzenreiche noch weit schwieriger herzustellen, als im Thierreich, wo ich mich jetzt mit dieser schwierigen Arbeit bei einigen Classen beschäftige. Die allgemeinere Arbeit über die Verwandschafts Verhältnisse der Thiere, von der ich Ihnen wohl schon schrieb, werde ich wohl erst in einigen Monaten beenden, da die Schwierigkeiten auf dem fast unbebauten Felde nicht gering sind und die Arbeit mir unter den Händen wächst.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Ich hoffe aber, dass Ihnen dieselbe viele Freude machen wird, da ich ziemlich viele Beweise für die Wahrheit Ihrer Lehre zu liefern hoffe. Jetzt in meiner Einsamkeit, wo durch den Tod meiner Frau mein Gemüthsleben so vereinsamt ist, ist mir diese umfassende Arbeit ein grosser Trost, und ich treibe sie mit um so grösserem Eifer, als meine Anna selbst mich immer zu ihrer Ausführung antrieb und mir diese Aufgabe wie ein Vermächtniss hinterlassen hat.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Meine Beobachtungen über die ausserordentliche Variabilität der Coelenteraten werde ich nun wohl erst nachher veröffentlichen.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Mit grossem Interesse werden Sie die vortreffliche Arbeit von <hi rend="underline">Fritz Müller</hi>: “<hi rend="underline">Für Darwin</hi>”—gelesen haben.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Dieser vorzügliche junge Zoologe ist ein geborener Pommer, jetzt Lehrer an einer Schule in Desterro (Brasilien). Er wanderte aber aus Preussen aus, weil der politische Druck dort zu sehr das freie Wort hemmt.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Mein Freund <hi rend="underline">Gegenbaur</hi> arbeitet jetzt die zweite Auflage seines Ihnen wohl bekannten Lehrbuchs aus: “Grundzüge der vergleichenden Anatomie” (Leipzig. 1855).<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Diese zweite Auflage wird er vollständig umarbeiten, da er überall das Princip der gemeinsamen Abstammung zu Grunde legen wird.</p>
<p>Sie haben die grosse Güte, verehrtester Freund, mir ein Exemplar Ihren Balaniden-Werckes anzubieten.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Ich nehme dieses Anerbieten mit dem aufrichtigsten Dan〈k〉 aus der Hand des Mannes an, dessen Ref〈orm-〉 Werck meine wissenschaftliche Richtung b〈e〉stimmt und mein Leben ausfüllen wird. Ich werde dieses Geschenk als ein theures Andenken betrachten. Die beste Gelegenheit wird sein, mir dasselbe durch die hiesige Buchhandlung von Fr. <hi rend="underline">Frommann</hi> zu übersenden, welche mit Londoner Buchhändlern in Verbindung steht.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>Mit der Hoffnung, dass Ihre Gesundheit sich mehr und mehr bessert, und Sie uns noch lange erhalten bleiben, verbleibe ich | mit der vorzüglichsten Hochachtung | Ihr ganz ergebener | Ernst Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘Your Pamphlets.’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi>; ‘Book sent off’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi> . ‘est’ sic TJ . trans revised SI . translation checked 24 August 94 TJ . Info on the bookshop’s location from Anna’s correspondence with Stadtarchiv and Ernst-Haeckel-Haus. See queries.doc on F:<hi rend="italic">anna</hi>queries. . Para 6: ‘which you will probably know’ could also be translated ‘well-known to you’: the only way to handle it is to insert an extra footnote in the translations appendix set of notes when separated out. SE &amp; AKM.</note>
            </div>

        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Jena</placeName>
                    <date>26 October 1864</date>
                    <salute>Highly honoured Sir and Friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The many tasks, which the beginning of the winter term and the preparation of the new lectures always bring with them,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> have hitherto prevented me from thanking you for your most welcome last letter. The important notes concerning the development of your great and extremely important views on the origin of species that you were kind enough to send me greatly interested me and I want to thank you especially for them, as do my friends <hi rend="underline">Schleicher</hi> 〈and〉 <hi rend="underline">Gegenbaur</hi>, to whom I communicated your letter.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> For us biologists 〈this information〉 about the history of the development of 〈your theory〉 is of the greatest importance, especially since 〈your views〉 on the origin of 〈species〉 are the basis of all our 〈knowledge〉. Every day I speak to Gegenbaur 〈and〉 Schleicher about you and 〈your theory〉, and every day we find new evidence for its truth and receive fruitful new inspiration for our works. Wherever I turn my eye in whatever branch of zoology, it is the principle of common descent that makes clear and comprehensible the most complex subjects and solves the most difficult riddles. But I especially receive the greatest joy in seeing to what extent your theory makes progress in all directions every day and is even frequently accepted by those who were at first your most vehement opponents.</p>
<p>〈In〉 the months of August and September I was engaged in 〈a lengthy〉 journey through the South of Germany and 〈Switzerland〉 and 〈visited〉 several universities, 〈where I could assure〉 myself of the increasing spread of the theory of descent. A follower who is almost as enthusiastic as I am, is my friend Édouard 〈Claparède〉 in Geneva, an excellent zoologist whose work is unfortunately hindered by a serious and incurable illness.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Also Prof. Max <hi rend="underline">Schultze</hi> in Bonn, our foremost histologist, and Prof. <hi rend="underline">Leuckart</hi> in Giessen, one of the best zoologists, have now been converted to your view.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> A few weeks ago, I had several very instructive conversations on the various fruitful aspects of your theory with Prof. Alexander <hi rend="underline">Braun</hi>, one of the most eminent German botanists, who, notwithstanding his quite advanced age, agrees with you on almost all points.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> For the rest, I find that the botanists know much less of your theory and also have less interest in it and use for it than the zoologists.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> This is probably due in part to the nature of the subject, since the comparative anatomy and embryology of animals, which at each step provide new evidence for the full truth of the doctrine of descent, are less known by far in plants.</p>
<p>The genealogical trees of the large groups are much more difficult to produce in the vegetable than in the animal kingdom, where I am now engaged in this difficult work with some of the classes. The more general work on genealogical relationships in animals, about which I may already have written to you, will probably be finished only in a couple of months since the difficulties in this nearly unexplored field are not few and the work grows under my hands.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> However, I hope it will give you much pleasure, since I hope to provide quite a lot of evidence for the truth of your doctrine. Now in my solitude, in which the death of my wife has made my emotional life grow so lonely, this extensive work is a great consolation for me, and I pursue it with even greater zeal, since my Anna herself had always urged me to its realisation and left me this task as a legacy.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I will probably publish my observations on the extraordinary variability of the Coelenterata only later.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>You will have read with great interest the excellent work of <hi rend="underline">Fritz Müller</hi>: “<hi rend="underline">Für Darwin</hi>”.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> This outstanding young zoologist is a Pomeranian by birth and now teacher in a school in Desterro, Brazil. He emigrated from Prussia because there free speech is hindered too much by political pressure.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>My friend <hi rend="underline">Gegenbaur</hi> is at present working at the second edition of his text book, which you will probably know: “Grundzüge der vergleichenden Anatomie” (Leipzig. 1855).<ref target="#foot.f13"/> He will completely revise this second edition, in order to make the principle of common descent its foundation in all its parts.</p>
<p>You have been kind enough, highly honoured friend, to offer me a copy of your work on the Balanidae.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I accept this offer with the most sincere thanks from the hand of the man whose reformatory work determines the direction of my scientific efforts and to which I will devote my life. I will regard this present as a precious memento. The best way will be to send it through the local Fr. <hi rend="underline">Frommann</hi> bookshop, which has connections with London booksellers.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>With the hope that your health will continue to improve and that you will be preserved for us for a long time, I remain with the highest esteem | your devoted servant | Ernst Haeckel.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, pp. 379–81.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For information on the courses taught by Haeckel in his capacity as professor extraordinarius of zoology at the University of Jena between 1861 and 1869, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7938.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Uschmann 1959</ref>, pp. 40–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, [after 10] August – 8 October [1864]</ref>. Haeckel refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">August Schleicher</ref> and Carl Gegenbaur (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 9 [July 1864]</ref> and n. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The reference is to the Swiss naturalist and invertebrate zoologist <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_931.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edouard Claparède</ref>, who contracted rheumatic fever in 1854. The attack left him with chronic and disabling heart problems, his symptoms including palpitations and spitting blood from the lungs. The illness prevented him from working for months on end, and during 1865 and 1866 he hardly worked at all (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6907.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Saussure 1873</ref>, pp. vii, xiii–xviii). In 1861 Claparède published a favourable review of CD’s theory (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1405.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claparède 1861</ref>); see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10. CD’s annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1405.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Claparède 1861</ref> is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In 1865 <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4240.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Johann Sigismund Schultze</ref> published a paper containing positive remarks on CD’s theory (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6988.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schultze 1865</ref>); there is a copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6988.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schultze 1865</ref> in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Rodolf Leuckart did not express a view on CD’s theory until 1867, when he reviewed Haeckel’s <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie</hi> and concluded that on the question of descent he agreed with Haeckel (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5926.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nyhart 1995</ref>, p. 138.) Nyhart also comments on Leuckart’s approach to teleology and adaptation: see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 138, 340. For more on Leuckart’s views on natural selection, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8523.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wunderlich 1978</ref>, pp. 73–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Haeckel had studied botany under <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Carl Heinrich Braun</ref> at Berlin university in the spring of 1852 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3508.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hemleben 1964</ref>, p. 23; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7939.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Uschmann 1984</ref>, p. 15). Braun had expressed some ideas on evolution in plants as early as 1848 (see Henfrey trans. 1853), and although he was never convinced by CD’s theory of natural selection, he did try to reconcile his own teleological approach to transformation with CD’s (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3860.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hoppe 1971</ref>, p. 405). For an overview of the reaction among German botanists, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Junker 1989</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">For further discussions of the reception of CD’s theory in Germany, see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 9 [July 1864]</ref> and n. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Haeckel is apparently referring to his <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie</hi>, which was eventually published in 1866 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref>). He had told CD about his plan to write the book in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 9 [July 1864]</ref>. There is an annotated copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Haeckel 1866</ref> in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 355–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Haeckel’s wife, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4299.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Anna Sethe</ref>, died on 16 February 1864 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4586.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 10 August 1864</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Haeckel published several essays on the Coelenterata between 1864 and 1865 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4555.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Ernst Haeckel, 9 [July 1864]</ref> and n. 15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The reference is to F. Müller 1864; CD’s lightly annotated copy of this work is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 609). F. Müller 1864 was a study of the developmental history of the Crustacea, which <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref> presented as a validation of CD’s theory. CD provided the financial backing for an English translation, which was published in 1869 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 16 March [1868]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1163.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi></ref> no. 6014), Möller ed. 1915–21, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">Before leaving Prussia in 1852, Müller had been barred from taking his medical degree owing to his democratic political opinions and his refusal to take an oath recognising the established church and orthodox religious views (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>). On Müller’s reasons for emigrating to Brazil, see Möller ed. 1915–21, 3: 24–44. For a discussion of state control and the suppression of political movements in German universities during this period, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5058.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McClelland 1980</ref>. For the state control of medical education and practice in Prussia, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3915.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Huerkamp 1990</ref>, including pp. 77-8 on the oath requirement. On the licensing of doctors in Prussia, see McClelland 1991, pp. 38–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Haeckel was mistaken: the first edition of Gegenbaur’s <hi rend="italic">Grundzüge der vergleichenden Anatomie</hi> was published in 1859; the second edition appeared in 1870. There is a copy of Gegenbaur 1870 in the Darwin Library–Down (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 299).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4631.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Ernst Haeckel, [after 10] August – 8 October [1864]</ref> and n. 13, and CD’s annotation to this letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">The reference is to the Friedrich Frommann bookshop, at house no. 225, later Markt 19, in Jena, owned by Friedrich Johann Frommann (<hi rend="italic">Meyers Enzyklopädisches Lexikon</hi>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>