<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5008A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Traherne Moggridge   15 February [1866]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20759</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5008A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5008A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5008A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp with sketches</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR Pamphlet collection G368 (bound in part of Moggridge 1865–8)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>Pamphlet collection (bound in Moggridge 1867)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3353.xml">Moggridge, J. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Maison Fontana, Mentone</placeName>
                <date when="1866-02-15">15 Feb [1866]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Is sending <hi rend="italic">Ophrys</hi> plants marked as CD requested as wild or under cultivation. Discusses arrangements for a scheme planned for 1867 and his method for marking his <hi rend="italic">Ophrys</hi> specimens.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Ophrys</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Maison Fontana | Mentone</placeName>
                    <date>Feb. 15</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>As we are sending a parcel by <hi rend="underline">Grand Vitesse</hi> to my brother at Leicester, I take the opportunity of enclosing a box of Ophryses for you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I have great doubts as to their fate, for the French railways do not really understand either speed or precision.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for your letter of Jan. 26, in accordance with which I am marking plants both under cultivation &amp; wild.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I am now so far restored to health that I do not think it likely that I shall return next year to Mentone; I shall therefore endeavour to get some one of my friends to carry out the scheme in 1867.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>I have, as you suggest, selected &amp; marked some plants which correspond to the early forms figured in my Plates;<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but I find variation so very prevalent, that I generally prefer making careful sketches of each of the marked plants.—</p>
<p>I have, however, obtained one bit of evidence which would tend to shew that there is a considerable degree of stability in the early forms (such as A plate 43);<ref target="#foot.f6"/> for the other day I again gathered the flowers from a certain well marked &amp; separate group of plants, which I have by chance observed as each of the last three previous Springs have come round, &amp; they have uniformly presented the green sepals &amp; petals of <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Oph.</hi> <hi rend="underline">aranifera</hi>. Thus no marked change has taken place throughout four successive years.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I feel quite sure also that there is a great tendency among seedlings to retain a resemblance to the parent plant; as I always notice that when a few isolated plants are closely grouped together they almost invariably have most of their peculiarities in common.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I am keeping a register of the difference of character which may frequently be found in flowers on the same spike: for I often find that though the lowest flowers may have a complex marking, those above present either the simple π marked or an approach to it, &amp; <hi rend="underline">vice versâ.</hi>—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>thus:—</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>DIAG HERE</p> </figure> 
<p>or thus:–</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>Labellum of Fl:1 of Fl:2 of Fl:3</p>
<p>labellum of Flowers 1, 3, 4 of 2, 5 6</p> </figure> 
<p>With respect to the Insects concerned in the fertilization of the Ophryses I have as yet no information to give, except indeed that one day lately I captured a small black ant gnawing the bracts of one of these plants.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I am thinking of making an attempt to capture these mysterious visitors by smearing the labellum of a few plants with some viscid (&amp; unattractive) matter</p>
<p>I find it a very accurate method for marking my Ophrys plants to fasten round each a little zinc label, such as they use in the Hotels here for the numbers on keys thus</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>—In this manner I can distinguish a very large series of individuals.</p>
<p>Believe me dear Sir | y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> very truly | J. Traherne Moggridge <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Ch. Darwin Es<hi rend="superscript">qr</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>0.3 Dear Sir … careful sketches of each 5.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 I am now … Mentone; 4.2] <hi rend="italic">2 crosses in margin, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>9.1 With respect to … the labellum of a few 9.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of first page</hi>: ‘Box | Health | Facts’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by Moggridge’s reference to 1867 as ‘next year’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Moggridge refers to his father, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Matthew Moggridge</ref>, who accompanied him to Mentone (<hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London</hi> 1882–3, pp. 42–3) and to his brother <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6360.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Matthew Weston Moggridge</ref>, curate of St John’s Church, Leicester (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1644.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Crockford’s clerical directory</hi></ref> 1868). French railways offered two classes of goods service: <hi rend="italic">grande vitesse</hi>, or express, and <hi rend="italic">petite vitesse</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5535.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Monkswell 1911</ref>, p. 85). Moggridge had sent a previous consignment of <hi rend="italic">Ophrys</hi> specimens in December 1865 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. T. Moggridge, 27 December [1865]</ref> and n. 2; see also Moggridge 1865–8, text accompanying plate XLV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The letter of 26 January has not been found. CD had earlier written to Moggridge asking him to mark spider orchids at Mentone (probably <hi rend="italic">Ophrys arachnites</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Ophrys fuciflora</hi>, the late spider-orchid) and subsequently to send them for cultivation at Down; CD’s object was to determine whether the plants ‘kept constant’ when planted in England (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. T. Moggridge, 13 October [1865]</ref> and n. 5). It is likely, however, that this scheme was extended in a missing letter to include related forms of <hi rend="italic">Ophrys</hi> described in Moggridge 1865–8. Moggridge could have marked plants of <hi rend="italic">O. aranifera</hi> (the spider ophrys) and a closely related form in flower at Mentone in February, but not other forms (including <hi rend="italic">O. arachnites</hi>) which flower later (see Moggridge 1865–8, text accompanying plates XLIV–XLV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Moggridge evidently returned to Mentone during the winter of 1866 to 1867 and wrote from Mentone to CD on 6 March [1867] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15). That letter prompted CD’s note dated 9 March 1867: ‘Mr M now informs me that with natural plants no marked change from last year.—’ The note is on CD’s annotated copy of part of Moggridge 1865–8 (<hi rend="italic">Contributions to the flora of Mentone</hi>); the copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL and is bound together with the present letter. Specimens collected at Mentone in spring 1867 are also recorded in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5518.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1869</ref> (‘Ueber Ophrys insectifera L. (part)’).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD had received copies of plates XLIII–XLV, and their accompanying text, from Moggridge 1865–8 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4914.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. T. Moggridge, 13 October [1865]</ref> and n. 2). The plates illustrated variation in the flowers of thirteen forms of <hi rend="italic">Ophrys insectifera</hi> L. (the fly orchid), under which taxon Moggridge included <hi rend="italic">O. aranifera</hi>, <hi rend="italic">O. arachnites</hi> (the late spider ophrys), <hi rend="italic">O. scolopax</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">O. apifera</hi> (the bee orchid), and were arranged in order of flowering date. For the earliest, that is those that flowered in February at Mentone, see n. 3, above. Moggridge refers to forms rather than species because his object was to identify forms that were intermediate between the named species (see Moggridge 1865–8, text accompanying plate XLIII).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Moggridge refers to <hi rend="italic">Ophrys aranifera</hi>; in his copy of Moggridge 1865–8, CD annotated flower A, plate XLIII: ‘O. aranifera Hudson’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In the text accompanying plate XLIV, Moggridge described his observations at Mentone, over four seasons, of a series of intermediate forms between the earliest flowering form, <hi rend="italic">Ophrys aranifera</hi>, and the latest, <hi rend="italic">O. apifera.</hi> By late February, he observed the first variant, a form having brown petals and pale sepals, rather than the green petals and darker sepals characteristic of <hi rend="italic">O. aranifera</hi> (Moggridge 1865–8). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 59, CD wrote: ‘Mr. Moggridge further shows that in Italy <hi rend="italic">O. aranifera</hi> flowers first, and <hi rend="italic">O. apifera</hi> last, the intermediate forms at intermediate periods.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">A fuller account of parental influences on the inheritance of characters in <hi rend="italic">Ophrys</hi> is given in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5518.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1869</ref>, pp. 6–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Similar variation in the markings of flowers on the same spike of a form that was intermediate between <hi rend="italic">Ophrys aranifera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">O. arachnites</hi> is illustrated in Moggridge 1865–8, plate XLIV; a further example was considered in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5518.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Moggridge 1869</ref>, p. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD had noted that in Britain <hi rend="italic">Ophrys</hi> species were seldom visited by pollinating insects (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 62, 66, 68). CD also referred to the pollination of the bee ophrys, <hi rend="italic">O. apifera</hi>, as his ‘greatest puzzle’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4200.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to P. H. Gosse, 2 June [1863]</ref> and n. 12). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 8, letter to <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, [4–5 June 1860] (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 34).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>