<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5038F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Robert McLachlan   23 March [1866]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21320</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5038F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5038F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5038F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18-Supplement</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="endorsement" subtype="letter">1866 | C. Darwin | Down | 23 March</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Raab Collection (dealer) (June 2014)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_501.xml">Raab Collection</repository>
                    <collection>June 2014</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1866-03-23">23 Mar [1866]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3274.xml">McLachlan, Robert</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for the paper on Sterrha (McLachlan 1865).</p>
        </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Mar 23 </date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am very much obliged to you for your paper on Sterrha, which I have read with very great interest.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Many of your observations are quite new to me. I was particularly glad to read about the varying organs in the Neuroptera;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> should you ascertain similar cases in the Trichoptera,<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be grateful for information.</p>
<p>Would it not be well worth while to get some of your friends to breed Eupithecia from eggs of the same female &amp; to feed them on different plants &amp; thus ascertain positively how the mimicry is effected.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I have been very glad to see (whether or not you have been influenced by my writings) that you have given up to a great extent the belief in the immutability of species;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> &amp; I feel sure that as you attend to other subjects besides the discrimination of species you will ultimately go further in your belief; at least I have hitherto found this to be the case with those who have doubted to a limited degree.</p>
<p>With my best thanks believe me dear Sir | yours very faithfully | Ch. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">An incomplete version of the letter text taken from a sale catalogue transcription was published in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 18, Supplement. This version is from a facsimile.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD refers to McLachlan’s paper ‘On some remarkable varieties of <hi rend="italic">Sterrha sacraria</hi> Linn., with general notes on variation in Lepidoptera’ (McLachlan 1865). <hi rend="italic">Sterrha sacraria</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Rhodometra sacraria</hi>, the vestal. It belongs to the family Geometridae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See McLachlan 1865, p. 467. The order Neuroptera is now restricted to lacewings and their kin, but used to include dragonflies and damselflies, which are now in the order Odonata (see also n. 6, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Trichoptera is the order of caddisflies.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Eupithecia</hi> is a genus of the family Geometridae; it includes most of the moths commonly known as pugs. McLachlan had observed that, among Lepidoptera, while the larva in this genus showed the greatest tendency to variation, the imago was most constant. He suggested that the larval variation was related to a tendency of the larva to mimic the colour of the food plant on which it developed (see McLachlan 1865, p. 465).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">McLachlan had referred to transitional species of <hi rend="italic">Gomphus</hi> (club-tailed dragonflies, then in the order Neuroptera) as evidence for development theory (McLachlan 1865, p. 467).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>