<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4202">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   [3 June 1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14756</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4202 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4202.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4202.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">10pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 93</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 93</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>Edinburgh Botanic Gardens</placeName>
                <date when="1863-06-03">[3 June 1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks CD for influence used with Hooker to obtain a colonial position. Has offended J. H. Balfour by refusing the Darjeeling post and James McNab has become unfriendly, although his experiments do not detract from his garden work.</p> 
<p>Will write <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> paper for Linnean Society as CD suggests.</p> 
            <p>His Darwinism is unpalatable at Edinburgh Botanic Garden.</p> 
<p>Describes results with non-dimorphic <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> species. Such cases do not accord with CD’s view that characters are slowly acquired.</p> 
            <p>Thanks for criticism of his writing style.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Primula</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Primula</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2357">Hooker, J. D.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Edinburgh Botanic Garden</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Scott, John 1864b</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">colonial position</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">Linnean Society</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Botanic Gardens [Edinburgh]</placeName>
                    <date>Wednesday. </date>
                    <salute>Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I duly received your letter of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am greatly indebted for trouble in my behalf: and favourable impression you have made upon D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker; as shown by his kind &amp; encouraging letter.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I can only express my most cordial thanks, and a hope that if through your influence with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hooker; he obtains for me a colonial appointment, you will have no cause to regret having exercised your influence in behalf of one, of whom you know so little. I will do my best to give satisfaction: In respect to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Hookers letter permit me to ask you for a few hints—at some future time—as to mental qualifications required; that I may apply myself more directly to the cultivation of such. I am painfully alive to the defects of an imperfect education; circumstances, having compelled me to finish it just at that period, when I was beginning to acquire a taste for learning.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Prof. Balfour seems to be not a little offended with me, for refusing the Darjeling situation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I hope, however, he will soon forget it. I feel assured he would have given me an excellent recommendation to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Anderson:<ref target="#foot.f6"/> and I shall certainly make it my earnest endeavour to <hi rend="underline">merit</hi> it no less in the future. I thank you for judicious counsel respecting duties to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.Nab.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have always been very careful that my experiments do not in the least interfere with my other duties; and I am glad to say—that—so far as I am aware—he is perfectly satisfied with me in this respect, and would I believe readily recommend me. If ever he had given me the slightest grounds for supposing that experiments were interfering with my duties to him, I would at once have restricted them, but he has given me no cause for such suspicions. It was very natural, however, for Dr. Hooker to suppose such. I cannot say what is the exact cause of his colder and less encouraging treatment: but for some months back there has been clearly a great change, in bestowal of <hi rend="underline">voluntary</hi> privileges. I was—and am—much grieved at observing this; as I previously thought that he had a kindly interest in my advancement. Rest assured, however, that though, unfortunately—working in perfect ignorance of the real cause of his changed demeanour, I will do my utmost to please him as to performance of duties. At present—I am sorry to say for him—I have more opportunities for doing so than ever: nearly all his duties in connection with Botanic Class having devolved upon me—he being unable to attend to them.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>I will have a care that neither Dr. Balfour nor M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.Nab know anything respecting Dr. Hooker’s letter: as I much fear your suspicion would otherwise be immediately verified.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>In conclusion, I would beg you to excuse this long detail of personal matters: they have interfered unpleasantly with our other correspondence. I would also again acknowledge how deeply I feel indebted for the kind and active interest you have taken in me. It would afford me a pleasure to be able to make you any return: for I have no right to trouble you with such matters. The experiments which you have already suggested, I will attend to: if there are any others which you would like me to try—if within my power—I will gladly undertake them.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>I will now turn to the scientific part of letter. In respect to closing of stigma in Orchids: I will yet attend to your hint, as to affinities required.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> From observations on closing of orifice it occurred to me on reading Bolbolophyllum case, that foreign pollen might possibly induce it;<ref target="#foot.f12"/> I had, however, at the time I performed experiments on this point, my Cypripedium Oncidium &amp; the Trichopilia in flower: so that my observations are not at all numerous. I feel perfectly satisfied, however that they are correct: having applied pollen to a few flowers, and extracted a little of it a few days after, when I distinctly saw pollen-tubes. I did not observe—as I ought—the depth these penetrated: the flowers were allowed to remain until quite withered: orifice likewise remaining open.</p>
<p>I thank you for kind offer respecting Primula work. I will draw up a paper, when I have seen results of present experiments, and forward. I will be glad indeed if you consider it worthy of communicating to the Linn. Soc. I do not think such papers are much cared for here.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> I am rather afraid now that the abstract of Orchid paper sent you, will be all that is published of it in Proceedings of Bot. Soc.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> From the great interest &amp; importance which your works &amp; correspondence has attached to such questions in my mind, I have often wondered at the low estimate in which they appear to be held here. Your remarks in late letters enlighten me: and here of course anything that savours of the “<hi rend="underline">Origin</hi>” is not at all palatable!<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Nevertheless, I, having a strong conviction of its truthful teachings, would not on account of such dogmatic prejudices—for I cannot think they are aught else—sacrifice the “integrity of my own mind”. As Emerson has expressed it;— “Bravely let us speak the utmost syllable of our confession .... nor be ashamed of that divine idea which each of us represents”<ref target="#foot.f16"/>— so would I did my qualifications permit.</p>
<p>Thanks for corroboration of <hi rend="underline">P. longiflora</hi>, you will observe it with a note mentioned in list formerly transmitted as <hi rend="underline">non-dimorphic</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> <hi rend="underline">P. verticillata</hi> is peculiar. In my list you will find it approaching the non-dimorphic state. The majority of flowers upon a plant which I am experimenting upon at present, have <hi rend="underline">Stamens</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Styles</hi> <hi rend="underline">equal</hi>: both being included within corolla tubes: the others have <hi rend="underline">styles</hi> slightly <hi rend="underline">exserted</hi> beyond tubes. In a specimen which I have lately examined in the University Herbarium I find a truly <hi rend="underline">long</hi>-<hi rend="underline">styled</hi> form—anthers near the <hi rend="underline">middle</hi> styles reaching the <hi rend="underline">mouth</hi> of corolla-tube.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">P. floribunda</hi> appears to present similar peculiarities. In list you will find it referred to <hi rend="underline">short</hi>-<hi rend="underline">styled</hi> form, with note on the occurrence of a non-dimorphic form. This I have again found presented by another specimen, while another, has presented one with the <hi rend="underline">long</hi>-styled condition. Of P. <hi rend="underline">floribunda</hi> I have no plants for experiments, and of P. verticillata I have only the <hi rend="underline">non-dimorphic</hi> form; which appears to be perfectly self-fertile.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> I believe I have been successful in application of <hi rend="underline">its</hi> pollen to long &amp; short-styled <hi rend="underline">P. Auricula</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> I am extremely curious to see results of this from a case which I will presently refer to, and on account of which I should have liked much to have tested the reciprocal sexual relations of these apparently <hi rend="underline">trimorphic species</hi>.</p>
<p>The sexual relations of the non-dimorphic Cowslip referred to in late letter, appear to be very different from what I expected!<ref target="#foot.f21"/> It seems to have undergone a special differentiation: being all but <hi rend="underline">inert</hi> in its action as <hi rend="underline">male</hi> on <hi rend="underline">long</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">short-styled</hi> forms—capsules being very small—as <hi rend="underline">female</hi>, pollen being applied from the <hi rend="underline">latter</hi> form it promises to be more productive—capsules being larger. The size of respective capsules farther illustrates, I think a fact which you have already pointed out, viz that <hi rend="underline">short-styled</hi> form is more feminine in nature &amp;c &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f22"/> Capsules on <hi rend="underline">short-styled</hi> plants are larger than those on <hi rend="underline">long-styled</hi>—both being fertilised with <hi rend="underline">non-dimorphic</hi> form. Again those flowers on the <hi rend="underline">latter</hi> fertilised with <hi rend="underline">long-styled</hi> pollen have <hi rend="underline">larger</hi> capsules than those fertilised with <hi rend="underline">short-styled</hi>! I did not at all anticipate such results: and I am now sorry that I did not make more numerous experiments with these forms. They have surprised me much; indeed, perplexed me. Since you have mentioned case of <hi rend="underline">Linum Lewisii</hi>—which is much like a case of <hi rend="underline">mere variability</hi>—there will be no harm I think in giving the above case.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> I am inclined to regard such cases as somewhat discordant with your views that these qualities have been <hi rend="underline">slowly</hi> acquired. Analogous cases have been <hi rend="underline">already passed</hi> by your <hi rend="underline">numerous critics</hi> so I may be wrong.</p>
<p>Another curious fact which I have lately discovered respecting <hi rend="underline">non-dimorphic</hi> Auriculas— will I think interest you. The few plants which I have observed in this state, agree with that mentioned by you in Primula paper, in having even smaller pollen-grains than the normal long-styled form: differing in this respect from the above Cowslip.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> In crossing with the <hi rend="underline">long</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">short</hi> <hi rend="underline">styled</hi> forms, I find that with the <hi rend="underline">former</hi> the capsules are <hi rend="underline">very small</hi>: <hi rend="underline">larger</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">finer</hi> with the <hi rend="underline">latter</hi>: which is favourable to your opinion that it is a case of abnormal developement of anthers. The self-fertilised capsules on non-<hi rend="underline">dimorphic</hi> form are <hi rend="doubleUnderline">larger</hi> than those produced by homomorphic crosses!</p>
<p>I am glad to find that the abstract of my Orchid paper interests you.<ref target="#foot.f25"/> I am also greatly obliged for the few critical remarks you have made.<ref target="#foot.f26"/> I now see that I would have rendered the case of <hi rend="underline">O.</hi> <hi rend="underline">sphacelatum</hi> much more striking if I had stated it as you have done. I wished to state it in as forcible a manner as possible but you see how signally I have failed! I have had so little experience. Your analysis of sentence on self-impotence, shows me how unfortunately I have expressed myself. It appears now so self-evident that I cannot help wondering how it escaped me! I thank you most sincerely for these criticisms: I will do my best to improve style, which is one of the greatest difficulties I have to contend with. I have no command of language, no power of expression; and I am afraid from the little knowledge I have of mental phenomena, that I will never overcome this; which I fear will eventually give me quite a distaste for writing. I often wonder at and envy you for that happy faculty of expressing the most recondite ideas in language which a child might almost understand</p>
<p>I have made no experiments on <hi rend="underline">Lobelia fulgens</hi>. I forgot when I wrote last your experiments on this plant in “Origin” and was writing under the impression that Gartner regarded it as absolutely sterile with own-pollen. while a friend of mine had succeeded in seeding it by fertilising it with own-pollen.<ref target="#foot.f27"/> I see, however, that I have misapprehended this case.</p>
<p>Are you making any experiments in <hi rend="underline">Linum Lewisii</hi>? It will be interesting from above case of Cowslip to test the reciprocal sexual relations. We have plants in the Gardens; if you think it worth while, and are not already engaged with it, I will make a few experiments: if plants present the trimorphic condition.</p>
<p>You ask if non-dimorphic Cowslip be the common yellow?<ref target="#foot.f28"/> It is a red variety of this approaching the form generally known as <hi rend="underline">rubra</hi>.</p>
<p>I have not yet succeeded in experiments on self-fertilisation of Orchids, by preventing expansion of perianth.<ref target="#foot.f29"/> I have seen pollen-tubes however developed by such means in a flower of <hi rend="underline">Bletia</hi> <hi rend="underline">Tankervillia</hi>: but all the others which I had thus treat dropped off, the capsules giving no indications of swelling. As there have been few species in flower, however, in the Gardens since the idea occurred to me, I have not been able to make my experiments: but I have no doubt that I will yet be able to demonstrate it.</p>
<p>I remain | Sir | Yours very respectfully | John Scott</p>
<p>P.S. I intended sending corrected copy of “Orchid paper to Gard. Chron.<ref target="#foot.f30"/> Before doing so I went to Prof. Balfour thinking that he might not have sent the copy off. I was too late however, and, being busy he said he would look it over after, and see whether it would be worth while sending it. My astonishment was great next morning when his assistant told me that he considered the corrections unnecessary. I of course was silent; though I thought it strange that the Prof. could so express himself. I am pleased to find that you have a different opinion in respect to this. | J. Scott.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.7 In respect … such. 1.9] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 I will now … be wrong. 9.17] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this letter, the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref>, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4207.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 8 [June 1863]</ref>; the Wednesday between 31 May and 8 June 1863 was 3 June.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Scott wrote ‘20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>’ in error; the reference is to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref> (see n. 3, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD enclosed the missing portion of the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4134.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [23–7 May 1863]</ref>, with his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Scott of 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref> and n. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_259.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hutton Balfour</ref> was keeper of the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh, where Scott was foreman of the propagating department (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1994</ref>). Scott had declined a position in charge of a <hi rend="italic">Cinchona</hi> plantation in India for which Balfour had offered to recommend him (see letters from John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 May 1863</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">26 May [1863]</ref>, and n. 6, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_112.xml">Thomas Anderson</ref>, superintendent of the Calcutta botanic garden, was a leading figure in a project to introduce species of <hi rend="italic">Cinchona</hi> to India for the production of quinine (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_342.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Balfour 1873</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). He planned to establish a plantation for the cultivation of <hi rend="italic">Cinchona calisaya</hi> near Darjeeling, and had written to Balfour, his former professor at the University of Edinburgh, asking for recommendations for the post of plantation overseer (see letters from John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 May 1863</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">26 May [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">As curator of the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3279.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James McNab</ref> was Scott’s immediate superior. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 22 May 1863</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4134.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [23–7 May 1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4177.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 22 May 1863</ref>, n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">In December 1862, CD had, at Scott’s request, suggested numerous experiments for Scott to attempt (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, letters from John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3847.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">6 December [1862]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3865.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">17 December [1862]</ref>, and letters to John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3853.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">11 December [1862]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3868.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">19 December [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See the enclosure to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4174.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 May [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref> and n. 2; Scott’s observations were published in Scott 1863a, pp. 545–6 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Scott of 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>, CD offered to communicate an account of Scott’s work on dimorphism in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref>, when finished, if Scott considered that it would not be adequately noticed by the Botanical Society of Edinburgh. Scott’s paper on <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> (Scott 1864a) was read before the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 4 February 1864, and published in the society’s <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for September 1864 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2782.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">General index to the Journal of the Linnean Society</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Scott read his paper on the pollination of orchids before the Botanical Society of Edinburgh on 14 May 1863 (Scott 1863a); he enclosed an abstract of the paper, which appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi> on 28 May 1863, p. 8, with his letter to CD of <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4190.xml">28 May [1863]</ref>. Scott’s paper was subsequently published in full in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Botanical Society [of Edinburgh]</hi> (Scott 1863a; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4213.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 16 June [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">See letters to John Scott, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4183.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">23 May [1863]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Scott paraphrases <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1504.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ralph Waldo Emerson’s</ref> essay ‘Self-reliance’, where Emerson states: ‘Nothing is at last sacred but the integrity of our own mind’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2335.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Emerson 1841</ref>, p. 50), and: ‘Bravely let him speak the utmost syllable of his confession. We but half express ourselves, and are ashamed of that divine idea which each of us represents’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 47).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>. Scott sent CD a list of dimorphic and non-dimorphic species of <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> at the end of 1862, but this list has not been found (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3844.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 3 December [1862]</ref> and n. 2). A similar list appeared in Scott 1864a, p. 80.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">In Scott 1864a, pp. 80 and 82, Scott treated <hi rend="italic">Primula verticillata</hi> as non-dimorphic, but described the length of the style as ‘slightly variable’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">In Scott 1864a, pp. 80–2, Scott treated <hi rend="italic">Primula floribunda</hi> as a short-styled species, but explained that it occasionally presented individuals with a non-dimorphic structure.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">See Scott 1864a, pp. 92–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4174.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 May [1863]</ref>, and Scott 1864a, pp. 105–10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">This is implied, although not explicitly stated, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, pp. 92–3 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 59–60).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref>, pp. 82–3 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 104–5), CD described the occurrence in <hi rend="italic">Linum lewisii</hi> of three forms of flower (short-styled, long-styled, and equal-styled) appearing on the same plant, a case that he believed to be ‘unique’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2048.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Dimorphic condition in <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi>’</ref>, p. 80 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 48). Scott described his observations and experiments on the dimorphic <hi rend="italic">Primula auricula</hi> in Scott 1864a, pp. 91–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">See n. 14, above, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 28 May [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 98, CD cited his observations of dichogamy in <hi rend="italic">Lobelia fulgens</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">L. cardinalis</hi>) as evidence that there were ‘special contrivances’ in many plants that prevented the stigma ‘receiving pollen from its own flower’. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3844.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 3 December [1862]</ref>. Scott may have been confused by CD’s additional reference in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 250, to ‘certain species of Lobelia’ being ‘far more easily fertilised by the pollen of another and distinct species, than by their own pollen’. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 19 November [1862]</ref>. Scott refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1774.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Friedrich von Gärtner</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4185.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 25 and 28 May [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f29">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4073.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, [1–11] April [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f30">See n. 14, above, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 31 May [1863]</ref>. The abstract of Scott 1863a published in the <hi rend="italic">Gardeners’ Chronicle</hi>, 13 June 1863, p. 558, has a number of minor from the abstract published in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Evening Courant</hi>, 28 May 1863, p. 8.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>