<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10724">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alphonse de Candolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   16 December 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14130</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10724 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10724.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10724.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Baehni (1955): 144</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 19</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 19</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml">Candolle, Alphonse de</persName>
                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                <date when="1876-12-16">16 Dec 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for <hi rend="italic">Cross and self-fertilisation</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Discusses geographical implications of inbreeding. Can the length of time an insular flora has been isolated be estimated by its weakness due to inbreeding?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Cross and self-fertilisation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">in-breeding</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time, ‘inorganic’ (geological, historical)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Genève</placeName>
                    <date>16 Dec. 1876</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai lu avec le plus vif intérêt l’ouvrage sur les <hi rend="underline">Cross and</hi> <hi rend="underline">self fertilizations</hi> que vous avez eu la bonté de m’envoyer.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Le sujet est important, et comme mèthode d’expérience, ou comme exposition, je ne crois pas que la physiologie végétale possede rien d’aussi satisfaisant. Votre persévérance pendant une série d’années aussi longue et l’ordre qui doit régner dans vos notes, me confondent. Vos publications partielles avaient deja fait connaitre les resultats principaux, mais l’ensemble est ici très concluant et très curieux.</p>
<p>Malgré ce que vous dites que les conditions changent d’un emplacement à un autre dans un même jardin ou une même localité,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> il serait intéressant de comparer comme vous l’avez fait, les descendants d’une espèce prise dans des îles, surtout de petites îles sans montagnes, avec les descendants de la même espèce venant d’un continent. Les individus d’une petit île sont presque completement de la même famille, car les transports sont rares au travers de la mer, surtout ceux qui aboutissent à des plantes développées, portant des fleurs. A priori on peut soupconner, d’après vos observations, d’assez grandes différences entre les insulaires d’une espèce et les autres, mais on manque de comparaisons précises. Aussurement les îles de S<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> Helène, Maurice, Bourbon et Ceylan<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (quoique cette dernière soit rapprochée de l’Inde) ont été le théatre d’invasions fréquentes d’espèces qui ont pris la place des anciennes espèces indigènes ou qui leur nuisent. Les espèces insulaires sont donc plus faibles, mais les individus d’une même espèce le sont-ils? C’est probable. Le degré relatif de faiblesse des individus insulaires indiquerait quelque chose sur l’ancienneté probable de l’isolement. Les formes extérieures sont peu modifiées dans beaucoup d’îles qu’on peut croire séparées depuis des milliers d’années, quoique, géologiquement parlant, ce soit depuis des périodes peu anciennes. Ainsi les espèces des deux rives de la Mediterranée se retrouvent dans les îles intermédiaires et aux Canaries et à Madeira, presque toujours sans qu’on hesite à les dire semblables. La séparation est cependant plus ancienne que celle da la Grande Bretagne d’avec le Continent.</p>
<p>L’avantage conféré par le mélange d’individus originaires de pays differents promet au Continent européen une superbe race à la suite des chemins de fer! Hélas, il n’est pas bien sur que d’autres causes ne contrebalancent pas cet effet heureux du mélange des familles, l’indépendance personnelle favorisant aussi le vice et amenant une concurrence qui surexcite les facultés et crée des cas d’aliénation et de suicide.</p>
<p>J’ai lu avec plaisir l’opuscule de Mons<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> votre fils sur certaines glands d’Acacia etc, aussi est-ce à lui que je prends la liberté d’adresser quelques lignes sur un point analogue.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Agréez, mon cher Monsieur, l’assurance de mes sentiments les plus dévoués. | Alph. DeCandolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                    <date>16 Dec. 1876</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have read with the most lively interest your work on <hi rend="underline">Cross and self fertilizations</hi>, which you have had the kindness to send me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The subject is important, and as regards experimental method, or exposition, I do not believe that plant physiology possesses anything as satisfying. Your perseverance over such a long series of years and the organisation which must prevail in your notes, astound me. Your preliminary publications had already disclosed the main results, but the whole is here very convincing and very curious.</p>
<p>Although you say that conditions change from one position to another in the same garden or the same area,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> it would be interesting to compare, as you have done, the descendants of a species collected on islands, especially on small ones without mountains, with the descendants of the same species originating on a continent. The individuals of a small island are almost all from the same family, for transports across the sea are rare, especially those which culminate with mature plants, bearing flowers. A priori, based on your observations, plenty of major differences between the insular varieties of a species and other ones can be suspected, but precise comparisons are lacking. Certainly the islands of St Helena, Mauritius, Bourbon and Ceylon<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (even though this last is getting closer to India) have been the scene of frequent invasions of species that have taken the place of ancient indigenous species or that are detrimental to them. Insular species are therefore more vulnerable, but are individuals of the same species equally so? It is likely. The relative degree of vulnerability of insular individuals would show something of the probable antiquity of isolation. The exterior forms are not much modified in many islands that can be thought to have separated thousands of years ago, even though geologically speaking this would not be since very ancient periods. Thus species from the two shores of the Mediterranean are found on islands in the middle, and in the Canaries, and at Madeira; almost always we would not hesitate to call them similar. The separation is however older than that of Great Britain and the Continent.</p>
<p>The advantage conferred by the mixing of individuals originating in different countries promises the European Continent a superb race in the wake of the railways! Alas, it is not certain that other causes do not counterbalance this favourable effect of blending of families, personal independence also promoting vice and bringing competition, which overexcites the faculties and creates instances of alienation and suicide.</p>
<p>I have read with pleasure your son’s paper on certain glands of Acacia, etc., so it is to him that I take the liberty of addressing a few lines on an analogous point.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I remain, dear sir, sincerely your devoted | Alph. DeCandolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 390–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Candolle’s name is on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref> (see Appendix III).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD discussed how changes in conditions affected the variability of plants whether in nature, in the garden, or in pots indoors in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>, pp. 452–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Saint Helena is in the South Atlantic Ocean. Mauritius, Bourbon (now Réunion), and Ceylon (now Sri Lanka) are in the Indian Ocean.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin’s</ref> paper ‘On the glandular bodies on <hi rend="italic">Acacia sphærocephala</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cecropia peltata</hi> serving as food for ants’ (F. Darwin 1876d) was read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 1 June 1876; see second <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10526F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Francis Darwin, [2 June 1876]</ref> and n. 5. Candolle’s letter to Francis has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>