<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6430">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Sven Nilsson to J. D. Hooker<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   25 October 1868</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10256</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6430 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6430.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6430.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 172: 68</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>172: 68</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3532.xml">Nilsson, Sven</persName>
                <placeName>Lund</placeName>
                <date when="1868-10-25">25 Oct 1868</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml">Hooker, J. D.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>His correspondents in Lapland will provide CD with the information on reindeer horns. Refers him to Linnaeus, <hi rend="italic">Amoenitates academicae</hi>, vol. 4.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">reindeer</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">correspondents</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1">Darwin, C. R.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Lapland</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lund (Suède)</placeName>
                    <date>25 Okt. 1868.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur le Professeur!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>J’ai écrit à deux de mes amis qui ont des connaissances personnelles à la Lapponie, pour avoir les renseignements qu’a souhaitté M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin, sur les Cornes du Renne &amp;c<ref target="#foot.f2"/>   Mais comme la poste va très lentement d’ici aux regions les plus septentrionales ou se trouve le Renne, il passera sans doute long temps avant que je puis avoir la reponse desirée.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>En attendant je preds la liberté de Vous avertir ou plutôt M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin par Vous, qu’il se trouve dans les Amoenitates Academiæ de Linné, Tome IV. pag. 149 et sequ. une description du Renne où on lit, à ce qu’il me semble la plus grande partie de ce que veut connaitre M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> De l’autre partie j’espère tôt ou tard pouvoir communiquer des notices.</p>
<p>Dans mon Album où j’ai recueilli des portraits d’un grand nombre d’illustres Savants, il manque encore des photographies de Vous et de M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin. Quant à Vous je prends la liberté de joindre ici la mienne en échange de la Votre, et j’espère que Vous avez la bonté de me recommender chez M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin pour avoir la sienne.</p>
<p>Je me suis engagé par M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Longman de lui procurer un manuscrit en Anglais, de mon “Age du Bronze”, qu’il veut bien publier à Londres.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je le ferai avec le plus grand plaisir, quoque je voie bien que ce sera sans doute très difficile de faire cette epreuve, parceque je sais que les Anglais ne veulent pas en general admettre que les phoeniciens ont eu des colonies sur leurs côtes.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Mais comme il me semble 〈les〉 recherches de la science 〈doivent〉 être exempts de la pol〈itique.〉</p>
<p>Votre très dev〈oué〉 | Sven Ni〈lsson〉</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Lund (Sweden)</placeName>
                    <date>25 Oct. 1868</date>
                    <salute>Professor!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have written to two of my friends who have personal knowledge of Lapland, to obtain the information that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin wanted about Reindeer Antlers &amp;c<ref target="#foot.f2"/>   But as the post travels very slowly between here and the regions in the far north where the Reindeer is found, a long time will doubtless go by before I can have the desired response.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>While waiting I shall take the liberty of advising you or rather M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin through you, that a description of the Reindeer is to be found in the Amoenitates Academiæ of Linné, vol. IV pag. 149 et sequ., where one can read, it seems to me, the major part of what M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin wants to know.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Regarding the rest, I hope to be able to pass on some notices sooner or later.</p>
<p>In the Album in which I have collected the portraits of a large number of famous Men of Science, the photographs of yourself and of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin are still missing. In your case I take the liberty of enclosing mine in exchange for yours, and I hope that you will have the goodness to recommend me to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Darwin to obtain his.</p>
<p>I have been engaged by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Longman to procure for him a manuscript of my “Bronze Age” in English, which he hopes to publish in London.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I shall do it with the greatest pleasure, even though I can quite well see that it is undoubtedly going to be very difficult to carry out this endeavour, because I know that the English do not generally admit that the Phoenicians had colonies on their coasts.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> But it seems to me that scientific research 〈should〉 be free of politics.</p>
<p>Your most devoted | Sven Ni〈lsson〉</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see part II: 811–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">For CD’s query, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6324.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 19 August 1868</ref>. Hooker passed CD’s query to Nilsson at the meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science in Norwich (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6333.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 30 August 1868</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Nilsson sent the response in his letter of 31 December 1868.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Nilsson refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2942.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl von Linné’s</ref> physical description of the reindeer in Linneaus 1785–90, 4: 149–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Nilsson refers to the London publisher <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Longman</ref>. Nilsson’s work on the Bronze Age had gone through several editions in Swedish and in German; a German translation (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5879.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nilsson 1866–7</ref>) had recently been published. An English translation was never published. Earlier in 1868, Longman’s, Green, and Company had published a translation of Nilsson’s book on the inhabitants of northern Europe during the Stone Age (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5880.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nilsson 1868</ref>); see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5881.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, 15 February [1868]</ref> and n. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5879.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nilsson 1866–7</ref>. In Lubbock 1869, pp. 59–73, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3026.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Lubbock</ref> disagreed with Nilsson’s views on the influence of Phoenician commerce in northern Europe during the Bronze Age. See also Lubbock’s comment on Nilsson’s view in Lubbock’s introduction to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5880.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Nilsson 1868</ref>, pp. xxxv–xxxvi.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>