<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12038">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   8 May 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5456</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12038 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12038.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12038.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B24–5</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B24–B25</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-05-08">8 May 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Will wait for CD’s preliminary essay before proceeding with German edition [of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>]. Regards CD’s essay as the principal attraction. Would like to finish German edition by end of July.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-29" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-15" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-19" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Proofread by Alison Pearn. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2018-08-29" status="copyedited">Copyedited by Samantha Evans. Corrections entered by Anne Secord.</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00166_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00166_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        <surface n="B:24r" xml:id="i166">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00166.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00166_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00166.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:24v" xml:id="i167">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00167.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00167_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00167.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:25r" xml:id="i168">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00168.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00168_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00168.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:25v" xml:id="i169">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00169.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00169_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00169.dzi" width="3725px" height="6309px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>d. 8.5.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Ihre freundlichen Zeilen vom 5<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. habe ich soeben empfangen, und danke Ihnen herzlichst dafür.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Da es meines Erachtens gar nicht darauf ankommen kann, ob die deutsche Ausgabe einige Wochen früher oder später herauskommt, so ziehe ich wohl besser vor, die Druckabzüge Ihrer Präliminar-Notiz abzuwarten, da diese erst den endgültig festgestellten Text enthalten werden.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Aber ich rechne auch ferner auf Ihre freundliche Vermittlung bei dem Buchhändler, dass er mir auch die übrigen Bogen gleich nach der Fertigstellung sendet, damit ich auch in diesen Theilen <hi rend="underline">den von Ihnen berichtigten Text</hi> der deutschen Ausgabe zu Grunde legen kann. Die Mittheilung Ihrer Präliminar Notiz erscheint mir als <hi rend="underline">Hauptsache</hi> auch für das deutsche Publicum, denn erst diese wird dem kleinen Essaÿ für die Leser Werth verleihen, und wenn man an meiner Arbeit etwas Verdienstliches finden sollte, so wird es in erster Linie darin bestehen, Sie, hochverehrter Herr, veranlasst zu haben, den bisher cursirenden und vielfach falschen Nachrichten über Dr. E. D. etwas Authentisches hinzugefügt zu haben.</p>
                    <p>Über ein Zustandekommen französischer und amerikanischer Ausgaben würde ich mich sehr freuen, obwohl ich mich einigermassen beschämt fühle, für die Neubearbeitung eines einer so grossen Verbreitung entgegengehenden Opusculum’s nicht mehr gethan zu haben resp. thun zu können.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Aber meine Hülfsmittel waren hier recht beschränkt, denn unsre öffentlichen Bibliotheken sind weder so reich ausgestattet, noch so bequem zu benützen, wie ich von den englischen höre.</p>
                    <p>Was die Fragen anbetrifft, die ich in meinem vorgestern an Sie gerichteten Briefe gethan habe, so wollte ich Ihnen hauptsächlich damit andeuten, an welchen Stellen mich meine Hülfsmittel völlig im Stiche gelassen haben, und wo ich deshalb ganz besonders auf Ihre gütige Nachhülfe rechnen muss.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Sehr lieb wäre es mir, wenn ich die deutsche Ausgabe bis Ende Juli druckfertig haben könnte, da ich August und September in der Schweiz zuzubringen gedenke. Ich hoffe Herrn Dallas die zweite Hälfte der Arbeit nun ziemlich bald senden zu können; es werden im Ganzen vielleicht 100 Seiten eines mässigen Octavformates werden.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Aus den drei Seiten der ursprünglichen Lebensbeschreibung sind nun c. 40 geworden; es schien mir, dass ich hier den ganzen Stoff zusammenfassen musste, der mir zugänglich war, wenn dieser Theil überhaupt bestehen bleiben sollte, andrerseits hoffte ich Ihnen dadurch einige Arbeit abzunehmen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Mitunter kommt es mir voreilig vor, dass ich überhaupt hier in Berlin ein solches Wagniss angefangen habe, dann denke ich aber wieder, sollte jemand sich nunmehr angeregt fühlen das Leben und Wirken der Dr. E. D. so ausführlich zu schildern, wie er es verdient, so wird die neue Anregung ihren Zweck völlig erfüllt haben. Vorläufig genügt mir, darauf hingewiesen zu haben, dass hier die Nachwelt einige Unterschätzung gut zu machen hat.</p>
                    <p>Mit den innigsten Wünschen für Ihre Frühlings-Erholung<ref target="#foot.f8"/> zeichne ich, hochverehrter Herr | Ihr aufrichtig ergebenster | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>8.5.79.</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Just now I received your kind lines of the 5th, and I thank you kindly for them.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Since it can hardly matter in my opinion whether the German edition comes out a few weeks sooner or later, I would rather wait for the proof-sheets of your preliminary notice, for only they will contain the final version of the text.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am, however, also counting in future on your kind mediation with the publisher so he will send me also the rest of the sheets as soon as they are ready, so that I shall be able to base these parts too of the German edition on <hi rend="underline">the text that you corrected</hi>. The announcement of your preliminary notice seems to me the <hi rend="underline">principal thing</hi> also for the German audience, for only this will make the little essay significant for readers, and should any merit be found in my work, it will primarily consist in having arranged, most esteemed Sir, for you to add something authentic to the reports on Dr E. D. that have been circulated to date and that have often been erroneous.</p>
                    <p>If French and American editions came about I would be very glad, although I am somewhat ashamed not to have done more or not to be able to do more towards the revision of a little work that is destined for such wide circulation.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> My resources here were rather limited, however, for our public libraries are neither as well stocked nor as convenient to use as I hear are the English ones.</p>
                    <p>As for the questions I asked in my letter to you the day before yesterday, I chiefly wanted to indicate to you in which places my resources let me down entirely and where I therefore must particularly count on your kind assistance.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>I would be very glad if I could have the German edition ready for the press by the end of July, for I am planning to spend August and September in Switzerland. I now hope I can send Mr Dallas the second half of the work fairly soon; all in all it will amount to perhaps 100 pages in a modest octavo format.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The three pages of the original biographical portrait have now become approx. 40; it seemed to me that here I had to summarise all the material to which I had access, if this section was to be kept at all; on the other hand I was hoping thus to relieve you of some work.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Sometimes it strikes me as rash that I have actually undertaken such a venture here in Berlin; then again I think that if somebody should now feel inspired to describe the life and activities of Dr E. D. in the detail he deserves, then this new stimulus will have fulfilled its purpose entirely. For the moment I am satisfied to have pointed out that posterity has to rectify its underestimation of him in a number of respects.</p>
                    <p>With the most heartfelt wishes for your spring holiday<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I remain, highly esteemed Sir | Yours sincerely devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
             
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11978.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 5 [May] 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had proposed waiting to send his biographical sketch of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> until he had proof-sheets (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11978.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 5 [May] 1879</ref>). It was a preliminary notice to an English translation of Krause’s revised essay on Erasmus Darwin (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>). A German edition was published in 1880 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had mentioned the possibility of such editions in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11978.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 5 [May] 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12032.xml">letter from Ernst Krause, 5 May 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> had agreed to translate Krause’s account of Erasmus Darwin (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12024.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 2 May 1879</ref>). Krause’s revised text was eighty-five pages long when published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. 131–216.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Krause’s original account of Erasmus Darwin had been published as an article in <hi rend="italic">Kosmos</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10668.xml">Krause 1879a</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD was on holiday from 6 to 26 May 1879 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>