<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7363">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. W. Reade   9 November 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16147</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7363 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7363.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7363.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 85: 109–112</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>85: A109–12</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3950.xml">Reade, W. W.</persName>
                <placeName>London, St Mary Abbot’s Terrace, 11</placeName>
                <date when="1870-11-09">9 Nov 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Ideas of female beauty of W. African Negroes are on the whole the same as those of Europeans.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Europeans</term>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Negroes</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Africa, W.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">perception and sensation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00224_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3139px" height="5806px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00224_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3139px" height="5806px"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="A109r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00224.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3139px" height="5806px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00224_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3139px" height="5806px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00224.dzi" width="3139px" height="5806px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="A109v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00225.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3081px" height="5963px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00225_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3081px" height="5963px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00225.dzi" width="3081px" height="5963px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="A110r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00226.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3139px" height="5951px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00226_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3139px" height="5951px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00226.dzi" width="3139px" height="5951px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="A110v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00227.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3066px" height="5905px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00227_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3066px" height="5905px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00227.dzi" width="3066px" height="5905px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i5" n="A111r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00228.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3103px" height="5956px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00228_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3103px" height="5956px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00228.dzi" width="3103px" height="5956px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i6" n="A111v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00229.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3046px" height="5835px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00229_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3046px" height="5835px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00229.dzi" width="3046px" height="5835px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i7" n="A112r">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00230.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3144px" height="5954px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00230_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3144px" height="5954px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00230.dzi" width="3144px" height="5954px"/>
        </surface>
        
        <surface xml:id="i8" n="A112v">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00231.jpg" rend="portrait" width="3062px" height="5883px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00231_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3062px" height="5883px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00085-000-00231.dzi" width="3062px" height="5883px"/>
        </surface>
</facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>11 S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Mary Abbot’s Terrace | Kensington</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 9. ’70</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I wrote to you at once on my return at the latter end of August, having come home two months earlier than I anticipated owing to the Phonician jealousy of the merchants who trade up the Niger, &amp; who w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. not give me a passage.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In that letter I replied to your queries about the frown of the chimpanzee by recommending you if you have a correspondent at Liverpool to make him look out for chimpanzees &amp; there make the experiment.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> These apes are often brought to Liverpool, &amp; die after a few days or weeks. I had seen one at S<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Leone—but it was gone before I rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> your query. (2) I have seen albinoes but not the blush. By the way I think I must have answered these queries from Africa. I remember asking everybody I met at Accra whether they had seen an albino blush—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> There was an albino girl there I believe: &amp; it was proposed to make the experiment: but how to raise a blush on an African countenance was the difficulty. My letter must have miscarried:<ref target="#foot.f4"/> I attributed your silence to your being so much occupied. I thank you much for your kind and cordial letter.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> The honour of being quoted in your work will be my <hi rend="underline">first</hi> reward for toils undergone. I assure you I am very proud of it, and also to receive a copy of your work from you.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> (This address is likely to be permanent).</p>
<p>I do intend to give a full account of my travels: but I think of first bringing out a volume on the history of Africa generally, and then my travels interspersed with essays on parts where I have not been &amp; on scientific questions connected with Africa—the ape &amp; man question for instance—so as to make it a tolerably complete work on Negroland.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have observed that books of travel do not live unless there is something in them besides travels. Can there be a more charming narrative than that of Mungo Park?<ref target="#foot.f8"/> But it is only a narrative, &amp; is forgotten though he is not. I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> easily dash off an amusing work à la Hepworth Dixon in a few months,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> but I see there is an opening for a comprehensive work on Africa, and I shall try to unite the solidity of a general work with the attraction of a narrative. The task may be beyond my strength; but industry can do much.</p>
<p>I am glad the fever statement caught you in time.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> I shall bring forward instances of it in my work, but having doctored negros with my own hand given them quinine between the paroxysms &amp;c. I am tolerably confident of the fact. Respecting the beauty question I will express myself more clearly than I have hitherto done. I have examined the question very carefully, and have been assisted in my inquiries not only by intelligent natives speaking English well, but by German missionaries who had lived years among the natives on the Gold Coast &amp; understood their language.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>1. I do not venture to assert, nor do I think it probable that the Africans w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> ever prefer the most beautiful European on mere grounds of physical admiration to a good looking negress.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> But I assert this: that if Africans had to choose from a number of European women they would certainly select those whom we should select as the best looking. They often talk about the Europeans they see among them, saying so &amp; so is handsome so &amp; so is ugly. It has been observed that their ideas on these people were the same as ours would be.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>Again nothing is more common in Africa than for Europeans to talk with their interpreters &amp; servants about the native women: it has invariably been found that the man’s idea of beauty &amp; his master’s correspond. To speak not only of the coast but of the interior I have noticed this over &amp; over again: when chatting with the natives one of them has remarked “Dont you think so &amp; so has a very handsome wife” or “look at that pretty girl over there” just as we do in England.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I have always found that the faces which are much admired are those which are the farthest removed from the prognathous type—from the regular Guinea negro—a type as exceptional in Africa as that of the Pontina Marsh people in Italy—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> What are the “points” wh. they admire in a woman I asked a lady who had spent her life among these people. Small hands &amp; small feet she replied: large eyes: a small nose: a well shaped <hi rend="underline">nape</hi>, or back of the neck. “Why do you tie a string round your upper arm? a native chief was asked. Because that gives one a fine round plump arm he replied. (I have among my notes taken years ago a statement that American women do the same whether Red Indians or Anglo-Americans I dont know: probably the latter who have thin arms).</p>
<p>The admiration of broad hips is carried to extravagance in Central Africa. Tight lacing with us is used not only to compress the waist, but to broaden the shoulders &amp; the hips. “The Europeans” say the Gold Coast negroes w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be good looking if they had better teeth. But they have fine hair”. They themselves use false hair chignons every possible contrivance to make their hair look plentiful just as we do. The <hi rend="underline">nose</hi> is the only doubtful point to my mind. But girls have been heard to say “I dont want to marry him he’s got no nose”:<ref target="#foot.f16"/> this shows that the <hi rend="underline">very</hi> flat nose is not admired. The large nose, the long nose is also disliked: but the negro nose when large is usually like what we call a bottle-nose though some of them have admirably shaped noses. No doubt habit has something to do with their ideas about the nose—</p>
<p>The black skin is most admired certainly, but that is because the black skin is really the most beautiful. It is not the force of habit, because black skins are the exception not the rule except among a few tribes such as Jollof, the Serracoulis &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> sum up as my belief &amp; as the belief of those who have lived long among these people that their ideas on the subject of beauty are <hi rend="underline">on the whole</hi> the same as ours.<ref target="#foot.f18"/></p>
<p>Respecting thickness of sculls.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> The Pagan negroes wear no covering on the head &amp; expose it to a vertical sun. It has been asserted I believe by all anatomists that the negro scull is abnormally thick, &amp; hard.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> I have seen a bullet wh. had flattened against the frontal bone of a French negro soldier inflicting a slight wound wh I inspected. This thickness is probably intended as a protection against the sun, &amp; may perhaps have been acquired by the practice they have of carrying their infants soon after birth (a week) bare headed in the sun. There is a most curious passage in Herod: comparing the sculls of Egyptians &amp; Persians. The thick sculls of the former he attributes to their being always in the sun, &amp; always bare-headed.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> I venture to think that this passage which I read on the banks of the Niger of w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> river he was the first to speak, may be applied to nat: sel:<ref target="#foot.f22"/> Any further point you may do me the honour to refer to me upon will be answered to the best of my ability by return of post and I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be happy now or after the book is published to run down to Beckenham for a couple of hours if there sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> happen to be a variety of points to discuss. If you write to me again pray do not fatigue yourself to write autographically but talk to me through your secretary.</p>
<p>Hoping that you will get better health now that your present work is approaching its consummation which so many are eagerly looking forward to</p>
<p>I remain | Yours very truly | Winwood Reade</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Jollof</hi> is so written.<ref target="#foot.f23"/></p>
<p>The people of the Gold Coast have been accustomed to Europeans. But my ideas on this subject are not based on my observations there alone— Much of the apparent horror of the white man among savage negroes is owing to their ideas not that the Devil is white (they have no Devil corresponding to ours) but that all demons, spirits or angels are white.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> I know the case of one traveller in the far interior who having been carefully surveyed by a woman for some time she said— “He is a fine young man”. Again the beard is usually much admired by negro women, though negroes scarcely ever have any.<ref target="#foot.f25"/></p>
<p>I may be able to supply you with additional particulars about love-making exogamy &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> for your 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edition: &amp; possibly on other points w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> will be suggested by your work.<ref target="#foot.f26"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 I wrote … language. 3.7] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 1.... negress. 4.3] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.3 To speak … prognathous type— 5.8] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.8 a type … Italy— 5.9] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 The admiration … Africa.] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.4 But … hair”.] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.8 but the … noses. 6.9] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.3 I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> … as ours. 7.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 Respecting … Reade 10.1] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>12.3 the Devil is white 12.4] <hi rend="italic">before closing square bracket pencil</hi></note>
                <note>12.4 (they … man”. 12.7] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>12.7 Again … any. 12.8] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘(Beauty)’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7315.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. W. Reade, 3 September 1870</ref> and n. 2. On Reade’s difficulty in attaining passage up the Niger, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6557.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1873</ref>, 2: 508–9; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7216.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. W. Reade, 4 June 1870</ref> and n. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD’s query was evidently in a letter that has not been found; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7255.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. W. Reade, 30 June [1870]</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">S<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Leone: Sierra Leone. Accra is a port in Ghana.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7315.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 3 September 1870</ref>, Reade reported that he had seen albinos in Africa but had not observed them blushing.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The letter from CD to Reade has not been found.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD cited Reade in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 289 and 2: 247, 344, 346, 350, 357–8, 374, and included quotations in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 351, 357. Reade was on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> (see DAR 210.11: 32, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">On Reade’s <hi rend="italic">The martyrdom of man</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6556.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1872</ref>), and the unusual structure of Reade’s <hi rend="italic">African sketch-book</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6557.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1873</ref>), see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2149.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Driver 2001</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD read an edition of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3671.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Mungo Park’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Travels in the interior districts of Africa</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6182.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Park 1799</ref>) in 1838 (see CD’s Reading notebooks, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1337.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hepworth Dixon</ref> had published books on his travels in the Middle East, the United States, and Russia (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2059.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dixon 1865</ref>, 1867, and 1870).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">See the postscript to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. W. Reade, 6 November 1870</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">For CD’s first query to Reade regarding perceptions of beauty among different peoples, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6754.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. W. Reade, 21 May [1868]</ref>. Reade addressed the question in his letters of 4 June 1870, 3 September 1870, and 6 November 1870. The Gold Coast was the name of the former British colony that now makes up the larger part of the country of Ghana (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref> s.v. Ghana).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">CD quoted this statement of Reade’s in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 351.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD cited Reade on this point in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">CD cited Reade for this observation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 344.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">The Pontine Marshes were in the Lazio region of central Italy, and were famous for malarial fever. (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6556.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reade 1872</ref>, p. 272.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">CD quoted this statement in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Europeans called some of the peoples living south of the Senegal River the Serrawoolli or Saracolets (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Prichard 1836–7</ref>, 2: 80).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">CD cited Reade on this point in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">See the postscript to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7359.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. W. Reade, 6 November 1870</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3864.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Cowles Prichard</ref> discussed the supposition that Africans had thick skulls and noted authors who had written of it in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Prichard 1836–7</ref>, 1: 282–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">See Herodotus 3.12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Herodotus 3.32. Nat. sel.: natural selection.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">CD may have asked for the correct spelling of ‘Jollof’, as the word was then also sometimes spelled ‘Iolof’ or ‘Whalof’ (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Prichard 1836–7</ref>, 2: 78).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">CD cited Reade on this point in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 346.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">CD cited Reade on this point in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">CD did cite Reade on additional points in the second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref>, though not on the practice of exogamy. For CD’s discussion of exogamy, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 360, 364.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>