<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5159">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. D. Walsh   17 July 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8748A</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5159 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5159.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5159.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Walsten (1974): 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_133.xml">Field Museum</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4944.xml">Walsh, B. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Rock Island, Ill.</placeName>
                <date when="1866-07-17">17 July 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On H. A. Dubois’ attack on "Darwin, Huxley and Lyell"</p> 
<p>and H. J. Clark’s <hi rend="italic">Mind in nature</hi> [1865].</p> 
            <p>BDW’s work [on Cynipidae].</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Cynipidae</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Mind in nature</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Dubois, H. A.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2486">Huxley, T. H.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3051">Lyell, Charles</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Clark, H. J. 1865</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#religious_beliefs">Religious Beliefs</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rock Island, Ill. U.S.</placeName>
                    <date>July 17, 1866</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas. Darwin Esq.</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I sent you by mail last week a short paper of mine exposing some misquotations of Prof. Dana’s, which I hope you have received.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I received in due course your welcome letter of April 20, &amp; was rejoiced to find that you were preparing a new Edition of the Origin.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As you are kind enough to promise me a copy, please forward it to me through Baillière 219 Regent S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. to Baillière Bros. of New York, with whom I deal, to be sent thence to me by Express.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The Smithsonian Institution is so awfully slow in their operations, that they quite put me out of patience.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Curiously enough, the same mail that brought me your last letter brought me also one from Wilson Armistead, saying that he had only just received my box of galls, though I had sent it to the Smithsonian the preceding autumn.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> He was delighted with what I sent, &amp; like Oliver Twist calls out for more.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I am gathering together another lot for him. I had sent him two bottles of galls packed in common salt brine, by way of experiment, &amp; he says it is a complete success &amp; far superior to alcohol—the chief disadvantage being that it is so vulgarly cheap.</p>
<p>I had a copy sent me the other day of an “Analysis of Darwin Huxley &amp; Lyell, by Henry A. Dubois of New York” being a reprint in pamphlet form from the “American Quarterly Church Review”, which by the way I never heard of before.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> The writer is a beautiful compound of fool &amp; knave &amp; makes some most ludicrous blunders in Natural History; besides accusing you of setting up a new God—yes, a real, personal, omniscient, omnipotent, omnipresent God—called “Natural Selection”.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Hence, one would infer that you must be a Deist. But when he comes to attack Huxley, he talks of “the atheistical views embraced in Darwin’s hypothesis”; so that you must be Deist &amp; Atheist both at the same time.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> “Throw plenty of mud, &amp; some of it is sure to stick”. My correspondent (W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Edwards of N.Y.)<ref target="#foot.f10"/> wanted me to review the review; but I thought it answered itself sufficiently, &amp; that anyhow “the game would not pay for the candle”.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>I believe I have done some little good, at all events among N.A. entomologists, in the way of converting them to the true philosophical faith on the origin of species.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> For I find a great many of them now who take much the same ground as Rev. Herbert,<ref target="#foot.f13"/> but cannot as yet “go the whole hog”, as we say out West.</p>
<p>Have you read Clark’s book on “Mind in Nature”? He strikes me as having almost as illogical a mind as Prof. Agassiz. From one end to the other of the Book I don’t see a single new fact or new argument to carry out his thesis, namely that “Mind” exists in Nature. But, so far as I am a judge, his original investigations seem very valuable.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> I never knew before the history of Agassiz’s treatment of him. It always puzzled me why there was no titlepage to the two first parts of the “Contributions”, but now I fully understand the why &amp; the wherefore.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>You mentioned some time ago the case of a foreign gall-fly having suddenly spread over England.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Was it not a species that made its gall on the leaf, so that leaf &amp; gall together might be blown great distances by the wind? I have often remarked that our “Oak-apples” are carried by the wind hundreds of yards with the living insect in them; but the species that make their galls in the twig, so that they are part &amp; parcel of the twig itself, infest the same tree year after year, without spreading, except very slowly indeed sometimes, to adjoining trees.</p>
<p>I find that my Paper on Dimorphism in <hi rend="underline">Cynips</hi> was reviewed by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Reinhard in the Berlin Entom. Periodical;<ref target="#foot.f17"/> &amp; that he proposes two hypotheses to account for my facts, <hi rend="underline">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</hi> that <hi rend="underline">spongifica</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> are distinct species, making undistinguishable galls on the same oak, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. that <hi rend="underline">spongifica</hi> is an inquiline.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> But my this year’s experiments confirm the fact that <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> generates <hi rend="underline">spongifica</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> indiscriminately; &amp; by next fall I shall in all human probability have facts to show that <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> (A) generates <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> (B), &amp; that in the following season aciculata (B) generates <hi rend="underline">aciculata</hi> (C), all of them being ♀ ♀ &amp; agamous. I have little doubt now that this process goes on for a considerable number of years in certain species—commonly called agamous—say for 10 or 15 years, until at last a brood of ♂ ♂ appears. This would be altogether analagous to the case of <hi rend="underline">Aphis</hi> ♀ producing 8 or 9 broods of ♀ ♀ through the summer by parthenogenesis &amp; finally in the autumn ♂ ♂.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> I am aware that the Germans maintain that the agamous <hi rend="underline">Aphis</hi> has no true ovary or “egg-stock” but only a “bud-stock”; but this seems to me a mere verbal distinction. Is it not essential to gemmative reproduction that it should be on the surface of the plant or animal &amp; not in its interior?<ref target="#foot.f20"/></p>
<p>I have the concluding part of my Willow Gall Paper now ready for the press. There are some facts in it respecting Galls that I think will please you, showing that Gall-making insects must have originated according to your theory.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> In the autumn I shall probably throw together the facts respecting Dimorphism in <hi rend="underline">Cynips</hi>, which I have been accumulating now for two years.</p>
<p>I discovered this morning that a pale green fleshy gall on the leaf of the Grape-vine, which had been described by D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fitch as Aphidian &amp; referred to the genus <hi rend="underline">Pemphigus</hi>, though he was unacquainted with the winged insect, is in reality the work of a <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Coccus</hi>!!! I believe this is the first recorded instance of any species of that family producing galls; at least my books mention none such.<ref target="#foot.f22"/> The gall is about like this</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>&amp; globular, &amp; occurs very abundantly, some leaves being almost covered with them. Inside there is a true wingless <hi rend="underline">Coccus</hi> with a parcel of eggs—say 100—many of which are already hatched out—&amp; no powdery or cottony matter among the young lice, as is always the case with the young plant-lice in galls. Besides, eggs are never found in Aphidian galls, the mother-louse generating viviparously. I wonder if you have any such galls in England.</p>
<p>Yours very truly | Benj. D. Walsh</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>3.1 Analysis of … York 3.2] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 Have … Nature”?] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.2 Was … wind? 6.3] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.4 But … indiscriminately; 7.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Walsh refers to his article on <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana</ref> (Walsh 1866c) and to Dana’s article (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1764.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dana 1866</ref>). Walsh had previously criticised Dana’s theory of classification in Walsh 1864a, pp. 238–49.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5061.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Walsh of [19] April [1866]</ref>, CD remarked that he was preparing a fourth edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin.</hi> Walsh’s name is on the presentation list for the book (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The French bookselling and publishing firm of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hippolyte Baillière</ref> had offices at 219 Regent Street, London, and 290 Broadway, New York (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_308.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Baillière 1853</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1866).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Walsh refers to the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4438.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Smithsonian Institution</ref> in Washington, DC.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5034.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. D. Walsh, 13 March 1866</ref> and n. 8, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5061.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, [19] April [1866]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The eponymous hero of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1313.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Dickens’s</ref> novel <hi rend="italic">Oliver Twist</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2002.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dickens 1838</ref>), asked for more gruel after three months in the workhouse.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Walsh refers to ‘The origin and antiquity of man: Darwin, Huxley and Lyell’ by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5561.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Augustus Dubois</ref>. The three-part article was published anonymously in the 1865 volume of <hi rend="italic">American Quarterly Church Review and Ecclesiastical Register</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Dubois] 1865</ref>), and evidently issued as an offprint under the author’s name.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Dubois claimed that in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, CD had defined natural selection as a ‘blind and materialistic’ force, but that ‘with singular inconsistency’ he had invested ‘physical agents with the attributes of a provident Deity’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Dubois] 1865</ref>, pp. 174, 190). For a discussion of similar criticisms of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5140.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from A. R. Wallace, 2 July 1866</ref> and nn. 2 and 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Dubois claimed that in <hi rend="italic">Man’s place in nature</hi> (T. H. Huxley 1863a), <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref> sought ‘to disseminate the atheistical views embraced in Darwin’s hypothesis’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2161.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">[Dubois] 1865</ref>, p. 337).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Walsh refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Henry Edwards</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">A variation of the expression ‘The game is not worth the candle’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">On Walsh’s enthusiastic support of CD’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8146.xml">Walsh 1864a</ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4663.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. D. Walsh, 7 November 1864</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7340.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sorensen 1995</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">CD discussed <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2250.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Herbert’s</ref> work on plant hybridisation in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 246–51, and added a summary of his view on species in the historical sketch in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed.</ref>, p. xiv: ‘the Dean believes that single species of each genus were created in an originally highly plastic condition, and that these have produced, chiefly by intercrossing, but likewise by variation, all our existing species’. For other remarks by CD on Herbert, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5123A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to George Henslow, 15 [June 1866]</ref> and nn. 6–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Walsh refers to <hi rend="italic">Mind in nature: or, the origin of life, and the mode of development of animals</hi> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry James Clark</ref>, a former student and assistant of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> at the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard. Clark defended spontaneous generation on the grounds that it allowed for the continuous operation of ‘the Creator’s controlling hand’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. J. Clark 1865</ref>, pp. 28–9), and concluded, ‘Thus it appears that there is a plainly visible, intelligent, <hi rend="italic">controlling power</hi>, which is manifested, with <hi rend="italic">unvarying regularity of character</hi>, in each of the five groups of animals’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 314). CD’s annotated copy is in the Darwin Library–Down (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 166–7). He cited <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. J. Clark 1865</ref> on the close relationship between reproduction by self-division and budding in his chapter on pangenesis in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 358–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Clark had been employed by Agassiz in 1855 to assist him in the preparation of <hi rend="italic">Contributions to the natural history of the United States of America.</hi> The four-volume work appeared with Agassiz as the sole author (J. L. R. <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_66.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Agassiz 1857–62</ref>), although Clark had performed much of the microscopical and embryological research and had written substantial portions of the sections on jellyfish. A dispute arose between the men, partly over Clark’s efforts to gain acknowledgment as an independent author. Clark circulated a statement of his case against Agassiz to zoologists and scientific societies in America and Europe, and reiterated his claim in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1414.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">H. J. Clark 1865</ref>, pp. 37–8 n. For an account of the dispute, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1991</ref>, pp. 47–65.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">CD had reported that a new gall had recently appeared in England and spread rapidly (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 19 December [1865]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Walsh’s paper, ‘On dimorphism in the hymenopterous genus <hi rend="italic">Cynips</hi>’ (Walsh 1864c), was reviewed by Hermann Reinhard in <hi rend="italic">Berliner Entomologische Zeitschrift</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reinhard 1865</ref>). CD’s annotated copy of Walsh’s paper is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Walsh had argued that the gall insect <hi rend="italic">Cynips quercus aciculata</hi> was a dimorphic female form of <hi rend="italic">C. q. spongifica</hi> (Walsh 1864c, pp. 447–8). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12. Reinhard has not been further identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Reinhard 1865</ref>, p. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Walsh gave a similar account of his research on <hi rend="italic">Cynips</hi>, noting the analogy with reproduction in <hi rend="italic">Aphis</hi>, in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4934A.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter to CD of 12 November 1865</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Walsh and CD had previously discussed reproduction by gemmation in <hi rend="italic">Aphis</hi> and other species (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4952.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 19 December [1865]</ref> and nn. 7 and 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">The reference is to Walsh 1866b. There is a heavily annotated copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Walsh had sent CD the first part of the paper the previous year (Walsh 1864b; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4778.xml" resp="#automat">letter from B. D. Walsh, 1 March 1865</ref> and n. 14). Walsh remarked that the study of gall-making insects had important implications for the origin of species (Walsh 1866b, p. 274). In his concluding remarks, he stated that the distribution of gall insects among different genera was inexplicable according to ‘the Creative Theory’; he added: ‘if our modern species were genetically derived from pre-existing species, several new species being generated from one old one, and whole groups from time to time becoming extinct, the actual state of facts … is precisely that which we should … expect to meet with’ (Walsh 1866b, pp. 287–8). The paper is cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 282.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">Walsh described the gall insect in Walsh 1866b, pp. 283–4, noting that it had been wrongly classified by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5652.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Fitch</ref> within the genus of gall-forming aphids, <hi rend="italic">Pemphigus</hi>, and claiming that it ‘must become the type of a new and very aberrant genus’ of the family <hi rend="italic">Coccidae</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 284 n.).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>