<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10399">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To J. H. Gilbert   16 February 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16953</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10399 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10399.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10399.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">LS</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="LS">3pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CULDAR144: (335)-337</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 3: 342</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Rothamsted Research (GIL13)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_361.xml">Rothamsted</repository>
                    <collection>GIL13</collection>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1876-02-16">16 Feb 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1871.xml">Gilbert, J. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes self- and cross-fertilisation experiments.</p>
            <p>Asks JHG’s advice on setting up an experiment designed to test whether the cause of variation in cultivated plants lies in different substances absorbed from the soil when absorption is not interfered with by other plants in a state of nature. Can JHG suggest how he can get soil free of all the substances which plants naturally absorb?</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">causation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cultivation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">soil and other substrates</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down | Beckenham | Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Feb 16. 76</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>When I met you at the Linn: Soc you were so kind as to say that you would aid me with advice, and this will be of the utmost value to me &amp; my son.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I will first state my object and I hope that you will excuse a long letter. It is admitted by all naturalists that no problem is so perplexing as what causes almost every cultivated plant to vary, and no experiments as yet tried have thrown any light on the subject. Now for the last ten years I have been experimenting in crossing and self-fertilising plants; &amp; one indirect result has surprised me much namely that by taking pains to cultivate plants in pots under glass during several successive generations, under nearly similar conditions and by self-fertilising them in each generation the colour of the flowers often changed, and what is very remarkable they became in some of the more variable species, such as Mimulus, Carnation &amp;c, quite constant like those of a wild species. This fact &amp; several others have led me to the suspicion that the cause of variation must lie in different substances absorbed from the soil by these plants when their powers of absorption are not interfered with by other plants with which they grow mingled in a state of nature. Therefore my son &amp; I wish to grow plants in pots in soil entirely, or as nearly entirely as is possible destitute of all matter which plants absorb; and then to give during several successive generations to several plants of the same species as different solutions as may be compatible with their life &amp; health. And now can you advise me how to make soil approximately free of all the substances which plants naturally absorb. I suppose white silver sand, sold for cleaning harness &amp;c is nearly pure silica, but what am I to do for alumina?<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Without some alumina I imagine that it would be impossible to keep the soil damp and fit for the growth of plants. I presume that clay washed over &amp; over again in water would still yield mineral matter to the carbonic acid secreted by the roots. I should want a good deal of soil, for it would be useless to experimentize unless we could fill from 20 to 30 moderate sized flower-pots every year. Can you suggest any plan; for unless you can it would I fear be useless for us to commence our attempt to discover whether variability depends at all on matter absorbed from the soil. After obtaining the requisite kind of soil my notion is to water one set of plants with nitrate of potassium another set with N of sodium, &amp; another with N of lime, giving all as much phosphate of ammonia as they seemed to support, for I wish the plants to grow as luxuriantly as possible. The plants watered with nitrate of Na &amp; of Ca would require I suppose some K; but perhaps they would get what is absolutely necessary from such soil as I should be forced to employ and from the rain water collected in tanks.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I could use hard water from a deep well in the chalk but then all the plants would get lime.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> If the plants to which I give nitrate of Na &amp; of Ca would not grow I might give them a little alum.</p>
<p>I am well aware how very ignorant I am and how crude my notions are, and if you could suggest any other solutions by which plants would be likely to be affected it would be a very great kindness. I suppose that there are no organic fluids which plants would absorb &amp; which I could procure. Do you think Hopkins and Williams would be good men from whom to get the salts?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I must trust to your kindness to excuse me for troubling you at such length &amp; I remain | Dear Sir yrs sincerely | Charles Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> had been in London to vote for <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Ray Lankester’s</ref> membership application at the meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2944.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linnean Society</ref> on 3 February 1876 (<hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London</hi> (1875–6): iii). Francis was assisting CD in his experiments for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8595.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Cross and self fertilisation</hi></ref>.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Silica is silicon dioxide (SiO<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>); alumina is aluminium oxide (Al<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>O<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The chemical symbol for nitrogen is N; sodium is Na; calcium is Ca; potassium is K; phosphorus is P. Potassium nitrate is KNO<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>; sodium nitrate is NaNO<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>; nitrate of lime is calcium nitrate or Ca(NO<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>)<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>. There are several forms of phosphate of ammonia, but diammonium phosphate ((NH<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>)<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>HPO<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>) is the most commonly used fertiliser.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Hard water is water with a high mineral content as a result of percolating through mineral deposits such as chalk (calcium carbonate).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Hopkin &amp; Williams were manufacturers of fine laboratory and photographic chemicals, with offices at 10 Cavendish Street, London, and a factory in Wandsworth, Surrey (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1875). CD had obtained chemicals from them when he was working on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9042.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. W. Baxter, 4 September 1873</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>