<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2943">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From W. H. Harvey   8 October 1860</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8544</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1993">1993</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2943 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2943.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2943.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Vorzimmer (1972): 63</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 8: 415</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 98 (ser. 2): 54–7</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>98: B54–57</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2161.xml">Harvey, W. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Trinity College, Dublin</placeName>
                <date when="1860-10-08">8 Oct 1860</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks CD for his patience and good-nature; does not want a controversial correspondence but wishes to reply to matters in CD’s letter, and does.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00433_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5453px" height="9075px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00433_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5453px" height="9075px"/>
        <surface n="B:54r" xml:id="i433">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00433.jpg" width="5453px" height="9075px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00433_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5453px" height="9075px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00433.dzi" width="5453px" height="9075px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:54v" xml:id="i434">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00434.jpg" width="5430px" height="9114px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00434_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5430px" height="9114px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00434.dzi" width="5430px" height="9114px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:55r" xml:id="i435">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00435.jpg" width="5373px" height="9109px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00435_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5373px" height="9109px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00435.dzi" width="5373px" height="9109px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:55v" xml:id="i436">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00436.jpg" width="5345px" height="9114px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00436_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5345px" height="9114px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00436.dzi" width="5345px" height="9114px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:56r" xml:id="i437">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00437.jpg" width="5389px" height="9069px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00437_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5389px" height="9069px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00437.dzi" width="5389px" height="9069px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:56v" xml:id="i438">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00438.jpg" width="5389px" height="9069px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00438_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5389px" height="9069px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00098-000-00438.dzi" width="5389px" height="9069px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>40 Trin. Coll. Dublin</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 8. 1860</date>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>My dear Sir</p>
<p>I have to thank you for the patience &amp; good nature with which you have listened to my crudities, &amp; the trouble you have taken to meet several of the points I ventured to bring to your notice— <ref target="#foot.f1"/> I do not want to lead you into a controversial correspondence, or to be drawn into one myself, but yet there are a few matters in your letter that I would like to reply to.—</p>
<p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. — I never supposed you to say that Natural Selection could act without previous Variability. On the contrary, throughout your book Natural Selection is represented as dependent on “<hi rend="underline">favourable</hi>” variations &amp; conditions, ready <hi rend="underline">to take advantage of</hi>, to perpetuate &amp; accumulate any <hi rend="underline">profitable</hi> item of differentiation;—but, in strict language, to <hi rend="underline">originate</hi> nothing. Hence in my letter I have called her a Wetnurse, rather than a Mistress, &amp; hence I can see how we may accept her as the manufacturer of multitudes of “<hi rend="underline">species</hi>” (so called), such as they exist in our arrangements; and yet reject her as explaining <hi rend="underline">unlimited</hi> divarications. The first impression of your book on my mind was that it too boldly assumed <hi rend="underline">unlimited</hi> variability as the cornerstone of the argument; and this was the first stumbling block in my way, for I am strongly impressed with the notion (perhaps wholly wrong) that there is no law of organic or inorganic nature <hi rend="underline">unlimited</hi> in its operation. And so, however widely species may vary, I suspect an oscillation in every case. In the case of your divaricating pigeons for instance, I should anticipate, after endless variations from type, either a return to type or extinction; but not the passage into a new type.</p>
<p>Among plants, I can believe in very wide limits of <hi rend="underline">transmutation</hi>; but not equally among all plants. Orchids, Amaryllideæ, Irideæ, &amp; perhaps most Endogens, &amp; all Cryptogamic plants, are <hi rend="underline">centrifugal</hi> in a very high degree:<ref target="#foot.f2"/>—so much so that whole genera or even suborders or Orders of our arrangement may be really no more than Natural Species. Thus, for instance granting Natural Selection to be <hi rend="underline">partially</hi> true, I can see how all <hi rend="underline">Gramineæ</hi> <hi rend="underline">may</hi> have sprung from one common parentage, one aboriginal grass (a <hi rend="underline">veritable</hi> Aira <hi rend="underline">præcox</hi>),—and how all <hi rend="underline">Cyperaceæ</hi>, in like manner, <hi rend="underline">may</hi> have sprung from one original Sedge. But here I stop, perhaps illogically, because between Gramineæ &amp; Cyperaceæ I think there is a “<hi rend="underline">saltus</hi>”, or vacant space in which it is difficult to conceive a <hi rend="underline">strictly</hi> intermediate type. The difference in structure of the seed—the relation of embryo to albumen—implies <hi rend="underline">opposition</hi> (or <hi rend="underline">polarity</hi>) to that degree that a half &amp; half structure must be proved to exist before I can believe in it. Now <hi rend="underline">Gramineæ</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Cyperaceæ</hi> are unquestionably very ancient types, if the widest distribution &amp; great diversity of specific form be proofs of antiquity; both also must have been dominant in a high degree for myriads of years or ages,—and yet, in embryological structure, in floral arrangement, in foliation &amp; in stem,—we have no reason for supposing that the earliest <hi rend="underline">grasses</hi> or <hi rend="underline">sedges</hi> respectively, were materially different from those of today. Both Orders differ from each other by an exact, definite character of seed; and in neither Order do the <hi rend="underline">genera</hi> rise in organization one above the other, but in both orders the genera, so to say, stand on a dead-level or common platform of organisation. This case (and several similar might be cited) appears to me to support the <hi rend="underline">notion</hi>, that natural variability has <hi rend="underline">strict limits</hi>; &amp; to bear, so far as it goes, against the notion of <hi rend="underline">unlimited</hi> derivation from a Protozoon.</p>
<p>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. — You regret having used the term Natural <hi rend="underline"> Selection</hi>, as tending to mislead, &amp; propose Nat. <hi rend="underline">Preservation</hi> as a better phrase. If you will not think it impertinent (understanding your theory so imperfectly as I do), I would suggest the term “Natural <hi rend="underline">Evolution</hi>” as expressing still more exactly the <hi rend="underline">idea</hi> conveyed to my mind by your theory. Do you not teach us that all organisms, past &amp; present, have been <hi rend="underline">evolved</hi>, through the action of secondary or <hi rend="underline">natural</hi> laws, from one <hi rend="underline">created</hi> or primæval form? If so, Natural Evolution would well express the combination of all the powers of nature in the production of species. 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.    A word or two respecting the Ostrich’s wings.— You suppose he has lost wings, “because the whole structure of a Bird is essentially formed for flight, &amp; the Ostrich is essentially a Bird”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> But—if all <hi rend="underline">organs</hi> (<hi rend="underline"> wings</hi> included) have been <hi rend="underline">gradually</hi> formed, through Nat. Sel. accumulating useful variations in successive generations;—unless the <hi rend="underline">primal organism</hi> had wings &amp; was essentially a flying animal;—then the <hi rend="underline">earliest</hi> essential bird, or his remote non-bird ancestor, may have had only rudimentary wings. Now the Ostrich may be a <hi rend="underline">slightly modified</hi> descendent of one of the earlier types, for his affinity to the Dinornis &amp; other wingless birds suggests it.—   If indeed the <hi rend="underline">primal-bird</hi> were formed “per saltum” or by an act of creation, the case would be different;—we should then suppose his organisation to be perfectly adapted for flight, completely furnished as a <hi rend="underline">typical</hi> bird should be. But if the primal-bird <hi rend="underline">ascended</hi> from a lower non-bird form, it is not at all probable that the earlier types would have been so fully furnished either with wings or with feathers as those more recently evolved. Hence, I do not see that it is “more complex” to suppose in this case an <hi rend="underline">evolution</hi>, than a <hi rend="underline">suppression</hi>;— when, according to your theory, the evolution <hi rend="underline">must</hi> have once occurred, whereas the suppression, at best, only <hi rend="underline">may</hi> have occurred. The only complexity I am guilty of is in supposing the Ostrich to represent an <hi rend="underline">early</hi> type of bird, not a <hi rend="underline">late</hi> one. Quere, what degree of carination of the sternum is requisite to constitute an<hi rend="underline"> “essential”</hi> or <hi rend="underline">typical</hi> bird?—  …  . After all, I only alluded to the Ostrich to show that the <hi rend="underline">facts</hi> of nature may be interpreted, by the help of your theory, in <hi rend="underline">opposite</hi> ways;—that if you take <hi rend="underline">one</hi> explanation, another may take the <hi rend="underline">opposite</hi>, and both be <hi rend="underline">equally</hi> plausible. It is a matter to me of indifference, whether the Ostrich be going up the hill or down again.</p>
<p>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. — You say that I beg the question of “Protococcus being doomed to perennial similarity”.—   I own to the <hi rend="underline"> begging</hi>;—but pray let me state how little I here beg. Truly we know nothing of the imaginary <hi rend="underline">Protozoon</hi>; but as you say <hi rend="underline">you</hi> “have less difficulty in imagining the creation of an asexual cell, encreasing by simple division” than an animal of higher organisation, I hope I am not incorrect in inferring that you suppose the Protozoon to have been such a cell, so encreasing.—   Now, <hi rend="underline">Protococcus nivalis</hi> is simply a spherical cell, asexual, encreasing by simple division. The sphere is also the simplest &amp; most self-balanced form of a cell. Grant it to vary in <hi rend="underline">outline</hi> however, &amp; in <hi rend="underline">size</hi>; for it does grow &amp; has an average size when mature.— But however variable in such minor points, the <hi rend="underline">structure</hi> is essentially the same in all individuals;—it is <hi rend="underline">a simple, nucleated cell &amp; no more</hi>. The question to be solved then is, <hi rend="underline">how long has</hi> <hi rend="underline">it remained in this condition?</hi>—   Of course, the epoch at which it was called into being is wholly undiscoverable, but for the following (theoretical) reasons I think it probable that <hi rend="underline">Protococcus</hi> is very ancient indeed.—   If, as you suppose, <hi rend="underline">all</hi> organisms were successively evolved from one primordial germ or Protozoon, by accumulations of useful variations from generation to generation, then it is reasonable to infer that organisms which depart least from the type of the Primordial are its nearest “blood relations”. There was an age of Protozoa before the world contained anything else, &amp; it was probably a long period, because it must (by theory) have continued till Variability, the Struggle for Life &amp;c &amp;c had evolved something better. There was time for protozoic forms to <hi rend="underline">diversify</hi> indefinitely, if not to exhaust all possible differentiations to which unicellular bodies could be stretched. In our times the world teems with such forms; their genera &amp; species may be counted by thousands &amp; tens of thousands,—&amp; yet, these are only remnants of the innumerable lost protozoic races that preceded them. Few, comparatively, are capable of fossilisation;—but the Diatomes are, and several of the fossil Diatomes are said to be <hi rend="underline">specifically</hi> identical with forms now living.— Now, it does not matter, for my argument, whether the Pre-silurian <hi rend="underline">Protococcus</hi> were <hi rend="underline">spherical</hi>, or <hi rend="underline">oval</hi>, or <hi rend="underline">square</hi>, or <hi rend="underline">stellæform</hi>; or whether it were <hi rend="underline">red</hi>, <hi rend="underline">green</hi> or <hi rend="underline">brown</hi>; it may have gone through indefinite variations of this kind, and yet I should say it was doomed to perennial similarity, if, through all changes, it remained <hi rend="underline">a simple, asexual cell</hi>.—   Now, as it could not have been <hi rend="underline">less</hi> complex than a cell &amp; have retained organisation;—and as, at the present day, it is not <hi rend="underline">more</hi> complex than a cell,—all I can say is that, since it was called into being, it has not materially improved in organisation. So far it has inherited “perennial similarity”; &amp; I see no reason why it should not inherit the same to the end of the world.—   But, you may say, why should <hi rend="underline">Protococcus</hi> &amp; similar organisms, be regarded as relics of a Protozoic, pre-silurian world &amp; not <hi rend="underline">modern organisations</hi>?— I reply:—either they must have come down to us as undivaricated protozoa, from your Protozoon by uninterrupted succession of generation;—or, they must represent higher animals &amp; plants which once flourished, but which through gradual loss of organs from disuse, &amp; a continual struggle with adverse circumstances, have dwindled down to a monadic condition;—or, they must have been <hi rend="underline">spontaneously generated</hi>, from age to age, that is to say, the creative act of calling a living cell from the dust, must have been <hi rend="underline">repeated</hi> an infinite number of times from the dawn of life to the present day.—   I can find no other way of accounting for their existence; &amp; I suppose your theory would prefer the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> supposition, as the simplest—that they have lived, as Protozoa, from the dawn of life to the present day.—</p>
<p>And here I would observe, that if you maintain that Protozoic organisms now living are lineal descendents of the aboriginal Protozoon;—and if you also maintain that all higher animals &amp; plants have descended (or rather <hi rend="underline">ascended</hi>) from the same aboriginal Protozoon, through the agency of natural laws alone, without the personal interference of an Intelligent First Cause,—you are bound to show theoretically how such widely different results have been arrived at. At starting we have similar elementary organisms, under similar conditions of life, all exposed to the same struggle, all subjected to similar “laws acting round them”. Why have some remained Protozoa to the present day, while others have developed into Whales or into Man?—   Have the “perennially similar” races had no struggle for life? I suppose not, for they have remained perennially similar. But what kept them out of the struggle while all around them, of their own kind &amp; in their own condition as respects outward circumstances were wriggling upward into higher beings? And what set these latter in motion? A struggle for life. Side by side, in the same sea, with the same water to swim in, the same food to eat, the same sun above them; one Protozoon remained in statu quo <hi rend="underline">unexterminated</hi>, another <hi rend="underline">advanced</hi> in organisation &amp; developed nerves, sinews &amp; bones; one perhaps was drawn into an <hi rend="underline">eddy</hi> &amp; so swam round &amp; round forever; the other floated on a <hi rend="underline">current</hi> &amp; gradually drifted into a new phase of being.—</p>
<p>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>— You dissent from my requiring myriads of years to overstock the Earth with the imaginary Protozoon &amp; refer to Ehrenberg’s calculation of the time it would take for an infusorium to make a cube of rock.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The <hi rend="underline">time required</hi> will depend on the nature of the protozoon. If it secreted <hi rend="underline">lime</hi>, like one of the Foraminifera, or <hi rend="underline">silex</hi>, like a Diatome, its dead shells would rapidly form strata; but if it were like a Protococcus or an Amoeba no such result could follow for infinite ages. But my argument had reference to something more than a question of <hi rend="underline">time</hi>;—I wished to show the difficulty of eliminating <hi rend="underline">a</hi> <hi rend="underline">struggle for life</hi>, of inducing <hi rend="underline">variation</hi>, &amp; leading, through Nat. Selection, to the evolution of higher animals from a protozoon, so placed in a universal sea.—</p>
<p>Granting however that it secreted lime, like a Foraminifer, &amp; rapidly propagated itself: what would result?—   I see nothing at first but a thin film of chalk spread out over the bottom of the ocean, &amp; gradually encreasing in thickness till the sea became shallower &amp; shallower, until (supposing <hi rend="underline">lime</hi> enough) it was filled up at last;—all which filling up must have occurred before the struggle for life commenced, for so long as clear water &amp; available lime remained the Protozoon (if analogous to his modern kindred) had all he required. And, as the available lime diminished, though the newer generations might have thinner &amp; thinner shells, &amp; might at last come to be membrane coated or gelatinous, they need not have made a single <hi rend="underline">onward</hi> step;—&amp; the fact of their contriving to do without lime would still further retard the <hi rend="underline">struggle for life</hi>, for they would have fewer wants to supply, their debris would more slowly accumulate &amp; the clear water would be less rapidly filled up. Suppose however that the lime diminished unequally, &amp; that, in some favoured localities the lime-secreting species continued to propagate;—though you might then have <hi rend="underline">two</hi> species “naturally selected” where but one had been before, yet the <hi rend="underline">newer</hi> might be the <hi rend="underline">lower &amp; feebler type</hi>, for the power of secreting lime would be lost, <hi rend="underline">by disuse</hi>, &amp; with it whatever apparatus was fitted to that purpose. We may indeed suppose that the power of secreting might remain &amp; be diverted to the secretion of silex or any other earth; and so we should get a third, or more species.—   To this I have nothing to object;—all these &amp; similar “specific” changes are compassable by Natural Selection. But it is yet to be shown whether all such <hi rend="underline">adaptations</hi> to circumstances have not, in every case, their natural limits. We can conceive a Protozoic world so originating &amp; becoming greatly varied in “species” without one of them rising sensibly in organisation above another. Like snow-crystals their <hi rend="underline">patterns</hi> may be innumerable, but their organisation all of a piece. The modern Protococcus may be very unlike the imaginary Protozoon in outward form &amp; in habits of life, and yet, in simplicity of organisation, it may be identical;—each a nucleated, asexual, spontaneously dividing cell.</p>
<p>The arguments above applied to an imaginary protozoon appear to me to fit as well in the case of a reefbuilding coral;—and if Agassiz observations on the reefs of Florida may be depended upon, namely, that there is no difference in species between the bottom &amp; top of a long persisting reef,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> it further illustrates the “perennial similarity” of low forms for indefinite periods.</p>
<p>6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. — A word or two more about <hi rend="underline">Variability</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I fear, by your referring me back to passages in the Origin where Variability is insisted on, you have misunderstood what I meant, when, in my letter, speaking of <hi rend="underline">Unknown</hi> Laws of Variation, I say:—“If therefore these are necessary, at starting, to set Natural Selection in motion, we are surely calling up a wholly different Agency to any set forth in your Theory” &amp;c. I did not mean that you had <hi rend="underline">ignored</hi> such Laws, for at the opening of Chap. 5, in speaking of them, you pointedly say that they are not due to <hi rend="underline">chance</hi>, but to an unknown cause. What I meant was that, to variation from this <hi rend="underline">Unknown</hi> Cause, &amp; not to “Variability from the indirect &amp; direct action of the external conditions of life, from use &amp; disuse” (p 490) we must, in the present state of science, attribute all the <hi rend="underline">Major</hi> divarications of the organic world, even on the theory of evolution from a primordial. We must, I think, draw a broad line between Variations arising from allied conditions of life, from use &amp; disuse, and those Variations that introduce <hi rend="underline">new stages</hi> of being, molding an animal body with symmetry of limbs &amp; definite position of internal organs; that, early in the history of life, introduced a <hi rend="underline">definite</hi> number of typical formulæ (radiate, articulate, molluscoid, vertebrate, &amp;c), &amp; have <hi rend="underline">retained</hi> these same types, through <hi rend="underline">every change</hi> of outward circumstances, to the present day.—   Variations arising from altered conditions &amp;c, being <hi rend="underline">impersonal</hi>, may fairly be referred to secondary causes;—but the other &amp; infinitely the larger class of unresolved Variations, including Correlation of Organs or modelling after a preconceived pattern, imply <hi rend="underline">personality</hi>, &amp; therefore (to avoid pantheism), I ascribe them to the Creator. Natural Evolution, no doubt, takes advantage of every such organic change &amp; commences a new set of modifications upon it, but (as I think) is insufficient to explain or <hi rend="underline">originate</hi> it. These <hi rend="underline">steps</hi> (however originated), and however small in amount each may be, are the <hi rend="underline">saltations</hi> for which I have all along been contending,—the non-recognition of which, in the theory of Natural Selection, appears to me like leaving out the keystone of the arch.</p>
<p>But it is useless to carry on the discussion. I must again apologise for my prolixity, &amp; remain,</p>
<p>My dear Sir | very truly yours | W. H. Harvey <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq, FRS. | &amp;c &amp;c</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.2 On the … conditions, 2.3] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>2.8 The first … argument; 2.10] <hi rend="italic">two crosses added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.8 But … space 3.9] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.13 Now … Protozoon. 3.23] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.5 Do you … form? 4.6] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.7 Now … it.— 5.8] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>5.17 The only … one. 5.18] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>7.4 without … at. 7.6] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 You … rock. 8.3] <hi rend="italic">cross added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.8 What … world, 11.11] <hi rend="italic">scored pencil</hi>; ‘6 fingered man— hard to say if indirect cause of conditions’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Verso of last page</hi>: ‘Harvey’ <hi rend="italic">brown crayon</hi>; ‘Dominant Forms | Struggle for Existence | Antiquity of World &amp;c’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2898.xml" resp="#automat">letter from W. H. Harvey, 24 August 1860</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. H. Harvey, [20–4 September 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The expression ‘centrifugal’ variation was coined by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> to represent changes that made the organism diverge from the parental type. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3746.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hooker 1844–7</ref>, p. 315, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic"> Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2512A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Charles Lyell, 28 October 1859</ref> and n. 4. Harvey and Hooker were close friends.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Harvey quotes from the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. H. Harvey, [20–4 September 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Ehrenberg 1854–6, pp. viii–ix. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2922.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. H. Harvey, [20–4 September 1860]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Agassiz 1851b.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Harvey apparently enclosed with the letter a pamphlet that addressed some of the same points about variability. The pamphlet gave the text of a lecture delivered at the Dublin University Zoological and Botanical Association on 17 February 1860 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3422.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harvey 1860</ref>). It is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL, marked ‘With the writers <hi rend="italic">repentance</hi>. Oct. 1860.’ In it Harvey stated: ‘It strikes me that there is fallacy at the very base of Mr. Darwin’s argument; and that his whole superstructure rests on the <hi rend="italic">assumption</hi> that Variability acts indefinitely and continuously, without check or hindrance.’ An annotation by CD on the back cover relating to this passage states: ‘Preface—good to admit that continued variation is an assumption’.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>