<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11122">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   31 August [1877]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6745</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11122 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11122.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11122.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 430</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Darwin: Letters to Thiselton-Dyer, 1873–81: ff. 89–91)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Darwin: Letters to Thiselton-Dyer, 1873–81: ff. 89–91</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1877-08-31">31 Aug [1877]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml" resp="high">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Discusses plants to be sent to Kew.</p> 
<p>Thanks for letter about <hi rend="italic">Trifolium</hi></p>  
<p>and for R. I. Lynch’s observations on sleep of <hi rend="italic">Erythrina</hi>.</p>  
<p>Mentions letter from F. J. Cohn, dealing with discovery by Francis Darwin, that CD has had printed in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> ["The contractile filaments of the teasel", <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 16 (1877): 339; <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 205–7].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Erythrina</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Trifolium</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_999">Cohn, F. J.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3058">Lynch, R. I.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Kew</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2016-11-02" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2016-11-02" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2020-11-15" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Aug 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Dyer</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The Schrankia, which I received from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ellacombe, shed at first all its leaves, but now has put forth new ones; yet does not look very healthy &amp; will not stand any sun.— I suspect that we have kept it too much watered.— I send it off today to Kew, as it is precious &amp; you may be able to doctor it.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I also send a Legum: plant from Queensland, which I raised from seed. My taller plants are really almost the most elegant plants, which I have ever seen; so that Kew ought to have it. If you know what genus it is, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. much like to hear, for in that case I will observe it.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Thirdly: do you know enclosed leaves from little very unhealthy tree at Abinger sent to Farrer from Kew: from what I could see it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be worth observing if I could have a healthy plant on loan.—<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Very many thanks for your valuable &amp; in many ways interesting letter of the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>; but I really did not expect you to write about the Trifolium.— The differences in the epidermic cells are what I said with the addition that there are differently shaped glands on the two sides.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Pray thank M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lynch for his good &amp; full observations on sleep of Erythrina.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> The case seems like that of Phaseolus which in my garden did not sleep during early part of summer out of doors, but did sleep in the greenhouse.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Notwithstanding all our hard work (&amp; very hard it is) God knows whether we shall make much of our subject.</p>
<p>I hope that you saw Cohn’s letter in ‘Nature’: it has pleased me <hi rend="underline">immensely</hi> after the rejection of Frank’s paper by the Royal Soc<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The referees seemed to think that if the filaments were not protoplasm, the discovery was worth nothing, which seems a strange conclusion.</p>
<p>I hope Hooker will return before very long &amp; then you will be not so hard-worked I hope.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I did not intend to have scribbled so much.</p>
<p>Yours gratefully | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>P.S. I see that Sachs (p. 786 of your Edit). speaks of some Scitamineæ going to sleep.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Have you any notion to what he refers? Would M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lynch look to any? I have a Hedychium &amp; will look to it, but it seems incredible that this sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. sleep.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Sachs also says that species of Œschinomene &amp; Smithia are irritable to a touch; or rather when shaken: can you help me to any species?<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.2 very] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.2 so … it. 2.3] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.3 what] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘even’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">3.1 very unhealthy] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.1 many] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘many’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n6">4.2 in] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘are’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n7">6.1 Notwithstanding] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘For’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n8">11.4 species of] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

  
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship between this letter and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11094.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 7 August 1877</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1489.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Nicholson Ellacombe</ref> sent CD a plant of <hi rend="italic">Schrankia uncinata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Mimosa quadrivalvis</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">angustata</hi>, littleleaf sensitive-briar) on the understanding that it would later be sent to the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6298.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. N. Ellacombe, 30 July [1877]</ref>). The plant was received at Kew on 3 September 1877 (Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, <hi rend="italic">Inwards book</hi>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">According to the record of receipt in the <hi rend="italic">Inwards book</hi> (3 September 1877, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew), the plant was an <hi rend="italic">Acacia</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had visited Abinger Hall, the home of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1599.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Farrer</ref>, from 20 to 25 August 1877 (see ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)). Thiselton-Dyer wrote the name of the tree, identified from the leaves CD had enclosed, as <hi rend="italic">Gleditschia sinensis</hi>, after this sentence in the letter. <hi rend="italic">Gleditschia sinensis</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Gleditsia sinensis</hi> (Chinese honey locust). Thiselton-Dyer’s reply has not been found. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD probably refers to Thiselton-Dyer’s <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11111.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 25 August 1877</ref>; no letter from Thiselton-Dyer dated 28 August 1877 has been found. CD had mentioned that the underside of only half of each lateral leaflet of <hi rend="italic">Trifolium resupinatum</hi> (Persian clover) had bloom on them and that the epidermal cells were of two different shapes on the upper and under sides of the leaf (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11086.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, [20–4 August 1877]</ref> and n. 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11116.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from R. I. Lynch, [28 August 1877]</ref>; <hi rend="italic">Erythrina crista-galli</hi> is the cockspur coral tree.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD’s notes on sleep in <hi rend="italic">Phaseolus</hi>, dated 11 and 12 July and 15 and 17 August 1877, are in DAR 209.10: 66–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD had forwarded parts of two letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ferdinand Julius Cohn</ref> to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>; Cohn’s letters discussed observations he made confirming some of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin’s</ref> observations in F. Darwin 1877b (see letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 15 August [1877] and nn. 2 and 3). Francis’s paper had been read at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4110.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Society of London</ref>, but only an abstract had been published by the society (F. Darwin 1877a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> was away on a three-month-long botanical trip in America (L. Huxley ed. 1918, 2: 204–17).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Thiselton-Dyer had assisted with the English translation of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Text-book of botany</hi> (Sachs 1875). In Bentham and Hooker 1862–83, 3: 636–57, Scitamineae was a natural order of plants that included plants now within the families Musaceae (banana), Zingiberaceae (ginger), and Marantaceae (arrowroot). Sachs’s description of Scitamineae leaves with the lamina attached to the petiole by a cylindrical contractile organ (Sachs 1875, p. 786) probably refers to the pulvinus of leaves in some plants in the Marantaceae such as <hi rend="italic">Thalia dealbata</hi>, which CD observed for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>. The pulvinus is the joint-like thickening at the base of these leaves that facilitates movement, allowing them to sleep.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><hi rend="italic">Hedychium</hi> is a genus of plants in the family Zingiberaceae (ginger; see n. 10, above). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3058.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Irwin Lynch</ref>, foreman of the propagating department at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, had been providing CD with both specimens and observations on sleep in plants (see, for example, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11116.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from R. I. Lynch, [28 August 1877]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In Sachs 1875, p. 787, Sachs referred to irritable movement in <hi rend="italic">Smithia sensitiva</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aeschinomene sensitiva</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Aeschynomene sensitiva</hi>, sensitive joint-vetch).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>