<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9190">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From James Crichton-Browne   27 December 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17913</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9190 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9190.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9190.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">11pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 321</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 321</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_677.xml">Crichton-Browne, James</persName>
                <placeName>West Riding Asylum, Wakefield</placeName>
                <date when="1873-12-27">27 Dec 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Is about to undertake an intensive investigation with other scientists of general paralysis in its various aspects. Would appreciate CD’s comments on photographs he would submit.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4972">scientists</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">pathology, disease</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">West Riding Asylum. | Wakefield.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Decem. 1873.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I venture to make a request which you must not hesitate to refuse should you see any objection to acquiescence in it. Impatient of the slowness of the advance which is made in our knowledge of the Pathology and Treatment of Nervous Diseases, I am about to try a new method of dealing with these subjects. Instead of trusting any longer to independent exertions scattered over a wide area, I propose to test the efficacy of combined effort upon one point. Having selected one well marked variety of mental disease—General Paralysis—throughout the whole course of which physical and mental symptoms progress <hi rend="underline">pari passu</hi> I have induced a number of able and distinguished friends to undertake its investigation in different aspects. Thus one will work out the Microscopic Anatomy, another—the Chemistry of the urine, another the variation of temperature another the appearances of the retinae. &amp;c &amp;c. Each investigator will briefly and clearly set forth the results at which he arrives and the monographs thus produced, will I believe when collected together form a complete natural history of the disease and greatly elucidate its causes, course and treatment   Now it has occured to me that you might immensley aid us in our work if you would consent to give us a very few remarks on the Physiognomy of the Disease. I could submit to you a series of photographs illustrating its various stages, and a very few words of yours would I am certain embody the true significance of the whole. I am aware that it is a very audacious request that I am making and nothing could justify it but the motive which is an earnest desire to advance Medical Science. You will at least forgive my boldness &amp;c<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>Believe me to be with profound esteem and all seasonable good wishes. | Yours very faithfully | J. Crichton Browne <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Charles Darwin Esq | &amp;c &amp;c <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p>P.S. Among my fellow labourers in this work are to be Prof. Ferrier. Dr Hughlings Jackson. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Clifford Allbutt. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Brunton<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp;c &amp;c | J. C. B.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Crichton-Browne later published an article, ‘Notes on the pathology of general paralysis’, in <hi rend="italic">West Riding Lunatic Asylum Medical Reports</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crichton-Browne 1876</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1620.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">David Ferrier</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5983.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Hughlings Jackson</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Clifford Allbutt</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_693.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Lauder Brunton</ref>. Although there is no evidence of a co-ordinated research programme on the scale envisaged here, all the researchers mentioned published papers in the <hi rend="italic">West Riding Lunatic Asylum Medical Reports</hi>, which was founded and edited by Crichton-Browne. Ferrier and Allbutt conducted research in the laboratory at Wakefield, and Crichton-Browne, Ferrier, and Hughlings Jackson were co-founders of the journal <hi rend="italic">Brain</hi> in 1878. Crichton-Browne ceased to be active in medical research when he left Wakefield in 1875 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref> s.v. Crichton-Browne, James; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6221.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pearn 2010</ref>; see also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8861.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from James Crichton-Browne, 16 April 1873</ref> and n. 2).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>