<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12239">
 <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt>
 <title xml:id="main_title">From E. Desrousseaux<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   30 September 1879</title>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
 <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
 <idno type="lognum">16727</idno>
 
 
 
 

 <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12239 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12239.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12239.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt>
 <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
 <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
 </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
 <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 173</bibl>
 <msDesc>
 <msIdentifier>
 <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
 <collection>DAR</collection>
 <idno>162: 173</idno>
 </msIdentifier>
 </msDesc>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc>
 <correspDesc>
 <correspAction type="sent">
 <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1306.xml">Desrousseaux, Édouard-Auguste</persName>
 <placeName>Alouzon</placeName>
 <date when="1879-09-30">30 Sept 1879</date>
 </correspAction>
 <correspAction type="received">
 <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
 </correspAction>
 </correspDesc>
 <abstract>
 <p>ED is at work on a book to be called "Les grands phénomènes de la nature", which will furnish additional proof of CD’s doctrine.</p>
 <p>Expounds his theory that all phenomena originate in movement.</p>
 </abstract>
 <textClass>
 <keywords>
 <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
 <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
 <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
 </keywords>
 </textClass>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-10-11" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-11" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="ampearn">Alison Pearn</name></change>
        <change when="2018-02-06" status="editorResponseCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-09-03" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-09-03" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00793_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00793_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="173:1r" xml:id="i793">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00793.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00793_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00793.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:1v" xml:id="i794">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00794.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00794_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00794.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:2r" xml:id="i795">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00795.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00795_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00795.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:2v" xml:id="i796">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00796.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00796_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00796.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:3r" xml:id="i797">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00797.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00797_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00797.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:3v" xml:id="i798">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00798.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00798_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00798.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:4r" xml:id="i799">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00799.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00799_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00799.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173:4v" xml:id="i800">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00800.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00800_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00800.dzi" width="3644px" height="6087px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="173 foldout" xml:id="i801">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00801.jpg" width="6892px" height="6020px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00801_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="6892px" height="6020px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="landscape" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00801.dzi" width="6892px" height="6020px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
 <text>
 <body>
 
 <div type="letter">
 <div type="text">
 <opener>
 <salute>Monsieur</salute>
 </opener>
 <div type="transcription">
 
 <p>J’ai lu avec un vif intérêt votre ouvrage si remarquable intitulé “Origine des Espèces” qui a soulevé des problèmes de premier ordre; s’il a trouvé des contradicteurs, en revanche il fait chaque jour de nouveaux partisans.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
 <p>Je compose dans ce moment un ouvrage sous le titre: “Ces grands phénomènes de la nature” et j’aurai l’honneur de vous en envoyer un exemplaire quand il sera terminé.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Les aperçus que j’y traite donneront une preuve de plus de la verité de la doctrine que vous avez exposée.</p>
 <p>Je suis en effet arrivé a la conclusion que tous les phénomènes, quels qu’ils soient, sont enfantés par le mouvement. La matière éternelle remplit l’espace sous forme d’atomes invisibles d’un type unique qui constituent l’Ether lui-même et sont la véritable semence des mondes. Ces atomes, autrement dit, la matière réduite à son dernier degré de division, sont soumis à des lois éternelles comme eux. Resserrés les uns les autres en vertu de leurs attractions naturelles, ils ne sont cependant pas en contact parce qu’ils sont doués de mouvement, lequel consiste en vibrations calorifiques; malgré ces vibrations, la température de l’éther est glaciale, à cause du défaut de rayonnement de son calorique qui est latent et combiné avec les particules. Celles-ci obéissent ainsi à deux forces contraires, attraction et répulsion, qui se font équilibre et donnent aux atomes des distances fixes.</p>
<p>Tel est l’état normal de la matière de toute éternité. Comment, cet état normal étant établi, les phénomènes peuvent-ils surgir? C’est parceque le repos et l’immobilité n’existent nulle part dans la nature, comme le prouvent les vibrations eternelles. L’évolution commence parceque, en réalité, l’equilibre entre les deux forces attractive et répulsive <hi rend="underline">n’est jamais stable</hi>; à tour de rôle, la première domine, puis la seconde; autrement dit, les atomes éprouvent sans discontinuité une oscillation pareille à celle du pendule et cette oscillation qui tantôt les sépare davantage, tantôt les rapproche, est la <hi rend="underline">véritable force mécanique de l’Univers</hi>; elle est fabuleusement lente et doit se chiffrer par des milliards de siècles pour un seul balencement. Comme pour le pendule, l’équilibre dérangé tend de lui-même à se rétablir, puis se dérange de nouveau précisément à cause de l’impulsion par laquelle il fait effort pour se rétablir; les atomes oscillent donc sans cesse de part et d’autre de leur positions normales et le mouvement est éternel, puisqu’il n’y a pas de frottement dans le vide absolu.</p>
<p>Telle est l’origine des nébuleuses sur différents points de l’espace. S’il se fait quelque part une condensation ou resserrement des atomes; c’est parce qu’ils avaient éprouvé antérieurement une séparation trop grande; l’excès du dérangements de l’état normal dans un sens appelle le même excès dans le sens opposé.</p>
 <p>Pour comprendre ce phénomène, il faut réflêchir que les atomes sont doués de mouvement (vibrations naturelles). Au point d’équilibre ces vibrations sont latentes et ne rayonnent pas, car elles font précisément contrepoids à la force attractive; mais si par suite de l’oscillation éternelle, les atomes quittent leurs positions normales pour se reserrer, ils vibrent de plus en plus; le calorique augmente, car le mouvement qui leur est communiqué rencontrant la résistance opposée au resserrement par les vibrations naturelles est obligé de se transformer et finalement de se convertir en calorique (le calorique est, comme on sait, une simple transformation du mouvement). C’est ainsi que les chocs sur une matière résistante donnent du calorique. Alors, non seulement il y a rayonnements (clarté dans la nébuleuse) puisque les vibrations sont en excès, mais la force expansive s’accroît et finit par amener un desserrement général. Les atomes sont ramenés ainsi à leurs positions primitives, mais n’y restent pas, à cause de l’impulsion que leur avaient imprimée les vibrations en excès; ils dépassent donc le point normal et se séparent trop. Le phénomène précédent se reproduit alors et donne des résultats inverses. Au lieu du rayonnement, il se fait un refroidissement et une augmentation de la force attractive, comme dans toute substance refroidie ou dilatée mécaniquement. En effet, les atomes en revenant a leurs positions normales ne possédaient plus à ce moment que leurs vibrations naturelles, mais comme ils dépassent le point d’équilibre en vertu de l’impulsion acquise lors du desserrement, ils sont obligés de perdre du calorique, puisque le mouvement qu’ils possèdent ne peut exister que par une transformation du calorique en mouvement; autrement dit, <hi rend="underline">le calorique disparaît parcequ’il se convertit en mouvement</hi>, et ne peut reparaître que lors d’une nouvelle condensation. Si donc la séparation des atomes devient exagérée, l’éther qui se dilate se refroidit; le manque de calorique pour ce nouvel état donne la prépondérance à la force attractive et les particules qui ont acquis par leur séparation une énergie de position exceptionelle finissent par revenir les unes vers les autres avec une grande puissance. Une condensation croissante en résulte et elle est assez intense pour amener une portion des atomes au contact.</p>
<p>La nébuleuse est alors en formation et l’évolution a commencé. Elle se continue, car les premiers éléments qui se sont unis servent de points de ralliement à ceux qui les suivent et sur ces noyaux d’attraction les atomes étherés ne cesseront de tomber pendant des périodes incalculables. Non seulement la nébuleuse fait rayonner son calorique par sa condensation, mais les particules qui tombent sur les noyaux se débarrassent par le choc d’une partie de leurs vibrations intrinsèques qui rayonnent dans l’espace et par leur émission leur permettent de s’unir en différentes proportions pour former les corps simples. Ces combinaisons chimiques d’une puissance qui leur donne la faculté de résister aux hautes températures des noyaux, grâce à l’énergie potentielle acquise avant la chute, sont la source d’une lumière éblouissante (transformation du mouvement de chute).</p>
<p>L’étoile a donc pris naissance et s’accroît sans cesse. La lumière se maintient à travers les âges, même quand à la longue la nébuleuse s’est dissipée. En effet le phénomène se continue car l’électricité dégagée par les combinaisons chimiques des corps simples se distribue positivement et négativement sur les éléments qui entourent l’etoile et sur ceux qui en font partie. L’astre a acquis par là une force d’induction qui lui permet d’attirer sans cesse à lui les atomes de l’éther et d’entretenir sa clarté par de nouvelles combinaisons chimiques.</p>
 <p>Nous avons ainsi l’explication de la permanence si mystérieuse de la lumière du soleil depuis un passé insondable et aussi celle de la lumière zodiacale qui consiste dans un calorique diffus qu’émettent les atomes resserrés sur le plan de l’écliptique par la force centrifuge, car tout en tombant sur le soleil ils gravitent autour de lui et s’en rapprochant de plus en plus pour disparaitre dans les combinaisons chimiques. Un phénomène semblable a lieu dans les nébuleuses arrivées à un degré d’avancement tel que les mouvements des atomes se sont à la longue mis en harmonie sur un plan commun. Dans leur chute sur les noyaux ils gravitent en spirale; de là une rotation de la nébuleuse. Ces atomes pressés les uns contre les autres constituent une espèce de nébulosité et par leurs chocs obliques à la surface du soleil ils donnent à celui-ci son mouvement de rotation, comme le prouve la plus grande rapidité de marche des taches à l’équateur où les particules sont plus resserrées et plus nombreuses et font mouvoir la photosphère plus vite qu’aux pôles.</p>
<p>Ainsi <hi rend="underline">le milieu universel est le principe de tout</hi>. Il ne se borne pas à servir d’intermédiaire entre les mondes pour le rayonnement et la pesanteur qui se transmettent de molécules en molécules éthérées; il les enfante; les nourrit de sa propre substance, et de plus leur communique <hi rend="underline">le mouvement</hi> et <hi rend="underline">enfin la vie</hi>.</p>
<p>Il nous faut en effet suivre la théorie jusque dans ses dernières conséquences. Le calorique et l’électricitè n’étant que le mouvement des atomes transformé, mouvement condensé (calorique) et mouvement emmagasiné (électricité) doivent nécessairement reproduire le mouvement lui-même lorsqu’ils réagissent sur la matière, car rien ne peut se perdre dans la nature. Or, en réalité, le mouvement est synonyme de vie; il est la vie qui anime l’univers. C’est pourquoi l’énergie transmise au soleil par les atomes qui tombent sur lui se convertit d’abord en calorique et en électricité, puis rayonne sur les planètes où ces deux agents font surgir la vie par une nouvelle transformation très mystérieuse. Ce sont encore eux qui nous donnent toutes les forces mécaniques que nous utilisons.</p>
<p>Ce n’est pas tout. Les mouvements des astres eux-mêmes n’ont pas d’autre origine. Si le soleil tourne sur son axe et se déplace dans l’infini, si les planètes pivotent et se meuvent dans leurs orbites, si enfin les satellites gravitent autour des planètes, c’est parceque tous ces rouages sont mis en jeu par la force centrale; dans leur chute sur le soleil les atomes agissent par leur énergie potentielle comme l’eau qui par son énergie de position fait mouvoir une turbine ou roue hydraulique. Le mouvement de chute des atomes est en effet une force immense qui, ne pouvant être perdue, se change en calorique et en électricité qui à leur tour de communiquent aux planètes et satellites par le véhicule de l’éther et reproduisent le mouvement qui les a engendrés.</p>
 <p>Il serait trop long de décrire ici le mécanisme très curieux au moyen duquel les agents physiques communiquent le mouvement aux astres; le calorique et aussi l’électricité transformée en courants qui enveloppent les planètes et satellites y jouent un rôle important. Pour le connaître j’ai dû étudier de près l’électricité et le magnétisme et j’ai fini par découvrir que si le calorique est le mouvement lui-même plus ou moins intense imprimé par les chocs des atomes étherés à la matière qui réagit pour restituer la force transmise, l’électricité a un lien de parenté très-étroit avec le calorique; c’est pourquoi les deux agents peuvent se convertir l’un en l’autre. En somme l’électricité est une forme particulière du mouvement; elle est le mouvement emmagasiné, converti en <hi rend="underline">ressorts moléculaires</hi> très puissants par l’effet d’un dérangement d’équilibre des molécules matérielles. Comme dans tout dérangement d’equilibre deux forces contraires, égales et complémentaires surgissent à la fois et sont les deux fluides qui se recombinent pour rétablir l’état normal. Les deux ressorts inverses se détendent reciproquement, c’est à dire que le mouvement qui avait été emmagasiné à l’aide d’une force mécanique ou électromotrice constitue des ressorts dont l’énergie potentielle <hi rend="underline">retourne à l’état actif</hi> dans le courant. Celui-ci par suite a la vertu de reproduire le mouvement à son tour, soit par ses réactions, soit par le calorique qu’il transmet.</p>
<p>Je ne pourrais vous décrire en quelques mots le phénomène par lequel le mouvement se convertit en électricité pour constituer deux ressorts inverses; cela demanderait trop de developpements. Il en est de même du mécanisme de la gravitation. Je me bornerai à vous indiquer par quel moyen le soleil peut se mouvoir dans l’éspace. C’est à l’aide de son magnétisme <hi rend="underline">qui réagit sur l’éther</hi> par attraction d’un côté et répulsion de l’autre en imprimant une vitesse inouïe de rotation aux particules éthérées autour des axes des lignes de force qui émergent des pôles, tout en les attirant ou les repoussant selon les pôles dont l’un est passif et l’autre actif, propriétés que l’étude du magnétisme m’a fait connaître. L’astre marche dans l’éther comme le navire sur l’eau frappée par l’hélice.</p>
 <p>Ces lois ne cadrent pas tout a fait avec la théorie newtonienne, mais je ne viens pas combattre cette théorie; il suffit de la compléter. Newton<ref target="#foot.f4"/> avait trouvé la force attractive, qui est l’un des deux facteurs de la gravitation; à son époque il ne pouvait soupçonner le second facteur, c’est à dire le mouvement transformé et reproduit. En introduisant dans sa théorie l’élément qui fait défaut, les calculs astronomiques restent les mêmes puisqu’il avait supposé la force centrifuge, seulement nous apercevons la cause de cette force centrefuge.</p>
<p>Une force vive ne peut naître d’elle-même et si les globes ont un mouvement de déplacement à travers l’espace, il faut bien qu’il y ait une cause à ce déplacement— Or, cette cause c’est la force vive transmise à l’étoile par les atomes éthérés qui tombent sur elle et dont la puissance d’énergie se transforme en agents physiques qui réagissent.</p>
<p>Et même en supposant que les astres aient reçu une impulsion primitive, et en ne tenant pas compte du frottement sur l’éther qui aurait cependant suffi, pour user et anéantir l’impulsion depuis tant de millions d’années, la gravitation serait encore impossible sans l’intervention des agents physiques. Une démonstration bien simple vous le prouvera—</p> 
     <figure rend="blockCentred width50">
         <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12239.png"/>
     </figure>     
 <p>En astronomie, on dit qu’une planète P lancée dans l’espace de A en C et passante à proximité de l’astre S, dévie lorsqu’elle arrive au point B et se transporte de B en E, en vertu de la loi du parallélogramme des forces. Or, je demande pourquoi la planète ne dévie qu’à partir du point B. Il faut donc supposer l’attraction <hi rend="underline">nulle de A en B</hi> et active seulement de B en C, mais en vertu de quelle loi ignorée l’attraction n’agit-elle pas avant le point B?</p>
<p>Il suffit de poser la question pour faire comprendre l’erreur. En ŕealité, la planète attirée dès A commencerait alors à dévier de plus en plus, et elle ne pourrait qu’aller tomber sur S par la diagonale d’après la loi même du parallélogramme. Pour empêcher la chute, il faut absolument l’intervention d’un second facteur qui lui permette de braver l’attraction en lui donnant le mouvement et par suite la force centrifuge. Le second facteur est le mouvement lui-même transformé en agents physiques.</p>
<p>Tout se tient dans la nature. La théorie de l’évolution ne peut que se fortifier, en dépit des résistances, par une meilleure connaissance du mécanisme réel de l’Univers. L’évolution commence dans l’oscillation éternelle de l’éther et fait surgir chaque phénomène l’un après l’autre, en vertu de la loi du mouvement qui est synonyme de vie. Le mouvement lui-même peut se déplacer et se métamorphoser, mais jamais d’anéantir, car si de l’éther il se communique aux étoiles en engendrant leur calorique, des étoiles il retourne par rayonnement dans le sein de l’éther au profit de ses atomes qui soumis à la dilatation incessante de l’oscillation sont avides de calorique et l’absorbent en l’emmagasinant pour le restituer dans un avenir inifiniment lointain lorsque le mouvement de condensation remplacera celui de dilatation pour enfanter de nouveaux mondes. Le mouvement est donc indestructible aussi bien que les atomes de l’éther.</p>
 <p>Je n’ai pas besoin d’admettre, comme Kant, une température inouïe et incompréhensible (que serait devenue cette chaleur?) dans un chaos inadmissible.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Il suffit que l’éther soit doué d’un calorique latent et tout s’explique par l’oscillation des atomes qui tantôt se refroidissent, tantôt vibrent davantage. Le calorique des étoiles est engendré par cette condensation poussée à un point extrême. Quant à la température de l’éther, elle est toujours glaciale, tant à cause du non rayonnement de son calorique naturel que parcequ’il exerce une action absorbante, quand il se dilate et produit un froid prodigieux.</p>
<p>La preuve de cette constitution de l’éther, telle que je la donne, est dans l’explication du phénomène de la pesanteur à distance, phénomène qui ètait très obscur. L’Ether à son état normal n’est ni attractif ni répulsif parceque les deux forces d’attraction et de répulsion se font équilibre, mais si une masse quelconque se trouve au milieu de l’éther, elle en attire les atomes à elle, et comme l’attraction a lieu de tous côtés à la fois, rien n’est encore changé. Si au contraire deux globes se trouvent en présence, ils attirent à eux les particules étherées qui, sollicitées dans deux sens différents, réagissent sur les deux globes; les atomes ne peuvent se porter dans ces deux directions opposées sans de séparer. Or si l’éther se dilate il se refroidit immédiatement et la force attractive domine; la séparation des atomes ne peut donc se faire que dans une minime mesure et ce sont les deux astres qui sont obligés de se porter l’un vers l’autre. On comprend mieux le phénomène en comparant le milieu à une bande de caoutchouc qui tiré de force rèagit et attire à son tour quand on le dilate. En se rapprochant les deux globes exercent une attraction de plus en plus vive sur les atomes intermédiares; le ressort acquis par ces atomes se tend en conséquence et la vitesse de chute devient accélerée.</p>
<p>Le même phénomène a lieu pour les attractions et répulsions entre les pôles des aimants qui font naître des spires dans le milieu autour des axes des lignes de force. Ces spires étant de <hi rend="underline">veritables courants</hi> sont attirées entre deux pôles différents mais comme elles s’attirent elles-mêmes elles ne peuvent obéir; en se sèparant une grande tension se manifeste dans le milieu et la réaction force les deux pôles à se porter l’un vers l’autre. La même tension se présente avec des résultats inverses entre deux pôles semblables; les spires étant de sens opposé sont repoussées par les pôles, mais comme elles se repoussent elles-mêmes elles ne peuvent obéir en se resserrant, et la réaction du milieu force les deux aimants à s’écarter.</p>
<p>Bien d’autres phénomènes électriques, tels que l’induction, s’expliquent par les réactions du milieu intermédiaire; je ne puis vous les indiquer toutes ici. Ce que je vous expose suffit pour vous montrer quelle est la constitution réelle de l’éther, et la force qui fait naître l’évolution.</p>
 <p>Persuadé que ces aperçus vous interesseront et que peut-être vous me ferez l’honneur d’une réponse; je vous prie, Monsieur, de recevoir l’assurance de ma très-haute considération, | Desrousseaux <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Mouzon (Ardennes) le 30 Septembre 1879</p> 
 </div>
 </div>

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 </div>
 
 
 <div type="translation">
 <div type="text">
 <opener> <salute>Sir</salute></opener>
 <div type="transcription"><p>I have read with lively interest your very remarkable work entitled “Origine des Espèces” which has raised excellent questions; it may have found itself opponents, but in turn it makes new supporters every day.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
 <p>At the moment I am composing a work with the title: “Ces grands phénomènes de la nature” and I will have the honour of sending you a copy of it when it is finished.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The insights that I deal with there will give one more proof of the truth of the doctrine which you have expounded.</p>
 <p>Indeed I have come to the conclusion that all phenomena, whatever they may be, are derived from motion. Eternal matter fills up space in the form of a unique type of invisible atoms that make up the Ether itself and are the actual seed of the worlds. These atoms, in other words, matter reduced to the last degree of division, are subject to eternal laws like them. Drawn together one against the other by virtue of their natural attractions, they are not however in contact because they are endowed with the motion, that consists of calorific vibrations; in spite of these vibrations, the temperature of the ether is glacial, because of the lack of radiation of its heat, which is latent and combined with the particles. These are thus subject to two opposing forces, attraction and repulsion, which produce equilibrium and give fixed distances to atoms.</p>
 <p> Such is the normal state of matter for all eternity. How, having established this normal state, can the phenomena arise? It is because rest and immobility do not exist anywhere in nature, as the eternal vibrations show. Evolution begins because, in reality, the equilibrium between the two attractive and repulsive forces <hi rend="underline">is never stable</hi>; taking turns, the first prevails, then the second: to put it another way, atoms show oscillation, without discontinuity like that of a pendulum and this oscillation, which sometimes separates them more, sometimes moves them closer, is the <hi rend="underline">true mechanical force of the Universe</hi>; it is fantastically slow and must amount to billions of centuries for a single swing. As in the pendulum, disturbed equilibrium tends to re-establish itself on its own, then disturb itself afresh precisely because of the impulse by which it makes an effort to re-establish itself; the atoms oscillate thus without ceasing on both sides of their normal positions and the motion is everlasting, since there is no friction in the absolute void.</p>
 <p>Such is the origin of nebulas at various points in space. If somewhere a condensation or compression of atoms takes place; it is because they had previously experienced too great a separation; excessive diversion from the norm in one direction produces the same excess in the opposite direction. </p>
 <p>To understand this phenomenon, we must remember that atoms are endowed with motion (natural vibration). At the point of equilibrium these vibrations are latent and do not radiate, for they act precisely as a counterbalance to the force of attraction; but if as a result of the eternal oscillation the atoms leave their normal positions to draw closer, they vibrate more and more; heat increases, for the motion that is transferred to them meeting the resistance acting against compression by natural vibrations is forced to transform and in the end to change into heat (heat is, as we know, a simple transformation of motion). This is how collisions on a resistant material produce heat. So, not only is there radiation (light in the nebula) because the vibrations are in excess, but the expanding force increases and ends by causing a general expansion. The atoms are thus brought back to their original positions, but they do not stay there, because of the impetus impressed on them by an excess of vibrations; so they go past the normal point and separate too much. Thus the preceding phenomenon recurs and gives inverse results. Instead of radiation, regelation takes place and an increase in the attractive force, as in any substance regelated or expanded mechanically. In effect, atoms in returning to their normal positions no longer possess at that moment anything but their natural vibrations, but as they go past the point of equilibrium by virtue of the impulse acquired during their expansion, they must lose heat, since the motion that they possess can only exist with a transformation of heat into motion: in other words, <hi rend="underline">heat disappears because it is converted into motion</hi>, and can only reappear during a new condensation. If therefore separation of the atoms becomes exaggerated, the ether that expands cools down; the loss of heat for this new state tips the balance to the force of attraction and the particles that have from their separation acquired abnormal potential energy finish by coming back with great force to one another. An increasing condensation results and it is strong enough to bring a percentage of the atoms into contact.</p>
 <p>The nebula is thus being formed and evolution has started. It continues, for the first elements that have joined together serve as rallying points for those that follow them and onto these nuclei of attraction the ethereal atoms will not cease to fall for countless ages. Not only does the nebula radiate its heat through its condensation, but the particles that fall on the nuclei dissipate by the impact of part of their intrinsic vibrations, which radiate into space and by their emission enable them to join together in different proportions to form simple bodies. These chemical compounds, because of a power which gives them the ability to resist the high temperatures of the nuclei, thanks to the potential energy acquired before the fall, are the source of dazzling light (transformation of the motion of falling). So the star has been born and it expands without ceasing. The light keeps going through the ages, even when in the long run the nebula has vanished. Indeed the phenomenon persists since the electricity released by the chemical arrangements of simple bodies distributes itself positively and negatively on the elements that surround the star and on those of which they form a part. By that the star has acquired an inductive force that enables it to attract unceasingly to itself the atoms of the ether and to maintain its brilliance by new chemical arrangements.</p>
 <p>Thus we have the explanation for the permanence of the sun’s light, which has been for an unfathomable time so mysterious, and also that of the light of the zodiac, which takes the form of diffused heat, which the packed atoms emit on the plane of the elliptic through centrifugal force, for in falling on the sun they orbit around it and moving closer and closer disappear within chemical arrangements. A similar phenomenon takes place in the nebulae that have reached a level of advancement such that the motions of the atoms are eventually put in harmony on a common plane. In their fall on the nuclei they orbit in a spiral; from there a rotation of the nebula. These atoms pressed against one another constitute a sort of nebulosity and by their oblique impacts at the surface of the sun they give it its rotational movement, as is shown by the fastest movement of the spots at the equator where the particles are more compressed and more numerous and make the photosphere move more quickly than at the poles. So <hi rend="underline">the universal medium is the principle of everything</hi>. It is not limited to acting as an intermediary between the worlds for radiation and gravity, which are transmitted from one ethereal molecule to another; it gives birth to them; it nourishes them with its own substance, and moreover transmits to them <hi rend="underline">motion</hi> and <hi rend="underline">ultimately life</hi>. Indeed we must follow the theory to its final consequences. Heat and electricity being nothing but the motion of atoms transformed, motion condensed (heat) and accumulated motion (electricity) must of necessity reproduce the motion itself when they react on matter, for nothing can be lost in nature. Now, in reality, motion is synonymous with life; it is life which animates the universe. It is why energy transmitted to the sun by the atoms that fall on it is converted first into heat and electricity, then radiates on the planets where these two agents cause life to arise as a result of a new very mysterious transformation. They are also those which give us all the mechanical forces that we employ.</p> 
     <p>That is not all. The motions of the stars themselves have no other origin. If the sun turns on its axis and moves in the infinite, if the planets rotate and move in their orbits, if finally satellites orbit around the planets, it is because all these parts are put into play by the central force; in their fall on the sun atoms would act by their potential energy like water, which because of its energy of position makes a turbine or waterwheel move. The motion of falling in atoms is indeed an immense force, which, because it cannot be lost, changes into heat and electricity, which in their turn are transmitted to the planets and satellites by means of the ether and reproduce the motion that has created them.</p>
     <p>It would take too long to describe here the most curious mechanism by means of which physical agents transmit motion to the stars; heat as well as electricity transformed into currents that surround the planets and the satellites play an important part in this. To understand it I had to study electricity and magnetism closely and as a result I discovered that if heat is motion itself acting more or less intensely as a result of the impact of ethereal atoms on matter, which reacts to restore the transmitted force, electricity has a very close family tie to heat; it is why the two agents can convert themselves from one into the other. To sum up electricity is a particular form of motion; it is accumulated motion, turned into very powerful <hi rend="underline">molecular springs</hi> as a result of the disturbance of the equilibrium of material molecules. As in all disturbance of equilibrium two opposing forces, equal and complementary, arise at the same time and are the two fluids that recombine to restore the normal state. The two opposing springs relax reciprocally, that is to say that the motion that had been stored with the help of a mechanical or electromotive force forms springs whose potential energy <hi rend="underline">returns to the active state</hi> in the current. This in consequence has the virtue of reproducing motion in its turn, whether by its reactions or by the heat that it transmits.</p> 
     <p>I could not describe to you in a few words the phenomenon by which motion is converted into electricity to create two opposing springs; that would require too many explanations. It is the same with the mechanism of gravity. I will content myself with pointing out to you in what way the sun can move in space. It is with the help of its magnetism, <hi rend="underline">which reacts on the ether</hi> by attraction on one side and repulsion on the other in impressing a tremendous rotational speed on the ethereal particles around the axes of the force-lines coming up from the poles, while attracting them or repelling them depending on the poles, one of which is passive and the other active, properties which the study of magnetism has made me understand. The star travels in the ether like a ship on water beaten by a propeller.</p> 
     <p>These laws may not quite fit with Newtonian theory, but I am not opposing this theory; it is enough to complete it. Newton<ref target="#foot.f4"/> had found the force of attraction, which is one of the two factors of gravity; in his time he was not able to conjecture the second factor, that is to say transformed and recreated motion. By introducing into his theory the element that is lacking, the astronomical calculations remain the same since he had postulated centrifugal force, only we perceive the cause of this centrifugal force. A living force cannot arise out of itself and if globes have a motion of displacement across space, there must be a cause of this displacement— Well, this cause is the living force transmitted to the star by the ethereal atoms falling on it and whose powerful energy transforms into physical agents that react.</p> 
     <p>Even supposing that the stars had received an initial impulse, and in not taking into account any friction on the ether, which had however been sufficient to exploit and exhaust the impulse for so many million years, gravity would still be impossible without the intervention of physical agents. A very simple demonstration will prove it to you— </p> 
     <figure rend="blockCentred width50">
         <graphic url="../images/DCP_LETT_12239.png"/>
     </figure>     
         <p>In astronomy, we say that a planet P launched into space from A to C and passing near star S, deviates when it reaches point B and travels from B to E, by virtue of the parallelogram law of forces. Well, I ask why the planet only deviates on leaving point B. It must therefore be supposed that the attraction <hi rend="underline">non-existent from A to B</hi> is active only from B to C, but by virtue of what unknown law does attraction not work before point B?</p>
     <p>Asking the question is enough to make the mistake comprehensible. In reality, the planet attracted from A would then begin to deviate more and more, and it could only fall on S along the diagonal according to the same parallelogram law. To prevent the fall, the intervention of a second factor is vital, which allows it to defy the attraction by giving it motion and consequently centrifugal force. The second factor is motion itself transformed into physical agents.</p> 
     <p>Everything makes sense in nature. The theory of evolution can only grow stronger, despite resistance, by a better understanding of the actual mechanism of the Universe. Evolution begins in the eternal oscillation of the ether and makes each phenomenon arise one after the other, by virtue of the law of motion, which is synonymous with life. Motion itself can be transferred and transformed, but never destroyed, for if it is conveyed from the ether to the stars generating their heat, it returns from the stars by radiation in the bosom of the ether to the advantage of its atoms, which, subjected to unceasing expansion from oscillation, are eager for heat and absorb it and accumulate it to reconstitute it infinitely far in the future when condensation will replace expansion to create new worlds. So motion is as indestructible as the atoms of the ether.</p> 
     <p>I do not need to suppose, like Kant, an unprecedented and incredible temperature (what would have become of this heat?) in unacceptable chaos.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It is enough that the ether may be endowed with latent heat and everything is explained by the oscillation of atoms that sometimes cool down, sometimes vibrate further. The heat of the stars is produced by this compression taken to an extreme. As for the temperature of the ether, it is always icy, because its natural heat is not radiated, and because it performs an absorbing action when it expands and produces prodigious cold. </p> 
     <p>The proof of this composition of the ether, such as I have given, is in the explanation of the phenomenon of remote gravity, a phenomenon that was very obscure. Ether in its normal state neither attracts nor repels because the two forces of attraction and repulsion create equilibrium, but if some mass appears in the middle of the ether, it draws the atoms to itself, and as the attraction takes place on all sides at once, nothing is changed yet. If on the contrary two globes are present, they draw to them the ethereal particles, which, attracted in two different directions, react on the two globes; the atoms cannot spread out in these two different directions without separating. So if the ether expands it cools down instantly and the force of attraction is dominant; the separation of the atoms can only take place to a minimal degree and the two stars themselves are forced to move towards one another. The phenomenon can be better understood by comparing the middle of a rubber band stretched by force, which reacts and attracts in its turn as it is stretched. As they move closer together the two globes exercise a more and more vigorous attraction on the intermediate atoms; the spring acquired by these atoms is tightened as a result and the speed of the fall becomes accelerated.</p> 
     <p>The same phenomenon happens in the case of attraction and repulsion between the poles of magnets, which create whorls in the middle around the axes of the lines of force. These whorls being <hi rend="underline">genuine currents</hi> are attracted between two different poles but as they attract themselves they cannot obey; as they separate themselves great tension appears in the middle and the reaction forces the two poles to move towards each other. The same tension appears with opposite results between two similar poles; the whorls being in opposite directions are pushed back by the poles, but as they push back themselves they cannot obey by drawing together, and the reaction in the middle forces the two magnets to separate.</p> 
     <p>Many other electrical phenomena, such as induction, are explained by the reactions of the intermediate middle; I cannot show you all of them here. What I have explained is enough to show you the actual constitution of the ether, and the force which gives rise to evolution. Convinced that these insights will interest you and that perhaps you will honour me with a reply; I beg you, Sir, to receive the assurance of my highest regard, Desrousseaux</p>  
     <p rend="left">Mouzon (Ardennes) 30 September 1879</p>
 </div>  
 </div> 
 </div> 
      
      
     <div type="footnotes"> 
         <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note> 
         <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see Transcript.</note> 
         <note xml:id="foot.f2">The most recent French edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_356.xml">Barbier trans. 1876</ref>.</note> 
         <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10521.xml">Desrousseaux 1879</ref>.</note> 
         <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3519.xml">Isaac Newton</ref>.</note> 
         <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2641.xml">Immanuel Kant</ref> was an early proponent of the nebular hypothesis, a theory about the formation and development of planetary systems from nebulous material. For more on the hypothesis and its connection with theories of organic evolution, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10522.xml">Brush 1987</ref>; see also <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 26, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11381.xml">letter from A. S. Wilson, 28 February 1878</ref>.</note>  
     </div>  
   
 </body> 
 </text>
</TEI>