<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6866">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   22 August 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16688</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6866 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6866.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6866.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (Italian)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 51</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 143</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 143</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                <date when="1869-08-22">22 Aug 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Declares himself CD’s defender; but he is a "teleologist".</p>
            <p>Sends CD three more papers.</p>
            <p>His research confirms his faith and belief in variability of species.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="people" ref="#">teleologist</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Firenze</placeName>
                    <date>22. Agosto 1869</date>
                    <salute>Celeberrimo uomo!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Animato dalla cortesia con cui la S.V. Si compiacque aggradire due miei scritti editi nel 1867, mi prendo la libertà di comunicar le tre altri miei lavori successivi. <ref target="#foot.f2"/> Accetti in omaggio il tenuissimo dono.</p>
<p>Le dottrine che harmo la fortuna di essere propugnate dalla prima Intelligenza del secolo nostro, trovano anche in me un difensore, scarso di mezzi sì ma pieno di buona volontà. Ho cercato di contribuire per quanto stava in me alla illustrazione delle dottrine della Dicogamia e della variabilità delle specie.</p>
<p>Duolmi per altro di non potere consentire in alcune idee generali. Forse per errore di mente ma certo con profonda convinzione io sono teleologo. Io credo che quel principio razionale di cui l’uomo si Sente animato, governi non meno tutti gli altri esseri, comprese le piante. E credo che la causa prima di tutte le variazioni, sia in bene che in male, con progresso o con regresso, consista appunto in questo principio intrinseco, innato in tutti gli esseri.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Comunque sia, dalle mie ricerche botaniche mi risulta che la variabilità delle specie non merita più di essere chiamata teoria: tutte le parti della scienza concorrono, almeno secondo me, a metterne in chiara luce l’assoluta verità di fatto.</p>
<p>Onore dunque alla Intelligenza che seppe dare tanto impulso al pensiero umano. Onore al primo naturalista del Secolo, del quale pregio protestarmi</p>
<p>Ossequentissimo discepolo | Federico Delpino <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Assistente di botanica al museo di Storia naturale in Firenze.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener>
            <placeName>Florence</placeName>
        <date>22. August 1869</date>
        <salute>Most famous man!</salute>
        </opener>
        <div type="transcription">
            <p>Encouraged by the courtesy with which you were kind enough to appreciate two works of mine published in 1867, I take the liberty to send you three later works of mine.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Please accept the homage of this humble offering. </p>
            <p>The doctrines that are fortunate enough to be propounded by the highest intellect of our century can count me amongst their supporters, albeit one poor in intellectual power but rich in good will. I have tried to make contributions to as great an extent as I could to the illustrations of the doctrine of dichogamy and the variability of species.</p>
            <p>On the other hand I regret not to be able to consent to some general ideas. Perhaps because of intellectual error but certainly with profound conviction, I am a teleologist. I believe that the rational principle by which man is conscious of being animated rules all other beings as well, plants included. And I believe that the first cause of all variations, whether for better or worse, progressive or regressive, lies exactly in this inner principle, inborn in all beings.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
            <p>Be that as it may, from my botanical researches I reach the conclusion that the variability of species cannot be called a theory: all aspects of science concur, at least according to me, to show that it is clearly an absolutely true fact.</p>
            <p>Praise be the intellect that was able to give so much impetus to human thought. Praise be to the foremost naturalist of the century, of which I have the honour of remaining | most humble disciple | Federico Delpino </p>
            <p rend="left">Assistant in botany at the Museo di Storia Naturale, Florence</p>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see p. 368.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Delpino refers to ‘Pensieri sulla biologia vegetale, sulla tassonomia, sul valore tassonomico dei caratteri biologici, e proposta di un genere nuovo della famiglia delle labiate’ (Thoughts on plant biology, taxonomy, the taxonomic value of biological characters, and the proposal of a new genus of the labiate family; Delpino 1867c), the first part of <hi rend="italic">Ulteriori osservazioni sulla dicogamia nel regno vegetale</hi> (Further observations on dichogamy in the vegetable kingdom; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>), and ‘Sulla darwiniana teoria della pangenesi’ (On the Darwinian theory of pangenesis; Delpino 1869a). Delpino had sent CD two papers on dichogamy in 1867 (Delpino 1867a and 1867b; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5622.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Federico Delpino, 5 September 1867</ref> and n. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For more on Delpino’s teleological approach to CD’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6173.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pancaldi 1991</ref>, pp. 107–36.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>