<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11945">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>   [before 20 March 1879]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15663</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11945 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11945.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11945.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 216</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 20 March 1879, pp. 462–3</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Nature 19 1879: 462</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1879-03-19">[before 20 Mar 1879]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3491.xml">Nature</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on a letter from Fritz Müller [<hi rend="doubleUnderline">11839</hi>] and particularly on the subject of the disappearance of certain structures in organisms. FM’s explanation deserves serious consideration.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="b" ref="#">11839</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3070">Müller, J. F. T.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-08-07" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-19" status="reviewed"> Reviewed by <name xml:id="pas">Anne Secord</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-09" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-07-19" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-07-19" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p rend="centre">Fritz Müller on a frog having eggs on its back—on the abortion of the hairs on the legs of certain caddis-flies, &amp;c.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallCaps">Several</hi> of the facts given in the following letter from Fritz Müller, especially those in the third paragraph, appear to me very interesting.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Many persons have felt much perplexed about the steps or means by which structures rendered useless under changed conditions of life, at first become reduced, and finally quite disappear. A more striking case of such disappearance has never been published than that here given by Fritz Müller. Several years ago some valuable letters on this subject by Mr. Romanes (together with one by me) were inserted in the columns of N<hi rend="smallCaps">ature</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Since then various facts have often led me to speculate on the existence of some inherent tendency in every part of every organism to be gradually reduced and to disappear, unless in some manner prevented. But beyond this vague speculation I could never clearly see my way. As far, therefore, as I can judge, the explanation suggested by Fritz Müller well deserves the careful consideration of all those who are interested on such points, and may prove of widely extended application. Hardly anyone who has considered such cases as those of the stripes which occasionally appear on the legs and even bodies of horses and apes—or of the development of certain muscles in man which are not proper to him, but are common in the Quadrumana—or again, of some peloric flowers—will doubt that characters lost for an almost endless number of generations, may suddenly reappear. In the case of natural species we are so much accustomed to apply the term reversion or atavism to the reappearance of a lost part that we are liable to forget that its disappearance may be equally due to this same cause.</p>
                    <p>As every modification, whether or not due to reversion, may be considered as a case of variation, the important law or conclusion arrived at by the mathematician Delbœuf, may be here applied;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> and I will quote Mr. Murphy’s condensed statement (“Habit and Intelligence,” 1879, p. 241) with respect to it: “If in any species a number of individuals, bearing a ratio not infinitely small to the entire number of births, are in every generation born with any particular variation which is neither beneficial nor injurious to its possessors, and if the effect of the variation is not counteracted by reversion, the proportion of the new variety to the original form will constantly increase until it approaches indefinitely near to equality.”<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Now in the case advanced by Fritz Müller the cause of the variation is supposed to be atavism to a very remote progenitor, and this may have wholly prevailed over any tendency to atavism to more recent progenitors; and of such prevalence analogous instances could be given.</p>
<p>C<hi rend="smallCaps">harles</hi> D<hi rend="smallCaps">arwin</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the date of publication of this letter in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11915A.xml">letter to J. N. Lockyer, 4 and 6 March [1879].</ref> </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11839.xml">letter from Fritz Müller, 21 January 1879</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Two letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">George John Romanes</ref> on the topic of use and disuse of organs appeared in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 9 April 1874, pp. 440–1, and 2 July 1874, p. 164 (Romanes 1874a and 1874b). CD had written to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> discussing the rudimentary males of some barnacles and the diminution of unused organs (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9061.xml">letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 20 September [1873]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1283.xml">Joseph Delboeuf</ref> had applied a mathematical formula to show the relative instance of a variation in a population over time (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9488.xml">Delboeuf 1877</ref>, p. 676).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3457.xml">Joseph John Murphy</ref> restated Delboeuf’s conclusion in the second edition of <hi rend="italic">Habit and intelligence</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10262.xml">Murphy 1879</ref>, pp. 241–2).</note>
        </div>  
      
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>