<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7512">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Julius Sachs<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   24 February 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10603</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7512 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7512.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7512.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 3</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 3</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml">Sachs, Julius von</persName>
                <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>
                <date when="1871-02-24">24 Feb 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for copy of <hi rend="italic">Descent</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Admires natural selection.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi> has attracted attention in Germany, but most botanists are interested in cell development and similar questions.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Climbing plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Descent</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">cell theory, cell behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sexual selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>
                    <date>24 Februar 1871.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Durch die gefällige Zusendung Ihres neuesten, von uns längst erwarteten Werkes “on descent of man” fühle ich mich um so mehr geehrt und zu lebhaftem Dank verbunden, als ich seit langer Zeit zu der grossen Zahl Ihrer Verehrer in Deutschland gehöre;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> auch für mich war, wie für so viele Andere, die Lektüre und das Studium Ihrer Werke der höchste wissenschaftliche Gewinn; denn wenn auch meine Forschungen bisher sich vorwiegend auf die physikalischen und chemischen Vorgänge in der Pflanze bezogen, so habe ich doch immer das lebhafteste Interesse für das grosse Problem der natürlichen Verwandtschaft der Organismen gehegt, ein Problem das durch Ihre Theorie, besonders in der Züchtung der Varietäten durch den Kampf um’s Dasein eine eben so grossartige wie einfache Lösung gefunden hat. Mit besonderem Vergnügen ergreife ich diese Gelegenheit, Ihnen zu sagen, wie ausserordentlich viel ich dem Studium Ihrer Werke verdanke.</p>
<p>Mit Bezug auf eine Bemerkung Ihres werthen Schreibens vom 9<hi rend="superscript">ten</hi> Juli 1870 erlaube ich mir noch zu erwähnen, dass Ihre Untersuchungen on climbing plants bei den deutschen Botanikern die grösste Anerkennung gefunden haben;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> man ist jedoch bei uns gegenwärtig so sehr mit dem Verhältniss der morphologischen Gliederung der Pflanzen zur Zellbildung und ähnlichen entwickelungsgeschichtlichen Aufgaben beschäftigt, dass jene biologischen Studien leider nur nebenbei betrieben werden. Was speciell die Ranken und schlingenden Stengel betrifft, so habe ich diesen seit längerer Zeit meine Aufmerksamkeit zugewendet und hoffe im Lauf der nächsten Jahre Verschiedenes darüber publicieren zu können.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Mit aufrichtigem Dank bin ich Ihr | hochachtungsvoll | ergebenster | Dr. J. Sachs</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>
                    <date>24 February 1871.</date>
                    <salute>Highly honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Having for so long been among the large number of your admirers in Germany, I feel all the more honoured and obliged to you for having so kindly sent me your latest and over here so long awaited work “on the descent of man”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Like so many others I have greatly benefited from the study of your work. For even if my own research to date has been predominantly concerned with the physical and chemical processes in plants, I have always maintained a lively interest in the great problem of the natural relationships among organisms, a problem which through your theory, particularly on the breeding of varieties through the struggle for survival, has found a solution as magnificent as it is simple. It is with particularly great pleasure that I take this opportunity to tell you to what an extraordinary extent I am indebted to your work.</p>
<p>Regarding a remark in your letter of 9 July 1870, I permit myself to mention further that your investigations on climbing plants have met with the greatest appreciation among German botanists;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but over here one is currently so occupied with the relationship of the morphological classification of plants to cytogenesis and similar ontogenetic problems, that these biological studies can unfortunately be carried out only on the side. As far as creepers and vine runners in particular are concerned, I myself directed my attention to them years ago, and I hope to be able to publish a number of things on the topic in the years to come.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>With my sincere gratitude I remain | most respectfully | your most devoted | Dr. J. Sachs.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Sach’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> (Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD’s <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Sachs of 9 July 1870</ref> has not been found, but probably contained his thanks for a copy of Sach’s <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Botanik</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6834.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sachs 1870</ref>). There is an annotated presentation copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6834.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sachs 1870</ref> in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 727). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7272.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 10 July 1870</ref>. Sachs also refers to <hi rend="italic">Climbing plants.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Sachs later published a short note on climbing plants (Sachs 1882); however, his student <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4908.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugo de Vries</ref> published on climbing plants in a series edited by Sachs (Vries 1873a and 1873b).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>