<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9194">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From H. H. Howorth   31 December 1873</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17666</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9194 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9194.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9194.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 278</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 278</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2420.xml">Howorth, H. H.</persName>
                <placeName>Eccles</placeName>
                <date when="1873-12-31">31 Dec 1873</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for subsidence references in response to HHH’s <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> paper ["The distribution of volcanoes", 9 (1874): 141–2].</p>  
<p>Hopes to refer to CD’s having previously suggested the corresponding elevation of continents and sinking of the larger oceans in his next letter to <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> [9 (1874): 201–2]. Occurrence of volcanoes at boundary between rising and sinking lands reconciles his views with CD’s.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">continents</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">oceans</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Nature</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Howorth, H. H. 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">subsidence and elevation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">volcanoes and earthquakes</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Derby House Eccles</placeName>
                    <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>/73.</date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Darwin.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have been away from home for a few days and only received your letter late last night.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>I am writing to thank you very much for the references you have kindly sent me and unless you object I should like in the next letter to Nature to refer to your having previously suggested the corresponding elevation of continents &amp; sinking of the larger oceans.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The most valuable facts about South America which we owe to you I have in great part abstracted and hope to print them in a paper on the Elevation of the Southern Circumpolar region for the Geographical Society<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The conclusion to which I have come that volcanoes are not found in areas of upheaval, may I think be reconciled with your conclusion previously unknown to me that they are absent from areas of subsidence by an alternative which I meant to state if I did not namely that they are found along the boundary lines between rising and sinking land and perhaps are the vent holes along the fissures by which the heat generated by contraction escapes. I was much startled by a paper in the Philosophical Magazine of last year proving that a contraction of the diameter of the sun to the extent of about 172 feet annually would suffice to produce the terrific heat evolved by it.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> To this I shall refer at greater length in Nature. The most curious part of generalization I arrived at if it be proved by subsequent experiments to be right is that the focus of elevation is in the polar regions and gradually diminishes towards the Equator coinciding with the focus of magnetic intensity but I am most unreasonably boring you with my crudities   it is perhaps natural that a young scholar who owes more than he can tell to your writings should presume somewhat upon your forbearance when he is honoured by becoming your correspondent. I was very sorry to hear from Dawkins<ref target="#foot.f5"/> that you were an invalid. I hope that the cheerful weather we have had lately will have reached you &amp; benefited you. Here we live in a kind of Bastion exiled from the centres of science and art, but we have a few good men, some of whom you will know Roscoe Binny<ref target="#foot.f6"/> and others. Binny told me a curious fact yesterday namely that a long time before the trees in Lancashire die, (you are aware that trees are disappearing most rapidly from the South of the County) they become barren. Oaks beeches etc have ceased for many years to bear fruit in places where swine were formerly fattened on acorns &amp; beech must. This has a curious connection surely with the growing barrenness of the New Zealand women on which I have a very interesting government report.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and of a similar barrenness in the Sandwich islands.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> and this seems at issue with the mass of facts that prove that dying trees and sickening animals are most fruitful.</p>
<p>I hope at any time that you will make any use of me you can down here. &amp; that you will not fail to let me know if you should ever come within reach of Manchester.</p>
<p>The only book you refer to that I have not seen is one on the geological formation of small islands, I should feel obliged for its full title &amp; will then get it.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> With all the good wishes of the season and many apologies for trespassing so much on your time | I remain | Yours very respectfully | Henry H. Howorth <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">C Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi>. F.R.S</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter has not been found, but evidently contained references for Howorth on the topic of volcanoes. Howorth had written a letter, ‘The distribution of volcanoes’, that appeared in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 25 December 1873, pp. 141–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In a letter, ‘The shrinking of the Earth and terrestrial magnetism’ (<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 15 January 1874, pp. 201–2), Howorth referred to information received in a letter from CD concerning the absence of volcanoes in areas of subsidence, as well as CD’s conclusion that the great continents were rising while the ocean beds were sinking.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Howorth’s paper, ‘Recent changes in the southern circumpolar region’, appeared in 1874 in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Geographical Society of London</hi> and referred to CD’s discussion in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Journal of researches</hi> 2d ed.</ref> of the evidence for the recent elevation of the coast of parts of South America (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3902.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howorth 1874</ref>, pp. 255–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Howorth may refer to an article, ‘The source of solar heat’, in <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Magazine</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3311.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">M. Hall 1872</ref>), but the author there claimed that a contraction of 129 feet per annum was sufficient to generate the heat produced by the sun.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1262.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Boyd Dawkins</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6648.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Enfield Roscoe</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_451.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward William Binney</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5641.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Dart Fenton</ref> had reported on the state of the aboriginal inhabitants of New Zealand (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2485.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fenton 1859</ref>). CD cited Fenton’s report in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1967.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 184 n. 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The Sandwich Islands are now Hawaii.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Howorth probably refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Corals and coral islands</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1765.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dana 1872</ref>). In an annotation to an earlier letter from Howorth, CD had written ‘Dana’s work’, probably as a reminder to mention the book (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 20, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. H. Howorth, 30 July 1872</ref> and n. 5).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>