<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-13307">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. J. Romanes   31 August 1881</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">15537</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-13307 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13307.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-13307.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="29">29</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">E. D. Romanes 1896, pp. 121–3</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Romanes, E. D. 1896: 121–3</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4071.xml">Romanes, G. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Garvock</placeName>
                <date when="1881-08-31">31 Aug 1881</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Asks CD to contribute to symposium on vivisection to be published in <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth Century</hi> [10: 920–48].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Nineteenth Century</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2020-03-10" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-20" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2020-04-30" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#pswhite">Paul White</name></change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-07-05" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Garvock, Perthshire:</placeName>
                    <date>August 31, 1881.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Mr. Darwin,—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                    
<p>It is not often that I write to dun you, and I am sorry that duty should now impose on me the task of doing so, but I have no alternative, as you shall immediately see.</p>
                    <p>The Physiological Society was formed, as you may remember, for the purpose of obtaining combined action among physiologists on the subject of Vivisection.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> The result in the first instance was to resolve on a tentative policy of silence, with the view of seeing whether the agitation would not burn itself out. It is now thought that this policy has been tried sufficiently long, and that we are losing ground by continuing it. After much deliberation, therefore, the society has resolved to speak out upon the subject, and the ‘Nineteenth Century’ has been involved as the medium of publication. Arrangements have been made with Knowles for a symposium-like series of short essays by all the leaders of biology and medicine in this country—each to write on a branch of the subject chosen by himself or allotted to him by the society.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In this matter of organising the contributions, the society is to be represented by Dr. Pye Smith, who combines science, medicine, and literary culture better than any other member of our body.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>As secretary I am directed to write to all the men whose names are mentioned in a resolution passed by the society in accordance with the report of a committee appointed by the society to consider the subject.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Hence these tears.</p>
<p>Of course, your name in this matter is one of the most important, and as the idea is to get a body of great names, it would be a disappointment of no small magnitude if yours should fail. It does not matter so much that you should write a long dissertation, so long as you allow yourself to stand among this noble army of martyrs. Two or three pages of the ‘Nineteenth Century’ on one, say, of the following topics would be all that we should want:—</p>
<p>‘The limits and safeguards desirable in carrying on scientific experiments on animals.’</p>
<p>‘Mistaken humanity of the agitation: real humanity of vivisection.’</p>
                    <p>‘The Royal Commission and its report.’<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Or any other topic connected with Vivisection on which you may feel the spirit most to move you to write.</p>
<p>Any further information that you may desire I shall be happy to give; but please remember how much your assistance is desired.</p>
<p>This is a very delightful place, though not very conducive to work.</p>
<p>If any of your sons are in Scotland and should care for a few days’ sport with other scientific men on the spree, please tell them that they will find open house and welcome here.</p>
                    <p>The proofs of my book on Animal Intelligence are coming in. I hope your work on Worms will be out in time for me to mention it and its main results.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>Ewart has pitched his zoological laboratory at Oban, so as to be as near this as possible. I shall go down when I can to keep his pot of sea-eggs upon the boil.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I remain, very sincerely and most respectfully yours, | <hi rend="smallCaps">Geo. J. Romanes</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The Physiological Society was founded in March 1876 to influence government on matters of medical science and to address critics of vivisection. Its members included <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1797.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Galton</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Henry Huxley</ref>; CD was an honorary member. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8928.xml">Sharpey-Schafer 1927</ref>, pp. 7–13.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2727.xml">James Thomas Knowles</ref> was the editor of the monthly magazine <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth Century</hi>; he had introduced the ‘symposium’ format to present contrasting viewpoints on a controversial topic (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11292.xml">Cantor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. 2004</ref>, p. 23). </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3889.xml">Philip Henry Pye-Smith</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The society had appointed a committee on 9 July 1881 to consider ‘accusations made against physiologists by anti-vivisection agitators’; at the 5 August 1881 meeting, the society proposed ‘a series of articles in a leading Review explaining the methods and aims of physiological research and the extent to which modern medicine is likely to be benefitted by it’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8928.xml">Sharpey-Schafer 1927</ref>, pp. 60, 62).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">A Royal Commission on vivisection had met from June to December 1875, and had published its report in January 1876; legislation on vivisection was passed in Parliament in August 1876. For details of the legislation and CD’s involvement in the vivisection controversy, see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 23, Appendix VI.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2241.xml"><hi rend="italic">Earthworms</hi></ref> was published on 10 October 1881 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2661.xml">Freeman 1977</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Animal intelligence</hi>, though not published until August 1882, described CD’s book as still ‘in the press’; ‘I shall not forestall any of the facts which it has to state,’ Romanes remarked, ‘nor should I yet like to venture an opinion as to how far these facts, when considered altogether, would justify any inference to a truly mental element as existing in these animals’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6723.xml">G. J. Romanes 1882</ref>, p. 24).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1561.xml">James Cossar Ewart</ref>. ‘Sea-eggs’ probably refers to his work with Romanes on echinoderms (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_11092.xml">G. J. Romanes and Ewart 1881</ref>).</note>
            
            
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>