<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3392">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From William Branwhite Clarke<ref target="#foot.f1"/>   16 January 1862</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16444</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3392 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3392.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3392.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">10pp damaged †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161.2: 172</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 172</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_952.xml">Clarke, W. B. (b)</persName>
                <placeName>Sydney</placeName>
                <date when="1862-01-16">16 Jan 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Answers CD’s questions on Australian flora, bees, geology.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Australia</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>St Leonards.</placeName>
                    <date>16 Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 1862.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I was extremely gr〈at〉ified by your letter of Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, this day received.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>It will give me great pleasure, if I be enabled to gratify any of your wishes, when the season comes for experiment.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I do not profess to be a <hi rend="underline">Botanist</hi>; but it is impossible to be uninterested in the subject of Botany, especially as one is requested to dabble in the matter in connection with the f〈ossi〉l beds of Antiquity.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>The Goodeniaceæ do not blossom here now. When the season arrives we will put some under a net as you propose: I am prepared to admit that insects do to some extent assist and hinder the work 〈of〉 propagation. I have never seen a blossom on our Gum Trees without finding ants and beetles in abundance,—even at the very top most branch.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I dare say, if one had time, the facts could be made out satisfactorily as to what plants certain insects attach themselves.</p>
<p>In this country the ants are the natural scavengers— they clear away whole trees—and convert the very hearts of our forest monsters in〈to〉 <hi rend="underline">papier maché</hi>—</p>
<p>Flies too do an immense amount of labour in one way or another. When I was in camp on the flanks of the Alps in 1851–2 I was so tormented with them, that I watched their ways.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I found that they became active about 4 AM. and came in to my tent—so I used to get up at 3 and circumvent them—else I could not have dressed, eaten or shaved in peace.</p>
<p>Crowds of them got 〈    〉 the top of the tent, and we beat them down at night-fall with green branches, making great slaughter. But to solve the mystery as to the morning visiting, I went out one night with a fire stick, and found by its light every blade of grass laden with them all over the space I traversed. What do they and the so-called Mosquitos live on—where no animals are found? Clearly on moisture, dew &amp;c and doubtless on honey—and if so they probably impregnate flowers. There are certain flowers in the bush, which contain a thin sweet juice, which I often sucked in 〈m〉y walks in a hot day—but I have always had to bite off the end of the flower to prevent the swallowing of the <hi rend="underline">ants</hi>.</p>
<p>As to Bees, I will mention only one incident.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Some years ago (1844 or 5) I had charge of the country from Paramatta to and beyond the Hawkesbury.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I formed acquaintance with the aboriginals. In one tribe (of which none now exist) was a man called “Captain” who used to get me native honey from <hi rend="italic">[</hi>Ourinbah<hi rend="italic">]</hi> and Doural. One day I found him cutting out a large establishment from the top of a very lofty Eucalyptus: and I asked him to bring it to Paramatta to my Cottage, which he did. The hollow in the bough was filled with the harmless native bees and their honey. It lay in the yard for two or three days, till it was discovered by English bees belonging to my friend D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Stuart, who lived in another part some distance off.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> In the course of a day or two these foragers killed off nearly all the little native bees and stole their honey. This I can vouch for. Yet I once saw a native hive under the same shed with English bees at the Vineyard, now “Subiaco” M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hannibal M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Arthur’s residence on the Paramatta River.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> The English bees are very common in the bush. They make their hives in hollows in the lofty Gum trees. But the native bee is very rare now where it was once common.— I wish M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macleay would give the world the benefit of his researches into our insect world.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>If I find any thing published on the subject mentioned in your P.S. “effect of introduced on native animal”, I will let you know.—<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>You will receive a pamphlet by this mail on the Geol<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> of Australasia; and I hope you will not be offended with the mention of your notice of N.Z. &amp; Oceania.<ref target="#foot.f13"/></p>
<p>I have always considered N. Zealand, N. Caledonia, &amp;c as merely the summits of the ranges parallel with our Australian “Cordillera”. There are soundings between this and N.Z.—<ref target="#foot.f14"/> There is mention of the reduced state of both countries in the pamphlet that also contains a notice of supposed Glacial action in N.Z. (p 54 to 7)   It brings in your doctrine of ‘submergence’ exemplified by the Reefs.—<ref target="#foot.f15"/> <hi rend="underline">My paper brings up all</hi> that is <hi rend="underline">known of Australasian Geology up to 31 De</hi> <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1861. and gives what is necessary to simplify the nature of my difference with M’Coy.<ref target="#foot.f16"/></p>
<p>Will you give me <hi rend="underline">your</hi> opinion of the deductions from his paper on the <hi rend="underline">Wollumbilla fossils</hi>. (p 48 No 5)<ref target="#foot.f17"/> and my <hi rend="underline">Section from</hi> Stony Ck (p 53– to 6)</p>
<p>The once <hi rend="underline">penal</hi> <hi rend="underline">Norfolk</hi> I<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> is the island on which the greenstone boulders repose. There is basalt in Howe’s Island. But I think no greenstone nearer than Tasmania or New Holland or New Zealand.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> What should prevent ice floes or icebergs in that region if the glacial period be no fiction. Are <hi rend="underline">scratches</hi> necessary? Are blocks <hi rend="underline">dropped</hi> from icebergs necessarily <hi rend="underline">scratched</hi>? Glaciers blocks would be—but ? of others. In my pamphlet I have inserted a paper on the recent journeys across this Continent. In p 60 last paragraph but two and last sentence, I define a strait. The younger Gregory boy just returned <hi rend="underline">from the point I marked</hi> finding the same desert sands A. C. G. found on Sturt’s Ck!<ref target="#foot.f19"/></p>
<p>Pardon this garrulity and allow me to remain, My dear Sir, Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. very truly | W B Clarke</p>
<p>P.S. One of the local School-masters in this one of my 5 Parishes, is a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hussey who says he is known to you. He is a great fisherman and tells me wondrous things of his catchings. Can you tell me of <hi rend="underline">him</hi>? He has been in Africa.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/> <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">C Darwin E<hi rend="superscript">sq</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of last page</hi>: ‘16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Jan. 1862— Rev. W. B. Clarke <hi rend="italic">of St Leonards</hi> | Sydney. Australia’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">This letter was apparently sent under the same cover as a postscript dated 21 January 1862. Since the postscript occupies an additional sheet and contains a separate greeting and valediction, it has been treated as a separate letter and appears in its proper chronological position (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3401.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. B. Clarke, 21 January 1862</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-3298.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to W. B. Clarke, 25 October [1861]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had asked Clarke to try an experiment that would indicate the extent to which species of Goodeniaceae, <hi rend="italic">Eucalyptus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Mimosa</hi> required the agency of insects in order to set seed (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3298.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Clarke, 25 October [1861]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Clarke carried out extensive research to determine the age of the coal formations in Australia (see n. 16, below), which necessitated the collection and examination of the fossil plants contained within them (see Clarke 1861a).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD recorded Clarke’s observation in a note that is now preserved in DAR 49: 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Clarke refers to the area known as the ‘Australian Alps’ which he visited during his government-sponsored survey of potential gold-bearing localities in the southern highlands of New South Wales, made between September 1851 and June 1852 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jervis [1945]</ref>, pp. 52–69).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD had asked about the effect of introduced hive-bees on native bee populations in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3298.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Clarke, 25 October [1861]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Clarke was offered charge of the new parish of North Parramatta in August 1840; he resided there for five years (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jervis [1945]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Dr Stuart has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The Vineyard, Parramatta, had been the home of the farmer and politician, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3087.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hannibal Hawkins Macarthur</ref>, who died in 1861 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Aust. dict. biog.</hi></ref>). (CD had visited Macarthur while in Australia during the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> voyage (R. D. Keynes ed. 1988, p. 405).)</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The retired diplomat and distinguished zoologist, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3118.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Sharp Macleay</ref>, had devoted much of his time since emigrating to Sydney in 1839 to amassing a large collection of Australian insects.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3298.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Clarke, 25 October [1861]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">In Clarke 1861b, p. 6, Clarke quoted what he believed to be an erroneous statement by CD that ‘not one oceanic island is as yet known to afford even a remnant of any palæozoic or secondary formation’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 308). Clarke pointed out that there was distinct evidence of Palaeozoic and Secondary formations in New Zealand and that CD himself had written of New Zealand as an oceanic island (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 390). Clarke had previously informed CD of this discrepancy (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3222.xml" resp="#automat">letter from W. B. Clarke, [August 1861]</ref>). The fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> introduced New Zealand as an exception to the general rule (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 372–3). There is a lightly annotated presentation copy of Clarke 1861b in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. The pamphlet was presumably posted so as to leave Australia on the same ship as this letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3298.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to W. B. Clarke, 25 October [1861]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9), CD stated that, in his mind, he had ‘excluded N. Zealand from the term oceanic Isl<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>, as being connected by a Bank’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Clarke refers to CD’s theory that coral reefs and atolls originated as fringeing reefs adjacent to or surrounding land that subsequently subsided, the reef continuing to grow upwards, with the living coral maintaining its position near the surface of the water (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">Clarke and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3261.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Frederick McCoy</ref> were engaged in a long-standing dispute about the age of the coal-fields of New South Wales following McCoy’s description of fossil specimens sent back to England by Clarke (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5069.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McCoy 1847</ref>). McCoy considered the coal deposits to belong to the Oolitic age while Clarke maintained that the deposits were Palaeozoic (Clarke 1861b, pp. 10, 17–48).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Clarke refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McCoy 1861</ref>, which he reproduced in its entirety in Clarke 1861b, pp. 48–52.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 373, CD, without giving details, referred to evidence of glacial action in south-eastern Australia. In response, Clarke provided CD with examples of such evidence including the existence of transported blocks of greenstone on Norfolk Island (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3222.xml" resp="#automat">letter from W. B. Clarke, [August 1861]</ref>). In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3298.xml" resp="#automat" cert="medium">letter to Clarke of 25 October [1861]</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9), CD had asked for further details of the boulders in order to verify that they were erratics.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">Clarke refers to the explorer <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1972.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Augustus Charles Gregory</ref> and his younger brother <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1973.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Thomas Gregory</ref>. In his paper, Clarke stated that if there had once been a strait running from south to north across Australia, it would probably have been between the Great Australian Bight (on the south coast) and the area of the north-west coast between Point Larry and Cape Joubert now known as Eighty Mile Beach. He asserted: ‘The sandy region found by Mr. A. C. Gregory, on Sturt’s Creek, is on the north-east side of such a strait, the southern boundary being probably, about 500 miles to the south-west of it’ (Clarke 1861b, p. 60). F. T. Gregory had just returned from an expedition to the north-west coast, where he had discovered, in the region identified by Clarke, the south-western edge of a desert plain, consisting of red drift sand, now known as the Great Sandy Desert (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3121.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">F. T. Gregory 1862</ref> and J. Bartholomew [1864?]).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Mr Hussey has not been identified.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>