<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4073">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From John Scott   [1–11] April [1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14744</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4073 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4073.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4073.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="endorsement" subtype="letter">April 1863</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">14pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 108: 183, DAR 177: 86 (fragile)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 86 (fragile),</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>108: 183</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">Scott, John</persName>
                <placeName>Botanic Gardens, Edinburgh</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1863-04-01" notAfter="1863-04-11">[1–11] Apr [1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Studying self-sterility, particularly in <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi>, where abortion occurs consistently but stigma functions normally. His hybrid orchid crosses show sterility occurs capriciously. Thus it is not a "special endowment".</p> 
            <p>Disputes Asa Gray’s and Hermann Crüger’s view of rostellar germination.</p> 
<p>Doubts absolute sterility of <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Disappointed by results with homomorphic cowslips.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Catasetum</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">cowslips</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oncidium</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4503">Cruger, Hermann</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_1957">Gray, Asa</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">abortion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">crossing</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertility and/or sterility</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">structural characters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name sameAs="#automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Botanic Gardens</placeName>
                    <date>April</date>
                    <salute>Sir.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You have correctly comprehended, what I imperfectly attempted to lay before you in my last: respecting the sterility of individual plants with own-pollen;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> though, both pollen, and stigma were found perfectly capable of performing their functions, when treat reciprocally with another species. I have not as yet succeeded in proving it with different individuals of a species. I have a case or two 〈<hi rend="underline">four lines excised</hi>〉 your cases in point of Passifloras;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but, I am looking forward for some interesting results from the experiments I will try this season. However I will give you illustrations of the above from my experiments on Orchids. I have made many experiments on our plants of <hi rend="underline">Oncidium sphacelatum</hi> with own-pollen; but, in no case have I succeeded in fertilising a single capsule.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> On one plant, I fertilised a hundred flowers and upwards, but every capsule aborted. I examined a number of these flowers, as they dropped off, and found in the style of each an <hi rend="underline">abundance</hi> of <hi rend="underline">pollen-tubes</hi>, which in most cases, I traced into the <hi rend="underline">ovary</hi>. Thus the stigmatic function &amp;c is perfect, abortion, apparently caused, by some inappreciable change, in sexual elements, preventing normal conjunction.</p>
<p>By applying the pollen of this species to <hi rend="underline">Oncidium</hi> <hi rend="underline">ornithorynchum</hi> I have got a nice plump capsule, though before I had <hi rend="underline">never</hi> succeeded in fertilizing the latter; with ‘<hi rend="underline">own-pollen</hi>’.— I have now a single capsule thus produced. My experiments with pollen from <hi rend="underline">O.</hi> <hi rend="underline">ornithorynchum</hi> or <hi rend="underline">sphacelatum</hi> were <hi rend="underline">ultimately</hi> unsuccessful; though <hi rend="underline">indications</hi> were given, of the capsules thus treat <hi rend="underline">swelling</hi>, which I <hi rend="underline">never</hi> observed or very <hi rend="underline">slightly</hi> with ‘<hi rend="underline">own</hi> <hi rend="underline">pollen</hi>’. I then tried pollen from O. <hi rend="underline">div</hi>〈<hi rend="underline">aricatum</hi>〉, from which <hi rend="doubleUnderline">four capsules</hi> are maturing. 〈<hi rend="underline">two words excised</hi>〉 from <hi rend="underline">this</hi> plant—<hi rend="doubleUnderline">sphacelatum</hi>—applied to 〈<hi rend="underline">one line excised</hi>〉 effective 〈<hi rend="underline">four lines excised</hi>〉 these.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> There is something, 〈<hi rend="underline">six words excised</hi>〉 <hi rend="underline">O. divaricatum</hi>, at least with the plants in the Gardens here.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I know nothing of it in other places. My experiments upon individuals growing in baskets with ‘<hi rend="underline">own-pollen</hi>’ have been numerous, yet all without <hi rend="underline">exception</hi> unsuccessful; the ovary scarcely ever give the <hi rend="underline">slightest indications</hi> of being affected by the pollen. I have, however, succeeded, in <hi rend="underline">fertilising four flowers</hi> with ‘<hi rend="underline">own-pollen</hi>’, upon a plant growing in a <hi rend="underline">pot</hi>— In the latter state the plants are keeped much damper, and the roots less exposed, which <hi rend="underline">may have</hi> some influence, especially in houses like those here in which a mixed collection of plants are grown. However, these capsules, are most <hi rend="underline">abnormal</hi> looking productions, which I scarcely expect to contain a <hi rend="underline">single seed</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Though I have not in the above experiments succeeded in reciprocally crossing any two species, I have, nevertheless, I think satisfactorily shown an individual impotence of organs, capable of elimination by the action of other species. And this in a most complex and capricious manner, which might I think with illustrations you have already given, well convince your many caterers, that sterility is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">not</hi> a special endowment.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> I have yet another case; and <hi rend="doubleUnderline">this</hi> of <hi rend="underline">reciprocal action</hi>, with the <hi rend="underline">Maxillarias</hi>, <hi rend="underline">atro-rubens</hi> and <hi rend="underline">squallens</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> I have made <hi rend="italic">[</hi>many<hi rend="italic">]</hi> <hi rend="underline">fruitless</hi> attempts to fertilise the former 〈with〉 ‘own-pollen’   I accordingly tried it with pollen from 〈the l〉atter; which has proved effective, as I have now 〈several〉 capsules maturing on <hi rend="underline">M. atro-rubens</hi>, thus ferti〈lised.〉 Again, the functional efficiency of the latters pollen 〈I〉 have also proved by applying it to flowers of <hi rend="underline">M. squallens</hi>, on which I have produced a capsule. I may state that <hi rend="underline">M. squallens</hi>, produces capsules freely when fertilised with ‘<hi rend="underline">own</hi> <hi rend="underline">pollen</hi>’.</p>
<p>I have thus imperfectly given you all the information my experiments have yet afforded me on the above subject. The use to be made of it, I beg to leave entirely to you, and I shall certainly be highly gratified if it merits your recording.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>In respect to fertilising ovules by application of pollen to rostellum, permit me to make a few remarks. In my last I mentioned <hi rend="underline">certain genera</hi> of Orchids, whose rostellum <hi rend="underline">still</hi> exercised stigmatic function, as evidenced by inducing pollen-grains to emit tubes.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> In making this statement, I did not at all <hi rend="underline">intend</hi> its general application: it had reference to those genera mentioned,—<hi rend="underline">only</hi>—in which I had <hi rend="underline">never</hi> observed the pollen tubes produced <hi rend="underline">in</hi> <hi rend="underline">situ</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Your observations have long since convinced me that the power of inducing germination of the pollen-grains, is not a peculiar prerogative of the stigma. Nevertheless, this power of dependent germination is not at all a common pheno〈menon as〉 far as yet known, I think you will readily a〈llow〉, the great majority of plants have been found 〈to prod〉uce pollen-tubes only, when their pollen is in contact 〈w〉ith stigma or its secretions. It was therefore 〈on this〉 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">consideration</hi> that I mentioned the <hi rend="underline">above statement</hi>. It is somewhat astonishing to see how much the degree of excitability of pollen-grains varies in species of a genus or even in individuals of the former. I am somehow inclined, however, to suppose that careful research and experiments will show that this difference in the degree of excitability is more <hi rend="doubleUnderline">apparent</hi> than <hi rend="doubleUnderline">real</hi>.</p>
<p>In respect to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gray’s observation, permit me to ask a single question.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Am I right in supposing that he found the tubes in the soft moist tip of rostellum <hi rend="underline">alone</hi>? or has he in reality traced them downwards? In his remarks, he speaks of the grains falling upon the naked cellular <hi rend="doubleUnderline">tip</hi> of the narrow process of rostellum, and upon the cellular sumit the process outside of each disc, and sending <hi rend="underline">tubes</hi> down freely into their <hi rend="doubleUnderline">substance,</hi> I am somehow, inclined to think that the term “<hi rend="underline">substance</hi>” has here a special reference to that portion of the rostellum mentioned—its cellular tip—though certainly it may possibly be intended to include the entire organ. As far as my observations go, the rostellum seems absolutely impervious by pollen-tubes; and certainly one might have expected to have seen, at least some, of the pollen-tubes protruding from pollen grains in contact with rostellum—mentioned in former letter<ref target="#foot.f14"/>—penetrating the latter, if it had been possible, instead of being immediately deflected, and extending themselves upon its surface. I am now, indeed, 〈more than〉 ever inclined 〈to a〉ccept your f〈irst su〉ggestion on the absence of stigmatic utriculi— on a〈  〉 〈    〉 tissue, which of course includes the former—probably preventing fertilisation.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> Indeed if it proves otherwise it will be a fatal blow to our attempts at discovering physiological changes in the structure of the styles of sterile hybrids, or at least of giving <hi rend="underline">such</hi> if discovered a <hi rend="underline">causal signification</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> But, independent of the above there are other difficulties, of an almost insuperable nature to contend with: for example, how is the <hi rend="underline">Catasetum</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Acropera</hi> cases to be reconciled with the preceeding view. You have shown that the structure of the female organs in the <hi rend="underline">former</hi> is <hi rend="underline">much less abnormal</hi> than in the <hi rend="underline">latter</hi>; nevertheless, consider the different results of experiments on their fertilisation.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> And even supposing, that Catasetum should ultimately yield a capsule to some assiduous &amp; skilful operator, we will still have the anomalous <hi rend="underline">Acropera</hi>! I candidly admit, that my experiments on the latter genus and Gongora—I have yet to state those on the latter, which are curious, I will do so in an early letter—lead me to doubt, (though perhaps, I may happily be wrong) the <hi rend="underline">absolute</hi> sterility of <hi rend="underline">Catasetum.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f18"/> Dr. Hooker’s experiments also as you will remember, in fertilising ovules of <hi rend="underline">Mecon</hi>〈<hi rend="underline">opsis</hi> by〉 direct application of the pollen, and thus entirely dispensing 〈with〉 stigma &amp; style, present a grave difficulty.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> 〈<hi rend="underline">five words missing</hi>〉, such 〈<hi rend="underline">three words missing</hi>〉 rapid extension of the tubes, as well as their passi〈n〉g through matter of a denser consistency will I am incline〈d to〉 think prevent any osmotic action between them and stigmatic utriculi. But I need not further particularize, as all are familiar to you, and I mention them merely as difficulties which I have felt in the following out of your suggestions. I will be glad, if time and health permit you, to hear whether or not, they are really such.</p>
<p>Since I last wrote you I have made an interesting and very opportune observation on <hi rend="underline">Epidendrum cochleatum</hi>, which you may like to hear.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> On a plant of the above I observed a somewhat abnormal looking flower, which was unusually long in expanding: this I found on examination to be due to complete adhesion of the outer segments of the perianth, which were much shorter than usual. Under the impression that there might possibly be some interesting abnormalities in the interior structure, I at last cut the flower for examination. I was disappointed in this, however, there being simply an abortion or nearly so of the inner circle of the perianth, and the column seemed perfectly normal. There, however appeared to be an unusual amount of viscous matter ab〈ove the〉 stig〈ma〉tic chamber, which covering 〈in〉 part the rostellum, <hi rend="underline">laterally</hi> reached, the sides of an〈thers〉 <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> 〈your〉 〈ob〉servations on <hi rend="underline">Neottia</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Aceras</hi> 〈imme〉diately induced a hope that probably this near approach of stigmatic secretions to the pollen-masses, might have excited the emission of pollen-tubes.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> I accord〈ing〉ly placed sections of the column under the microscope and was much gratified to find that they had protruded; and this not only from below that <hi rend="underline">lateral</hi> <hi rend="underline">portion</hi> of the anther where the stigmatic secretions, all but touched the pollen-masses; but, likewise, from the <hi rend="underline">centre</hi> extending themselves <hi rend="underline">over</hi> the anterior surface of rostellum, downwards into the stigma. Thus the <hi rend="underline">simple rostellum</hi> of Epidendrum has likewise afforded me no illustration of its penetrability by pollen-tubes. If I have an opportunity this season, I will make a few experimental observations on the British Gymnadenia, and see if I can discover anything analogous to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gray’s observation.<ref target="#foot.f22"/></p>
<p>I have seen your letter in Cottage Gardner.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> I thank you most sincerely for the honour you have done me in referring to my observations.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> Permit me to ask a single question or so in reference to Dr Cruger’s observations on the pollen-masses of unopened flowers becoming 〈pu〉lpy, and then emitting their tubes.<ref target="#foot.f25"/> Does he make no mention of the production of <hi rend="underline">fungi</hi> upon this pulpy 〈m〉ass? This I ask in consequence of an ob〈serva〉ti〈on〉 upon polle〈n m〉asses of Blet〈ia〉 〈which〉 assumed a somewhat pulpy form. I placed a little 〈of〉 th〈is〉 under the microscope, and was much pleased to observe, what I <hi rend="doubleUnderline">then</hi> fancied, an abundance of pollen-tubes. Great was my astonishment, however, on a careful examination under a higher power, to find that what I had fancied, pollen-tubes, were in reality the threads of some <hi rend="underline">fungus</hi>. (Possibly—but I know nothing about fungi—a species of Aspergillus.) They protruded from the pulpy mass, in the form of elongated jointless filaments, some of which bore at their extremities processes from which neck-laces of spores originate. But for the <hi rend="underline">latter</hi>, I candidly admit—though perhaps it is a most unpardonable admission—that I should have considered this as illustrative of the emission of tubes from pollen while still <hi rend="underline">in situ</hi>. I have made similar observations on pollen from another flower, but after the most careful scrutiny I failed to observe a single pollen-tube, though I saw an abundance of fertile and sterile threads of a fungus.</p>
<p>Permit me to make a few remarks on Dr Cruger’s suggestion that the emission of pollen-tubes-grains <hi rend="underline">in situ</hi> is due to ants carrying stigmatic secretion to pollen,<ref target="#foot.f26"/> and that of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Anderson’s that flowers of an imperfect character have a great tendency to produce seed-capsules.<ref target="#foot.f27"/> Dr Cruger, may possibly have based his suggestion on the observance of stigmatic secretions in contact with anthers. If it should be 〈an observ〉ation of this nature, my experiments on fertilising the rostellum, incline me to suppose, that he possibly mistakes the <hi rend="underline">effect</hi> for the cause. I have already made—as you may remember—a somewhat similar mistake in Lælia.<ref target="#foot.f28"/> I then stated that two lateral processes were developed by the stigmas which extended themselves upwards to rostellum, and thus connected the pollen-masses applied to that organ with the stigma. These processes are simply the hardened stigmatic secretions. In all my experiments on this point—excepting of course those in which plaister of Paris was applied to the stigma—I in general observed a superabundance of viscous matter exuded by the stigmas. But this I now believe does not take place until at least some of the pollen-tubes have penetrated the stigma: these somehow concentrate, assimilating or organising forces of the flower, and induce an increased activity in the secretion of viscous matter, which in most cases fills the stigmatic cavity, and even in that of Epidendrum, above referred to—reached the anther. Before the penetration of the stigma by the pollen-tubes the secretion of viscous matter is limited, in consequence of the assimilative forces of the flower being directed somewhat equally to its different parts, and we find that this balance is in <hi rend="underline">general</hi> maintained in an unfertilised flower; its various parts decaying together. The penetration of the stigma by pollen-tubes however, turns the balance, the 〈perianth〉al parts quickly fade, and all is directed to the supply of the ovary. The mere circumstance then, of the viscous matter of the stigma reaching the anthers or pollen-masses—does not in my opinion, justify us in regarding it as necessary for the emission of tubes; it must rather in my opinion be regarded as a consequence of the <hi rend="underline">emission</hi> and <hi rend="underline">penetration</hi> of the stigma by pollen-tubes.</p>
<p>In respect to Mr Anderson’s observations, or rather—as I see he limits it to flower wanting a sepal or petal—Dr Cruger’s on unopened flowers so frequently setting fruit.<ref target="#foot.f29"/> The greater <hi rend="doubleUnderline">humidity</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleUnderline">equability</hi> of temperature, consequent on such conditions, is I believe the <hi rend="underline">probable</hi> cause for these abnormally conditioned flowers, so frequently fertilising themselves. A consideration of the extreme delicacy of the pollen-tubes must at once convince us of the greatly increased facility such conditions afford for accomplishing the above phenomenon, than obtained in the normal condition. Indeed; in my opinion, I do not think it improbable that the above phenomenon—the germination of pollen grains <hi rend="underline">in situ</hi>—which in the majority of cases occurs <hi rend="underline">only</hi> in <hi rend="underline">closed</hi> flowers, is a purely accidental occurrence, having <hi rend="underline">no ultimate import</hi> in the economy 〈of〉 the spec〈ies.〉 That in fact the latent vitality of the pollen grains is simply, and necessarily excited by the abnormal conditions of the flower. I certainly admit that those cases of <hi rend="underline">Viola</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Oxalis</hi>, on which the different flowers are produced at distinct periods, renders the above somewhat improbable.<ref target="#foot.f30"/> But are you aware of the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">strict observance</hi> of this law in those cases? do they <hi rend="doubleUnderline">not</hi> also occur <hi rend="doubleUnderline">together</hi> upon the plant? the abnormal, self-fertilising flowers being arrested in their development. I think, but I will study the subject more carefully, that I have observed both flowers together on plants of <hi rend="underline">Oxalis Acetosella</hi> in our hot-houses, in some of which it has become a great pest. In the cases of <hi rend="underline">Impatiens</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Campanula</hi> they seem to occur on plants at the same period and thus I think justify us in regarding the imperfect flowers, as simply due to a casual arrest in the development of the perianth, and having nothing whatever to do with special purposes in the economy of the species. That in fine we have no more <hi rend="underline">right</hi> to look for such <hi rend="underline">ends</hi> in this case—even though the ultimate end of vegetal life is perfectly accomplished—than we have in the case of <hi rend="underline">other</hi> abnormalities in the flower, <hi rend="underline">regularly</hi> reproduced—peloria, for example. I may be quite wrong in this view, nevertheless I cannot but think that we might w〈i〉th <hi rend="doubleUnderline">equal justice</hi> suppose that nature had some <hi rend="underline">ultimate</hi> <hi rend="underline">end</hi> to serve 〈in the〉 <hi rend="underline">latter</hi> as well as the <hi rend="underline">former</hi>. I have ventured these remarks, under the conviction that the inferences 〈as w〉ell as the demands, I have seen founded on this phenomenon, are alike unwarranted. I cannot see for example how it can possibly be maintained, that this continued self-fertilisation exercises no baneful influence on successive progeny. Now, inasmuch, as no single species, I think, can be instanced, as <hi rend="underline">absolutely</hi> dependent on this exclusive mode of self-fertilisation: the “struggle for existence” between the offspring of the perfect and imperfect flowers, must necessarily be brought into action, and thus invalidates the objection, to your views, on the necessity of occasional crosses for the healthy continuation of species.<ref target="#foot.f31"/> But I need not further follow out this subject, I have said sufficient to show you in what light I regard it. And if I am wrong, I have already said more than enough. I may remark that I have commenced experiments to elucidate, if possible the subject in Orchids, by <hi rend="doubleUnderline">cementing</hi> the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">perianth</hi> of <hi rend="doubleUnderline">perfect</hi> flowers shortly before their <hi rend="doubleUnderline">expansion</hi>. I will thus see if I can artificially produce the phenomenon.</p>
<p>The results with homomorphic Cowslips is a little provoking.<ref target="#foot.f32"/> I now think, however, we ought to have anticipated these results, from experiments with such plants, as Cowslips, Primroses &amp; Auricula &amp;c. which present both forms. Inasmuch as the plant from which we save our seed might have heteromorphic parents, and thus would have a greater tendency to produce heteromorphic offspring. An exact experiment, would thus necessarily require a knowledge of a plants lineage for a number of generations. On a consideration of this I think we may look for satisfactory elucidations of this point from those long-cultivated exotic species, that present both forms in their native wilds; but of which <hi rend="underline">one</hi> only has been introduced. These I look forward to with more hope; though certainly in the case of homomorphic crosses with Cowslips &amp;c. we ought to have the majority of offspring presenting parent form.<ref target="#foot.f33"/></p>
<p>But I fear I will long ere this have exhausted your time and patience: Pray excuse me,</p>
<p>And now sincerely trusting that your health is still progressing favourably, I remain | Sir | Yours very respectfully | John Scott</p>
<p>I have just had a letter, in reply to one I sent, from one of the most experienced Auricula growers in Scotland.<ref target="#foot.f34"/> He informs me that as soon as a long-styled plant presents itself it is immediately thrown out. And yet from seed saved from these <hi rend="doubleUnderline">short</hi>-<hi rend="underline">styled</hi> plants, he states that <hi rend="underline">usually</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">one-fourth</hi> are <hi rend="doubleUnderline">long-styled</hi>. They certainly bear a <hi rend="underline">much</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">higher proportion</hi>, than I expected.<ref target="#foot.f35"/> | J. S.</p>
<p>He also informs me that he never observed the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">two forms</hi> produced by <hi rend="underline">one</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">plant</hi></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.8 There is … in a <hi rend="italic">pot</hi>— 2.14] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.3 recording.] <hi rend="italic">before closing square bracket,</hi> <hi rend="italic">brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>5.1 In respect] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket, brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.33 But I need … phenomenon. 10.42] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>11.1 The results … of which <hi rend="italic">one</hi> 11.9] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>11.9 only has been … John Scott 13.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>14.1 I have just … <hi rend="italic">one</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">plant</hi> 15.2] <hi rend="italic">scored brown crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">Sterility of Orchids | </hi> John Scott.— | <hi rend="italic">Orchid Portfolio</hi>— Rostellum’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi>; ‘Crüger’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ‘April. 1863’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date range is established by the relationship between this letter, the letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863] (published in the issue for 31 March 1863), and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4084.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 12 April [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref> and n. 4, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref> and n. 4, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Scott’s experiments in pollinating species of <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi> with their own pollen are discussed in Scott 1863a, pp. 545–7. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his account of these experiments prepared for the Botanical Society of Edinburgh, Scott wrote that he found his most successful crossings to be those in which he pollinated six flowers of <hi rend="italic">Oncidium sphacelatum</hi> with pollen from <hi rend="italic">O. divaricatum</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">cupreum</hi>; four fine capsules resulted. He also tried unsuccessfully to fertilise flowers of <hi rend="italic">O. altissimum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">O. graminifolium</hi> with pollen from <hi rend="italic">O. sphacelatum</hi> (Scott 1863a, pp. 547–8).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Scott was a foreman in the propagating department at the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1994</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">See Scott 1863a, pp. 548–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Scott 1863a, p. 549. Scott discussed the function of sterility and its relation to CD’s theory in Scott 1863a, pp. 543–4. CD discussed his opposition to the notion of sterility being a special endowment in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 260–3. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref> and n. 10, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, Appendix VI.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Scott’s experiments with species of <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria</hi> are described in Scott 1863a, p. 549.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">CD encouraged Scott to publish his results (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4084.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 12 April [1863]</ref>). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 133, CD discussed Scott’s work with <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi>, also stating that ‘Mr. Scott found that <hi rend="italic">Maxillaria atro-rubens</hi> was “totally insusceptible of fertilisation with its own pollen,” but fertilised, and was fertilised by, a widely distinct species, viz. <hi rend="italic">M. squalens</hi>’. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 289.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref>, and letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863] and n. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref> and nn. 7 and 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> had reported that in <hi rend="italic">Gymnadenia tridentata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Platanthera clavellata</hi>, the small green wood orchid) pollen grains could fall onto ‘the naked cellular tip of narrow process of the rostellum’, germinate, and their pollen tubes would penetrate the rostellum (A. Gray 1862a, p. 426). After CD sent Scott a copy of A. Gray 1862a (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4031.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 6 March 1863</ref>), Scott discussed Gray’s statement, noting that in his own experiments he had never observed pollen tubes ‘insinuating themselves into the tissues’ of the rostellum (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">The reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 311 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3921.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 16 January 1863</ref> and n. 6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 260–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">The role of the rostellum, stigma, and style in pollination appeared to be different in <hi rend="italic">Catasetum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Acropera</hi> compared with other orchids (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 203–10, 231–48, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3997.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 18 February [1863]</ref> and nn. 4 and 5). See also letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4258.xml">John Scott</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3934.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 January [1863]</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">20 [February 1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">24 March [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4021.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 3 March 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">Scott apparently refers to his pollination experiments with <hi rend="italic">Gongora truncata</hi>, the difficulty and ultimate success of which he reported in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4087.xml">letter to CD of [after 12] April [1863]</ref>. Scott had previously told CD of his success in pollinating <hi rend="italic">G. atropurpurea</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4021.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 3 March 1863</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19">The reference is to experiments described in J. D. Hooker 1854a. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3904.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 6 January 1863</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">CD compared the stigma and rostellum of <hi rend="italic">Epidendrum cochleatum</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Prosthechea cochleata</hi>, the clamshell orchid) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 310–11, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 249–50; Scott’s specific observations were not mentioned.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 324 n., and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">See n. 13, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">CD’s letter to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi> of [17–24 March 1863] appeared in the issue for 31 March 1863.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24">In his letter to the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi> of [17–24 March 1863], CD referred to Scott as an ‘excellent observer’, and cited his observations of orchid pollen tubes.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">See letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863]. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Crüger, 23 February 1863</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 24 March [1863]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Hermann Crüger, 23 February 1863</ref> and n. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">See letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863], and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_109.xml">James Anderson</ref>’s letter in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture</hi>, 17 March 1863, pp. 206–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3921.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 16 January 1863</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4055.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 21 March [1863]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f29">See letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f30">See letter to <hi rend="italic">Journal of Horticulture and Cottage Gardener</hi>, [17–24 March 1863] and n. 7. CD began experimenting in 1862 with the unopening, ‘imperfect’ flowers of <hi rend="italic">Viola</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oxalis</hi>; these appeared at different times of the year from the larger, opening flowers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3805.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Scott, 12 November [1862]</ref> and n. 5, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3808.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from John Scott, 15 November [1862]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f31">In the last paragraph of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 359, CD argued that nature ‘abhors perpetual self-fertilisation’. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 96–101.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f32">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4060.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter to John Scott of 24 March [1863]</ref>, CD stated that cowslips raised from seed resulting from self-pollination of a short-styled parent yielded both short- and long-styled progeny; CD had expected short-styled seedlings only.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f33">With CD’s encouragement, Scott was already undertaking his own experiments with <hi rend="italic">Primula</hi> species, including cowslips (see Scott 1864a, pp. 106–10).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f34">Scott may refer to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2924.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Lightbody</ref> of Falkirk, who raised numerous varieties of <hi rend="italic">Primula auricula</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1985.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">R. Desmond 1994</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f35">Scott later published his own work with <hi rend="italic">Primula auricula</hi> (see Scott 1864a, pp. 86–97).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>