<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4929A">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Fritz Müller<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   5 November 1865</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">20478</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2002">2002</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4929A by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4929A.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4929A.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="13">13</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc">(German trans)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Möller 1915–21, 2: 76–7.</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Möller, Alfred 1915–21 2: 76–7</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="high">Müller, J. F. T.</persName>
                <placeName>Desterro, Brazil</placeName>
                <date when="1865-11-05">5 Nov 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="high">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks CD for the copy of <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> and papers on <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lythrum</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi> 2: 93–105; 106–31].</p>  
<p>Intends to travel to the River Itajahy and will make observations on climbing plants. Is not sure whether <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia</hi> is a winding plant.</p> 
            <p>CD has changed FM’s whole perception of nature.</p>
            <p>CD has helped him to understand distribution of coastal flora.</p>
            <p>The vegetation on Desterro is changing.</p>
            <p>Louis Agassiz is seeking evidence against transmutation in the distribution of the fish in the Amazon.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fish</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">climbing plants</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchids</term>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">coasts</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Orchids</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_43">Agassiz, J. L. R.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Amazon</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Desterro</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">River Itajahy</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geography</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>5. November 1865.</date>
                    <salute>Verehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ich habe Ihnen zu danken für Ihren freundlichen Brief vom 20. September und auch für Ihr Orchis-Buch und zwei Abhandlungen über Linum und Lythrum, welche ich mit der letzten französischen Post richtig empfing.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich habe diese verschiedenen Abhandlungen mit dem grössten Interesse gelesen. Wie merkwürdig verwickelt sind doch die Geschlechtsverhältnisse bei Lythrum salicaria! Die einzige Pflanze von dieser Familie, welche ich bis jetzt gefunden habe (eine Nesaea, Unter-Gattung Heimia), ist monomorph;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> aber es mögen vielleicht dimorphe Arten unter den verschiedenen Cuphea unserer Flora sein.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Wir sind hier sehr reich an Orchideen, und ich hoffe, ich werde einige von den wunderbar vollkommenen Anpassungen selbst sehen können, welche Sie in Ihrem Buch beschreiben.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Es giebt in den Wäldern des Festlandes viele Kletterpflanzen, welche sogar die riesigsten Stämme besteigen, aber ich kann mich nicht entsinnen, ob windende Formen dabei sind; im nächsten Monat beabsichtige ich eine Reise nach dem Itajahy-Fluss zu machen und bei dieser Gelegenheit werde ich meine Aufmerksamkeit auf diesen Punkt richten.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Bezüglich Dalbergia, von der Sie anführen, dass sie dicke Bäume besteigt, habe ich einigen Zweifel, ob sie ein ächter Winder ist oder nicht vielmehr ein Zweigklimmer wie manche andere Pflanzen desselben Stammes; d. h. ob sie mit Hülfe der schwingenden Bewegung ihrer Schösslinge klettert oder dadurch, dass sie sich nach der Seite krümmt, welche zufällig einen Stamm berührt.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Die letztere Bewegung in Verbindung mit dem Wachsthum des Schösslings nach oben würde bewirken, dass er spiralig aufsteigt, wie ein ächter Winder. Eine von unsern Zweig-klimmenden Dalbergieen, welche ich zuerst ohne Blätter fand und die nun junge Blüthenknospen hat, scheint eine Triptolemaea zu sein, und diese Gattung setzt Endlicher unmittelbar hinter Dalbergia.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Sie fragen, ob nicht Naturgeschichte ausserordentlich anziehend gemacht wird durch solche Ansichten, wie wir beide haben.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Ganz sicherlich! Seitdem ich Ihr Buch über die Entstehung der Arten<ref target="#foot.f10"/> gelesen habe und seitdem ich zu Ihren Ansichten bekehrt worden bin, sind mir viele Thatsachen, auf die ich früher mit Gleichgültigkeit sah, ausserordentlich bemerkenswerth geworden; andere, welche früher reine bedeutungslose Wunderlichkeiten erschienen, haben eine hohe Bedeutung erlangt, und so hat die ganze Natur ihr Angesicht verändert. Ich werde deswegen niemals im Stande sein, meine tiefe Dankbarkeit entsprechend auszudrücken, noch die grosse Verbindlichkeit, die mir Ihnen gegenüber obliegt.</p>
<p>Ich will eine einzige Thatsache anführen, welche mich sehr verwirrte, bis sie mir durch Ihr Buch verständlich wurde. In den Spalten granitischer Felsen an der Ostküste unserer Insel fand ich eine Art von Apium, welche in ihrem allgemeinen Aussehen und noch mehr in ihrem Geruch der wilden Sellerie ausserordentlich ähnelte, wie ich sie in früheren Jahren auf den sumpfigen Wiesen an der Ostseeküste gesammelt habe; dieses Apium war in Gesellschaft von einer Tetragonia, welche gleich schien mit Tetragonia expansa, die in Deutschland unter dem Namen neuseeländischer Spinat kultivirt wird, und an demselben Fleck war die sandige Küste bedeckt von einer Scaevola, welche in unserer Flora, soweit ich weiss, die einzige Gattung ist aus einer fast ganz auf Neuholland<ref target="#foot.f11"/> beschränkten Familie. Jetzt, durch Ihr Buch, verstehe ich, warum Küstengattungen viel leichter einen so weiten Verbreitungsbezirk haben als andere Pflanzen.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>Ich beabsichtige bis 1870 oder 1871 in Desterro zu bleiben und dann nach dem Itajahy-Fluss zurückzukehren, wo ich von 1852–1856 lebte und wo ich eine kleine Kolonie besitze.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Die Landschaft auf unserer Insel ist sehr schön; sogar Reisende, welche die Inseln des Stillen Oceans, Java, u. s. w. besucht hatten, sagten mir, dass unsere Insel einer der schönsten Punkte wäre, welche sie je gesehen hätten. Unglücklicherweise hat die Vegetation jetzt viel von ihrer früheren Grossartigkeit verloren; die Urwälder sind beinah vollständig verschwunden, und viele unserer Hügel sind jetzt fast ausschliesslich bedeckt von niedrigen Büschen einer unansehnlichen Dodonaea.</p>
<p>Herr L. Agassiz erforscht augenblicklich den Amazonenstrom; wie ich aus einem in einer Rioer Zeitung veröffentlichten Briefe entnehme, so hofft er, dass die geographische Verbreitung der Fische in jedem Strom schlagende Gründe gegen die Umwandlungstheorie liefern wird.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> Es scheint mir unmöglich, dass eine einigermassen vollständige Kenntniss von der geographischen Verbreitung der Fische in jenem mächtigen Strom und seinen zahlreichen Zuflüssen in ein paar Jahren erworben werden kann, und ich kann mir nicht denken, dass irgend ein entscheidender Einwand aus einer unvollkommenen Erkenntniss derselben abgeleitet werden kann.</p>
<p>Mit dem Wunsche, dass Ihre Gesundheit recht bald wieder gut werde, bin ich, werther Herr, in der aufrichtigsten Hochachtung | immer treulichst der Ihrige. | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Desterro, Brazil,</placeName>
                    <date>5. November 1865.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have to thank you for your kind letter of 20 September and also for your Orchid book and the two essays on <hi rend="underline">Linum</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Lythrum</hi> that I received in good order by the last French post.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have read these various papers with the greatest interest. How remarkably complicated are the relations of the sexes in Lythrum salicaria! The only plant of that family which I have found up to now (a Nesaea, sub-genus Heimia), is monomorphic;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> but there may perhaps be dimorphic species among the various <hi rend="underline">Cuphea</hi> in our flora.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> We are very rich in orchids here and I hope I will be able to see for myself some of the wonderfully perfect adaptations that you describe in your book.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>In the forests of the mainland here there are many climbing plants that ascend even the thickest trunks but I cannot remember whether there are twining forms among these; next month I plan to make an excursion to the Itajahy River and on this occasion I will direct my attention to that point.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Concerning <hi rend="underline">Dalbergia</hi>, of which you state that it climbs thick trees, I have some doubts whether it is a true twiner or more likely a branch-climber like many other plants of the same family; that is, whether it climbs with the help of the swinging motion of its shoots or by means of bending to the side that by chance touches a trunk.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> This latter movement together with the upward growth of the shoot would cause it to climb spirally like a true twiner. One of our branch-climbing dalbergias, which I found without leaves first and which now has young flower buds, appears to be a <hi rend="underline">Triptolemaea</hi> and this genus Endlicher places immediately after <hi rend="underline">Dalbergia.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>You ask if Natural History is not rendered exceptionally interesting by such views as we both hold.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> To be sure! Ever since I read your book on the origin of species<ref target="#foot.f10"/> and was converted to your views, many facts which I used to view with indifference have become quite remarkable; others which previously seemed meaningless oddities have acquired great significance, and thus the countenance of all Nature has been transformed. I will for that reason never be able to express fully my deep gratitude or the great obligation that I feel towards you.</p>
<p>I will mention just one fact that confused me a lot until it made sense because of your book. In the crevices in the granite rock on the east coast of our island, I found a species of <hi rend="underline">Apium</hi> that in its general appearance and still more in its scent was extraordinarily similar to the wild celery that I collected years ago in the marshy meadows on the Baltic coast; this <hi rend="underline">Apium</hi> was in the company of a <hi rend="underline">Tetragonia</hi> resembling <hi rend="underline">Tetragonia expansa</hi>, which in Germany is cultivated under the name of New Zealand spinach, and at the same spot the sandy coast was covered with a <hi rend="underline">Scaevola</hi>, which, in our flora, as far as I know, is the only genus of a family almost completely restricted to New Holland.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> Now, through your book, I understand why coastal genera are more likely to have a so much wider distribution than other plants.<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>I plan to remain in Desterro until 1870 or 1871 and then to return to the Itajahy River, where I lived from 1852–1856 and where I own a small homestead.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> The landscape of our island is very beautiful; even travellers who have visited the islands of the Pacific, Java, etc. have said to me that our island was one of the most beautiful spots that they have ever seen. Unfortunately the vegetation has now lost much of its former splendor: the virgin forests have almost completely vanished, and many of our hills are now covered almost exclusively by low bushes of an unattractive <hi rend="underline">Dodonaea.</hi></p>
<p>Mr. L. Agassiz is at present researching the Amazon River; as I gather from a letter of his that is published in a Rio newspaper, he hopes that the geographic distribution of fishes in each river will furnish conclusive evidence against the theory of transmutation.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> It seems impossible to me to acquire a fairly complete knowledge of the geographic distribution of fishes in this enormous river and its numerous tributaries in a couple of years, and I cannot imagine that any conclusive objection could be derived from incomplete information about this.</p>
<p>With the wish that your health will soon improve I am, dear Sir with the most sincere respect | Yours very truly | Fritz Müller.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4881A.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Fritz Müller, 12 August 1865</ref>, n. 1. For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in the German ofits printed source, see pp. 294–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4895.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 20 September [1865]</ref>, CD said that he had sent Müller the German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1862), and two papers on dimorphism, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Two forms in species of <hi rend="italic">Linum</hi>’</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7749.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Three forms of <hi rend="italic">Lythrum salicaria</hi>’</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">When CD described <hi rend="italic">Nesaea verticillata</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Decodon verticillatus</hi>, swamp loosestrife) as trimorphic in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 167, he added a note that Müller had observed a homostyled species of the genus in Santa Catarina, Brazil.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2613.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Forms of flowers</hi></ref>, p. 168, CD described three species of <hi rend="italic">Cuphea</hi> (family Lythraceae) as possessing traits of heterostyly, suggesting that they may have reverted from a heterostyled condition. CD’s notes on <hi rend="italic">Cuphea</hi> are in DAR 109: B2. Müller found only homostyled species of <hi rend="italic">Cuphea</hi> in Brazil (see Müller 1868b, p. 113).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Müller published papers on orchids, and is cited extensively in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD had asked Müller for information on twining plants ascending thick trunks in his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4895.xml" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">letter of 20 September [1865]</ref>. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, p. 21, CD had noted that English plants, with the exception of honeysuckle (<hi rend="italic">Lonicera periclymenum</hi>), never twined around trees, while tropical climbers were able to ascend thick trees. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1458.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Climbing plants</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 37 n., CD added Müller’s observations of root-climbers and tendril-bearers ascending thick trees in southern Brazil. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4682.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 26 November [1864]</ref>, and letters from J. D. Hooker, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4684.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">29 November 1864</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4692.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">2 December 1864</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1456.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Climbing plants’</ref>, p. 22, CD had reported that, according to Thomas Thomson and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, some <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia</hi> species ascend thick trees by twining. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 12, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4684.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 29 November 1864</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4697.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 4 December [1864]</ref>. On branch-climbers, see letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3070.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fritz Müller</ref>, [12 and 31 August, and 10 October] and nn. 2, 8, and 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">In <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1508.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stephan Ladislaus Endlicher’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Genera plantarum</hi>, the description of <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia</hi> is immediately followed by that of <hi rend="italic">Trioptolemea</hi>; both are placed in the tribe Dalbergieae (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2352.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Endlicher 1836–42</ref>, pp. 1304–5).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4895.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Fritz Müller, 20 September [1865]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Origin.</hi> The first German edition was published in 1860 (Bronn trans. 1860).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">New Holland was the Dutch name for Australia (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2248.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">EB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 358–65, CD presented evidence suggesting that plants could migrate across large bodies of water by means of seeds or fruit that floated, or had been embedded in drift wood or icebergs, or carried by birds. To test his theory, CD had performed experiments between 1855 and 1856 in which he immersed seeds and fruits in salt water (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 5 and 6); he discussed the theory with Hooker over several years (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4921.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 22 and 28 [October 1865]</ref> and nn. 12–14).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Müller explored the region of the Itajaí Açu River in south-eastern Brazil between 1852 and 1856. In 1854, he acquired a homestead in the German settlement of Itajaí, at the mouth of the river. He began teaching mathematics at a provincial school in Destêrro (Florianópolis) in 1856, but retained his property in Itajaí (Möller ed. 1915–21, 3: 61–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> began his Brazilian expedition, which included a voyage on the Amazon River, in April 1865. While on the steamer travelling from New York to Rio De Janeiro, he delivered a lecture to his students in which he expressed his conviction that the combination of animals in South America would give him the means of showing that the transmutation theory was ‘wholly without foundation in facts’ (J. L. R. Agassiz and Agassiz 1868, p. 33). Agassiz never published a formal description of the expedition’s specimens, or an analysis of their variation or distribution (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1991</ref>, pp. 66–76). His informal comments on the fish of South America are given in J. L. R. Agassiz and Agassiz 1868, pp. 216–27, 237–41, and 377–84.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>