<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10175">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Oswald Heer<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   28 September 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14326</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10175 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10175.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10175.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 132</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 132</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2199.xml">Heer, Oswald</persName>
                <placeName>Zurich</placeName>
                <date when="1875-09-28">28 Sept 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on <hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Describes his own work on fossil flora of Eastern Siberia.</p> 
<p>Discusses genus <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Ginkgo</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Siberia, eastern</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fossils</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">higher groupings (‘family’, ‘class’, ‘order’ etc)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Mein geehrtester Freund!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Verzeihen Sie, dass ich erst so spät Ihnen meinen wärmsten Dank sage für das schöne Buch über die Insektenfressenden Pflanzen, welches Sie mir zu übersenden die Güte hatten.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ich war bei seiner Ankunft sehr beschäftigt u. hatte das Lesen desselben auf die Ferien versparrt, welche ich auf dem Lande zubringen wollte. Die von Ihnen gewonnenen Resultate haben mich aufs lebhafteste interessiert u. die mit bewundernswerther Umsicht u. Ausdauer durchgeführten Beobachtungen machen einen überwältigenden Eindruck. So auffallend es ist, dass dieselben Zellen zersetzende Stoffe ausscheiden u. andere Stickstoffhaltende aufsaugen u. als Nahrung verwenden, dass ohne Nervensubstanz so complicirte Bewegungen ausgeführt werden, so wunderbar, dass ein Minimum von gewissen Stoffen schon solche Bewegungen u. Umbildungen in den Zellen veranlassen kann,—ist diess u. so vieles andere durch Ihre Untersuchungen nachgewiesen. Sie werden aber auch vielen neuen Untersuchungen rufen; die vielen mit klebrigen Drüsenhaaren besetzten Pflanzen müssen auf ihr Verhalten zur Insectenwelt geprüft werden u. auch die Aufsaugung der Nahrung durch die Wurzelfasern wird einer neuen Prüfung unterzogen werden müssen, indem der Ausscheidung der Wurzelzellen wahrscheinlich eine grössere Bedeutung zukommt, als man bis jetzt annimmt. Auch dieses Ihr Werk wird daher wieder nach den verschiedensten Richtungen hin Licht u. Leben bringen!</p>
<p>Ich war in den letzten Monaten mit der Untersuchung der Jura=Flora Ostsibiriens u. des Amurlandes beschäftigt, zu welcher mir die Petersburger Akademie die Materialien geliefert hat.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Es besteht die Flora aus zahlreichen Farn, aus Cycadeen u. Coniferen, unter letztern zeichnen sich die Taxineen durch Ihr zahlreiches Auftreten aus.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Die Gattung <hi rend="underline">Ginkgo</hi> (Salisburia) erscheint in 6 Species, welche nicht nur in vielen, vortrefflich erhaltenen Blättern, sondern z. Th. auch in den männlichen amentis u. Früchten dargestellt werden konnten, dazu kommt eine nahe verwandte, ausgestorbene Gattung, die auch in Blättern, Blüthen u. Früchten erhalten ist.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Es scheint Ginkgo zur Jurazeit das Maximum der Entwicklung erreicht zu haben u. lässt sich von da durch den Wealden, das Urgon, Cenoman u. Miocen bis zur Jetztwelt verfolgen. Ginkgo adiantoides, der im Miocen von Grönland u. Mittel Italien auftritt u. mir neuerdings auch von der Insel Sachalin zugekommen ist, ist kaum mehr von G. biloba L. zu unterscheiden.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Anderseits enthält die raetische Formation mehrere Pflanzenformen, die als Jeanpaulia u. Baiera beschrieben wurden, welche nahe an Ginkgo sich anschliessen u. von den Carbon=Pflanzen stehen offenbar Noeggerathia u. Cordaites mit dieser Gattung naher Beziehung.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Sie aufs freundlichste begrüssend | Ihr hochachtungsvollst ergeben | Oswald Heer</p>
<p><lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Zürich 28 Septemb. 1875.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <salute>My most honoured friend!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Forgive me for taking so long in sending my warmest thanks for the beautiful book on insectivorous plants which you were so kind as to send me.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I was very busy when it reached me &amp; had saved reading it for my holidays, which I intended to spend in the country. Your results have interested me greatly &amp; the admirable circumspection &amp; tenacity with which you carried out your observations made an overwhelming impression on me. How striking it is that the same cells secrete decomposing substances &amp; that others absorb nitrogenous material for their nutrition, that without nerve fibre such complex moves are carried out, how marvellous, that a minimal amount of certain substances can already activate such movements &amp; transformations in the cells,—this &amp; so much more has been shown by your research. Moreover, you will open up many new lines of investigation. All the many plants that are covered with sticky glandular hairs will have to be examined in their relation with insects, &amp; also the absorption of nutritive substances through the root fibres will need re-examining, since the secretions of the root cells very probably have a greater significance than has been hitherto assumed. So this new work of yours will therefore yet again bring light &amp; life in the most diverse ways.</p>
<p>During the past months I was busy investigating the Jurassic flora of East Siberia &amp; the Amur country, for which purpose the Academy of St. Petersburg supplied me with materials.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The flora consists of numerous ferns, Cycadeae &amp; conifers, with Taxineae being prominent among the latter.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The genus <hi rend="underline">Ginkgo</hi> (Salisburia) appears in 6 species, which could be represented not only in many excellently preserved leaves, but partly also in male catkins &amp; in the fruit, in addition, there is a closely related extinct genus that is preserved in leaves, flowers &amp; fruit.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It looks as if Ginkgo had reached the peak of its development in the Jurassic period. From then on it can be traced through the Wealden, the Urgonian, the Cenomanian &amp; the Miocene to the present. Ginkgo adiantoides, which appears in the Miocene of Greenland &amp; central Italy &amp; which recently has been sent to me from the island of Sakhalin, is scarcely any more different from G. biloba L.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> On the other hand the Rhaetian formation contains a number of plant forms that would be described as Jeanpaulia &amp; Baiera, which are closely related to Ginkgo, &amp; among the Carboniferous plants Nœggerathia &amp; Cordaites are obviously closely related to this genus.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>With the warmest greetings | Your most respectfully devoted | Oswald Heer</p>
<p><lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">Zurich 28 Septemb. 1875.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 375–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Heer’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (Appendix IV). The book was published on 2 July 1875 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Heer published his observations in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8915.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1876</ref>. Academy of St Petersburg: the Imperial Academy of Sciences of St Petersburg.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Cycads are now in the family Cycadaceae. In his classification, Heer divided the Coniferae into two sections, Taxineae and Taxoidieae, and placed the genus <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi> in Taxineae. <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi> is now placed within its own class Ginkgoopsida, while the present class Pinopsida (conifers) includes the family Taxaceae (yews).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Salisburia</hi> was an alternative genus name for <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8925.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Smith 1796</ref>), but is now considered to be illegitimate. The extinct genus that Heer identified as closest to <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi> was <hi rend="italic">Baiera</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8915.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1876</ref>, p. 11).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Heer listed <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo adiantoides</hi> of Sakhalin Island, off the east coast of Siberia, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heer 1878</ref>, pp. 21–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Jeanpaulia</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Baiera</hi>.These genera were seen to represent the phylogeny of <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi>, from the earliest <hi rend="italic">Cordaites</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Trichopitys</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Noeggerathia</hi>, then <hi rend="italic">Baiera</hi> and finally <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo</hi>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>