<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7247">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. J. Weir   27 June 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11040</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7247 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7247.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7247.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">incomplete</note>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">22pp inc †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 404</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 82</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 82</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5048.xml">Weir, J. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Blackheath</placeName>
                <date when="1870-06-27">27 June 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>On behaviour of birds when frightened and when threatening.</p> 
<p>Purple <hi rend="italic">Cytisus</hi> grafted onto yellow stock produces some yellow flowers.</p> 
            <p>Mutations in rabbits.</p>
            <p>Cites case of variegated leaf form of one plant apparently spreading to a neighbour.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">rabbits</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Cytisus, purple</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">change</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">grafting</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>6 Haddo Villas | Blackheath, SE</placeName>
                    <date>27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1870</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>How I have longed, during my protracted illness, to reply to your enquiries, but this is the first day I have felt myself able, although still very weak &amp; my nerves in a tremble.<ref target="#foot.f1"/></p>
<p>In some way or other, I poisoned my hand, the disease spread rapidly, assumed a malignant form, &amp; necessitated a series of acutely painful surgical operations.—</p>
<p>The agony endured during ten days night &amp; day was beyond anything I ever felt, but I will not trouble you further with my own complaints, &amp; have only said this much by way of apology for the delay in answering your kind letter.—</p>
<p>I should say as a general rule that birds when <hi rend="underline">frightened</hi> closely adpress their feathers &amp; it is astonishing the apparent reduction in bulk, that fear appears to produce in most species, I have noticed it most in the Melopsittacus undulatus, &amp; in the Quail, the latter when frightened looks about half the size when undisturbed. One of the first things a bird does when recovering from a surprise is to shake out the feathers.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Some finches when angry, erect the feathers all over the body most species however only spread out the wings and tail, among the former, the Canary, Goldfinch &amp; preeminently, the Goldfinch male, make each “dividual” feather “to stand on end like quills upon the fretful porcupine”.</p>
<p>I have a Goldfinch male, often in my dining room, of the most irascible disposition, even if a servant when waiting at table goes too near the cage, he at once appears a ball of erected feathers<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The irascibility of most birds, Robin<ref target="#foot.f4"/> excepted, is greatest during the breeding season, &amp; many then which do not erect the feathers all over the body, erect a ruff of them round the neck, all the buntings &amp; most of the finches do this, the Chaffinch<ref target="#foot.f5"/> at the same time shewing a small concealed crest at the back of the head, a spot in the same place is not concealed in the female, nor in either sex of the Brambling, “Fringilla montifringilla, nearly all when angry rush at each other with open beak &amp; with threatening gestures.</p>
<p>As to birds exhibiting impatient gestures, the only birds I have observed in my aviary, which shew by signs they are hungry are the Siskins,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> these if hungry as soon as they see me cling to the wires of the aviary, it may be observed the species mostly seeks its food clinging like a Tit.—</p>
<p>There is one curious habit of captive Ratels<ref target="#foot.f7"/> which has much interested me, they are in the constant habit of turning summersaults, the head &amp; back being brought with considerable force on to the ground, this appears to me to be the action, which these mellivorus mammals use, to free themselves from the bees, which must attack them in great numbers, when robbing their hives.—</p>
<p>I forgot to observe when speaking of the erection of feathers that the angry robin erects the feathers all over the body, the Whitethroat, C Cinerea,<ref target="#foot.f8"/> also erects them all around the throat.—</p>
<p>I shall be glad to give at all times any further information in my power.—</p>
<p>I take the opportunity now to mention a few other subjects—</p>
<p>The first bears on the Cytisus Adami.—</p>
<p>My Brother has but two kinds of Laburnum viz Cytisus purpureus, very erect, &amp; Cytisus Alpinus? very pendulous, he had several stocks of the latter grafted with the purple one, &amp; this year, the grafts being two years old, I saw in one, fairly above the stock, about four inches, a raceme of purely yellow flowers, with the usual dark markings, and above them a bunch of purely purple flowers, the branches of the graft in no way shewed an intermediate character, but had the usual rigid growth of Purpureus.—<ref target="#foot.f9"/> The second case bears on latent gemmules.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>My Brother keeps a large number of Rabbits at Brenchley, not that he is a “Fancier’ of them, he has had the breed a long time &amp; they are supposed to be pure bred English lop eared.—</p>
<p>Some time since, in a litter, there appeared one with the very thick coat which distinguishes the variety known as the French, the hair was remarkably long &amp; woolly, but the peculiarity was that it was a grey a color Harrison had never seen in the French variety.—</p>
<p>The specimen was a male &amp; he had from 30 to 40 young from it, without one shewing a trace of the long hair of the male parent, but curiously enough this Spring a litter appeared from a doe, not a descendant of the long hair, with 4 young of the long haired variety, and one of the usual smooth haired.—</p>
<p>The four young were all fawn in color.— The third case bears on the question of hereditary mutilations.—</p>
<p>You will recollect 〈<hi rend="underline">two pages missing</hi>〉</p>
<p rend="left">the bones were put by for you, but unfortunately were mislaid &amp; lost.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>The fourth case bears on the question of contagious variegation in plants.—</p>
<p>I have an ivy called the Golden lobe, by Gardeners Hedera helix aurea densa, this has twined into a common Hedera helix<ref target="#foot.f12"/> which from its close habit I call the clinger; now the clinger has caught the yellow mottling from Aurea Densa, &amp; thus a perfectly new variety has been formed, which was much needed as Aurea Densa was rather too arboreal in its growth.—</p>
<p>Had it been a mere sport I should not have attached any importance to it, but the improbability of the sport being like Aurea Densa, with which its roots &amp; branches are so intimately intertwined, is very great unless by infection or rather perhaps contagion.</p>
<p>I enclose a leaf of Aurea Densa, lobed shaped, of the clinger before sporting &amp; afterwards.—</p>
<p>I am surprised I have had strength to write so much, but I am so interested in your subjects &amp; your enquiry was quite a solace during my illness.—</p>
<p>Believe me | Yours very sincerely | J Jenner Weir <lb resp="#mjhawkins"/></p>
<p rend="left">C Darwin Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 How … letter.— 3.3] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 I should say] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.4 One … feathers. 4.5] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.6 Some … tail, 4.7] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.2 erect … do this, 6.3] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.6 “Fringilla … gestures. 6.7] <hi rend="italic">double scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.6 nearly … gestures. 6.7] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.1 As … hives.— 8.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 There … hives.— 8.5] ‘Ratels’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note>10.1 I shall … Adami.— 12.1] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>13.1 My Brother] <hi rend="italic">after opening square brackets blue crayon, pencil</hi></note>
                <note>13.7 The second case] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>13.7 latent gemmules] <hi rend="italic">closing square bracket blue crayon, del blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>14.1 My Brother … eared.— 14.3] ‘<hi rend="italic">Reversion</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">added pencil</hi></note>
                <note>14.1 My Brother] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>14.1 My Brother … variety.— 15.4] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>21.1 I have … growth.— 21.5] ‘(Contagion of Variegation)’ <hi rend="italic">pencil, square brackets in MS</hi></note>
                <note>21.1 I have] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket pencil</hi></note>
                <note>24.1 I am … illness.— 24.2] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘J. Jenner Weir | Expression) | (Erection of feathers)’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For CD’s enquiries, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7231.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. J. Weir, 14 June [1870]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD cited Weir for this information in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 100. <hi rend="italic">Melopsittacus undulatus</hi> is the budgerigar. The quail is <hi rend="italic">Coturnix coturnix.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD cited Weir for the information about angry birds fluffing out their feathers in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 99. Weir quotes from Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> 1: 5. The canary is <hi rend="italic">Serinus canaria</hi>; the goldfinch, known to CD as <hi rend="italic">Carduelis elegans</hi>, is now <hi rend="italic">C. carduelis.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Erithacus rubecula</hi>, the European robin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Fringilla coelebs.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Carduelis spinus</hi>, the Eurasian siskin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Mellivora capensis</hi>, also known as the honey badger.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Weir presumably refers to the European or common whitethroat, <hi rend="italic">Sylvia communis</hi>, formerly <hi rend="italic">Sylvia cinerea</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Curruca cinerea</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Montagu 1831</ref>, p. 538).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Weir’s brother was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5047.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Harrison William Weir</ref>. CD discussed <hi rend="italic">Cytisus adami</hi> in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 387–90 and 2: 364–5. <hi rend="italic">Cytisus adami</hi>, a graft hybrid of the common yellow laburnum <hi rend="italic">C. laburnum</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Laburnum anagyroides</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">C. purpureus</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Chamaecytisus purpureus</hi>, purple broom) is now known as +<hi rend="italic">Laburnocytisus adamii</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_477.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bean 1970–88</ref>, 2: 510–11). <hi rend="italic">C. alpinus </hi>is now <hi rend="italic">Laburnum alpinum</hi>, Scotch laburnum. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4825.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [1 May 1865]</ref> and n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Latent gemmules were a feature of CD’s hypothesis of pangenesis (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 357–404), according to which cells threw off minute granules (gemmules) that circulated freely throughout the system, and had the potential to develop into cells like those from which they were derived (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 374).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">CD evidently tore off the half-sheet describing this case, which has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><hi rend="italic">Hedera helix</hi> is the English ivy.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>