<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6656">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Georg Recht<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   1 March 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10451</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6656 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6656.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6656.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 176: 75</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>176: 75</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3952.xml">Recht, Georg</persName>
                <placeName>Munich</placeName>
                <date when="1869-03-01">1 Mar 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thanks for money, which will enable him to complete publication. Explains principles of his physiological theory.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, miscellaneous</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-05-04" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release by <name sameAs="#mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00289_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00289_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="75:1r" xml:id="i289">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00289.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00289_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00289.dzi" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="75:1v" xml:id="i290">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00290.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00290_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00290.dzi" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="75:2r" xml:id="i291">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00291.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00291_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00291.dzi" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="75:2v" xml:id="i292">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00292.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00292_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00176-000-00292.dzi" width="5992px" height="7903px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>München Schommergasse N. 2/III</placeName>
                    <date>den 1<hi rend="superscript">sten</hi> März 1869</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Euer Wohlgeboren!</seg>
                    <salute>Edler Gönner &amp; Wohlthaeter!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Gestern erhielt ich Ihre Anweisung ausbezahlt, und das erste Geld davon will ich verwenden, Ihnen meinen Dank zu sagen für diese Stütze, die mich auf ein Paar Monate aller Sorgen überhebt, und es mir moeglich macht, meine Schrift weiter zu versenden.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Meinen herzlichen Dank für diese unerwartete Unterstützung. Als kleine Erkenntlichkeit kann ich Ihnen das Ihnen bestimmte Exemplar übersenden.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Ich kann mich vor der Hand nicht weiter über den Inhalt desselben aussprechen, nur wollen Sie mir erlauben, zu bemerken, dass das Princip d’Alembert die Hauptstütze desselben bildet. Dieses Princip heisst: Im Zustande einer jeden Bewegung stehen Kraft &amp; Hindernisse im Gleichgewichte.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>In dieser einfachen form erscheint das erwaehnte Princip als selbstverstaendlich und von keiner weitern Bedeutung, als dass es die nöthigen Gleichungen gibt. Allein bringt man damit in Verbindung, dass die Hindernisse bei einer Bewegung keine rückwirkende, sondern nur eine hemmende Kraft sind, so entsteht dadurch die gleichmässige Bewegung, und ihre Geschwindigkeit als das Maass derselben, während eine rückwirkende Kraft den Zustand der Ruhe erzeugen würde. Bei der gleichmässigen oder gleichförmigen Bewegung ist das Moment der Hindernisse gleich dem Momente der Kraft oder dem Momente der entbundenen Waerme.</p>
<p>Überall in der Natur erblicken wir die gleichmaessige Bewegung unter Einwirkung zweier Kraefte oder zweier Geschwindigkeiten und zwar von den Grundelementen des Weltalls—Raum &amp; Zeit—bis herab zu den Organen der geringsten Thiere. Der Raum ist das ruhige gegebene oder hemmende Element, die Zeit das bewegliche, und so besteht jedes Organ aus zwei solchen Elementen. Jedem beweglichen Knochen z. B. steht ein fester oder hemmender gegenüber. Die Anwendung des d’Alembertischen Principes auf die Natur insbesondere auf die Chemie verspricht meines Erachtens ungeheuere Resultate und macht diese Wiesenschaft dem Calcul zugaenglich. Schon jetzt wollte ich ein grosses Buch schreiben aus lauter Folgerungen beshehend, deren Wahrheit mehr oder weniger durch die Erfahrung bestaetigt sind, und die Wahrheit dieser Folgerungen laesst mich schliessen, dass ich in meiner Schrift die richtigen Principien niedergelegt habe.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Ich bitte um Entschuldigung wegen der belehrend scheinenden Form meines Schreibens, indem ich auf eine andere Gelegenheit warte, um Ihnen meine weitern Resultate mitzutheilen. Nur einen Satz erlauben Sie mir noch; naemlich: Die Haut des Menschen mit ihren spiralfoermig gewundenen Drüsen zerfaellt in innere &amp; aeussere. Die aeussere ernährt den Menschen mit Licht durch die Augen, mit Electricitaet durch die Ohren &amp; mit Waerme durch das Gefühl; die innere durch Geruch &amp; Luft, durch Geschmack und durch Verdauung.</p>
<p>Damit mochte ich aussprechen, dass ich sechs anstatt fünf Sinne am Menschen unterscheide, und dass jeder Sinn ein Ernaehrungsorgan ist.</p>
<p>Mit der herzlichsten Bitte, dass beifolgende Exemplar als ein Zeichen meiner Achthung &amp; Verehrung aufzunehmen, sage ich Ihnen wiederholt meinen Dank.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Euer Wohlgeboren | ergebenster | D Recht</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener><placeName>Munich Schommergasse N. 2/III</placeName>
       <date>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> March 1869</date>
       <seg type="supplemental">Your Honour!</seg>
            <salute>Noble patron &amp; benefactor!</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>Yesterday I received payment of your transfer, and I will employ the first of the money in conveying my thanks to you for your assistance, which will relieve me of all worries for a few months, and which will enable me to continue to send out my work.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> My most cordial thanks for this unexpected support. Now I am able now send you your copy of my pamphlet as a small token of my appreciation.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p> 
       <p>For the time being I cannot say more about its content, but permit  me to remark that d’Alembert’s principle is its main support. This  principle states: in every state of motion, force and resistance are  in balance.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> </p> 
      <p>In this simple form, the aforementioned principle appears to be self-evident and of no further significance beyond supplying necessary equations.  However, understood in conjunction with the idea that in any movement, obstacles are not a reciprocal but merely a constraining force, the result is uniform motion and its speed as a measure of the same, while a reciprocal force would result in a state of rest. In regular or uniform motion the momentum of the resistance is equal to the momentum of force or the momentum of released heat.</p> 
        <p>Everywhere in nature we see uniform motion under the influence of two forces or two velocities, namely from the basic elements of the universe---space &amp; time---right down to the organs of the lowest animals. Space is the given stationary or inhibiting element, time the moving one, and thus every organ is composed of two such elements. Every movable bone, for example, is faced by a stationary or restraining one. The application of the d’Alembertian principle to nature, especially to chemistry, promises, in my opinion, to yield amazing results and makes this science accessible to calculus. Right now I would like to write a large work consisting only of inferences whose truth is more or less confirmed by experiment, and the truth of these inferences allows me to conclude that I have set down the correct principles in my treatise.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p> 
        <p>Please excuse the didactic seeming style of my writing, as I await a later opportunity to communicate further results to you. Allow me to add just one further remark; namely: human skin, with its coiled helical glands, consists of inner and outer layers. The outer layer nourishes man with light through the eyes, with electricity through  the ears and heat through the sense of touch; the inner, through scent &amp; air, through taste and through digestion.</p>  
            <p>By this I want to say that I distinguish between six instead of five senses, and that each sense is a nutritive organ.</p> 
        <p>With the most cordial request to accept the enclosed copy as a token of my      respect &amp; veneration, I thank you again.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
        <p>Your Honour | most devotedly | D Recht</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 103–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6609.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Georg Recht, 9 February 1869</ref>. A payment of £3 to Recht on 13 February 1869 is recorded in CD’s Account Books–banking account (Down House MS).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6609.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Georg Recht, 9 February 1869</ref> and nn. 2 and 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Recht refers to Jean le Rond d’Alembert and to the principle of classical mechanics first elucidated in his <hi rend="italic">Traité de dynamique</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_109.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alembert 1743</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Recht’s proposed larger work was apparently never completed. Recht also refers to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6560.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Recht 1869</ref> (see n. 6, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Recht enclosed a copy of his work on the development of world laws (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6560.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Recht 1869</ref>; see also n. 3, above).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>