<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-377">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury   31 August 1837</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1834</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-377 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-377.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-377.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance"><hi rend="italic">Fossil Mammalia</hi>, pp. ii–iii</bibl>
            <bibl type="printedSource">Fossil Mammalia: ii</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <orgName key="../nameregs/nameregs_7872.xml">Board of the Treasury</orgName>
                <placeName>Treasury Chambers</placeName>
                <date when="1837-08-31">31 Aug 1837</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>The Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury approve CD’s request for £1000 in aid of publication [of <hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi>].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="business" ref="#">Darwin himself, publications</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Zoology</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Darwin himself, personal life</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="italic">Treasury Chambers,</hi></placeName>
                    <date><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 31, 1837.</date>
                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>It having been represented to the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury, from various quarters, that great advantage would be derived to the Science of Natural History, if arrangements could be made for enabling you to publish, in a convenient form, and at a cheap rate, the result of your labours in that branch of science, my Lords will feel themselves justified in giving their sanction to the application of a sum, not exceeding in the whole one thousand pounds, in aid of such a publication; upon the clear and distinct understanding that the Work should be published, and the plates engraved, in such a manner as to be most advantageous to the Public at large, upon a plan of arrangement to be previously submitted to, and sanctioned by the Board, after consultation with those persons, who, from their attainments in this branch of science, are the most capable of advising their Lordships thereupon; and that the payments on account of the said sum of one thousand pounds are to be made to you from time to time, on a certificate that such progress has been made in the engravings, in accordance with the plan previously approved of, as to justify the issue then applied for. My Lords have therefore directed me to communicate to you the views they entertain upon this subject; and to apprize you that they will be prepared to act in conformity with their arrangement, upon learning from you that you are ready to proceed with the Work upon the principles above laid down, and upon receiving from you a statement of the manner in which you think the Work should be published, and the plates engraved, so as most effectually to accomplish the object my Lords have in view, in sanctioning the payment from the Public Funds, in aid of the expenses of the Work in question.</p>
<p>I remain, | Sir, Your Obedient Servant, | A. Y. Spearman.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>
        
    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>