<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10508">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Mary Treat   15 May 1876</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10993</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10508 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10508.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10508.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 178: 179</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>178: 179</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4796.xml">Treat, Mary</persName>
                <placeName>Green Cove Spring, Fla.</placeName>
                <date when="1876-05-15">15 May 1876</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends her article on <hi rend="italic">Utricularia</hi> ["Is the valve of <hi rend="italic">Utricularia</hi> sensitive?", <hi rend="italic">Harper’s New Mon. Mag.</hi> 52 (1875): 382–7].</p>  
<p>Proposes to write on <hi rend="italic">Sarracenia</hi> ["Carnivorous plants of Florida", <hi rend="italic">Harper’s New Mon. Mag.</hi> 53 (1876): 546–8, 710–14].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">carnivorous plants</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Sarracenia</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Utricularia</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Harper’s New Mon. Mag.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Treat, Mary 1876</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Green Cove Spring, Fla.</placeName>
                    <date>May 15, 1876.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. Darwin—</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Your most welcome letter was forwarded me from Vineland.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I am staying here longer than I had anticipated, in order to make good and abundant specimens of the water lily to which I refered in my last letter to you.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> It did not commence blooming until about the first of May. It seems that Audubon found and figured this yellow lily in his book of birds of the South, but Prof Sargent—Director of the Garden at Harvard—tells me that “botanists had generally considered it a poetic fancy of the author, rather than a true delineation of nature”, so it was not mentioned in any of our books of Botany.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> You may imagine how delighted they are at Harvard to get this lily. I shipped them a box of roots some time ago, and now word has come for 500 more roots. Dr. Gray has already sent a plant by mail to Dr. Hooker, and I will be pleased to send him pressed specimens if he would like.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Yes, I received your book on “<hi rend="underline">Insectivorous Plants</hi>”, and thought I had acknowledged its receipt.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I was so fascinated with it that I sat up nearly all night before I could lay it down.</p>
<p>I think I have proven that the valve of <hi rend="underline">Utricularia</hi> is sensitive, I will leave you to judge when you read the article. I have written to the Editor of the Magazine to forward you a copy, and it will probably reach you shortly after this letter.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I saw a large number of mosquito larvae caught in the valve with their heads left sticking out, and I put a great many such specimens in alcohol intending to send them to you, but my departure for Florida was quite unexpected, and I left them behind. If you would like them I will send when I return to Vineland.— The drawing of the mosquito larva (and the way it was caught) was made by Prof. C. V. Riley, from specimens I sent him.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>I have been at work on <hi rend="underline">Sarracenia variolaris</hi>, for some time past; it seems to me to be the most wonderful of all our insectivorous plants. My account of this will also be published in Harper’s Magazine.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>Dr. Gray asked me to publish the Sarracenia article in the <hi rend="underline">American</hi> <hi rend="underline">Naturalist</hi>, and you may wonder at my selecting a literary Magazine rather than a scientific one, but I am wholly dependent upon my own exertions, and must go where they <hi rend="underline">pay best</hi>.</p>
<p>I start for the north tomorrow, it is very warm here—like July and August at the north.</p>
<p>Most sincerely yours, | Mary Treat.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10464.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Mary Treat, 21 April [1876]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Treat had mentioned in her letter of 3 April 1876 that she intended to leave Florida and return to Vineland, New Jersey, on 10 May 1876; she also mentioned having found a new species of water lily that had been overlooked by botanists.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The water lily, thought by Treat to be a distinct species and named <hi rend="italic">Nymphaea lutea</hi> by her, had been depicted by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_187.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John James Audubon</ref> with an American swan in his <hi rend="italic">Birds of America</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_251.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Audubon 1840–4</ref>, 6: 226). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7625.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Sprague Sargent</ref> was director of the Arnold Arboretum at Harvard University.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref> also verified the holotype of <hi rend="italic">Nymphaea lutea</hi> Treat (later found to be the same as <hi rend="italic">N. flava</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">N. mexicana</hi>); it is in the Gray Herbarium at Harvard, and is made up of specimens collected by Treat (<hi rend="italic">Global plants</hi>, plants.jstor.org/stable/10.5555/al.ap.specimen.gh00263250 (accessed 20 April 2015)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10464.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Mary Treat, 21 April [1876]</ref>. Treat’s name is on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 23, Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Treat had sent CD a copy of her article in <hi rend="italic">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</hi> on the sensitivity of the valve in <hi rend="italic">Utricularia</hi> (Treat 1876a), but it had not arrived when CD wrote Treat on 21 April. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7626.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Mills Alden</ref> was the editor of <hi rend="italic">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</hi>; he evidently sent the copy of Treat 1876a that is in DAR 226.2: 160–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4008.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Valentine Riley’s</ref> drawing appeared as figure 8 in Treat 1876a.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Treat’s study of <hi rend="italic">Sarracenia variolaris</hi> (the yellow pitcher-plant, a possible synonym of <hi rend="italic">Sarracenia minor</hi>, the hooded pitcher-plant) was published as the second part of her article ‘Carnivorous plants of Florida’ in the October issue of <hi rend="italic">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</hi> (Treat 1876b, pp. 710–14).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>