<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-10155">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   11 September 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16703</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-10155 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10155.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-10155.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (Italian)</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 89</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 154</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 154</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                <date when="1875-09-11">11 Sept 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for Thomas Belt’s <hi rend="italic">Naturalist in Nicaragua</hi> [1874], which confirms some of his observations,</p>  
<p>and for <hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi>, which he praises.</p> 
            <p>Suggests that a book integrating knowledge of plant–animal interactions be written by a Darwinist.</p>
            <p>Defines biology as the science of external interactions.</p>
            <p>German reception is far more positive than Italian.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Insectivorous plants</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Naturalist in Nicaragua</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Darwinist</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Italy</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Belt, Thomas 1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">food</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">predators</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">scientific fieldwork/fieldtrips</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2019-11-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        <change when="2024-01-11">CUL document images added by <name xml:id="did">Digital Innovation and Development, CUL</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00695_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00695_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
        <surface n="154:1r" xml:id="i695">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00695.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00695_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00695.dzi" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="154:1v" xml:id="i696">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00696.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00696_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00696.dzi" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="154:2r" xml:id="i697">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00697.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00697_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00697.dzi" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="154:2v" xml:id="i698">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00698.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00698_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00162-000-00698.dzi" width="3615px" height="6071px" resp="#did"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                    <date>addì 11. 7bre 1875</date>
                    <salute>Venerato e celeberrimo maestro!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Debbo esternarle la mia profonda gratitudine per la squisita gentilezza, di cui Ella volle far prova verso di me nel mandarmi l’interessante libro di Belt “The naturalist in Nicaragua” e il classico lavoro della S.V. sulle piante insettivore.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Questa bell’opera che è degna di stare a fianco delle antecedenti numerose publicazioni colle quali la S.V. ha saputo rivocare e ricondurre sulla via della verità la Storia naturale, fuorviata da molti pregiudizii scolastici, quantunque da molto tempo fossi persuaso della vera natura e funzione degli organi entomoctoni di dette piante, la lessi con mio grande profitto ed istruzione, ed ebbi occasione di ammirare il talento nella esperimentazione dalla S.V. spiegato in questo lavoro.</p>
<p>Ultimamente spedii alla S.V. una mia breve memoria sui “rapporti tra gl’insetti e i nettarii che nelle piante non servono alla dicogamia”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Ora è stato un grande piacere per me il vedere come Belt, con osservazioni affatto indipendenti dalle mie e fatte in località dall’Italia tanto distante, sia venuto a conclusioni molto analoghe.</p>
<p>Così anche ebbi la soddisfazione di vedere confermata da Belt la mia congettura concernente la fecondazione delle Marcgravie mediate i trochilidi.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>Oramai quella interessante parte della Botanica che studia gli adattamenti di vita esteriore delle piante, ossia i rapporti tra le piante e gli agenti esterni, mediante il vigoroso impulso dato dalla S.V. col mirabile lavoro sulla fecondazione delle Orchidee,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> ha preso un grandioso sviloppo, e domanda urgentemente che uno spirito paziente ed accurato raduni tutte le osservazioni, esperimenti, studii fatti in proposito, e ne formi un trattato completo, il quale riuscirebbe interessante al più alto grado.</p>
<p>A questa parte della Botanica che vanta per genitori la S.V. e C. C. Sprengel, io diedi il nome di <hi rend="underline">biologia</hi>. Forse il nome non è appropriato, ma io non ne trovai nessun altro migliore. Credo per altro, se non sono in errore, che da qualche autore in Inghilterra sia stato accettato il temine “biologia” nello stesso preciso significato di “scienza dei rapporti esterni ossia della vita esteriore.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Godo assai dello sviluppo che la dottrina darwiniana va di giorno in giorno prendendo nella dotta Germania; ma mi rincresce che la stessa cosa non si possa dire per l’Italia.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Troppi interessi contrarii vi sono, ed io, nella mia piccola sfera, ho avuto ed avrò non poche contrarietà a superare. Ma coi principii non si transige.</p>
<p>Mi dichiaro della S. V. | Ossequentissimo discepolo | F. Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                    <date>11. Sept 1875</date>
                    <salute>Venerated and most distinguished master!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I must offer you my profound thanks for the exquisite kindness that you chose to show towards me by sending me the interesting book by Belt, “The naturalist in Nicaragua”, and the classical book by your honour on insectivorous plants.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> This beautiful book deserves its place next to all the numerous other publications with which your honour successfully conducted back to the path towards truth the field of natural history, which had been misguided by so many scholastic prejudices. I have for a long time been convinced of the true nature and function of the insect-killing organs of the plants in question, but even so, I read your book to my great profit and instruction. I also had occasion to admire the talent at experimentation of your honour that has been manifested in this work.</p>
<p>Recently I sent your honour a short essay of mine on “rapporti tra gl’insetti e i nettarii che nelle piante non servono alla dicogamia”.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Now, it has been a great pleasure for me to see how Belt, through observations that are quite independent of mine and that have been carried out in a locality so distant from Italy, should have arrived at very analogous conclusions.</p>
<p>Thus I also had the satisfaction of seeing my conjecture regarding the fertilisation of the Marcgraviae through the Trochilidae confirmed by Belt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>This interesting part of Botany, the study of the adaptations of the external life of plants, that is, of the relations between plants and external agents, has now taken off magnificently, through the vigorous impulse your honour has given it with the marvellous work on the fertilisation of Orchids.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It urgently requires a patient and precise mind to gather all the observations, experiments and research undertaken regarding it, and to produce a complete treatise, which would be of interest in the highest degree.</p>
<p>This part of Botany which boasts your honour and C. C. Sprengel as its founding fathers, I gave the name <hi rend="underline">biology</hi>. Perhaps this name is not appropriate, but I was unable to find a better one. I believe, however, unless I am mistaken, that some author in England has accepted the expression “biology” with precisely the same meaning, “science of the external relations, or of external life”.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I am so very delighted by the progress that the Darwinian doctrine is making day by day among educated circles in Germany, but it pains me that the same can’t be said for Italy.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> There are too many adverse interests, and I, in my tiny province, have had and will continue to have quite a few obstacles to overcome. But to compromise principles won’t do.</p>
<p>I remain your honour’s | Most faithful disciple | F. Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 355–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Delpino refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_383.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Belt</ref> and Belt 1874a. Delpino’s name appears on CD’s presentation list for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4097.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Insectivorous plants</hi></ref> (Appendix IV).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">No article with this exact title (Relations between insects and nectaries that do not serve dichogamy in plants) has been found. A summary of Delpino’s article ‘Rapporti tra insetti e tra nettarii estranunziali in alcuni piante’ (Illegitimate relations between insects and nectaries in some plants appeared in <hi rend="italic">Atti della Società Italiana di Scienze Naturali</hi> in 1875 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8918.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1875</ref>). There is an annotated copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL; CD wrote ‘9 Sept 1875’ on the back.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">See Belt 1874a, pp. 128–30. Delpino’s conjectures on the fertilisation of the Marcgraviaceae were published in Delpino 1869.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The term biology had been in use in English since at least 1799, but was still controversial in some quarters (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4232F.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray to J. D. Hooker, 6 July 1863</ref> and n. 9; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4495.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Herbert Spencer</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Principles of biology</hi> had defined life as the continuous adjustment of internal relations to external relations (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7369.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Spencer 1864–7</ref>, 1: 80). Sprengel was one of the earliest to study the interrelatedness of flowers and insects, and CD studied the morphology of orchids as it related to the insects that aided in their fertilisation.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">On the reception of Darwinism in Germany and Italy, see Corsi and Weindling 1985 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9053.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Brömer 2008</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>