<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-12162">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Ernst Krause<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   16 July 1879</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">5461</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-12162 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12162.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-12162.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 92: B33–4</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>92: B33–B34</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml">Krause, Ernst</persName>
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                <date when="1879-07-16">16 July 1879</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Rejects proposal that CD’s sketch appear as a supplement or appendix to his own. Offers alternative suggestions. Proposes title-page for German edition of <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Erasmus Darwin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-21" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-05-22" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-06-04" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-08-29" status="finalProofreadCompleted"/>
        <change when="2018-08-29" status="copyedited"/>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="translation" status="released">Translation cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00184_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <graphic decls="#preview-tile-zoomed" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00184_files/11/1_1.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        <surface n="B:33r" xml:id="i184">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00184.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00184_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00184.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:33v" xml:id="i185">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00185.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00185_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00185.dzi" width="3725px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:34r" xml:id="i186">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00186.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00186_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00186.dzi" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
        <surface n="B:34v" xml:id="i187">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00187.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00187_files/8/0_0.jpg" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
            <graphic decls="#display" rend="portrait" url="https://images.lib.cam.ac.uk/content/images/MS-DAR-00092-000-00187.dzi" width="3681px" height="6261px"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>den 16.7.79.</date>
                    <salute>Hochverehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>Die Idee, der Sie in Ihrem gütigen Schreiben vom 12 Juli Ausdruck geben, dass es vielleicht das Richtigste wäre, wenn Sie Ihre eigenen Mittheilungen als Supplement oder Nachtrag bezeichnen wollten, ist mir in letzter Zeit öfter gekommen, allein ich habe ihn immer wieder verworfen, und zwar aus folgenden Gründen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>Die deutsche Gewohnheit in solchen Angelegenheiten würde es niemals gestatten, dass Ihr Antheil an dem Buche <hi rend="underline">hinter</hi> den meinigen gestellt würde; er muss nach meinem Gefühle unter allen Umständen das Buch eröffnen. Es würde mir daher als der beste Ausweg erscheinen, wenn Sie denselben weder als Vorwort noch als Nachwort oder Supplement bezeichnen wollten, sondern lieber einen neutralen Titel, wie z.B. “Familien-Nachrichten” oder “Beiträge zur Charakteristik Dr. E. D.’s aus mündlichen Mittheilungen und Familien-Papieren”, oder einen ähnlichen wählen möchten.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>Dagegen würdees vielleicht zweckmässig sein, wenn Sie, sei es nach den ersten einleitenden Sätzen, sei es dort, wo Sie von der Familie auf die Person übergehen, dem Leser rathen wollten, wegen des fragmentarischen und ergänzenden Charakters Ihrer Mittheilungen, lieber erst meine kurze, nach dem schon veröffentlichten Material zusammengefasste Lebens-Skizze zu lesen, damit er wisse, worauf einzelne Ihrer Bemerkungen sich beziehen.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Dadurch würde, wie mir scheint, nach allen Seiten einem unbilligen Tadel hinsichtlich der Anordnung des Stoffes am besten begegnet sein, und ich glaube nicht, dass Sie, diese Bemerkungen vorausgeschickt, etwas zu ändern, oder zu streichen nöthig hätten. Ich habe inzwischen Ihre Mittheilungen wiederholt durchgelesen, finde, dass sie selbst in den einfachsten Brief-Details wohlthuend wirken, und überall Licht auf Personen und Zeitverhältnisse werfen, so dass ich in dem für die Öffentlichkeit bestimmten Drucke ungern irgend etwas davon vermissen und entbehren würde.</p>
                    <p>In meinem Theile fallen von selbst die Nachrichten über die Söhne fort, dagegen möchte ich fast dafür sein, dass die Jugendgeschichte u. der Bericht über die letzten Stunden dort bliebe, damit es eine vollständige kleine Skizze sei, Sie könnten leicht das etwa Irrthümliche darin ändern, wie ich Sie auch bitten möchte, die falschen Angaben über die Priorei gleich in meinem Texte zu verbessern.</p>
                    <p>Es ist ein grosser Vorzug Ihrer Einleitung, dass Sie mit allgemeinen Nachrichten über die Familie beginnen konnten, weil dadurch dem ergänzenden Theil der Character einer Einleitung zurückgegeben wird; auf diese Weise, wird, namentlich bei der Wahl eines neutralen Titels, dem Kritiker jede Gelegenheit entzogen, die Anordnung zu tadeln, besonders wenn noch ein besondres Abtheilungs-Titelblatt den Beginn meines Essaÿs andeutet.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>Auf dem Haupttitel würde es, wie ich glaube, den Absatz sehr erleichtern, wenn dort Ihre Beiträge zu dem Buche als <hi rend="underline">ausführliche</hi> bezeichnet werden könnten. Ich werde mir erlauben, Ihrem Urtheil einen Titel-Entwurf für die deutsche Ausgabe auf der folgenden Seite zu unterbreiten, mit der Bitte, mir freundlichst sagen zu wollen was Ihnen möglicherweise daran nicht gefallen sollte.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p rend="centre">Erasmus Darwin</p>
    <p rend="centre">Der Grossvater Charles Darwin’s</p>
    <p rend="centre">Sein Leben und Wirken</p>
    <p rend="centre">als Arzt, Philosoph und Dichter</p>
    <p rend="centre">Ein Beitrag zur Geschichte der Descendenz-Theorie</p>
    <p rend="centre">von</p>
    <p rend="centre">Dr. Ernst Krause.</p>
    <p rend="centre">Mit einem Lichtdruck-Portrait</p>
    <p rend="centre">und ausführlichen Mittheilungen aus Familien-Papieren,</p>
    <p rend="centre">Briefen und andern bisher unbenützten Quellen</p>
    <p rend="centre">von</p>
    <p rend="centre">Charles Darwin.</p>
    <p rend="centre">Leipzig u.s.w.</p> </figure> 
                    <p>Vielleicht würden Sie es vorziehen, die zweite Zeile zu streichen; der Buchhändler<ref target="#foot.f7"/> würde seinerseits wahrscheinlich für ihre Beibehaltung stimmen. Verzeihen Sie mir, hochverehrter Herr, dass ich mich so unbefangen über alle diese zum Theil delicate Punkte äussere allein ich vertraue darauf, dass Sie meine Absicht, Ihnen einzig Material zur Entscheidung vorzulegen, nicht missverstehen werden, und zeichne</p>
                    <p>Mit den wärmsten und herzlichsten Wünschen für Ihr Befinden | Ihr | treulich ergebenster | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
               
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Berlin N.O. Friedenstrasse 10. II.</placeName>
                    <date>16.7.79.</date>
                    <salute>Highly esteemed Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>The notion which you expressed in your kind letter of 12 July, that it might perhaps be best if you were to call your own communication a supplement or postscript, had occured to me a number of times recently, but I dismissed it every time for the following reasons.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
                    <p>The German custom in such matters would never allow that your part of the book appear <hi rend="underline">after</hi> mine; it must, I feel, at all costs open the book. Therefore it would appear to me that the best option would be if you were to call it not a preface or a postscript or supplement but rather to choose a neutral title, such as e.g. “Family information” or “Contributions to the characterisation of Dr E. D. from oral communications and family papers”, or something similar.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
                    <p>On the other hand it might perhaps be expedient, either following the first introductory sentences or where you proceed from the family to the person, to advise the reader, owing to the fragmentary and supplementary nature of your communication, to read my brief biographical sketch summarising the published sources first, in order to know what your particular remarks relate to.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Thus, it seems to me, any undue criticism on all sides regarding the order of the material would be countered, and I don’t think that, having said this in advance, you would need to change or strike out anything. In the meantime I have read through your communication several times and find that even in the simplest quotation from letters it has an agreeable effect and throws light on persons and the circumstances of the time in all respects, so that I would not like to miss or do without any part of it in the printing for the public.</p>
                    <p>In my section, the information on the sons can simply be left out; on the other hand I almost want to argue that the narration of his adolescence &amp; the report on the last hours should remain, so that it will be a complete little sketch by itself; you could easily alter anything that is erroneous, and I should likewise ask you also to correct directly in my text all errors concerning the priory.</p>
                    <p>It is a great advantage of your introduction that you were able to start at once with general information about the family, for this restores to the supplementary part the character of an introduction; in this manner, particularly through the choice of a neutral title, the critic is deprived of any opportunity of expressing disapproval regarding the order, especially if a separate part title page also indicates the start of my essay.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                    <p>On the title page it would, I think, facilitate sales of the book considerably if your contribution could be described as <hi rend="underline">substantial</hi> there. I venture to present you with a draft title for the German edition for your consideration, with the request that you may kindly tell me what displeases you about it.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
    <p rend="centre">Erasmus Darwin</p>
    <p rend="centre">grandfather of Charles Darwin</p>
    <p rend="centre">his life and work</p>
    <p rend="centre">as a physician, philosopher and poet</p>
    <p rend="centre">A contribution to the history of the theory of descent</p>
    <p rend="centre">by</p>
    <p rend="centre">Dr Ernst Krause.</p>
    <p rend="centre">With a collotype portrait</p>
    <p rend="centre">and extensive communications from his family papers,</p>
    <p rend="centre">letters and other new sources</p>
    <p rend="centre">by</p>
    <p rend="centre">Charles Darwin.</p>
    <p rend="centre">Leipzig etc.</p> </figure> 
                    <p>Perhaps you would prefer it if the second line were removed; the publisher, on his part would however probably vote for it to remain.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Forgive me, most esteemed Sir, for discussing all these partly delicate matters in so uninhibited a manner, but I trust you won’t misinterpret my intention, which is merely to present you with matters for you to decide about, and remain</p>
                    <p>With the warmest and most cordial wishes for your health | Yours | truly devoted | Ernst Krause</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see Transcript.</note> 
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-12150.xml">letter to Ernst Krause, 12 July [1879]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the published version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 2, CD’s essay is titled ‘Preliminary notice’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In a short preface preceding the ‘Preliminary notice’ in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, pp. iii–iv, CD explained that his introduction was based on private materials that added to the knowledge of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin’s</ref> character; he did not recommend that the reader ought to read Krause’s section first. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the published version of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2365.xml"><hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin</hi></ref>, p. 130, Krause’s section is titled ‘The scientific works of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref>’ on a part title page. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The full title page of the German version (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10752.xml">Krause 1880</ref>) reads: ‘<ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1219.xml">Erasmus Darwin</ref> | und seine Stellung | in der Geschichte der Descendenz-Theorie | von <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2758.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ernst Krause</ref>. | Mit seinem Lebens- und Charakterbilde | von <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Darwin</ref>. | Nebst Lichtdruck-Portrait und Holzschnitten.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Krause’s publisher was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_61.xml">Karl Alberts</ref>, the director of Ernst Gunther’s Verlag, Leipzig.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>