<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-9919">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Federico Delpino<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   8 April 1875</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16701</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-9919 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9919.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-9919.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (Italian) †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Pancaldi (1984): 84</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 152</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 152</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml">Delpino, Federico</persName>
                <placeName>Vallombrosa</placeName>
                <date when="1875-04-08">8 Apr 1875</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends last part of his book [<hi rend="italic">Ulteriori observazioni sulla dicogamia</hi> (1868–74)] [osservazioni!?] and describes contents.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Ulteriori observazioni sulla dicogamia</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Delpino, Federico 1868–1874</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">dichogamy, sexual dimorphism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Pontassieve | per | Vallombrosa</placeName>
                    <date>8. Aprile 1875</date>
                    <salute>Celeberrimo uomo!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Mi onoro di spedirle l’ultima parte delle mie osservazioni sulla Dicogamia.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Ella vedrà che quasi ad ogni pagina figura il suo nome; nome che tanta orma ha lasciato in questo genere di ricerche. Nella conclusione del lavoro, a pag. 336, dichiaro la mia piena adesione alla teoria transformista propugnata dal primo naturalista del secolo.</p>
<p>Ho scoperto un singolare fenomeno di dimorfismo in una specie anemofila, nel noce.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Non so se Ella troverà giuste le mie idee sul vero significato funzionale di quest’ordine di fenomeni, e se approverà la proposta nomenclatura.</p>
<p>In questo volume ho cercato di estendere un quadro possibilmente completo degli adattamenti delle piante a pronubi viventi (zoidiofile).<ref target="#foot.f4"/> L’argomento è interessante all’estremo, ma non so se sono riuscito nell’intento. Spero che altri proseguirà e compirà l’opera mia.</p>
<p>Vi sono quà e là delle osservazioni mie inediti. Fra gli apparecchi florali più singolari che ho studiato ultimamente sono quei del <hi rend="underline">Lilium Martagon</hi> e del <hi rend="underline">Lilium croceum</hi>, con bellissimi adattamenti alle sfingi.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>In quanto alla mancanza di nettare nei nettarii del genere Orchis le mie osservazioni coinciderebbero con quelle di Sprengel.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Ho rilevato che Wächter fino dagli ultimi anni del secolo passato aveva argutamente osservato e interpretato il processo d’impollinazione nella <hi rend="underline">Mieottia Nidus avis</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Ho riportato fra gli <hi rend="underline">apparecchi a carcere</hi>, l’apparecchio a bagno involontario segnalato dal Crüger nei Coryanthes.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> La Cephalanthera ensifolia si deporta da noi molto diversamente della C. grandiflora (p. 149)<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Finalmente ho steso i caratteri di 47 tipi florali diversi. Con molta fatica e con non minore convincimento ho elaborato questo lavoro; ma non so se trascinerò la convinzione degli specialisti. Lo spero ad ogni modo, e spero altresì che altri in seguito farà meglio di me.</p>
<p>È da un pezzo che non ho nuove della di Lei preziosa salute. Spero ch’Ella si trovi egregiamente, e che possa fruire ancora per lunghi anni dei segni di reverenza e di rispetto, dovuti a Lei da tutti naturalisti</p>
<p>Pieno di ammirazione e di affetto verso di Lei sono | suo ossequentissimo discepolo | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>
<p><hi rend="italic">End of letter</hi>: ’p118 False nectaries</p>
<p>323 Lilium martagon</p>
<p>211’<ref target="#foot.f10"/> <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></p></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Pontassieve | per | Vallombrosa</placeName>
                    <date>8 April 1875</date>
                    <salute>Most distinguished man!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have the honour of sending you the last part of my observations on Dichogamy.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You will see that your name appears on almost every page, the name that has left such a mark on this kind of research. In the conclusions, on p. 336, I declare my full support for the transformist theory advocated by the foremost naturalist of the century.</p>
<p>I discovered a singular example of dimorphism in an anemophilous species of the walnut.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I do not know whether you will approve my ideas on the true functional significance of this order of phenomena, and whether you will approve of my proposed nomenclature.</p>
<p>In this volume, I tried to provide as complete as possible an outline of the adaptations of plants to living pollinators (zoidiophilous plants).<ref target="#foot.f4"/> The argument is extremely interesting, but I am not sure whether I have achieved my goals. I hope that others will pick up my work and complete it.</p>
<p>There are unpublished observations I made here and there. Among the most unique floral apparatus that I have studied are ultimately those of <hi rend="underline">Lilium Martagon</hi> and of <hi rend="underline">Lilium croceum</hi>, with the most beautiful adaptations to the sphinx-moths.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Regarding the absence of nectar in the nectaries of the genus Orchis my observations coincide with those of Sprengel.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have learnt that Wächter, since the concluding years of the last century, has keenly observed and interpreted the process of pollination in <hi rend="underline">Mieottia Nidus avis</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Among the flowers that are <hi rend="underline">apparatuses of entrapment</hi>, I have reported the apparatus of involuntary bathing, which has been pointed out by Crüger in Coryanthes.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Cephalanthera ensifolia behaves very differently from C. grandiflora (p. 149) over here<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>Finally, I have listed the characteristics of 47 different floral types. It took a lot of work and not a little faith to carry out this labour, and I am not sure whether I have managed to sway expert opinion with it. In any case I do hope so, and I also hope that others later on will improve on my work.</p>
<p>It has been quite some time since I had news about your precious health. I hope you are very well, and that you may be able to enjoy for many years yet the tokens of veneration and respect that all naturalists owe you.</p>
<p>Full of admiration and affection towards you I remain | your most faithful disciple | Federico Delpino</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original Italian, see pp. 131–2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">A heavily annotated copy of both parts of <hi rend="italic">Ulteriori osservazioni sulla dicogamia nel regno vegetale</hi> (Further observations on dichogamy in the vegetable kingdom; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>) is in the Darwin Library–CUL (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 191–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">An appendix on dimorphism in the walnut species <hi rend="italic">Juglans regia</hi> is in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>, 2: 337–42. Anemophilous: wind-pollinated (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1347.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Chambers</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Zoidiophilous: pollinated by the agency of animals (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4109.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Jackson 1900</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><hi rend="italic">Lilium martagon</hi> is the Turk’s cap lily, and <hi rend="italic">Lilium croceum</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Lilium bulbiferum</hi>) is the tiger lily. Delpino may be referring to the phototropic style of the flowers; for details, see Brantjes and Bos 1980.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4503.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Konrad Sprengel</ref> described orchids as ‘<hi rend="italic">Scheinsaftsblumen</hi>’ or false-nectar flowers, because their nectaries contained no fluid (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7390.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sprengel 1793</ref>, p. 403). See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>, p. 150 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7247.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Johann Karl Augustin Wächter</ref> discussed the role of insects in the fertilisation of <hi rend="italic">Ophrys nidus</hi> (Not a valid taxon, but probably intended <hi rend="italic">Ophrys nidus-avis</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Neottia nidus-avis</hi>, bird’s-nest orchid) in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8619.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wächter 1801</ref>, pp. 211–13. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>, p. 150 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Crüger</ref> had noted how the pollen-mass of <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> was secured onto the back of the bee (<hi rend="italic">Euglossa</hi>) as it tried to force its way out through a passage after falling into a ‘bucket’ of nectar; when the bee next fell into the bucket of the same or another flower, the pollen was deposited on the stigma as it tried to leave (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1676.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Crüger 1864</ref>, p. 130). For previous correspondence with Delpino on this subject, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1286.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Federico Delpino</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6928.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">9 October 1869</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6965.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">1 November 1869</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Coryanthes</hi> is the genus of bucket orchids.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>, p. 149 n. <hi rend="italic">Cephalanthera ensifolia</hi> (sword-leaved helleborine) is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">C. longifolia</hi>; the plant is pollinated by solitary bees. <hi rend="italic">Cephalanthera grandiflora</hi> is another synonym of <hi rend="italic">C. longifolia</hi> </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The page references are to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Delpino 1868–75</ref>; for the topics see nn. 6 and 7, above. They may be notes for CD’s reply, which has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>