<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3257">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Henry Fawcett   18 September [1861]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">13330</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1994">1994</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3257 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3257.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3257.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="24">24-Supplement</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="09">9</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp &amp; C 3pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 194;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Stephen (1885): 100</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 9: 269</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Karpeles Manuscript Library Museums</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_208.xml">Karpeles</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>144: 103</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1861-09-18">18 Sept [1861]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1602.xml">Fawcett, Henry</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Comments on MS of HF’s address ["On the method of Mr Darwin in his treatise on the origin of species", <hi rend="italic">Rep. BAAS</hi> (1861) pt 2: 141–3]. "How odd it is that anyone should not see that all observation must be for or against some view if it is to be of any service."</p> 
            <p>Describes his health.</p>
            <p>The response to his views in Germany, Holland, and Russia.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Darwin himself, bad or deteriorating</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Rep. BAAS</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Germany</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Holland</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Russia</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Fawcett, Henry 1861</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-03-13">Links to letter transcriptions added by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Down. | Bromley. | Kent. S.E.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Sept. 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fawcett</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I wondered who had so kindly sent me the newspapers which I was very glad to see;<ref target="#foot.f2"/> &amp; now I have to thank you sincerely for allowing me to see your M.S.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> It seems to me very good &amp; sound; though I am certainly not an impartial judge. You will have done good service in calling the attention of scientific men to the means &amp; laws of philosophising.— As far as I could judge by the papers your opponents were unworthy of you. How miserably Prof Williamson talked of my reputation, as if that had anything to do with it.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> As for D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lankester he is a mean prater who never observed a new fact, I believe, in his life.— It made me laugh to read of his advice or rather regret that I had not published facts alone. How profoundly ignorant he must be of the very soul of observation.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> About 30 years ago there was much talk that Geologists ought only to observe &amp; not theorise;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> &amp; I well remember some one saying, that at this rate a man might as well go into a gravel-pit &amp; count the pebbles &amp; describe their colours. How odd it is that every one should not see that all observation must be for or against some view, if it is to be of any service.—</p>
<p>I have returned only lately from a two months’ visit to Torquay, which did my health at the time good; but I am one of those miserable creatures who are never comfortable for 24 hours; &amp; it is clear to me that I ought to be exterminated. I have been rather idle of late; or speaking more strictly working at some miscellaneous papers, which however have some direct bearing on the subject of species; yet I feel guilty at having neglected my larger Book.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> But to me, observing is much better sport than writing.— I fear that I shall have wearied you with this long note.</p>
<p>Pray believe that I feel sincerely grateful that you have taken up the cudgels in defence of the line of argument in the Origin: you will have benefitted the subject.—</p>
<p>Many are so fearful of speaking out.— A German naturalist came here the other day &amp; he tells me that there are many in Germany on our side; but that all seem fearful of speaking out &amp; waiting for some one to speak &amp; then many will follow.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> The naturalists seem as timid, as young ladies should be, about their scientific reputation.— There is much discussion on the subject on the continent even in quiet Holland;<ref target="#foot.f9"/> &amp; I had a pamphlet from Moscow the other day by a man who sticks up famously on the imperfection of the Geological Record; but complains that I have sadly <hi rend="doubleUnderline">under</hi>rated the variability of the old fossilised animals!<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>But I must not run on; with sincere thanks &amp; respect | Pray believe me | Yours very sincerely | Charles Darwin</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Davidson, who knows some groups of fossils better than any man in Europe, I can see, is coming round by inches, &amp; declares he will well consider &amp; discuss &amp; publish on the relations of the Brachiopods from the earliest dawn of life to the present day on genealogical principles.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> This is the sort of work which will finally settle the fate of the Origin one way or the other.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">4.6 by a man] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘with’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">5.1 run on:] ‘on;’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to the reports printed in the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Examiner</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi> (see n. 2, below). This letter was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9 from the text published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7455.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Stephen 1885</ref>. This transcription, from the original in the Karpeles Manuscript Museum, restores two sentences beginning at ‘As for D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lankester ...’ and the paragraph after the signature. The footnotes have been altered.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The <hi rend="italic">Manchester Examiner</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi> both carried reports on 9 September 1861 of the discussion that followed Fawcett’s address to the British Association for the Advancement of Science. The British Association met in Manchester from 4 to 11 September 1861. There are copies of both reports in DAR 226.1: 92–3.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The title of Fawcett’s paper, as it appeared in the abstract printed in the <hi rend="italic">Report of the 31st meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science</hi>, was ‘On the method of Mr. Darwin in his treatise on the origin of species’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2472.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fawcett 1861</ref>). In the abstract, however, it was reported that Fawcett’s original title was: ‘That the method of investigation pursued by Mr. Darwin, in his Treatise on the Origin of Species, is in strict accordance with the principles of logic.’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The report of the discussion given in the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi>, 9 September 1861, p. 6, cites <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5165.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Crawford Williamson</ref> as saying that ‘while he would not say that Mr. Darwin’s book had caused him a loss of reputation, he was sure that it had not caused a gain.’ Williamson was professor of natural history, anatomy, and physiology at Owens College, Manchester. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ML</hi></ref> 1: 195 n.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">According to the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi>, 9 September 1861, p. 6, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2815.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edwin Lankester</ref> said that the facts brought forward in support of the hypothesis had a very different value indeed from that of the hypothesis. Lankester was professor of natural history at New College, London.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Fawcett had defended CD’s use of hypothesis and induction (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2868.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Henry Fawcett, 16 July [1861]</ref> and nn. 3 and 4). For a discussion of the strictures concerning the use of theory in early Victorian science, see Morrell and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7693.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thackray 1981</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Having published <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> as an abstract of his ‘big book’ on species (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>), CD planned to revise the longer manuscript for publication (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Murray, 22 December [1859]</ref>). In the event, only the first part of the projected work was published, broadly based on the first two chapters of the original manuscript (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The visitor from Germany has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">A Dutch translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5203.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Tiberius Cornelius Winkler</ref> was published in 1860 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3202.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">letter from T. C. Winkler, 7 July 1861)</ref>. For an account of the reception of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in Holland, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1059.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bulhof 1974</ref> and Leeuwenburgh and van der Heide 2008.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The pamphlet, <hi rend="italic">Übergänge und Zwischenvarietäten</hi>, was by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4792.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Adolfovich Trautschold</ref> of the Petrovsky Academy in Moscow (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7800.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Trautschold 1861</ref>). It was a privately printed reprint of a paper originally published in the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin de la Société Imperiale des Naturalistes de Moscou</hi> 33 (1860): 519–30. The annotated copy is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. Trautschold stated that for several years he had been aware of the existence of many varieties and transitional forms in the fossil species in Jurassic formations near Moscow but laid no value on the specimens until he read the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (Bronn trans. 1860). His paper describes a series of what he believed to be transitional varieties and species of ammonites. Beside a list of various transitional varieties on p. 5 (p. 522 in the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>), CD wrote in pencil: ‘All these vars. seem to be found in same middle bed’. But next to a subsequent description of a series of forms transitional between <hi rend="italic">Ammonites biplex</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A. humphriesianus</hi>, CD wrote: ‘But here we have cases of vars. leading to a species in a lower bed.—’</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3131.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Thomas Davidson, 30 April 1861</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3135.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Thomas Davidson, 3 May 1861</ref>. Davidson, an expert on fossil brachiopods, had briefly mentioned CD’s work in an article in the <hi rend="italic">Geologist</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1834.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Davidson 1861</ref>, pp. 58–9). In the next volume of his monograph series (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1833.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Davidson 1851–86</ref>, 2: 212–13, published in 1863), Davidson mentioned the possibility that fossil brachiopods might provide evidence for CD’s view of species and varieties. His work on recent brachiopods was published posthumously (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_9429.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Davidson 1886–8</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>