<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6915">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Alphonse de Candolle<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   28 September 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3946</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6915 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6915.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6915.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 261.11: 32.i (EH 88206083)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>261.11: 32.i (EH 88206083)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_813.xml">Candolle, Alphonse de</persName>
                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
                <date when="1869-09-28">28 Sept 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Reports on the differences of growth and development of plants of three species grown at Geneva from seed collected at different localities. Forwards seed for CD to plant and observe differences in development.</p> 
<p>Carl Linsseer has published a memoir on the times of flowering, foliation, etc. of diverse species in different parts of Europe [<hi rend="italic">Mem. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg</hi> 7th ser. 11 no. 7 (1868)] and concludes that the northern forms are more forward and that this is hereditary. AdeC’s experiments carried out on annuals, show only the effects of heredity; probably the direct action of physical conditions affects development, at least in perennial species.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Mem. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Petersbourg</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Europe</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Geneva</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Linsseer, Carl 1868</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">heredity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">seeds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">time and age (‘organic’ time)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Genève</placeName>
                    <date>28 Sept. 1869.</date>
                    <salute>Mon cher Monsieur</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je vous envoie des graines qui ont un véritable interet au point de vue dont nous nous occupons tous les deux et je viens vous proposer de les semer pour suivre à une expérience commencée et pour la vérifier vous même.</p>
<p>J’ai fait venir en 1868 des graines de quelques espèces <hi rend="underline">spontanées</hi> de quatre localités et même cinq localités, très distantes, en Europe, savoir: <hi rend="underline">Palerme</hi> et <hi rend="underline">Montpellier</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Kharkoff</hi> <ref target="#foot.f2"/> et <hi rend="underline">Moscou</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Edinburgh</hi>; afin de les semer à Genève et de voir si la même espèce etait devenue plus précoce ou plus tardive pour avoir eu des ancêtres exposés pendant des siècles à des climats très-differents.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> J’ai choisi des espèces faciles à reconnaitre et n’offrant pas des variétés bien distinctes. Malheureusement mes correspondants n’ont pas tous recueilli toutes les espèces demandées et il m’a fallu restreindre l’experience à peu d’espèces. Malheureusement aussi le jardinier au quel j’avais cru pouvoir me fier pour certains détails, n’a pas élevé convenablement toutes les plantes semées. Néanmoins il est arrivé dans mes semis de 1869, sur trois espèces, bien comparables, que les <hi rend="underline">Senecio vulgaris</hi> et <hi rend="underline">Sisymbrium officinale</hi> originaires du nord, ont été les plus prompts à se developper et à fleurir. Au contraire dans le <hi rend="underline">Trifolium repens</hi>, les plantes du nord ont été plus lentes, mais elles etaient aussi plus faibles, plus petites dans toutes les parties, et l’on peut dire qu’elles avaient l’apparence d’une variété <hi rend="underline">minor</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>J’ai semé en 1869 à Genève des <hi rend="underline">Senecio vulgaris</hi> des 4 origines, et à cette seconde génération, la précocité des plantes du nord s’est maintenue.</p>
<p>Combien de temps cela durera-t-il? Voila qui n’est pas sans interêt.</p>
<p>La rigueur de notre climât et le peu de serres et jardiniers dont je dispose ne me permettent pas de recommencer un semis dans cette saison. Peut-être seriez vous disposé à le faire chez vous et si vous préferez, vous pouvez vous entendre avec le D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker, par example, pour faire un semis qu’on observerait soigneusement.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Je vous envoie:</p> 

    <table>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left" rows="4">Sisymbrium officinale de 1868, recueilli à</cell>
            <cell rend="width10" rows="4"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="left width25">Edinburgh</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Moscou</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Kharkoff</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Palerme</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left" rows="2">Trifolium repens, de 1868, recueilli à</cell>
            <cell rend="width10" rows="2"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="left width25">Moscou</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Palerme</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left" rows="2">Senecio vulgaris, de 1868, recueilli à</cell>
            <cell rend="width10" rows="2"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="left width25">Moscou</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Palerme</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left" rows="4">Id. de 1869, recueilli à Genève, originaires de</cell>
            <cell rend="width10" rows="4"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="left width25">Edinburgh</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Moscou</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Montpellier</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="left width25">Palerme</cell>
        </row>
    </table>

<p rend="left">Ces derniers sont les plus intéressants.</p>
<p>Vous savez que plusieurs indices font croire que la même espèce ressent differemment les effets de la temperature selon le climat. Ainsi nos arbres d’Europe se feuillent à Madère sous des températures analogues à celles de l’ètè de l’Angleterre, et restent sans feuilles sous la température d’hiver semblable à celle de nos printemps. J’avais cru en trouver la cause dans un repos plus complet des sucs dans les régions froides, repos qui prépare une végétation vigoureuse au printemps des pays du nord; repos qui est imparfait ou qui manque à peu près completement à Madère, à Naples, etc. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lindseer jeune astronome de S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Petersbourg, a publié depuis dans les Mémoires de l’Académie de S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Petersb<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>. un mémoire sur les époques de foliaison, floraison, etc, de diverses espèces en divers points de l’Europe, et il arrive à la conclusion d’une qualité differente de la même espèce au nord et au midi pour ressentir la chaleur, les espèces etant plus hâtives au nord, et il croit que cela tient à l’hérédité.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Probablement les deux causes hérédité et état des plantes en hiver concourent, au moins dans les espèces vivaces et ligneuses, mais les experiences que je viens de faire sur des espèces annuelles montrent bien l’effet de l’hérédité seule. Le <hi rend="underline">Trifolium repens</hi> a été different— Cela vient-il de l’état des graines ou de la difference de variété? Je ne sais.</p>
<p>J’aurais aimé avoir des espèces plus surement indigènes, les Senecio, Sisymbrium et Trifolium pouvant bien provenir de graines importées avec les marchandises, graines, etc. Cependant j’ai eu soin de recommander qu’on les recueillit hors des jardins, loin des habitations, ce qui a été fait. Ces espèces ont été choisis parce qu’il y a vraiment très peu d’espèces communes à des pays aussi éloignés en Europe, et en même temps faciles à trouver et sans variétés differentes.</p>
<p>J’ai envoyé mes Senecio de la recolte de 1869 de Genève, à <hi rend="underline">Florence</hi>, où j’espère les trouver semés lorsque j’irai dans cette ville en automne. Mon projet est effectivement d’aller passer 2 mois dans le nord de l’Italie, depuis le milieu d’octobre prochain et je resterai au moins 15 jours à Florence—tout à vos ordres si vous desirez quelque renseignement.</p>
<p>Recevez, mon cher Monsieur, l’assurance de mes sentiment très dévoués | Alph. de Candolle</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.12 Au … faibles, 2.13] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 J’ai … maintenue. 3.2] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>7.10 de diverses … chaleur 7.12] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>9.3 Cependant … fait. 9.4] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
        <opener>
            <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
            <date>28 Sept. 1869.</date>
            <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <div type="transcription">
            <p>I am sending you some seeds that have a genuine interest from the point of view with which we are both concerned and I want to suggest that you sow them in order to pursue an experiment that is already underway and to confirm it for yourself.</p>
            <p>In 1868 I had seeds from some <hi rend="underline">spontaneous</hi> species sent to me from four or five locations that are very far apart in Europe: <hi rend="underline">Palermo</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Montpellier</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Kharkov</hi><ref target="#foot.f2"/> and <hi rend="underline">Moscow</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Edinburgh</hi>, in order to sow them in Geneva and to see whether the same species had become more precocious or more retarded as a result of having had ancestors that had been exposed to very different climates for centuries.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I chose species that are easily recognised and that do not have any very distinct varieties. Unfortunately, not all my correspondents collected all the species I asked for and I have had to limit the experiment to a few species. Also unfortunately, the gardener on whom I had thought I could rely for certain details did not raise all the plants that had been sowed suitably.  Nevertheless, from my sowings of 1869, it transpired that in three species that can readily be compared, the <hi rend="underline">Senecio vulgaris</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Sisymbrium officinale</hi> coming from the north were quicker to develop and flower. Conversely in <hi rend="underline">Trifolium repens</hi>, the plants from the north were slower, but they were also weaker, smaller in all their parts, and one might say that they had the appearance of a <hi rend="underline">minor</hi> variety.<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
            <p>In 1869 I sowed <hi rend="underline">Senecio vulgaris</hi> from all 4 sources at Geneva, and in this second generation, the precocity of the northern plants persisted.</p>
            <p>How long will it last? That’s a subject not lacking in interest.</p>
            <p>The rigour of our climate and the lack of greenhouses and gardeners available to me do not allow me to make a new sowing this season. Perhaps you may be disposed to make one at your house, or if you prefer, you might communicate with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hooker, for instance, in order to sow these so that they would be carefully observed.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
            <p> I am sending you: </p>
             
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left" rows="4">Sisymbrium officinale of 1868, collected at</cell>
                            <cell rend="width10" rows="4"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Edinburgh</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Moscow</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Kharkov</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Palermo</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="3"/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left" rows="2">Trifolium repens, of 1868, collected at</cell>
                            <cell rend="width10" rows="2"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Moscow</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Palermo</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="3"/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left" rows="2">Senecio vulgaris, of 1868, collected at</cell>
                            <cell rend="width10" rows="2"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Moscow</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Palermo</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="3"/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left" rows="4">Id. of 1869, collected at à Geneva, originating at</cell>
                            <cell rend="width10" rows="4"><hi rend="stretchyVertical">{</hi></cell>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Edinburgh</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Moscow</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Montpellier</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="left width25">Palermo</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                
              <p> These last are the most interesting.</p>
            <p>You will know that several indicators suggest the same species feels the effects of temperature differently according to climate. Thus our European trees come into leaf in Madeira in temperatures analogous to those of an English summer, and remain leafless in winter temperatures similar to those of our springs. I believed I had found the cause in the fact that in cold regions the sap is more completely dormant, a dormancy that prepares for vigorous vegetative growth in the springtime in northern countries; a dormancy that is imperfect or almost completely absent in Madeira, Naples, etc. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lindseer, a young astronomer of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Petersburg, has since published a memoir in the Mémoires de l’Académie de S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Petersb<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>. on the times of foliation, flowering, etc, of various species in various points of Europe, and he reaches the conclusion that the same species has a different propensity for feeling the heat in the north and the south, with species being more hasty in the north, and he believes that this relates to heredity.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
            <p>Probably the twin causes of heredity and the condition of plants in winter act together, at least in perennial woody species, but the experiments I have just made on annual species show well the effects of heredity alone. <hi rend="underline">Trifolium repens</hi> was different— Does this come from the condition of the seeds or from varietal difference? I don’t know.</p>
            <p>I should have liked to have had species that were more reliably indigenous, since Senecio, Sisymbrium and Trifolium might well derive from seeds imported along with merchandise, seed, etc. However, I took care to recommend that they should be collected outside gardens,  far from dwellings, and that has been done. These species were chosen because there are really very few species common to European countries that are so far apart, yet easy to find and without different varieties.</p>
            <p>I have sent my Senecio from the 1869 Genevan harvest, to <hi rend="underline">Florence</hi>, where I hope to find them sown when I go to that town in the autumn. My plan is actually to go and spend 2 months in the north of Italy, from the middle of next October and I shall remain at least a fortnight in Florence—completely at your service should you wish for any information.</p>
            <p>Please accept, my dear Sir, the assurance of my most devoted sentiments |  Alph. de Candolle.</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see pp. 410–12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Kharkov (now Kharkiv) is a city in eastern Ukraine, in the Donets valley (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had written extensively on the effect of changes in climate and other conditions of life on various domestic plants and animals (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 1: 271–92).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><hi rend="italic">Senecio vulgaris</hi> is common groundsel, a winter annual. <hi rend="italic">Sisymbrium officinale</hi> is hedge-mustard. <hi rend="italic">Trifolium repens</hi> is white clover.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD forwarded Candolle’s letter and most of the seed to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6923.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 2 October [1869]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Candolle refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6181.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carl Linsser</ref> and his monograph ‘Die periodischen Ersheinungen des Pflanzenlebens in ihrem Verhältniss zu den Wärmeerscheinungen’ (The periodic appearance of plant life in relation to heat-phenomena; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4814.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Linsser 1867</ref>). For a discussion of Linsser’s work on the effects of temperature on plant development, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7747.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thornthwaite 1943</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>