<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-548">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. G. Malcolmson   30 November 1839</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1886</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1987">1987</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-548 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-548.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-548.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="02">2</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 39: 15–17</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>39: 15–17</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3140.xml">Malcolmson, J. G.</persName>
                <placeName>Forres</placeName>
                <date when="1839-11-30">30 Nov 1839</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Sends specimens of coralline with vermiform holes.</p> 
<p>J. Allan’s observations of Aldabra and the Cormoros [see <hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi>, p. 186] and news of his experiments on the growth of coral.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">coralline</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_79">Allan, J.</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Aldabra</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Cormoros</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">coral</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">isolation, islands</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2019-09-09" status="alteredPostPublication" type="footnotes">n4. Identified Allan.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Forres</placeName>
                    <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1839</date>
                    <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I take advantage of a young friend going to London to send you a specimen of a coralline, which I obtained from a reef of rocks extending from the little island of “Sowna” into the Pentland frith. It lived, along with actinia and many other animals, in a hollow in the bituminous rocks of that region. I was surprised to see the shore of the south east of Hoy covered with <hi rend="underline">vast quantities </hi> of white sand and gravel—not as usual composed of shells but of ramose corals. My interest in this specimen, however, is of a different kind. The oysters of our <hi rend="underline">raised beaches</hi> are marked by serpentine depressions such as you see on the base of the coralline;—and the limestones both of the <hi rend="underline">Lias</hi> and <hi rend="underline">old red Sandstone</hi> at Cromarty, are similarly marked, when washed ashore. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fleming<ref target="#foot.f1"/> had been interested in this, when at Cromarty some time before, but could not find out the origin of the grooves: In breaking up some of the argillaceous limestone shale of the old red sandstone in 1837, at extreme low water mark, I found them to be marked in the same way, and I found each groove, or rather canal to contain a nereis of <hi rend="underline">corresponding</hi> <hi rend="underline">size,</hi> and satisfied myself that this feeble creature had bored an habitation for itself. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fleming, to whom I sent some specimens, would not admit this—and Miller<ref target="#foot.f2"/> hesitated (till he saw the coral). D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fleming seemed to think it assuredly an <hi rend="underline">ancient borer,</hi> and referred to similar markings on the <hi rend="underline">surface of the chalk under the</hi> <hi rend="underline">London clay,</hi> as giving additional interest to the subject. I was therefore well pleased to find these recent corallines everywhere bored in the same way, both where they adhered to the smooth flagstone, and through their mass. Numerous other borers preyed on this newly formed limestone at the same time. Each canal contained a larger or smaller nereis according to its size and they had a relation to each other that could not have existed, had the worm only used the holes of another creature. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fleming says that they only bore clay and submarine peat—but I see no reason why they, as well as some of the more delicate and smooth shells, should not penetrate limestone. I have sent some of the worms to D<hi rend="superscript">r </hi>Johnston of Berwick;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> and as you are engaged on corals think you may like to have a specimen so marked.</p>
<p>I find I was right at first in my understanding of Allan’s account of Aldabra— he is positive that the island is of coral vitrified or silicified. Recollect that Mr Lonsdale even, at first, took the corals from Shahar in arabia for trap. Allan promised to write you a long letter and I gave him your journal to read for the purpose of his adding some remarks regarding it— I hope to get his letter soon—but he is in great demand and being young, more close attention is expected from him, than would be requisite had he been longer here. The subject is also painful to him, from his never to be repaired loss. He is positive about the Comoros. If you could send him the loan of Owen’s<ref target="#foot.f4"/> (of whom he has not a high opinion) or some other chart he would insert remarks on all the places he visited, and many of which he <hi rend="underline">survey</hi> 〈<hi rend="underline">ed.</hi>〉 It would be returned to you. My brother 9 King William Street will take care of it.</p>
<p>I had intended to have said something of sheepdogs but I have not time. I could send you a few small specimens of “Kunkar” and of “Laterite” our two Indian puzzles, if they could be of use to you for the purpose of comparison. We have added an important new locality of the lower fossils on the Bogie river near Huntly, in Aberdeenshire. I have not yet been there.</p>
<p>Yours truly J G Malcolmson</p>
<p>I have asked allan to write down his very important experiments on the growth of coral. 3 feet in 6 months! think of that</p>
<p>Please to send the packet to Royle over from the Geol. anytime you are there</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1660.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Fleming</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3330.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hugh Miller</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">George Johnston</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Allan: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_79.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Brands Allan</ref>. Owen: <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3633.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Fitzwilliam Owen</ref>. See <hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi>, p. 62 n.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>