<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-8574">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. V. Carus   24 October 1872</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8715</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2013">2013</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-8574 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8574.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-8574.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="20">20</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 86</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 86</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml">Carus, J. V.</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1872-10-24">24 Oct 1872</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Doubts accuracy of Bible translations quoted by CD as evidence that Semitic races blush.</p>
            <p>Questions his note on derivation of words like "ugly", "huge", etc.</p>
            <p>Lists some mistakes and misprints.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="human_group" ref="#">Semitic races</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">communication</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">historical time</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">social behaviour</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Leipzig,</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 24. 1872.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I beg your pardon for troubling you again, but after a serious consideration I think it my duty to let you know my doubts. On two places you quote the Bible, first (p 316) to prove that the Semitic races do blush, and then (p 322) to give an instance of the movements which accompany the blushing   In this latter place the term “blush” occurs again   Of course I was about to give these two places in Luther’s words, but I was struck that he did not mention the “blushing”, i.e the reddening of the face.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> On turning to the original hebrew text I saw that it did not know any more this blushing   In both places the same verb is used (kalam), which means ferire, vulnerare, also morally used: verbis perforare and struck with shame, but there is not the slightest hint to colour in it.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Then I found out that in the whole Bible there is not one place, where the “blushing” is mentioned, nor does exist a word in Hebrew, which means blushing or reddening of the face, whilst the Arabs know it; they possess a verb absolutely synonymous with our blushing and “Erröthen”. Now I think you cannot prove the blushing of the old Hebrews by quoting a wrong translation (p 316). That it occurs in Esra<ref target="#foot.f3"/> (s. p 322), is irrelevant in this respect.</p>
<p>My second doubt is about note 28 on p 307. You say, that the movements which are performed in feeling horror lead to sounds which may be expressed by words like “uh” or “ugh”. Of course these sounds must be the same in all men with similarly organized throats, whenever the same movements occur. Now Mr Wedgwood ‘shows (as you quote in the note) by intermediate forms that the sounds here referred to have probably given rise to many words, such as “ugly”, “huge” etc.’ Why then, I ask, have not these same movements led to similar words with the other Arian nations?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> There are still some words in our modern languages, which have originated from such interjections or which are onomatopoetic, but extremely few. But with regard to “ugly”, it has its definite etymology and is the result of an organic development as are most of our modern words. You will find in <hi rend="underline">Max Müller</hi>’s Lectures on the Science of Language, 6. edit. 1871. Vol. I. p 426, a short notice of the etymology of ugly.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I am not of Müller’s opinion that language will remain “our Rubicon”; but in cases like this, where the history of the word can be traced, we are not allowed to neglect the intermediate stages of the development of the word and to take the quite accidental similarity of it with an interjection as a proof of their genealogical identity. Therefore I think you better leave out the last two lines of the note 28.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>In a second print, will you kindly notice the following mistakes or misprints:</p>
<p>p. 243, you mention the Kafirs of South <hi rend="underline">America</hi>   of course you mean Africa (l. 14 from top</p>
<p>p 245 you spell Dr Brow<hi rend="underline">n</hi> without the <hi rend="underline">e</hi> (l. 11, fr. t.)<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>p 79. you spell Spen<hi rend="underline">c</hi>er, p 262 Spen<hi rend="underline">s</hi>er, the old English poet. For ought I know Spen<hi rend="underline">c</hi>er is correct.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>p 295. l. 5 from top: “Kafir, Gaika says”, dele the stop.<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>p 285. R. Brough Sm<hi rend="underline">i</hi>th (l. 6 from bottom); in other places the name is spelt Sm<hi rend="underline">y</hi>th, also in the Index.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>Pray don’t be angry about my remarks. The places, which induced me to make them, struck me too much. If you will kindly ask a better Hebrew scholar than I am, I dare say he will give you still better information. Ask Will Wright in Cambridge, a most obliging man and dear friend of mine.<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>Three sheets of the translation are printed and it goes on rapidly. With respect of the above mentioned places, I don’t know what to do. The deepest heartfelt reverence and the scientific conscience comes to a sad conflict.</p>
<p>Believe me, | My dear Sir, | Yours most sincerely, | J. Victor Carus</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>2.1 My second … the note 28. 2.17] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon; enclosed in square brackets blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.17 Therefore … note 28.] <hi rend="italic">double scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>6.1 Spen<hi rend="italic">s</hi>er] <hi rend="italic">double underl blue crayon</hi>; <hi rend="italic">two crosses in margin blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>8.2 Sm<hi rend="italic">y</hi>th] <hi rend="italic">double underl blue crayon</hi>; ‘right—’ <hi rend="italic">added blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘To be returned.’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 316, CD quoted Jeremiah 6:15, ‘Nay, they were not at all ashamed, neither could they blush’. The translation is from the King James Bible. The <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6234.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Martin Luther</ref> 1545 translation of the same passage reads, ‘wiewohl sie wollen ungeschändet sein und wollen sich nicht schämen’ (however they would not be shamed and would not be ashamed). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 322, CD quoted Ezra 9:6, ‘O, my God! I am ashamed, and blush to lift up my head to thee, my God’. The Luther version reads, ‘Mein Gott, ich schäme mich und scheue mich, meine Augen aufzuheben zu dir, mein Gott’ (My God, I am ashamed and dread to lift up my eyes to you, my God).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><hi rend="italic">Kalam</hi>: shame (Hebrew); <hi rend="italic">ferire</hi>, <hi rend="italic">vulnerare</hi>: injure, wound (Latin); <hi rend="italic">verbis perforare</hi>: pierce with words (Latin).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">‘Esra’ is the German spelling of ‘Ezra’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In the first printing of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, p. 307, the note reads, ‘See remarks to this effect by Mr. Wedgwood, in the Introduction to his “Dictionary of English Etymology,” 2nd edit. 1872, p. xxxvii. He shows by intermediate forms that the sounds here referred to have probably given rise to many words, such as <hi rend="italic">ugly</hi>, <hi rend="italic">huge</hi>, &amp;c.’ In the second printing, the last sentence was omitted. The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5019.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hensleigh Wedgwood</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8252.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wedgwood 1872</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Carus refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3233.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Max Müller</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5322.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Müller 1871</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Carus refers to Max Müller’s statement, in his lecture ‘The theoretical stage, and the origin of language’: ‘Language is our Rubicon, and no brute will dare to cross it’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5320.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Max Müller 1861</ref>, p. 340).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">The errors on pp. 243 and 245 are corrected in the second printing of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The spelling of ‘Spenser’ is correct in the first printing of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-8548.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. V. Carus, 7 October 1872</ref> and n. 13).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">There is a comma following ‘Gaika’ in the first printing of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">The correction was made in the second printing of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>. The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4441.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Brough Smyth</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7056.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Wright</ref> was the Sir Thomas Adams Professor of Arabic at the University of Cambridge (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5933.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi></ref>). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2401.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 335, a note was added following the quotation from Jeremiah 6:15: ‘According to Professor Robertson Smith, these words do not imply blushing. It seems possible that pallor is meant. There is, however, a word <hi rend="italic">haphar</hi> occurring in Psalm xxxiv. 5, which probably means to blush.’ <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4433.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Robertson Smith</ref> succeeded Wright as Adams Professor of Arabic at Cambridge in 1889. The second edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> was edited by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Francis Darwin</ref> and published after CD’s death.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>