<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11883F">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Francis Darwin   [<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 25 February 1879]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">21532</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11883F by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11883F.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11883F.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="27">27</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS"/>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 274.1: 60</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>274.1: 60</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Darwin, Francis</persName>
                <placeName>Colonne Voirol, Algiers</placeName>
                <date when="1879-02-25">[<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 25 Feb 1879]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Directs CD where to find tools in his room. Has been looking at agave and aloe flowers. Thanks family for their letters.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Agave</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">aloe</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4908">De Vries, Hugo</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2017-12-22" status="footnoted">Footnoted by <name xml:id="fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2018-01-24" status="reviewed">Reviewed by <name xml:id="sainnes">Shelley Innes</name></change>
        <change when="2018-03-23" status="editorResponseCompleted">Editor response by <name sameAs="#fjn26">Francis Neary</name></change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2021-10-17" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Villa Beau Séjour | Colonne Voirol | Algiers</placeName>
                    <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I am very sorry you have been hunting for the thing with the hollow handle. I am afraid I can’t tell anything about it. All the rough tools of that kind I put in the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> draw from the left in that sort of of table behind the balance table in my room: you will find 2 sizes of bradawls there but I am afraid not the hollow thing. I brought one fine pincers here as I meant to put litmus on leaves if there was heavy dew: the other one is 〈in〉 a wooden box in the dark cupboard which Lettington knows.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I am very sorry you have had a bother about it— There are 3 wire forceps hanging up on nails on the right of the fireplace if you want them.</p>
                    <p>Thank you for you kind words. I am getting on very well, I can get along with doing nothing pretty well.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I havn’t had energy to take lessons in French, as it envolves going in nearly 4 miles &amp; out again. I have been looking at some compositæ which have rosettes of leaves, (as you were).<ref target="#foot.f4"/> They dont seem to care about geotropism for they make perfect rosettes with the outer leaves all flat against the ground even when they grow on vertical surfaces of earth of which there are many here at the sides of the lanes. I forget what D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Vries says about them.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I found wasps going to an Agave in flower; &amp; cutting it open I found the inside of the flower lined with aphides &amp; some of them sticking to the honey—they dont often go inside do they. These aloe leaves where they overlap and press against one another in the bud make perfect impressions of the edge of one leaf on the surface of the next, &amp; the formation of bloom seems affected as there is a thicker layer where the pressure has been, &amp; this helps to define the impression.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I have been out a Sunday herborisation with old Durando   there were 20 or 30 French people &amp; they seemed quite interested about the flowers, writing down the names &amp; putting specimens in tin boxes; he gave very good little jaws about them   I am going to meet him today in the Jardin d’Acclimatisation where he will take me round I suppose—<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I have been there for a short time but G was tired &amp; we came away— it is the place Dyer<ref target="#foot.f8"/> meant &amp; is very interesting with all sorts of things growing out of doors. I forget to say that the Klein meeting was pretty well attended &amp; it is agreed to give him a testimonial not as a lump of money but as an expression of sympathy—so I suppose it is not necessary to give very large subscriptions. I think I shall give £5; if you subscribe before I come back will you pay 5£ for me saying that I am away—but I don’t know that there is any hurry— The secretary is</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
    <p>Malcolm Morris Esq</p>
        <p>63 Montague Sq<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p> </figure> 
                    <p>Please thank mother &amp; Bessy<ref target="#foot.f10"/> for their letters— I am glad poor Ubbadubba<ref target="#foot.f11"/> has got some nice dirt to play with instead of my saw dust   Give him my best love &amp; say I will bring him a little red cap with blue tassel like the little ubbadubbas here were— I forgot that new caps are rather painful to him so perhaps it had better not be mentioned.</p>
<p>Goodbye dearest father | Your affec son | Frank Darwin</p>
                    <p>It was very good of Henrietta to write to me about vaccination but I dont think it is necessary<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the reference to the subscription to the Klein testimonial; see n. 9, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11883A.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, [before 25 February 1879]</ref> and n. 2. CD’s gardener was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2906.xml">Henry Lettington</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1222.xml">Francis</ref> had gone to rest and visit <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1224.xml">George Howard Darwin</ref> in Algiers; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11857.xml">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 3 February 1879</ref> and n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">‘Rosettes’ are circular arrangements of leaves in which either the upper foliage dies back with the remaining vegetation protecting the plant, or internodes along a stem are shortened, bringing the leaves closer together; this leaf structure is common in the Compositae (daisy family).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">No work by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4908.xml">Hugo de Vries</ref> on these structures has been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">The genera <hi rend="italic">Agave</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aloe</hi> both have fleshy leaves arranged in a rosette pattern, but they are native to Central and South America and Africa, respectively. However, <hi rend="italic">Agave</hi> species have been naturalised in Africa since the sixteenth century and were grown commercially in Algeria, so when Francis refers to aloe leaves he probably means <hi rend="italic">Agave</hi> leaves. CD began studying bloom (the waxy coating on the leaves and fruit of many plants) in 1873 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 21, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9007.xml">letter to J. D. Hooker, 13 August 1873</ref>).  He suspended his work on the subject in 1874 (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 22, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-9571.xml">letter to W. T. Thiselton-Dyer, 28 [June 1874]</ref> and n. 7), and began again in 1877 (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-10960.xml">letter to Fritz Müller, 14 May 1877</ref>). CD never published on bloom, but in 1878 Francis followed up <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs’s</ref> suggestion about the relation of bloom to distribution of stomata (see <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> vol. 26, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11628.xml">letter from Francis Darwin, 24 and 25 July 1878</ref>); Francis published some of the results of these experiments in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10276.xml">F. Darwin 1886</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5577.xml">Gaetano Durando</ref> was a correspondent of CD’s and had provided him with seeds; see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11815.xml">letter to Francis Darwin, [4 February – 8 March 1879]</ref> and n. 4. The Jardin d’acclimatation (originally Jardin d’essai or experimental garden, now Jardin botanique du Hamma) was in the Hamma district (now Belouizdad) of Algiers.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">William Turner Thiselton-Dyer</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In December 1878, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2716.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Emanuel Klein</ref> had followed other staff at the Brown Institution, London, in resigning his position. After the Cruelty to Animals Act was passed in 1876, the institution had become a prominent target of attack and its research plans were severely restricted (see <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 19 December 1878, pp. 151–2). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_8462.xml">Malcolm Morris</ref> lived at 63 Montagu Square, London. An entry for ‘Klein’s Test’ in CD’s Classed account books (Down House MS) dated 25 February 1879 records a payment of £5 5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1217.xml">Elizabeth Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1206.xml">Bernard Darwin</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1225.xml">Henrietta Emma Litchfield’s</ref> letter has not been found in the Darwin Archive–CUL.</note>
        </div>
    
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>