<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2193">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Edward Hewitt   22 December 1857</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">17619</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2193 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2193.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2193.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">DAR 166: 197</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 197</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2270.xml">Hewitt, Edward</persName>
                <placeName>Sparkbrook</placeName>
                <date when="1857-12-22">22 Dec 1857</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Replies to more queries about fowl hybrids.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">fowl</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">hybrids</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Eden Cottage, Spark Brook, | n<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Birm<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>.</placeName>
                    <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. | 22/57.</date>
                    <salute><anchor xml:id="ann.a1" type="annotationStart"/>My dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I duly rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. your letter and at once to the best of my knowledge, reply to your queries.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> In retrospect, I certainly do think my time might have been far more profitably employed than in breeding Hybrids; although at the time I was making these efforts, my attention (so far as poultry-matters went,) rested on this almost exclusively. To the subject—<anchor xml:id="ann.a2" type="annotationEnd"/></p>
<p>In the year I tried so many, and so various “crosses”; certainly more than 300 Eggs were placed for incubation under foster-mothers, of which as certainly not a dozen hatched, the eggs that proved faulty were opened only when there was absolute certainty they would not produce chickens, and all “hope” was gone of their so doing, simply to see if they were fecundated, and <hi rend="underline">guess</hi>, if possible, “why” they did not progress.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> The result is in my last letter. This I invariably noticed, that eggs laid in April and May, (by fowls to Pheasants,) were the <hi rend="underline">only</hi> ones with me productive, later in the season failure was <hi rend="underline">universal</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I bred several at different times from a Golden Cock Pheasant and Common Hen <hi rend="underline">Pheasant</hi>, but not from Golden or Silver cock Pheasants, and a fowl. It was only the <hi rend="underline">English</hi> cock Ph<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. with the <hi rend="doubleUnderline">fowl</hi> that produced.</p>
<p>I raised three (all hens,) and singularly enough, very plain coloured birds, from a Golden cock Ph<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. and Silver Hen Ph<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>., but never could produce a single bird if I reversed the sexes, of the parents.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Indeed with <hi rend="doubleUnderline">best</hi> luck, the product was most uncertain. As unfortunately at that time I did not keep a diary, I have no present direct reference, but I well remember from 55 eggs, <hi rend="underline">under very careful hens</hi>, only 3 youngsters saw day-light, yet the parents copulated openly, without fear of bystanders, several times daily, many eggs being germinated.<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I never knew, but of the single instance mentioned in my former note, of a <hi rend="underline">cock</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">fowl</hi> breeding with a hen <hi rend="underline">pheasant</hi>, in all other cases, the hen pheasant quite declined the amours of her appointed companion, and indeed simple aversion at the onset, always ended in perfect hate. In the pair now spoken of—cock silverlaced Sebright with hen common Ph<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.—copulation was frequent and daily, yet only the one solitary egg fertilized out of many, the remainder being what are commonly called “clear-eggs”. The really small size of this product is easily supposed by its weight not 24 ounces, and looking even <hi rend="underline">considerably</hi> less to the eye, but it “handles” well. Another remarkable caprice of Dame Nature, (for thus putting her out of her way,) is, in the legs of this bird, f<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. hatching time the colour of the legs and feet until lately was deep-horn inclining to a shade of blue, but now they are become of a kind of sullied creamy white, together with the bill, the upper mandible however, as yet retains a narrow stripe of the original colour down the centre throughout, but it also appears to be fast fading away. The comb and wattles although perfect, are rudimental, and will never be developed as in the sire.</p>
<p>Again altho’ I have seen Hybrids of 6 or seven years standing, I never yet myself saw one with well-formed spurs, available to do real duty in an affray,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> but Hybrids do not want them particularly for this purpose, for with the most uncontrolable predeliction for “a row”, or rather to oppress all weaker companions, even their own kind, they oft-times become perfect cannibals, and will tear and eat their victim (if not removed) peacemeal even while living. The last I ever kept destroyed and consumed nearly the whole of the flesh of its only companion, all along the back before I was aware of the fact, tho’ the poor creature still lived, and in perfect horror, I eschewed Hybrids from that very day. They are recklessly cruel and capricious with all about them, tyrannous, and unusually wild, even where their parents were perfect “pets.”<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>The Sebright Hybrid at present seems more docile, but youth is still on its side, and time will most likely tell tales. In conclusion, tho’ carefully &amp; most <hi rend="underline">narrowly</hi> watched, I never saw any salacious efforts on the part of the males towards their similarly bred female companions, or in favour of other poultry, nor yet the females manifest the slightest natural desires, my experience tells me, Hybrids like to be solitary, and the aversion on the part of other poultry is reciprocal.</p>
<p>These few hurried notes may possibly amuse you, and with my best wishes | I am, My D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Sir, | Yours very faithfully, | Edward Hewitt.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note target="#ann.a1" targetEnd="#ann.a2"><hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note> 3.7 many … germinated.] <hi rend="italic">underl pencil</hi> </note>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">CD’s letter, written in response to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1614.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Hewitt, 18 December 1857</ref>, has not been located.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Information from this letter was reported in CD’s discussion of the sterility of hybrids (see <hi rend="italic">Natural</hi> <hi rend="italic">selection</hi>, pp. 422, 429). CD also cited Hewitt’s view that the early death of embryos caused the sterility of such crosses in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 264.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 431.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 435 n. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 422.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 452.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">CD used this information in his discussion of the instincts of animals (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 486).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>