<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2185">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To T. H. Huxley   16 December [1857]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3293</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1990">1990</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2185 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2185.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2185.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="06">6</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp, C encl 2pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 104</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 6: 505</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Imperial College of Science, Technology and Medicine Archives (Huxley 5: 151); DAR 145: 178</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_192.xml">Imperial College</repository>
                    <idno>Huxley 5: 151</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>145: 178</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1857-12-16">16 Dec [1857]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2486.xml">Huxley, T. H.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>THH’s catalogue [THH and R. Etheridge, <hi rend="italic">A catalogue of the collection of fossils in the Museum of Practical Geology</hi> (1865), part published in 1857] best <hi rend="italic">résumé</hi> he has seen of science of natural history. On classification he is not quite sure that he wholly goes along with THH. Encloses a few criticisms of THH’s preface.[enclosure survives as copy only].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">A catalogue of the collection of fossils in the Museum of Practical Geology</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Huxley, T. H. and Etheridge, Robert 1865</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive criticism of correspondent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">systematics</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Huxley</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>In my opinion your Catalogue is simply the very best Resume by far, on the whole Science of Natural History, which I have ever seen.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>I really have no criticisms; I agree with every word. Your metaphors &amp; explanations strikee me as <hi rend="underline">admirable</hi>. In many parts it is curious how what you have written agrees with what I have been writing, only with the melancholy difference for me that you put everything in twice as striking a manner, as I do.</p>
<p>I append more for the sake of showing that I have attended to the whole, than for any other object, a few <hi rend="doubleUnderline">most</hi> trivial criticisms.</p>
<p>I was amused to meet with some of the arguments, which you advanced in talk with me, on classification; &amp; it pleases me, as my long proses were so far not thrown away, as they led you to bring out here some good sentences.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>But on classification I am not quite sure that I yet wholly go with you, though I agree with every word you have here said.— The whole, I repeat, in my opinion is admirable &amp; excellent—</p>
<p>Ever yours | C Darwin</p>
<p>I return by the same post your pamphlet.—</p>
<p>[Enclosure]<ref target="#foot.f4"/></p>
<p>p. 2. <hi rend="underline">all</hi> crust of earth is not formed of <hi rend="underline">strata</hi>, as in injected Trap and <ref target="#foot.f5"/> masses of the wider extent.</p>
<p>p. 6. <hi rend="underline">indefinite</hi> series of alterations: according to our present knowledge is not thus too strong, though I believe in it.</p>
<p>15. Silex <hi rend="underline">chief</hi> ingredient of flint; may it not be called sole ingredient.</p>
<p>18. Sexes never combined in same individual. Quatrefages seems to believe in Serranus being hermaphrodite;<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I forget author’s name.</p>
<p>20. Is it wise to give, <hi rend="underline">without any allusion to common view</hi>, your view of Star-fish &amp;c. being Annulosa; the rest of world looking at them as type of one of the grandest Divisions of animal kingdom.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>27. I think little expansion is wanted in middle paragraph to show how a fish can be morphologically more complex and physiologically less so than the highest molluscs. I do not quite understand.</p>
<p>Higher in page. Sentence beginning “the other sense” was not <hi rend="underline">at first</hi> clear, as I did not see with what contrasted.</p>
<p>39. I do not understand how you can say that if only fossils existed there would be no difficulty in practically species—as there is variation amongst fossils, as with recent, there seems to be same difficulty in grouping.</p>
<p>40. Top sentence strikes me as too long.</p>
<p>44. Mud being deposited in all parts of sea, sufficient to imbed remains and to be preserved to future generations, I believe this to be the <hi rend="underline">gravest of errors</hi>: but I cannot enter into argument much too long.</p>
<p>57. Is it not bold to say one foot never deposited in one year: think of floods after earthquake, at least add never a foot over wide area.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.1 on] <hi rend="italic">over illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.2 explanations] <hi rend="italic">after del illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.3 been writing] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘written’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.4 you put] ‘you’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">4.1 meet with] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘see’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is given by the reference to Huxley’s <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi> (see n. 2, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD was at the time reading proof-sheets of Huxley’s ‘explanatory introduction’ to <hi rend="italic">A catalogue</hi> <hi rend="italic">of the collection of fossils in the Museum of Practical Geology</hi> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2194.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 25 December [1857]</ref>). The work, with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1541.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Robert Etheridge</ref> as co-author, remained unpublished until 1865.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">CD had discussed classification in letters to T. H. Huxley, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2141.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">15 September [1857]</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">26 September [1857]</ref>, [before 3 October 1857], and 3 October [1857].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">It is likely that the following comments on Huxley’s introduction, transcribed from a copy in DAR 145, were enclosed with this letter. The original manuscript of the enclosure is not with this letter in the Huxley papers at Imperial College.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">A space was left at this point by the copyist.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6461.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Quatrefages de Bréau 1855–6</ref>, p. 80, referred to fishes of the genus <hi rend="italic">Serranus</hi>. The case is cited in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5799.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Natural selection</hi></ref>, p. 44, where CD also mentioned that Jean Louis Armand de Quatrefage de Bréau’s source was perhaps a memoir by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1408.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Adolphe Dufossé</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2175.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dufossé 1856</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Huxley, drawing upon Johannes Peter Müller’s researches on the developmental history of echinoderms, had arrived at the conclusion that the structure of the larvae of echinoderms was founded on a plan similar to the idealised form of annelid larvae. He proposed the unorthodox view that echinoderms were most closely related to the annelids (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4003.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">T. H. Huxley 1856–7</ref>, 13: 635–9, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8437.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1976</ref>, pp. 113–21).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>