<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7885">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Theodor Piderit<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   28 July 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10395</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7885 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7885.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7885.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">3pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 174: 43</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>174: 43</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3788.xml">Piderit, Theodor</persName>
                <placeName>Detmold</placeName>
                <date when="1871-07-28">28 July 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Interested in forthcoming <hi rend="italic">Expression</hi>.</p> 
            <p>Sends publications.</p>
            <p>Describes physiological theory of mental activity. Asks for CD’s opinion of his theory.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Expression</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mind, cognitive behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Detmold</placeName>
                    <date>d 28 Juli | 1871.</date>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In Ihrem neuen und Epoche machenden Werke über “Die Abstammung des Menschen” finde ich eine Bemerkung, dass Sie mit einer Arbeit über <hi rend="underline">den Ausdruck der Gemüthsbewegungen im menschlichen Gesichte</hi> beschäftigt sind.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Da ich diesem Gegenstande seit längerer Zeit ein specielles Studium gewidmet habe, so sehe ich dem Erscheinen Ihrer Schrift mit freudiger Spannung entgegen. Ich habe in Ihren Werken oft Gelegenheit gehabt, zu bewundern, wie sehr Sie die Litteratur aller Nationen beherrschen und anerkennend berücksichtigen; daraus schöpfe ich die Hoffnung, dass Sie mir meine ergebene Bitte nicht versagen und dem beifolgenden Buche einige Aufmerksamkeit schenken werden.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>Ich bin 14 Jahre lang als Arzt in Chile thätig gewesen, einem Lande, dem Sie in Ihrem berühmten Buche über die Reise des “Beagle” so interessante Capitel gewidmet haben.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Seit einigen Jahren von Valparaiso zurückgekehrt, habe ich meine Mussezeit dazu verwendet, um mein “Wissenschaftliches System der Mimik und Physiognomik” auszuarbeiten, und bin nun im höchsten Grade gespannt, ob und in wie weit Sie den von mir aufgestellten Grundsätzen beistimmen werden.</p>
<p>Eine kleine Schrift: “Gehirn und Geist” habe ich mir erlaubt ebenfalls beizulegen.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Sie enthält einen Versuch, die menschliche Geistesthätigkeit auf physiologische Weise zu erklären, indem die Hypothese aufgestellt wird, dass die Function des Gehirns der Function des Rückenmarks analog ist, und dass die bekannten Grundkräfte des Rückenmarks auch als Grundkräfte des Gehirns thätig sind. Diese Theorie schien mir zu genügen, um das geheimnissvolle und complicirte Getriebe der thierischen und menschlichen Geistesthätigkeit auf einfache, physiologische Gesetze zurückzuführen. Sie würden mich ausserordentlich erfreuen, wenn Sie mir gelegentlich einige Zeilen schenken und mir sagen wollten, ob Sie glauben, dass meine Ansicht einigen Anspruch auf Berechtigung machen darf.</p>
<p>Indem ich Sie, hochgeehrter Herr, bitte, freundlichst zu entschuldigen, dass ich mir erlaube, Ihre kostbare Zeit in Anspruch zu nehmen | empfiehlt sich hochachtungsvoll ergeben | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Th. Piderit</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Detmold</placeName>
                    <date>28 July | 1871.</date>
                    <salute>Highly honoured Sir!</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>In your latest and epochal work on “The Descent of Man” I find a remark that you are engaged in writing a treatise on <hi rend="underline">the expression of emotions in the human face</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> As I myself have dedicated particular attention to this subject over a prolonged period, I am awaiting the appearance of your treatise in joyful suspense. I have often had opportunity to admire in your work the extent to which you command and give appreciative consideration to the literature of all nations; and hence I am hopeful that you will not refuse my humble request and give some attention to the enclosed book.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>For 14 years I worked as a doctor in Chile, to which country you devoted such interesting chapters in your famous book on the voyage of the “Beagle”.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Since I returned from Valparaiso a number of years ago, I have spent my hours of leisure developing my “Wissenschaftliches System der Mimik und Physiognomik”, and now I am so very anxious to see whether and to what extent you will agree with the principles I put forth.</p>
<p>I have permitted myself to include also a booklet: “Gehirn und Geist”.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It constitutes an attempt to account for human mental activity in terms of physiology; thus, I suggest that the function of the brain is analogous to the function of the spinal cord, and that the known principal powers of the spinal cord are active also as the principal powers of the brain. This theory to me appeared to suffice in order to reduce the mysterious and complex mechanism of animal and human mental activity to simple physiological laws. I would be more than happy if you could send me a few lines some time to tell me whether, in your opinion, my views can claim any authority.</p>
<p>I beg you, dear Sir, to kindly forgive me for taking up your valuable time, and remain most respectfully devoted | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Th. Piderit</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 5. Piderit may have read the German translation, Carus trans. 1871. CD’s work on expression in humans and animals was published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> in 1872.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Piderit refers to his <hi rend="italic">Wissenschaftliches System der Mimik und Physiognomik</hi> (Scientific system of facial expression and physiognomy; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6304.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Piderit 1867</ref>). There is a heavily annotated copy in the Darwin Library–CUL, including manuscript translations of parts of it by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1179.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Sweetland Dallas</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 675–7 and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5917.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from W. S. Dallas, 22 February 1868</ref>). CD cited it a number of times in <hi rend="italic">Expression.</hi> Piderit also published an earlier work on the subject, which CD had not seen (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6302.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Piderit 1858</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Piderit refers to <hi rend="italic">Journal of researches.</hi> Chapters 14 to 18 cover CD’s explorations in Chile.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The reference is to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6303.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Piderit 1863</ref> (Brain and mind). There is a copy in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>