<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7623">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From G. B. A. Duchenne<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   25 March 1871</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14194</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7623 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7623.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7623.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="19">19</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp † (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 243</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 243</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1404.xml">Duchenne, G. B. A.</persName>
                <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1871-03-25">25 Mar 1871</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Gives CD permission to use photographs of expressions.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">expression, emotion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">quotations / citations</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>25 Mars 1871.</date>
                    <salute>Monsieur et très savant maître,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je suis un des admirateurs de vos magnifiques recherches geologiques et je me sens très honoré de la proposition que vous me faites de mentionner quelques extraits de mon ouvrage sur le mécanisme de la physionomie humaine, dans votre essai sur l’expression dans l’homme et dans l’animal.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> J’ai voulu rester l’unique propriétaire de mon ouvrage et je n’ai pris d’éditeur que pour éviter les ennuis de l’affaire commerciale. Vous comprenez donc, Monsieur, qu’entre hommes de science là question d’argent ne saurait exister. Choisissez, dans mon album, toutes les figures qui vous conviendront.</p>
<p>En réponse à une question que vous me faites l’honneur de m’adresser sur le triangulaire des lèvres, il résulte de mon observation continue jusqu’à ce jour, que ce muscle est un de ceux qui obeïssent le moins à la volonté;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> que fonctionellement il se contracte seulement sous l’influence de nausées, de dégout et dans certaines 〈f〉ièvres graves; mais qu’il est un des muscles les plus expressifs et qu’il laisse un cachet presque ineffaçable sur la physionomie; par éxample, chez les gens d’un caractère facheux et dédaigneux, il se contracte habituellement et finissent par l’emporter sur ses antagonistes, il abaisse les commissures labiales; ordinairement, dans ces cas, les fibres concentriques de l’orbiculaire des lèvres s’assoçiant à ce muscle amincissent celles-ci, ce qui est un des signes de méchanceté, et donne alors un caractère spécial de malveillance, cette expression n’est pas représenteé dans mon album.</p>
<p>Associé à la contraction des fibres de l’orbiculaire superficiel des paupierès il exprime un profond dédain (voyez fig   )<ref target="#foot.f4"/> le caractère expressif fondamental de son action propre est la tristesse; aussi le voit-on s’associer aux muscles de la douleur, pour exprimer la souffrance morale profonde et resigné (Voyez la figure   ).<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Permettez-moi, Monsieur, bien que je me reconnaisse incompétent dans cette question, quelques remarques que j’ai faites sur l’expression de la face du singe avec lequel j’ai vécu pendant près d’une année; qui m’était attaché; il dinait à ma table et aimait beaucoup les friandises. Lorsque je lui en donnais une qu’il connaissait; je remarquais une expression de satisfaction dans sa physionomie, <hi rend="underline">par une légère élévation</hi> de <hi rend="underline">ses commissures labiales</hi>; mais lui présentai-je quelque chose d’inconnu, <hi rend="underline">ses sourcils s’élevaient</hi>, témoignant une <hi rend="underline">une grande attention</hi>, puis prenant entre ses doigts et le pouce cet objet, il le regardait en abaissant ses sourcils qui devenaient rectilignes, <hi rend="underline">ce qui donnait à sa physionomie</hi> une <hi rend="underline">expression de réfléxion</hi>; ensuite après l’avoir examiné quelque temps, le grattant avec l’autre main et le sentant, il élevait tout à coup son sourçil <hi rend="underline">et renversait un peu la tête en</hi> arrière comme pour regarder en haut et faire appel à ses souvenirs   Après ce manège il se décidait à gouter; si cela lui plaisait, il y avait sur sa face une manifestation de satisfaction. Dans le cas contraire, il rejetait l’objet en faisant une grimace.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>En somme, j’ai fait ces observations pendant près d’une année en vivant dans l’intimité de ce moine dont j’avais conquis l’amitié. Je suis convaincu que les mouvements expressifs du sourcil (d’attention et de réflexion) que je viens de décrire, sont naturels chez le singe, et qu’ils ne sont pas le résultat de l’imitation. En est-il de meme dans les autres espèces?— Si vous faites usage de ces remarques veuillez bien dire qu’elles me sont personnelles.</p>
<p>Recevez Monsieur l’assurance des Sentiments les plus distingués de votre tout dévoué | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Duchenne (de B<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 Je suis … conviendront 1.8] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>2.2 il resulte … volonté; 2.3] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.4 de nausées, de dégout] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.7 il se contracte … album 2.11] ‘Some portion of the lip’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 Associé … personelles 5.6] <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi></note>
                <note>4.1 Permettez-moi … friandises 4.4] ‘gave him food which he knew &amp; like’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
                <note>4.4 friandises] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.4 connaissait] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.6 mais lui … inconnu] ‘when some food not known was given him’ <hi rend="italic">ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Keep’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi>; ‘Authorisation for use of Photographs—(other letter on spit) | Triangulation of lips involuntary | [‘Expression of Monkey’ <hi rend="italic">del</hi>] satisfaction &amp; surprise’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <date>25 March 1871.</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir and most learned master,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I am one of the admirers of your magnificent geological research and I feel very honoured by your proposal to mention some extracts from my work on the mechanism of human physiognomy, in your essay on expression in man and animal.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I wanted to remain the sole proprietor of my work, and I only took a publisher so as to avoid the bother of the commercial side. So you will understand, dear Sir, that between men of science the question of money cannot exist. Choose all the figures you like from my album.</p>
<p>In reply to a question which you have done me the honour of sending me on the triangular of the lips, my continuous observation up till now shows that this muscle is among those least subject to the will;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> that functionally it only contracts under the influence of nausea, disgust and certain serious fevers; but that it is one of the most expressive muscles and that it leaves a virtually ineffaceable mark on the physiognomy; for example, among people of an irritable and contemptuous character, it habitually contracts and ends by predominating over its antagonists. It lowers the labial commissures (ordinarily, in such cases, the concentric fibres of the orbicular muscle of the lips unite with that muscle to thin the lips, which is one of the signs of ill-nature), thus conferring a special character of malevolence; this expression is not represented in my album.</p>
<p>When allied to the contraction of the fibres of the upper orbicular muscle of the eyelids, it expresses a profound disdain (see fig   )<ref target="#foot.f4"/>   The fundamental expressive character of its specific action is sadness; so one finds it allied to the muscles of grief to express profound and resigned moral suffering (See figure   ).<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Allow me, dear Sir, even though I acknowledge my incompetence on this matter, to transmit some remarks I have made on the expression on the face of a monkey with which I lived for nearly a year; who was attached to me; he would dine at my table and loved tidbits. When I gave him one that he knew, I would remark an expression of satisfaction on his physiognomy, <hi rend="underline">through a slight elevation</hi> of <hi rend="underline">his labial commissures</hi>; but if I presented him with something unknown, <hi rend="underline">his eyebrows would rise</hi>, demonstrating <hi rend="underline">great attention</hi>, then taking the object in question between his fingers and thumb, he would look at it while lowering his eyebrows, which became rectilinear, <hi rend="underline">giving his physiognomy</hi> an <hi rend="underline">expression of reflection</hi>; then after having examined it for some time, scratching it with the other hand and sniffing it, he would suddenly raise his eyebrows, <hi rend="underline">tilting his head slightly</hi> backward as if to gaze upwards and draw upon his memories   After this performance he would decide to taste it; if it pleased him, there would be manifest satisfaction on his face. In the opposite case, he would reject the object with a grimace.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>In short, I carried out these observations for nearly a year while living in intimacy with this monk whose friendship I had won. I am convinced that the expressive movements of the eyebrow (of attention and reflection) which I have just described, are natural to monkeys, and that they are not the result of imitation. Is it the same in other species?— If you make use of these please say that they are my personal remarks.</p>
<p>Please accept, dear Sir, the assurance of the Regards of yours truly | D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Duchenne (de B<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 19, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. QQQQ.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7566.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. B. A. Duchenne, about 10 March [1871]</ref> and n. 2. Duchenne refers to CD’s research for <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref> and to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duchenne 1862</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7566.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to G. B. A. Duchenne, about 10 March [1871]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Duchenne evidently intended to refer to an illustration in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2172.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Duchenne 1862</ref>, but the figure has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The figure has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Expression</hi></ref>, pp. 133 and 145, CD described the expressions of Duchenne’s monkey when given a treat or trying new foods.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">De B: de Boulogne. Duchenne was born in Boulogne-sur-Mer (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1892.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DBF</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>