<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6602">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Frederik Anthony von Hartsen<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   5 February 1869</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14319</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6602 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6602.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6602.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">5pp (German)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 166: 114</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>166: 114</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_2156.xml">Hartsen, F. A. von</persName>
                <placeName>Cannes</placeName>
                <date when="1869-02-05">5 Feb 1869</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Believes that species or genus may have originated more than once from separate ancestors, i.e., polyphyletically.</p> 
<p>Discusses relation of CD’s theory to religion. Has written popular account of CD’s theory in Dutch [<hi rend="italic">Darwin en de Godsdienst</hi> (1869)].</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Darwin en de Godsdienst</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">Dutch</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Hartsen, F. A. von 1869</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">multiple origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#religious_beliefs">Religious Beliefs</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Cannes</placeName>
                    <date>5 Febr—1869</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Herrn Charles Darwin Hochwohlgeboren.</seg>
                    <salute>Hochgeehrter Herr</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Ich würde mir nicht unterstehen, Eu Hw. wieder zu schreiben, wäre es nicht aus herzlichem Interesse zu Ihrer Forschungen, und zur Wissenschaft überhaupt.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
<p>Es ist gegen Ihre Theorien Manches eingewandt worden. Nun scheint es mir dass die meisten Gegner dieser Theorien derselben viel zu schwere Anforderungen stellen. Darum ist m E. zur Apologie der Theorien nöthig, von vornherein dieses zuzugestehen,: es ist in den meisten Fällen ganz unmöglich, <hi rend="underline">zu beweisen</hi> dass die sämmtlichen Individuen einer Gruppe einen gemeinschaftlichen Urheber gehabt haben. M. E kann man in den meisten Fallen nicht weiter gehen als, zu beweisen dass solches nicht <hi rend="underline">ungereimt</hi> sein würde.</p>
<p>Ich sage, es sei selten möglich zu beweisen dass die Individuen einer natürlichen Gruppe einen gemeinschaftlichen Urahn gehabt haben. Was ich meine ist Folgendes. Ist es möglich dass ein Naturvorgang durch <hi rend="underline">natural selection</hi> aus einen einfachen Organismus eine gewisse Gruppe höherer Organismen bildet, so lässt sich nicht einsehen warum dieses nur auf <hi rend="underline">einem</hi> Puncte der Erde geshehen soll. Ich kann mir, zum Beispiel, vorstellen dass in Ostindien aus einer sehr einfachen Pflanze allmählig <hi rend="underline">Palmen</hi> enstanden sind, und dass in Süd-Amerika, ganz unabhängig davon, <hi rend="underline">ebenfalls</hi> aus einer sehr einfachen Pflanze Palmen entstanden sind. Kurz, ich kann mir denken dass auf 2, 3 ja mehrere Puncte der Erde, <hi rend="underline">dasselbe</hi> Genus, ja vielleicht <hi rend="underline">dieselbe</hi> Species, aus dem Anorganischen Reiche hervorgegangen ist.</p>
<p>Nach Ihrer Theorie also lässt sich m E sehr wohl annehmen dass diese oder jene Gruppe von Organisme nicht <hi rend="underline">Eins</hi>, sondern <hi rend="underline">mehrere</hi> Centra des Ursprungs gehabt hat. Es würde also die Theorie ihren Werth behalten, wäre es sogar dass die Individuen einer Gruppe, aus geographischen Gründen, unmöglich einen gemeinschaftlichen Ursprung gehabt haben könnten. Ueberhaupt kann ich mir denken dass die anorganische Masse auf <hi rend="underline">mehreren</hi> Puncten der Erde lebendige Wesen hervorgebracht hat und dass diese Wesen sich auf mehreren Puncten <hi rend="underline">auf ähnliche Weise</hi> weitergebildet haben, so dass z B. die Schnecken Englands einen anderen Ursprung wie die Schnecken Amerikas haben.</p>
<p>Diese Bemerkung schien mir vielleicht zur Entkräftung geographischer Einwände gegen Ihre Lehre nicht ungeeignet zu sein.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Daher dass ich so frei bin, sie Ihnen mit zu theilen.—</p>
<p>“Carl Vogt” hat in Holland Vorlesungen gehalten und darin Ihre Theorien mit seinem Materialismus verwebt.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Manche Leute sind dadurch veranlasst zur Ansicht dass Materialismus und Atheismus das letzte Wort des Darwinismus ist. Ich habe nun eine populäre Darstellung Ihrer Lehren verfasst, und dabei gezeigt dass dieselben über die Hauptfragen der Religion gar nichts entscheiden.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> Es ist aber nicht warscheinlich dass Eu Hw Holländisch lesen, daher Holländische Schriften für Sie wenig Interesse haben dürften.—</p>
<p>Prof. Fechner schreibt mir dass ein D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pfaff Ihre Ansichten critisirt hat.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Ich hoffe die Schrift von Pfaff zu lesen, lege aber auf Einwände von Deutscher Seite wenig werth, weil dieselben meistens aus Vorurtheil stammen.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> Nur bedauere ich dass wir nicht wissen wie das Organische Leben auf <hi rend="underline">anderen Sternen</hi> entsteht. Eine vergleichende “Organismogenie” wäre sehr schätzbar! Vielleicht kommen wir noch einmal dazu!</p>
<p>Herr Traherne Moggridge geht glücklich besser.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> Er ist ein sehr enthousiastischer Discipel von Ihnen!</p>
<p>Und hiermit danke ich ergebenst für die freundliche Zuschrift mit welcher Sie, nach Veranlassung meines Essay’s mich beehrt haben.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Hatte ich gewusst dass Sie mir eine so ausführliche Antwort zugedacht hatten, ich würde vielleicht nicht den Muth gehabt haben, Ihnen meine Schrift zu übersenden. Mit herzlichen Wünschen für Ihr Wohlsein erlebe ich | Hochgeehrter Herr | Ihr Hochw. ergebenster | F. A. v. Hartsen</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>


<div type="translation">
    <div type="text">
       <opener> <placeName>Cannes</placeName>
           <date>5 Febr—1869*</date>
       <seg type="supplemental">Mr Charles Darwin Esq</seg>
        <salute>Most esteemed Sir</salute></opener>
        <div type="transcription"><p>I would not have dared to write again to your honour if it were not for my heartfelt interest in your research and to science in general.<ref target="#foot.f2"/></p>
        
            <p>A number of objections have been raised against your theories. To me, however, it looks as though most opponents of these theories expected them to meet far too difficult requirements. In my opinion, therefore, it is vital for the defence of these theories to admit in  advance the following: that in most cases it is quite impossible <hi rend="underline">to prove</hi> that all the individuals of a group have had a common ancestor. In most cases, I think, one can’t do more than show that this would not constitute an <hi rend="underline">inconsistency</hi>.</p>
        
        <p>I maintain, it is rarely possible to prove that the individuals of a natural group have a common ancestor. What I mean by this is the following. If it is possible for a natural process, through <hi rend="underline">natural selection</hi>, to produce a group of higher organisms from a simple organism, then there is no reason why this process should occur only at <hi rend="underline">a single</hi> place on earth. For example, I can imagine that in East India, <hi rend="underline">palm trees</hi> gradually developed from a very simple plant, and that quite independently in South America palms <hi rend="underline">also</hi> originated from a very simple plant. In short, I can imagine that at 2, 3 or more places on earth <hi rend="underline">the same</hi> genus, perhaps even <hi rend="underline">the same</hi> species have emerged from the realm of inorganic matter.</p>
        
        <p>Hence, according to your theory we can in my view very well surmise that some group or other of organisms did not have <hi rend="underline">one</hi> but rather <hi rend="underline">several</hi> centres of origin. The theory therefore would remain valid even if the individuals of a group, for geographical reasons, could not possibly have a common origin. I can imagine anyway that inorganic mass has produced living creatures in <hi rend="underline">a number of</hi> places on earth and that these creatures continued to evolve <hi rend="underline">along similar lines</hi> in these various places, so that e.g. the snails of England have a different origin from the snails of America.</p>
        
            <p>To me this observation seemed not unsuited for the refutation of geographical arguments against yourdoctrine.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> This is why I take the liberty of communicating it.—</p>
        
            <p>“Carl Vogt” has been giving lectures in Holland, and in them he has interwoven your theories with his ownmaterialism.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> As a result, some people over here have been led to assume that materialism and atheism are the ultimate conclusion of Darwinism. I have now completed a popular account of your doctrines, in which I have shown that they actually do not decide the cardinal questions ofreligion.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It seems unlikely, however, that Your Honour reads Dutch, hence Dutch works must be of little interest to you.—</p>
        
            <p>Prof. Fechner writes me that a Dr. Pfaff has criticised yourviews.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I hope to read Pfaff’s publication, although I do not place much stock on objections of German provenance, since these are mostly derived fromprejudice.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> I regret only that we do not know how organic life develops on <hi rend="underline">other planets</hi>. A comparative “organismogeny” would be most valuable! Perhaps one day we will acquire one!</p> 
            <p>Mr Traherne Moggridge is fortunately doingbetter.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> He is a very enthusiastic disciple of yours!</p> 
            <p>I also thank you most humbly for your kind letter with which you have honoured me upon receiving myessay.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> Had I known that you intended to reply in such detail, I should perhaps not have had the courage to send you my book.  With heartfelt wishes for your health I remain | highly honoured Sir | your devoted servant | F. A. v. Hartsen</p></div>
    </div>
</div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.17, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original German, see pp. 65–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5778.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from F. A. von Hartsen, 5 January 1868</ref>. The abbreviation ‘Eu Hw.’ is not standard, but Hartsen evidently intended ‘Eure Hochwohlgeboren’.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 351, CD had argued that species of the same genus, although widely separated geographically, must originally have proceeded from the same source, as they had descended from the same progenitor. He then discussed geographical distribution and the means of dispersal of species to new locations (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 356–410). In subsequent editions of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, CD added material to counter objections to his theory based on difficulties associated with dispersal.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">For more on Vogt’s popular lectures of 1868 and 1869, see Kockerbeck ed. 1999, pp. 23–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Hartsen refers to his book, <hi rend="italic">Darwin en de Godsdienst</hi> (Darwin and religion; Hartsen 1869).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Hartsen refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1604.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gustav Theodor Fechner</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6524.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Friedrich Pfaff</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his book, <hi rend="italic">Die neuesten Forschungen und Theorien auf dem Gebiete der Schöpfungsgeschichte</hi> (Latest research and theories on the history of creation; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6260.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pfaff 1868</ref>), Pfaff argued that CD’s theory was untenable in the light of geological findings.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Hartsen refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3353.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Traherne Moggridge</ref>. In his letter of 5 January 1868 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16), Hartsen had mentioned that Moggridge’s health was bad.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">CD’s reply to Hartsen’s letter of 5 January 1868 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 16) has not been found.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>