<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4663">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From B. D. Walsh   7 November 1864</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">14676</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4663 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4663.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4663.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="12">12</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp †</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 248</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 12: 401</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 10</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 10</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4944.xml">Walsh, B. D.</persName>
                <placeName>Rock Island, Ill.</placeName>
                <date when="1864-11-07">7 Nov 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Notes Louis Agassiz’s opinions on CD’s views.</p>
            <p>Mating and sexual organs of insects.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_43">Agassiz, J. L. R.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding behaviour</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">type and morphology</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Rock Island, Illinois, U.S.</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 7. 1864</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">Chas. Darwin Esq.</seg>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>Your welcome letter of Oct. 21 was received two days ago.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I transmit you by this Mail a Paper of mine on “Certain Entomological Speculations of the New England Naturalists”, in which I have taken occasion to show the absurdity of Agassiz’s refutation of the “Origin of Species”.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Since it was published, I have received a long letter of seven pages of letter-paper from Alex. Agassiz, criticizing in a friendly way sundry passages in it.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Amongst other things, he observes in regard to my charge that Prof. Agassiz had misstated your theory, that “Darwin in a recent letter to father <hi rend="underline">thanks him</hi> for the manner in which he has conducted his opposition to his theory.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> So you see that opinions may differ on the misstatement of Darwin’s Theory”. In reply, I suggested that that fact merely showed that having been abused as an atheist, deist, infidel &amp;c by other writers, you probably felt grateful to any writer who was willing to allow you “a spirit quite as reverential as his own”. (<hi rend="underline">Meth. Study</hi> Pref. p. iv.)<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>I cannot resist the temptation of quoting the sentiments of a botanical friend of mine,<ref target="#foot.f6"/> to whom I had written that I was about to enter a plea in the great case of <hi rend="underline">Agassiz.</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">vs.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Darwin</hi>,—“I hope you will give Agassiz a thorough blowing up. It may do some young naturalists good; but as for your penetrating the sublime self-complacency of the great <hi rend="underline">I Am</hi> &amp; disturbing his infallible theories, that is another matter. I cannot be so lenient as you are even—to attribute his course of argument to a mind so illogical that he <hi rend="underline">cannot</hi> educe a correct conclusion. It is wilful, mean pettifogging—taking hold of every trivial thing that can be twisted into a fancied support of his position—&amp; knowingly ignoring the most patent truths (that of themselves need but be stated to grind his deductions to powder) in a way that is insulting to a person of decent intelligence”.</p>
<p>I do not know what the European Scientific World thinks of Agassiz, but here he is popularly considered as the incarnation of Science &amp; as infallible as the Bible.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> He strikes me as a very much overrated man, who perpetually allows his imagination to get the better of his judgement, &amp; who not unfrequently argues for victory instead of for truth. I have heard him myself in a Public Lecture<ref target="#foot.f8"/> assert in the most unqualified manner as a notorious truth that <hi rend="doubleUnderline">all</hi> the animals of every Geological Epoch were specifically distinct from those of the Epochs preceding &amp; following it &amp; that in the Eocene, Miocene &amp;c periods there merely began to be some approximation to the present order of things. I am told by a New England correspondent,<ref target="#foot.f9"/> who belongs to his School, that he positively denies the truth of the facts upon which the very names Eocene &amp;c are based. Do any European authorities uphold him in these views? I am told Pictet does.<ref target="#foot.f10"/></p>
<p>You ask, “What can be the meaning or use of the great diversity of the external generative organs” in many groups of Insects?<ref target="#foot.f11"/> I don’t know that I can completely explain this matter, which has long occupied my attention, but I can quote you a few facts which throw some little light on it.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</hi> In all the <hi rend="underline">Agrionidæ</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Libellulidæ</hi>, as you are doubtless aware, after the ♂ has embraced the neck of the ♀ with his caudal forceps, no copulation can possibly take place unless the ♀ <hi rend="underline">voluntarily</hi> curves her abdomen downwards &amp; forwards so as to meet the ♂ <hi rend="underline">penis.</hi> <ref target="#foot.f12"/> I conceive that the various thorns, tubercles, incurvings &amp; excurvings which we find on the ♂ caudal forceps are so many different appliances for enciting the amorous passions of the ♀ &amp; inducing her to curve her abdomen in the manner necessary to accomplish the <hi rend="underline">coitus</hi>. In both sexes of many species, when they are roughly handled after capture, the abdomen is frequently curved downwards in a similar manner, which I suppose originated the English name of “Horse-stingers”. I conceive that a puncture from one of the sharp thorns found on the caudal ♂ forceps of many species would operate in the same manner, &amp; that the first individual that had such a thorn gained an advantage in his amours over his thornless compeers. I have often watched the united sexes careering backwards &amp; forwards for a long time without the ♀ consenting to the <hi rend="underline">coitus</hi>.—</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.</hi> You must often have noticed how repeatedly the ♂ butterfly in many species strikes in the air at the ♀ without effectuating a connection. A very slight change in the shape or armature of his forceps might enable him to sieze the ♀ genitals more readily, &amp; gain an advantage over other ♂ ♂.—</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">3<hi rend="superscript">rdly</hi> </hi> Simple as the <hi rend="underline">coitus</hi> of insects appears, there are four distinct modes in which it is effected. <hi rend="underline">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</hi> The normal mode, where the ♂ abdomen squarely surmounts the ♀ abdomen, the ♂ tip curving slightly downwards &amp; the ♀ tip slightly upwards. <hi rend="underline">2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.</hi> Where the ♂ surmounts the ♀ in the usual manner, but slips the tip of his abdomen sideways under that of the ♀, the <hi rend="underline">penis</hi> being erected vertically—</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>Years ago in England I observed this was the method in the Nepidous genus <hi rend="underline">Ranatra</hi>, &amp; I observe it here in <hi rend="underline">Perla</hi> &amp; its allies. <hi rend="underline">3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>.</hi> Where the ♂ surmounts the ♀ in the usual manner but curves the tip of his abdomen downwards &amp; forwards by the side of ♀ abdomen, so as to embrace the entire abdomen of the ♀ forward of the vulva, with the caudal forceps <hi rend="underline">a</hi>, thus bringing ♂ ♀ genitals into contact,</p> 
<figure type="diagram"> 
<p>[DIAG HERE]</p> </figure> 
<p>I observe this method in the Phasmide genus <hi rend="underline">Diapheromera</hi>. <hi rend="underline">4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> </hi> The well-know coitus of <hi rend="underline">Agrionidæ</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Libellulidæ</hi>.— There may be other modes which I have not noticed, but these are sufficient to show that there is a great diversity in the mode in which the <hi rend="underline">coitus</hi> of insects is effected, &amp; in almost every case the structure of the parts is such that the ♀ can, <hi rend="underline">if she chooses</hi>, refuse coition. Hence I conceive has arisen the great variation in the structure &amp; armature of the ♂ organs.</p>
<p>You express a desire to know what my life in this new country is. I will, at the risk of <hi rend="underline">boring</hi> you, give you the particulars. When I left England in 1838, I was possessed with an absurd notion that I would live a perfectly natural life, independent of the whole world—<hi rend="underline">in meipso totus teres atque rotundus</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> So I bought several hundred acres of wild land in the wilderness, 20 miles from any settlement that you would call even a village, &amp; with only a single neighbor. There I gradually opened a farm, working myself like a horse day after day, &amp; raising great quantities of hogs &amp; bullocks. Being far away from any mechanics, &amp; having the natural gift of turning my hand to almost anything except blacksmithing, I did all kinds of jobs for myself, from mending a pair of boots to hooping a barrel or putting a new head into it, for the simple reason that it was less trouble to do such work myself than to hitch up my team &amp; drive 10 or 20 miles to a mechanic’s. I suppose I should at this present moment be vegetating there like a cabbage, but there was a Swedish Colony that settled in the neighborhood<ref target="#foot.f14"/> &amp; dammed up the river everywhere for mill-seats, so that a great deal of malaria was generated &amp; I had some severe attacks of fever, one of which brought me almost to death’s door. So at the end of 12 years I sold out at a great sacrifice, &amp; found that I was just $1000 poorer than when I began. I then moved to Rock Island<ref target="#foot.f15"/> &amp; went into the Lumber business—“lumber” in America means all kinds of sawed boards &amp; planks, “timber” being stuff that is hewed with the broad axe—&amp; in seven years time had made a good many thousand dollars. I then, thinking I had been a slave about long enough, quitted that business, &amp; invested most of my funds in building ten two-story brick houses for rent, upon the proceeds of which &amp; a few of Uncle Sam’s Bonds, I manage to live &amp; keep all the time out of debt. If the times were what they used to be, I should have my whole time to myself &amp; as large an income as I care about. As it is, what with the depreciation of such property &amp; what with the war-taxes &amp;c,<ref target="#foot.f16"/> I have to devote about <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of my time to executing sundry repairs on my tenements, &amp; the remaining <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula> I devote to Entomology. I suppose I have the largest collection of Insects in America, except one or two in the great Atlantic Cities.<ref target="#foot.f17"/></p>
<p>Will you favour me with your Photograph, &amp; if convenient Prof. Westwood’s,<ref target="#foot.f18"/> for my Entomological Album? I enclose you my own.</p>
<p>Believe me, my dear Sir, | very sincerely yours | Benj. D. Walsh</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 Your welcome … intelligence”. 2.11] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi>; ‘Morphology? | Sexual Organs of | Insects—’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon over text</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 I do not … Pictet does. 3.12] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note>8.1 You express … Atlantic Cities. 8.29] <hi rend="italic">crossed ink</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of page</hi>: ‘Sexual Organs of Insects’ <hi rend="italic">ink, circled ink</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1"><ref target="./DCP-LETT-4640.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Letter to B. D. Walsh, 21 October [1864]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The reference is to Walsh 1864b. Walsh claimed that <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz’s</ref> <hi rend="italic">Methods of study in natural history</hi> (Agassiz 1863b) contained an implicit attack on CD’s theory of species as presented in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see Walsh 1864b, pp. 223–4). Walsh argued that Agassiz had misrepresented CD’s theory, ignoring natural selection and the struggle for existence (Walsh 1864b, pp. 223–31). An annotated copy of Walsh 1864b is in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, letters from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4186.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">26 May 1863</ref> and n. 12, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4346.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">23 November 1863</ref> and n. 18. For a discussion of Walsh’s public support of CD’s theory, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7340.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sorensen 1995</ref>, pp. 199–200 and 211–12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Walsh refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_41.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alexander Agassiz</ref>, son of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4460.xml">letter of 12 April 1864</ref>, CD had thanked Agassiz for his presentation copy of <hi rend="italic">Methods of study in natural history</hi> (Agassiz 1863b). A lightly annotated copy of Agassiz 1863b is in the Darwin Library–Down (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 13). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4695.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 4 December [1864]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In the preface to <hi rend="italic">Methods of study in natural history</hi>, Agassiz stated his opposition to ‘the transmutation theory’, allowing that others might hold contrary views ‘in a spirit quite as reverential’ as his own. He insisted, however, that the theory was ‘opposed to the processes of Nature, … contradicted by the facts of Embryology and Paleontology’, and that the experiments upon domesticated animals and cultivated plants, on which its adherents based their views, were ‘entirely foreign to the matter in hand’ (Agassiz 1863b, pp. iii–v). For a discussion of Agassiz’s book and its role in a public campaign against transmutation theory in America, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4977.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lurie 1960</ref>, pp. 306–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Walsh’s botanical friend has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Although Agassiz was highly regarded in American literary and intellectual circles in the 1860s, his reputation among professional naturalists was less secure (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4977.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Lurie 1960</ref>, pp. 309–11). Agassiz’s scientific reputation among his colleagues at Harvard may have been tainted by jealousy over his success in attracting patronage for his Museum of Comparative Zoology (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, pp. 224–6, 313–23). On Agassiz’s controversial professional style and his deteriorating relationship with his students during this period, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1991</ref>, pp. 27–42 and 44–65.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">Walsh may have attended one of the public lectures given by Agassiz on his tour of the mid-western United States from December 1863 to March 1864 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5213.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Marcou 1896</ref>, 2: 138–9).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Walsh’s New England correspondent has not been identified; however, for a list of Agassiz’s students at Harvard, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1991</ref>, pp. 35–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Walsh refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3787.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">François Jules Pictet de la Rive</ref>. See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4695.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 4 December [1864]</ref> and n. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">See <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4640.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to B. D. Walsh, 21 October [1864]</ref>. Walsh’s observations of male insects that were structurally adapted for the grasping of females were eventually published in the <hi rend="italic">Practical Entomologist</hi> (Walsh 1867, p. 88). CD cited this article in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 342.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 361–4, CD discussed sexual selection in the order Neuroptera, which included Agrionidae, or damsel-flies, and Libellulidae, or dragonflies; on Walsh’s view of the variation of sexual organs, and natural selection, in Neuroptera, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8439.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Winsor 1991</ref>, pp. 99–100. CD cited <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8142.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Walsh 1862a</ref> on differences of coloration between the sexes (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 361–2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13"><hi rend="italic">In meipso totus teres atque rotundus</hi>: ‘in myself a whole, smoothed and rounded’. The phrase is adapted from Horace’s <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi>, 2.7.86, <hi rend="italic">in se ipso totus, teres atque rotundus</hi>: ‘in himself a whole, smoothed and rounded’ (Fairclough trans. 1978).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14">Bishop Hill, Illinois.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">Rock Island is a town on the Mississippi River in north-western Illinois (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1526.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Columbia gazetteer of the world</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">For a discussion of taxes levied by the Union government and economic conditions during the American Civil War, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5147.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">McPherson 1988</ref>, pp. 442–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">Walsh’s collection was destroyed in the Chicago fire of 1871 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1727.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DAB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">The reference is to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5077.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Obadiah Westwood</ref>. Westwood enclosed a photograph for Walsh in his letter to CD, 2 December 1864. See also letters to B. D. Walsh, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4695.xml">4 December [1864]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4698F.xml">[4 December 1864?</ref>].</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>