<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-11499">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To W. T. Thiselton-Dyer   9 May [1878]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">6758</idno>
            
            
            
            

        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-11499 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11499.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-11499.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 144: 438</bibl></relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Thiselton-Dyer, W. T., Letters from Charles Darwin 1873–81: 119–21)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_213.xml">Kew</repository>
                    <idno>Thiselton-Dyer, W. T. letters: 119–21</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Bassett</placeName>
                <date when="1878-05-09">9 May [1878]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4712.xml">Thiselton-Dyer, W. T.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>CD wants some plants; asks Lynch to raise some Cactaceae for him. Observations on sensitivity and movements of radicle.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Cactaceae</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3058">Lynch, R. I.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">chemistry, chemicals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">vibration, including sound</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Basset, Southampton.</placeName>
                    <date>May 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                    <seg type="supplemental">(we return home on the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.)</seg>
                    <salute>My dear Dyer</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
                    <p>I have given you &amp; Hooker a rather long holiday, but now I want some aid badly.— I have written on separate slip of paper what I want.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I daresay I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> get the Cissus &amp; Bignonia at Veitchs’, but Hooker told me to apply first to Kew.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> When at Kew a few months ago, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lynch gave me fruits of 2 Cacteæ: we sowed the seed fresh &amp; dried under various temperatures, but not one germinated. Of all the seeds of Cycas so kindly sent me only two cracked &amp; these died.<ref target="#foot.f4"/>  Why we failed I cannot imagine.</p>
<p>I have extreme wish to observe seedlings of Cacteæ &amp; Cycas; if you have any seeds of latter, would you get M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lynch to raise a few for me &amp; of some Cacteæ, <hi rend="underline">&amp; as soon as the earth cracks over the seeds or a</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">vestige</hi> <hi rend="underline">of a cotyledon appears</hi>, to <hi rend="underline">despatch the pots to me</hi>.</p>
<p>I shall die a miserable, disgraced man if I do not observe a seedling Cactus. As for Cycas I have hardly any hope.—</p>
                    <p>We have been doing some really pretty work on radicles; but it is too long a story for you to read or for me to write. What trifles determine the success of experiments; Sachs missed a pretty little discovery solely by keeping his germinating beans too warm.— What magnificent work he has done on radicles.—<ref target="#foot.f5"/> </p>
                    <p>I hope M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Dyer is going on well.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
                    <p>I saw a paragraph in Times from you about plants not turning to the Light for their profit, which has astounded me, &amp; some time I must talk with you about this.<ref target="#foot.f7"/> </p>
<p>Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
                    <p>P.S. I cannot resist telling you a little about the radicles. The apex is sensitive, &amp; instead of turning to touching object like a tendril, it turns from it. The apex is so sensitive that if little squares (about <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>20</mn></mfrac></math></formula><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of inch) of card &amp; thin paper of exactly same size are fixed to opposite sides of apex, the radicle, (growing freely downward in damp air) bends always from the card side.— The apex of a radicle growing in earth tries to circumnutate, &amp; thus prefers the earth on all sides; if one side is harder than the other the radicle will bend from this side, &amp; thus it will discover with unerring precision the lines of least resistance in the ground.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/> </p>
<p>Do not trouble yourself by answering this scrawl, but aid me if you can about the plants.— | C.D.</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="tnotes">
                <note xml:id="tnote.n1">0.1 Basset, Southampton] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘<hi rend="italic">Down, | Beckenham, Kent. | Railway Station | Orpington. S.E.R.</hi>’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.4 the] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘these’ </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.4 seed] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.6 only] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="tnote.n5">8.5 of … earth 8.6] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi> </note>
            </div>

              
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the address; CD was at Bassett, Southampton, from 27 April to 13 May 1878 (CD’s ‘Journal’ (Appendix II)).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The enclosure has not been found, but was evidently a list of seeds that CD wanted for his experimental work on the movement of cotyledons (seed-leaves). <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> was director of the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (Thiselton-Dyer was assistant director).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><hi rend="italic">Cissus</hi> is the genus of treebind; <hi rend="italic">Bignonia</hi> is a genus of vines. The Veitch nursery had often provided CD with plants for his experimental work. </note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3058.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Richard Irwin Lynch</ref> was foreman of the propagating department at Kew. He had provided CD with several plant specimens for his experimental work on plant movement, as well as performing some experiments for CD (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, letters from R. I. Lynch, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11070.xml">25 July 1877</ref> and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11118.xml">first</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11117.xml">second</ref> letters of [before 28 July 1877]. Cacteae (a synonym of Cactaceae) is the family of cacti; <hi rend="italic">Cycas</hi> is the only extant genus of the family Cycadaceae, a very ancient group of trees. CD had been sent seeds of <hi rend="italic">Cycas</hi> in November 1877 and February 1878 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 25, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11229.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 8 November [1877]</ref>, and this volume, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-11380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 28 [February 1878]</ref>). According to the <hi rend="italic">Outwards book</hi> (Archives, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew), CD was sent seedlings of <hi rend="italic">Cycas pectinata</hi> on 16 May 1878.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4143.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Julius Sachs</ref> had examined the movement of plant roots, in particular of the radical, or embryonic root, in ‘Ueber das Wachsthum der Haupt- und Nebenwurzeln’ (On the growth of primary and adventitious roots; <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_10400.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Sachs 1873–4</ref>). Many of his experiments were performed with <hi rend="italic">Vicia faba</hi> (broad or fava bean). CD also used <hi rend="italic">V. faba</hi> for many of his experiments on the movement of the radicle, later published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Thiselton-Dyer’s wife, Harriet Anne, had given birth to their first child, Frances Harriet, on 9 April 1878 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_117.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Allan 1967</ref> s.v. ‘Hooker pedigree’).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">An article in <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 4 May 1878, p. 6, commented on the first of five lectures on vegetable morphology given by Thiselton-Dyer at the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_7845.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Royal Institution of Great Britain</ref>; the first lecture was on 30 April 1878. Thiselton-Dyer had reportedly said that light paralysed the protoplasm, making cells unyielding; the shaded side thus grew more readily, resulting in a bending toward the light.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">CD devoted a chapter of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5637.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Movement in plants</hi></ref> to a discussion of the sensitivity of the apex of the radicle (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 129–200).</note>
        </div>    
        
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>