<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2599">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Asa Gray   24 December [1859]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">3528</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2599 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2599.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2599.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">6pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 153: 162</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>HRS, no. 18;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 1: 455</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 445</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance" resp="#mjhawkins" cert="high">Archives of the Gray Herbarium, Harvard University (46)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_156.xml">Harvard Gray Herbarium</repository>
                    <idno>46</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1859-12-24">24 Dec [1859]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Thanks for AG’s Japan memoir [<hi rend="italic">Mem. Am. Acad. Arts &amp; Sci.</hi> 6 (1857–9): 377–452]. Does not think AG’s arguments for a warm post-glacial period are sufficient, but will not be sorry to be proved wrong.</p> 
            <p>Believes natural selection explains many classes of facts which repeated creation does not.</p> 
<p>Writes of some responses to the <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">post-glacial</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Mem. Am. Acad. Arts &amp; Sci.</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">Japan</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Gray, Asa 1858–1859</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">creationism, religion</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#asa_gray_set">Asa Gray Letters</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Dec. 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>My dear Gray</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
<p>I have been for 10 weeks at Water Cure &amp; on my return a fortnight ago through London I found a copy of your Memoir, &amp; heartily do I thank you for it.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I have not read it, &amp; shall not be able very soon, for I am much overworked &amp; my stomach has got nearly as bad as ever.</p>
<p>With respect to the discussion on climate, I beg you to believe that I never put myself for a moment in competition with Dana; but when one has thought on subject, one cannot avoid forming some opinion.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> What I wrote to Hooker I forget, after reading only a few sheets of your memoir, which I saw would be full of interest to me.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Hooker asked me to write to you, but as I told him, I would not presume to express an opinion to you without careful deliberation. What he wrote I know not.— I had previously several years ago seen (by whom I forget) some speculation on warmer period in U. States <hi rend="underline">subsequent</hi> to Glacial period; &amp; I had consulted Lyell who seemed much to doubt, &amp; Lyell’s judgment is really admirably cautious.— The arguments advanced in your paper &amp; in your letter seem to me hardly sufficient; not that I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be at all sorry to admit this subsequent &amp; intercalated warmer period—the more changes the merrier I think.—</p>
<p>On the other hand I do not believe that introduction of Old world forms into New world <hi rend="underline">subsequent</hi> to Glacial period will do for the modified or representative forms in the Two Worlds; there has been too much change in comparison with the little change of isolated Alpine forms; but you will see this in my Book.—</p>
<p>I may just make a few remarks, why at first sight I do not attach much weight to the argument in your letter about the warmer climate. Firstly about the level of the land having been lower subsequently to Glacial period, as evidenced by the whole &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> I doubt whether metereological knowledge is sufficient for this deduction: turning to the S. hemisphere it might be argued that a greater extent of water made the temperature lower. And when much of the northern land was lower, it would have been covered by the sea &amp; intermigration between old &amp; new worlds would have been checked. Secondly I doubt whether any inference on nature of climate can be deduced from extinct species of Mammals. If the musk-ox &amp; deer of great size of your Barren Grounds had been known only by fossil bones, who would have ventured to surmise the excessively cold climate they lived under. With respect to food of large animals, if you care about the subject, will you turn to my discussion on this subject partly in respect to the Elephas primigenius in my Journal of Researches (Murray’s Home &amp; Colonial Library) Ch V. p. 85.— In this country we infer from remains of Elephas primegenius, that the climate at the period of its embedment was very severe, as seems countenanced by its woolly covering,—by the nature of the deposit with <hi rend="underline">angular</hi> fragments,—the nature of the coembedded shells, &amp; coexistence of the Musk Ox. I had formerly gathered from Lyell that the relative position of Megatherium &amp; Mylodon with respect to the Glacial deposits, had not been well made out; but perhaps it has been so recently.— Such are my reasons for not as yet admitting the warmer period subsequent to Glacial epoch; but I daresay I may be quite wrong, &amp; shall not be at all sorry to be proved so.—</p>
<p>I shall assuredly read your Essay with care, for I have seen as yet only a fragment; &amp; very likely some parts, which I could not formerly clearly understand, will be clear enough.— And I am very sorry that Hooker said a word about my opinion.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>I have been much interested by all that you say in early part of letter about “Creation” &amp; the philosophy of the subject. As you truly remark, if one admits a certain amount of creation there is no obvious reason why not admit many acts.— But I rest on the fact that the theory of Natural selection explains many classes of facts, which, as far as we can see, repeated acts of Creation do not explain. On this latter view we can only say “so it is” &amp; not at all “why it is so”.— Pray do not decide either way till you have read Ch. XIII &amp; the Recapitulation (Ch XIV) which will, I think, aid you in balancing facts.— I value your opinion most highly; &amp; I hope you will not think me presumptuous in saying how sincerely I have admired your several letters to me &amp; some to Hooker which I have occasionally read. I am rejoiced to say that Lyell is a complete convert; &amp; is heroic &amp; candid enough to be now writing a public change of opinion.— Huxley, a first-rate zoologist, &amp; Carpenter first-rate physiologist are converts; as is H. C. Watson. So that I am more than contented. I am <hi rend="underline">sure</hi> to be in error in many parts; but my general view, I conclude, must have some truth in it.— There are however many <hi rend="underline">bitter</hi> opponents. I sent the copy of my Book through Murray. I had written out the Forbesian doctrine of Alpine plants 4 years before Forbes published, as Hooker knew, but I do not believe that Forbes had ever heard of it: so he is originator, as you will see in my Book, I do not allude to my prior work in M.S.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>My dear Gray | Yours most sincerely | C. Darwin</p>
<p>Murray writes he sent my Book by Steamer Dec 3. &amp; has now sent off clean sheets of the Reprint, as much as is yet printed.<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 got] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘so soon’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">2.6 opinion to you] ‘to you’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">2.7 several years ago] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.11 this subsequent … period 2.12] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">3.1 Old] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘old’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">3.2 New] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘new’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.2 period] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.2 do for] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘not in my opinion’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.3 the little … isolated 3.4] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">3.4 isolated] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘the’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">4.7 would] <hi rend="italic">after omitted point</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n12">4.7 have been covered] ‘have’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n13">4.7 been covered] ‘en’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n14">4.8 have been checked] ‘have’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n15">4.8 been checked] ‘en’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n16">4.12 the subject] ‘the’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n17">4.13 partly … primigenius] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n18">4.16 very] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n19">4.17 with <hi rend="italic">angular</hi> fragments] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n20">4.18 coembedded] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n21">5.2 formerly] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n22">5.4 opinion—] <hi rend="italic">full stop over comma</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n23">6.3 why] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘by’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n24">6.7 either way] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n25">6.7 (Ch XIV)] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n26">6.15 however] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n27">6.18 believe] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘suppose’</note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the relationship to the letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Asa Gray</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2592.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">21 December [1859]</ref>, and to John Murray,22 December [1859].</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1858–9</ref>. There is an annotated copy of the paper in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The point at issue was whether there was sufficient geological evidence to indicate that there had been a warm period <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the glacial era as well as <hi rend="italic">before</hi>. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1190.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Dwight Dana</ref> believed that there were clear signs of a post-glacial warm period, and Gray used this information to explain the apparent mingling of Arctic and northern floras (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1858–9</ref>, p. 447). CD had discussed the point with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> (<ref target="./DCP-LETT-2461.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 11 May [1859]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2589.xml" resp="#automat">letter from J. D. Hooker,[20 December 1859]</ref>), and with Gray (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2321.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 11 August [1858]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Hooker had sent CD the concluding section of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1858–9</ref>, which discussed the geological evidence that possibly explained the relation between the flora of Japan and that of the north-eastern region of the United States. CD had also read the preliminary remarks that Gray had made at a meeting of the <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">American Academy of Arts and Sciences</ref> in Boston in January 1859 (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2457.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 3 May [1859]</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1859</ref>, pp. 447–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In a <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter to Asa Gray, 31 May 1859</ref> (Gray Herbarium, Harvard University), Hooker praised <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3015.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1859</ref> but stated: ‘Your Geological distribution we cannot follow at all, &amp; Darwin &amp; I both doubt your Geological facts, especially the Zoological Palæontology.’ See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2610.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 28 [December 1859]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2321.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 11 August [1858]</ref>, CD outlined his views on a former worldwide cold-period, mentioning that he had written these out four years before a similar theory was published by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1680.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Forbes</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2580.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Forbes 1846</ref>). Gray had taken this to mean that CD was the originator of the theory and implied this in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">A. Gray 1858–9</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See letters to John Murray, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2594.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">22 December [1859]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2597.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">24 December [1859]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>