<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-7141">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From F. C. Donders<choice><seg type="original"><ref target="#foot.f1"/></seg><seg type="translation"><ref target="#foot_trans.f1"/></seg></choice>   17 May 1870</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">16766</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2010">2010</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-7141 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7141.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-7141.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp (French)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 162: 224</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>162: 224</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1354.xml">Donders, F. C.</persName>
                <placeName>Utrecht</placeName>
                <date when="1870-05-17">17 May 1870</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>The illness and death of his daughter have delayed his answers to CD’s queries. He has, however, worked on the circulation of the eye and has almost finished a paper on it, which he will send to CD. In general, the views of Charles Bell are confirmed.</p>
            <p>As for CD’s second query, he doubts that the relationship exists, but will answer fully in next letter.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">Donders, F. C.’s daughter</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Utrecht,</placeName>
                    <date>17 Mai | 1870</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Je sens maintenant que j’aurais dû vous donner la triste nouvelle de la perte de notre fille, notre unique enfant, l’objet et le centre de notre vie, notre bonheur et notre espoir. Elle est décedée le 5 du mois de Mars, 5 Jours seulement après avoir donné la vie à deux enfans, qui, quoique bien faibles, lui ont survécu jusqu’ici.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Nous vivons dans une tristesse qui semble ne pouvoir plus finir, et autant que mon gendre bien-aimé, le Docteur Engelmann,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> J’ai eu de la peine à rentrer dans le laboratoire et à vaquer à nos occupations. Déjà dans les deux derniers mois de la grossesse, notre fille était téllement souffrante, que nous vivions dans une inquiétude continuelle. Sans cela le petit travail que vous m’aviez fait l’honneur de me confièr, aurait été terminé depuis long-temps. Pourtant je venais justement d’y remettre la main, et vous le recevrez dans peu de jours. J’ai examiné avec quelque soin la circulation de l’oeil, et il ne me faut qu’un peu de disposition pour finir ma note à ce sujet que je desire publier dans mon Journal: en général je crois pouvoir confirmer les vues de Sir Charles Bell.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Le Docteur Moore<ref target="#foot.f5"/> vous enverra la traduction anglaise de cet article. Quant à l’autre question, je ne pense pas que le rapport supposé existe.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> Dans ma lettre suivante, je formulerai ma reponse. Soyez sûr de l’avoir en mains dans 8 Jours après la reception de celle-ci, et avant ce temps Mr. Moore aura reçu un exemplaire imprimé de mon article sur la première question.</p>
<p>Veuillez agréer l’assurance de mon respect et de mon affection, | Dear Sir, | Votre bien devoué | Donders</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="translation">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Utrecht,</placeName>
                    <date>17 May | 1870</date>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I now feel that I ought to have given you the sad news of the loss of our daughter, our only child, the object and the centre of our life, our happiness and our hope. She died on 5th March, just 5 Days after having given birth to two babies, who, though very weak, have survived her up to now.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> We are living with a sorrow which it seems can never end, and just like my much-loved son-in-law, Doctor Engelmann,<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I have found it hard to return to the laboratory and to attend to our occupations. In the last two months of her pregnancy, our daughter was already suffering so much that we lived in constant apprehension. But for this the small piece of work you did me the honour of confiding to me, would have been finished long since. However, I have just turned my hand to it once more, and you will have it in a few days. I have examined the circulation of the eye with some care, and all I am lacking is the inclination to finish my note on this subject, which I want to publish in my Journal: in general I believe I can confirm the views of Sir Charles Bell.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Doctor Moore<ref target="#foot.f5"/> will send you the English translation of this article. As for the other question, I don’t think that the supposed relationship exists.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> In my next letter, I shall formulate my reply. You may be certain of having it in hand within a week of receiving this one, and by then Mr. Moore will have received a printed copy of my article on the first question.</p>
<p>Please accept the assurance of my respect and affection, | Dear Sir, | Your most devoted | Donders</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For a translation of this letter, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 18, Appendix I.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot_trans.f1">For a transcription of this letter in its original French, see p. 121.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Donders’s daughter was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5605.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Marie Engelmann</ref>; his wife was Ernestine J. A. Donders. The two babies were <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5604.xml">Frans</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5606.xml">Paula Engelmann</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1512.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Theodor Wilhelm Engelmann</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD had asked Donders questions about the contraction of the muscles around the eye, and about <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_373.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Charles Bell’s</ref> account of the physiology of weeping (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7187.xml" resp="#automat">letter to F. C. Donders, 13 May [1870]</ref> and n. 2). Donders refers to the <hi rend="italic">Nederlandsch Lancet</hi>, of which he was editor (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2160.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DSB</hi></ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_6373.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Daniel Moore</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Donders refers to CD’s query regarding the possibility of contraction of the muscles around the eyes producing tears (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-7187.xml" resp="#automat">letter to F. C. Donders, 13 May [1870]</ref>, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 17, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6878.xml" resp="#automat">letter to F. C. Donders, 6 September 1869</ref> and n. 3).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>