<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-6048">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Edward Blyth   [before 25 March 1868]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1485</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-6048 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6048.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-6048.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="16">16</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="description">Amem</note>
            <note type="physdesc">Amem 4pp †</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 83: 154–5, DAR 84.1: 131–3, DAR 48: A77, DAR 84.2: 187v</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>83: 154–5,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>84.1: 131–3,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>48: A77,</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>84.2: 187v</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_498.xml">Blyth, Edward</persName>
                <placeName>unstated</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1809-01-01" notAfter="1868-03-24">[before 25 Mar 1868]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Detailed notes on secondary sexual differences in various species of birds and mammals.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">birds</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">mammals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">information, data, scientific description</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">sex differences</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="doubleUnderline">Melanism</hi>. Among mammalia, perhaps peculiar (or nearly so) to the male sex in <hi rend="underline">Felinæ</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f2"/> but not so in wolves and jackals. In some <hi rend="underline">Marsupiata</hi>, as <hi rend="underline">Phalangista</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Phascolomys</hi>, apparently peculiar to the males, doubtfully so in the spotted <hi rend="underline">Dasyuri</hi>, which latter should be seen to.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> Among the sheath-horned ruminants, the deep black colour of this male of the Indian antelope (<hi rend="underline">Cervicapra bezoartica</hi>) is peculiar to the rutting season, and disappears more or less afterwards. In castrated individuals of the Indian antelope, probably the Sable antelope (<hi rend="underline">Ægoceros niger</hi>), certainly the nil-gai, and the banteng (<hi rend="underline">Bos sondaicus</hi>), the colour remains as in the female;<ref target="#foot.f4"/> &amp; Raffles remarks (in his History of Java) that in a castrated banteng the colour <hi rend="underline">reverts</hi> to that of the female.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> In the nil-gai, the bluish-grey of the adult male is analogous; and I believe that <hi rend="underline">Ant. leucophæa</hi>, auct. (supposed by some to have been extirpated) is merely the <hi rend="underline">Ægoceros equinus</hi>, auct., in corresponding phase of colouring.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> <hi rend="underline">N.B.</hi> The castrated nil-gai has small and slender horns, which are wanting in the females, and the castrated Indian antelope has horns like those which are very rarely developed in the female sex, being <hi rend="underline">not spirally twisted</hi> (as in the entire males, but gyring round to the front with a tendency outwards.</p>
<figure rend="blockCentred width20">
    <graphic url="../images/DCP-LETT-6048.svg"/>
</figure>
<p rend="left">They are longer and thicker than those which do sometimes occur in the female sex.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">N.B.</hi> I cannot recal any instance in which the female sex undergoes a seasonal change of colouring among the mammalia. The Indian antelope is a strongly marked instance in the other sex, analogous to that observed in both sexes among the plovers and sandpipers in the bird class, black tern, &amp;c. In the <hi rend="underline">Gallicrex cristatus</hi>,<ref target="#foot.f7"/> the change in the males only is analogous to that of the Indian antelope.</p>
<p>Among wild birds, cases of true melanism are rare. The <hi rend="underline">Corvus corone</hi> would seem to be no other than a permanent melanous race of <hi rend="underline">C. cornix</hi>, &amp; the familiar black crow of the Indo-China countries &amp; of Ceylon to be an analogous race of the Indian <hi rend="underline">C. splendens</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f8"/> In certain <hi rend="underline">Falconidæ</hi>, one or both sexes become black with full maturity, as <hi rend="underline">Spizaëtus limnäetus</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Buteo sancti-Johannis</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Astur melanoleucos</hi>(?), and <hi rend="underline">Circus maurus</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f9"/> In the first-mentioned I am tolerably sure that both sexes become ultimately black.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> In the yellow orioles, both sexes are alike when fully mature, except that there is a slight greenish cast upon the back of the females, but the latter are slower in attaining this phase of plumage, probably not till the second or third moult.<ref target="#foot.f11"/> The same, I think, is the case with <hi rend="underline">Lanius rufus</hi>, and more rarely with <hi rend="underline">L. collurio</hi>, in which I have dissected a fertile female in the plumage generally considered to be peculiar to the male.<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Ditto in a hen common linnet, which had crimson poll and breast.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> Many black birds have brown or chestnut females, <hi rend="underline">e.g.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Turdus merula</hi> &amp; kindred species, the <hi rend="underline">Copsychi</hi> (more or less so), <hi rend="underline">Saxicola opistholeuca</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Pratincola caprata</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Thamnobia fulicata</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Campephaga aterrima</hi>, &amp;c.<ref target="#foot.f14"/> The American Thamnophilinae have generally black or very dark ashy males &amp; rufous females.<ref target="#foot.f15"/> <hi rend="underline">Tetreo tetrix</hi> the different Kallij pheasants, <hi rend="underline">Rollulus niger</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Struthio camelus</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> In certain Hornbills, as <hi rend="underline">Buceros nipalensis</hi>, <hi rend="underline">B. plicatus</hi>, &amp;c., and in the small fire-back pheasants (<hi rend="underline">Euplocamus erythropthalmus</hi> &amp; its Bornean congener), the female is wholly black, while the male is otherwise coloured; but this is the usual rule of brighter colours in the male sex, reversed in <hi rend="underline">Rhynchæa</hi> &amp; one or two other instances.<ref target="#foot.f17"/> Among the <hi rend="underline">Picariæ</hi>, or non-passerine Insessores, difference of plumage in the sexes is rare, but we get it in several hornbills, trogons, <hi rend="italic">[illeg]</hi> slightly in most woodpeckers (very strongly in <hi rend="underline">Picus validus</hi>) and in the genus <hi rend="underline">Eudynamis</hi> among the parasitic cuckoos, wherein the males are black &amp; the females speckled.<ref target="#foot.f18"/> In some of the hornbills, as <hi rend="underline">B. cavatus</hi>, the male has a crimson iris, the female a white iris, as in the storks of the genus <hi rend="underline">Xenorhynchus</hi> the ♂ has a black iris, in the ♀ yellow.<ref target="#foot.f19"/> Perhaps the most striking seasonal sexual distinction among birds is instanced by the whidahs (<hi rend="underline">Vidua</hi>), and the ruff perhaps next, but some few reeves have a slight development of the frill.<ref target="#foot.f20"/> Among the <hi rend="underline">Rallidæ</hi>, in the genus <hi rend="underline">Gallicrex</hi>, &amp; I think also in the weka (<hi rend="underline">Ocydromus</hi>) of New Zealand, the males only become deeply tinged with dark ashy (by a change of colour in the same feathers) during the breeding season, analogous to the black in the males of the Indian antelope.<ref target="#foot.f21"/> Among the <hi rend="underline">Anatidæ</hi> we have several black males &amp; br〈own〉 females, as notably the scoters (<hi rend="underline">Oidemia</hi>).<ref target="#foot.f22"/> Sexual diversity of colouring is not usual among parrots, but occurs in the <hi rend="underline">Platycercinæ</hi>, in <hi rend="underline">Palæornis</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Psittacula</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Loriculus</hi>, and among the black cockatoos.<ref target="#foot.f23"/> Among pigeons, chiefly with the fruit-eaters, <hi rend="underline">Treron</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Ptilinopus</hi>, but a striking instance occurs in <hi rend="underline">Turtur humilis</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f24"/> The female exceeds the male in size in the <hi rend="underline">Falconidæ</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Strigidæ</hi>, the Cassowaries, <hi rend="underline">Apteryx</hi>, Cariama, &amp; in the snipe and plover series (with the exception of the ruff).<ref target="#foot.f25"/> In the cranes, &amp; in the herons, storks, &amp; ibises, the male is larger. In <hi rend="doubleUnderline">some</hi> <hi rend="underline">Turnices</hi> (as <hi rend="underline">T. luzoniensis</hi>, <hi rend="underline">T. pugnax</hi>), the female is larger, &amp; is distinguished by more or less of black on the throat and breast, &amp; in these the males are said to incubate;<ref target="#foot.f26"/> the same is probable of <hi rend="underline">Rhynchæa</hi>, &amp; certain of the cursorial birds, inclusive of <hi rend="underline">Apteryx</hi> and also <hi rend="underline">Tinamus</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f27"/> In the bustards, some have the males much larger, as <hi rend="underline">Otis tarda</hi>, &amp; the <hi rend="underline">Eupodotis</hi> group, &amp; these appear to be polygamous (like the ruff, and doubtless the <hi rend="underline">Gallicrex</hi> among the <hi rend="underline">Rallidæ</hi> the ♂ of which is <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> larger than the ♀). In <hi rend="underline">O. tetrax</hi> the sexes are alike in size, but the male only is adorned during the breeding season.<ref target="#foot.f28"/> In the houbaras, I believe that both sexes are adorned, &amp; they are of about the same size. In the florikens (<hi rend="underline">Sypheotides</hi>) the female is larger, &amp; the male only is adorned in the breeding season, while the sexual intercourse would appear to be indiscriminate.<ref target="#foot.f29"/> There is thus remarkable variation in the different forms of bustard. In <hi rend="underline">Vulturidæ</hi>, &amp; I think also <hi rend="underline">Polyboridæ</hi>, the males are larger.<ref target="#foot.f30"/> In annulose animals generally the females are larger, but exceptions occur in <hi rend="underline">Lucanus</hi> among the <hi rend="underline">Coleoptera</hi>, &amp; in various crabs and prawns (as notably in the large Indian <hi rend="underline">Palæmon carcinus</hi>).<ref target="#foot.f31"/> I do not remember any mammal in which the female is larger, but there are instances both ways in <hi rend="underline">Reptilia</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Pisces</hi>.</p>
<p>The only secondary sexual distinctions which I can think of among the <hi rend="underline">Primates</hi>, besides the beard &amp;c in man, is that also of the orangutan, which again has much more formidable canines in the male sex. In some of the lemurs, the sexes are so different as to have been regarded as different species. Thus <hi rend="underline">L. leucomystax</hi> is the female of <hi rend="underline">L. nigrifrons</hi>, and again the black <hi rend="underline">L. niger</hi> has a brown female. In <hi rend="underline">L. catta</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">L. macaco</hi> the sexes are quite similar in colouring.<ref target="#foot.f32"/> In birds I know of no other case like that of <hi rend="underline">Passer montanus</hi>, in which the young, as well as the adults of both Sexes, are clad in a plumage analogous to that characteristic of the adult male only of <hi rend="underline">P. domesticus</hi>, while in other sparrows, as <hi rend="underline">P. petronius</hi>, <hi rend="underline">P. flavicollis</hi>, &amp;c, both sexes retain the colouring analogous to that of the female and young of <hi rend="underline">P. domesticus</hi>.<ref target="#foot.f33"/> In <hi rend="underline">Rhynchea</hi> the young have the less brightly coloured plumage of the adult <hi rend="underline">male</hi>. In <hi rend="underline">Rhynchea</hi> it is also most remarkable that the female only of <hi rend="underline">R. australis</hi> should have the excessively elongated trachea described by Gould, while the female of the (hardly distinguishable externally) <hi rend="underline">R. bengalensis</hi> (few <hi rend="underline">capensis</hi>)) has no elongation of the trachea whatever.<ref target="#foot.f34"/> In <hi rend="underline">Platalea leucorodia</hi> the figure of 8 convolution of the trachea described by Yarrell is not of constant occurrence.<ref target="#foot.f35"/></p>
<p>—Have you anywhere worked in the fact that <hi rend="underline">Palamedea</hi> is a goose, in which the web to the toes has quite disappeared? The semipalmate goose (<hi rend="underline">Anseranas melanoleuca</hi>) makes a distinct approach to <hi rend="underline">Palamedea</hi> in the peculiar shape of the bill as well as in the reduced palmature of the toes.<ref target="#foot.f36"/> <hi rend="underline">Phœnicopterus</hi> is another most extraordinary modification of the goose type.—<ref target="#foot.f37"/></p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.1 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">Melanism.</hi> … colouring. 1.12] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.4 black colour 1.5] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>1.10 bluish-grey] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>2.1 <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> … antelope. 2.5] <hi rend="italic">scored and crossed blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.1 The … <hi rend="italic">maurus</hi>. 3.5] <hi rend="italic">crossed blue crayon</hi>; ‘Birds’ <hi rend="italic">added above blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.8 but … moult. 3.9] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.24 the parasitic cuckoos] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.24 the males … speckled.] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.28 (<hi rend="italic">Vidua</hi>)] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.28 ruff perhaps next] <hi rend="italic">underl blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.37 The female exceeds … series 3.38] <hi rend="italic">scored red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.38 snipe and plover] <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.38 In the cranes, … larger 3.39] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.39 <hi rend="doubleUnderline">some</hi> <hi rend="italic">Turnices</hi>] ‘<hi rend="italic">Turnices</hi>’ <hi rend="italic">underl red crayon</hi>; ‘Turnices’ <hi rend="italic">added below blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.43 In the bustards, … ♀ 3.45] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.45 <hi rend="italic">O. tetrax</hi>] ‘Otis’ <hi rend="italic">added below blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.48 In the florikens] <hi rend="italic">after cross red crayon</hi>; ‘see QQQQ QQQQ class’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
                <note>3.48 the female … indiscriminate 3.49] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.50 forms of bustard. ] ‘Bustard’ <hi rend="italic">added below blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>3.51 In annulose] <hi rend="italic">after opening square bracket blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.3 In some … colouring. 4.6] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.7 as well] ‘CC’ <hi rend="italic">added and del blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.8 clad] ‘clad’ <hi rend="italic">added blue crayon</hi></note>
                <note>4.14 In … occurrence.— 4.16] <hi rend="italic">scored blue crayon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">crossed pencil</hi>, ‘2’ <hi rend="italic">added and circled pencil</hi></note>
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Blyth sexual selection mammals’ <hi rend="italic">blue crayon</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The date is established by the relationship between this memorandum and the letters to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Blyth</ref>, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6049.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">25 March [1868]</ref> and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-6091.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">4 April [1868]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Felinae is a subfamily of the family Felidae and includes all but the big cats.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Marsupiata was the subclass of Mammalia now called Marsupiala. Blyth also refers to <hi rend="italic">Phalangista</hi>, formerly a genus of possums, to <hi rend="italic">Phascolomys</hi>, formerly a genus of wombats, and to <hi rend="italic">Dasyurus</hi>, a genus of quoll. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 294, CD mentioned black varieties of wombat and ‘vulpine phalanger’, but cited <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_300.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Abraham Dee Bartlett</ref> for the information.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Hollow-horned or sheath-horned ruminants such as antelope have horns made of a permanent bony inner layer covered with an outer layer of keratin; these horns are never shed. Solid-horned ruminants such as deer have antlers made entirely of bone and shed their horns annually. <hi rend="italic">Cervicapra bezoartica</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Antilope bezoartica</hi>, is now <hi rend="italic">Antilope cervicapra</hi> (blackbuck). <hi rend="italic">Aegoceros niger</hi>, a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Antilope niger</hi>, is now <hi rend="italic">Hippotragus niger.</hi> The nilgai is <hi rend="italic">Boselaphus tragocamelus</hi> and the banteng is now <hi rend="italic">Bos javanicus.</hi> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 288–9, CD cited Blyth for information on colour in <hi rend="italic">Antilope bezoartica</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A. niger.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6505.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raffles 1817</ref>, 1: 111, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3916.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Thomas Stamford Bingley Raffles</ref> states that the banteng after castration invariably becomes red in colour. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 289, CD discussed colour in the banteng and colour reversion in castrated bulls.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><hi rend="italic">Antilope leucophaea</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Hippotragus leucophaeus</hi>, the blue antelope or bluebuck) probably became extinct around 1800 (see Lichtenstein 1811, 1: 265). Blyth evidently believed it to be a colour variant of <hi rend="italic">Aegoceros equinus</hi>; the name does not appear to have been published but probably refers to <hi rend="italic">Hippotragus equinus</hi>, the roan antelope. In a letter of 24 February 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15), Blyth made a similar claim about the identity of the two species, incorrectly referring to the former as <hi rend="italic">Aigoceros leucophaeus.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7"><hi rend="italic">Gallicrex cristatus</hi>, the watercock, is now <hi rend="italic">Gallicrex cinerea.</hi> For more on the change in colour in the male, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Blyth, 24 February 1867</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The hooded crow, <hi rend="italic">Corvus cornix</hi>, is now considered to be a separate species, although once considered a subspecies of <hi rend="italic">C. corone</hi> (the carrion crow; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1450.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clements 2000</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Corvus splendens</hi>, the house crow, has a number of subspecies (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1450.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clements 2000</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9"><hi rend="italic">Spizaetus limnaetus</hi>is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Nisaetus cirrhatus</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">limnaeetus</hi>, the changeable hawk-eagle. <hi rend="italic">Buteo sancti-johannis</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Buteo lagopus</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">sanctijohannis</hi>, the rough-legged hawk. Blyth’s <hi rend="italic">Astur melanoleucos</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Accipiter melanoleucus</hi>, the black goshawk. The genus <hi rend="italic">Astur</hi> (goshawks; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 2: 377) no longer exists; goshawks are now included in the genus <hi rend="italic">Accipiter</hi> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1450.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Clements 2000</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Circus maurus</hi> is the black harrier.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10"><hi rend="italic">Spizaetus limnaetus</hi> has a dark form. For more on plumage variations in the species, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_651.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Birds of the world</hi></ref> 2: 203.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">The yellow auriole is <hi rend="italic">Icterus nigrogularis.</hi> For more on plumage variations, see Hilty and Brown 1986.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">For more on colour dimorphism in the sexes of <hi rend="italic">Lanius rufus</hi>, the woodchat shrike, and <hi rend="italic">L. collurio</hi>, the red-backed shrike, see Lefranc and Worfolk 1997.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Only the male common linnet (<hi rend="italic">Linaria cannabina</hi>, referred to by CD in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_7951.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Variation</hi></ref> 2: 158 as <hi rend="italic">Linota cannabina</hi>) normally has the red colouring described by Blyth during the breeding season (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3113.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Greenoak 1997</ref>, pp. 207–8). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 180 and n., CD cited Blyth on cases where fertile females acquired male coloration.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><hi rend="italic">Turdus merula</hi>: the blackbird. The genus <hi rend="italic">Copsychus</hi> is the genus of shamas (Indian song-birds). <hi rend="italic">Saxicola opistholeuca</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Oenanthe picata</hi>, the eastern pied wheatear. <hi rend="italic">Pratincola caprata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Saxicola caprata</hi>, the pied bushchat. <hi rend="italic">Thamnobia fulicata</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Saxicoloides fulicatus</hi>, the Indian robin. <hi rend="italic">Campephaga aterrima</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">C. flava</hi>, the black cuckoo-shrike.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">The Thamnophilinae (bush-shrikes) previously formed a subfamily of the family Formicariidæ, ant-thrushes (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 1: 20). It is now a separate family, Thamnophilidae (antbirds). Blyth added this sentence along the left margin.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16"><hi rend="italic">Tetrao tetrix</hi> is the black grouse. ‘Kalij’ was a name applied to several pheasants of the genus <hi rend="italic">Euplocamus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gallophasis</hi> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 2: 476). It now refers to the species <hi rend="italic">Lophura leucomelanos</hi>, which has several subspecies. Blyth’s <hi rend="italic">Rollulus niger</hi> is probably <hi rend="italic">Rollulus rouloul</hi>, the crested partridge. <hi rend="italic">Struthio camelus</hi> is the ostrich.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17"><hi rend="italic">Buceros nipalensis</hi> (the rufous-necked hornbill) is now <hi rend="italic">Aceros nipalensis</hi>; <hi rend="italic">B. plicatus</hi> (Blyth’s hornbill) is now <hi rend="italic">A. plicatus.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Euplocamus erythropthalmus</hi> (the crestless fireback pheasant, now <hi rend="italic">Lophura erythropthalma</hi>), has a Bornean subspecies. The genus <hi rend="italic">Rhynchaea</hi> (painted snipes) is now called <hi rend="italic">Rostratula.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f18">The former order Picariae is roughly equivalent to the modern order Coraciiformes. Insessores: ‘The Perchers or Perching birds, having feet with three toes in front and one behind, adapted for perching on trees; the name given by Vigors in 1823 to the second Order of Birds in his classification, coinciding nearly with the Passeres and Picæ of Linnæus’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5936.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi></ref>). <hi rend="italic">Picus validus</hi> (the orange-backed woodpecker) is now <hi rend="italic">Reinwardtipicus validus.</hi> The genus <hi rend="italic">Eudynamis</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Eudynamys.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f19"><hi rend="italic">Buceros cavatus</hi> (the great hornbill) is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">B. bicornis cavatus</hi>. The stork genus <hi rend="italic">Xenorhynchus</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Ephippiorhynchus</hi>; in <hi rend="italic">E. asiaticus</hi> (the black-necked stork) males have dark brown eyes while females have yellow eyes (see Grimmett <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1998). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 129, CD cited Blyth for information on iris colour in <hi rend="italic">B. bicornis</hi> and also mentioned colour differences in <hi rend="italic">Xenorhynchus.</hi> Blyth used an upside-down female symbol instead of a male symbol.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f20">Males of the genus <hi rend="italic">Vidua</hi> (indigo-birds or whydahs) grow elongated tail feathers during the breeding season. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 181, CD mentioned plumage changes in <hi rend="italic">Vidua</hi>. The ruff and reeve are the common names of the male and female respectively of <hi rend="italic">Machetes pugnax</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Philomachus pugnax</hi>). CD discussed the plumage variations in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 41–2, 81.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f21">The family Rallidae are rails and crakes; the weka was <hi rend="italic">Ocydromus australis</hi>, and is now <hi rend="italic">Gallirallus australis</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f22">The genus <hi rend="italic">Oedemia</hi> (scoters; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 3: 818), in the family Anatidae, is now <hi rend="italic">Melanitta.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f23">Platycercinae are broad-tailed parrots. The genus <hi rend="italic">Palaeornis</hi> is now subsumed within the genus <hi rend="italic">Psittacula</hi> (rose-ringed parakeets). <hi rend="italic">Loriculus</hi> is the genus of hanging parrots; black cockatoos belong to the genus <hi rend="italic">Calyptorhynchus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f24"><hi rend="italic">Treron</hi> is the genus of green-pigeons; <hi rend="italic">Ptilinopus</hi> is the genus of fruit doves; <hi rend="italic">Turtur humilis</hi> is the red collared-dove, now <hi rend="italic">Streptopelia tranquebarica</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f25">Falconidae are falcons; Strigidae, owls. Cassowaries: <hi rend="italic">Casuarius</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Apteryx</hi>: kiwis; <hi rend="italic">Cariama</hi>: seriemas, crane-like South American birds. Blyth probably refers to the former order Grallae or Grallatores, which included snipes and plovers (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 2: 379–80). These birds are now placed in the order Ciconiiformes, (or sometimes Charadriiformes), with snipes in the family Scolopacidae and plovers in the family Charadriidae.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f26"><hi rend="italic">Turnix</hi> is the genus of button quails. Blyth’s <hi rend="italic">T. luzoniensis</hi> is probably <hi rend="italic">T. ocellata</hi> (the spotted button quail; see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5941.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ogilvie-Grant 1893</ref>, p. 548). <hi rend="italic">Turnix pugnax</hi> (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">T. taigoor</hi>) is now a subspecies of <hi rend="italic">T. suscitator</hi> (the barred button quail). For more on the breeding habits of this genus, see Johnsgard 1991, pp. 41–2, 103. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 201, CD discussed the plumage of <hi rend="italic">T. taigoor</hi>, but cited Blyth only concerning juvenile plumage.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f27">The tinamou (<hi rend="italic">Tinamus</hi>) is a partridge-like South American bird.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f28">In <hi rend="italic">Otis tarda</hi>, the great bustard, the average weight of the males can be three times that of the females (Johnsgard 1991, p. 127). Size differences in the sexes of species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Eupodotis</hi> are not nearly as great (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 169–202). <hi rend="italic">Otis tetrax</hi>, the little bustard, is now <hi rend="italic">Tetrax tetrax</hi> (for sexual differences in this species, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 117–19). Blyth used an upside-down female symbol instead of a male symbol in this text.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f29">The houbara bustard is now <hi rend="italic">Chlamydotis undulata</hi>. There are two species of florican: <hi rend="italic">Houbaropsis bengalensis</hi>, the Bengal florican, and <hi rend="italic">Sypheotides indica</hi>, the lesser florican. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5418.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Edward Blyth, 24 February 1867</ref> and n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f30">The former family Vulturidae included all the old world vultures (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 4: 1016). These are now in the family Accipitridae, which also includes hawks, eagles, and kites. Caracaras were formerly placed in a separate family, Polyboridae, by some authors, but are now in the family Falconidae (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5856.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Newton 1893–6</ref>, 1: 75).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f31">The genus <hi rend="italic">Lucanus</hi> (stag beetles) is now <hi rend="italic">Pseudolucanus.</hi> The prawn species <hi rend="italic">Palaemon carcinus</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Macrobrachium rosenbergii</hi> (the giant freshwater prawn).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f32"><hi rend="italic">Lemur leucomystax</hi>, <hi rend="italic">L. niger</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">L. macaco</hi> are now classified as <hi rend="italic">Eulemur macaco</hi>, the black lemur. <hi rend="italic">Lemur nigrifrons</hi> is now <hi rend="italic">Eulemur mongoz</hi>, the mongoose lemur. <hi rend="italic">Lemur catta</hi> is the ring-tailed lemur. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 290, CD discussed colour differences in male and female <hi rend="italic">L. macaco.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f33"><hi rend="italic">Passer montanus</hi> is the Eurasian tree sparrow; <hi rend="italic">P. domesticus</hi>, the house sparrow; <hi rend="italic">P. petronia</hi> ‘petronius’ is a misspelling), the rock sparrow (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Petronia petronia</hi>); <hi rend="italic">Passer flavicollis</hi>, the jungle sparrow (a synonym of <hi rend="italic">P. pyrrhonotus</hi>). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 212, CD cited Blyth for information on plumage in sparrows.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f34"><hi rend="italic">Rhynchaea australis</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Rostratula australis</hi>, the Australian painted snipe; <hi rend="italic">R. bengalensis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">R. capensis</hi>  are synonyms of <hi rend="italic">Rostratula benghalensis</hi>, the greater painted snipe. Blyth refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Gould</ref> and to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2964.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Gould 1865</ref>, 2: 275. CD scored the passage on the trachea in his copy of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2964.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">J. Gould 1865</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi></ref> 1: 340). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 202–3, CD cited Blyth and Gould on the sexual differences in the trachea of these birds.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f35"><hi rend="italic">Platalea leucorodia</hi> is the white spoonbill; Blyth also refers to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5275.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Yarrell</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8552.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Yarrell 1845</ref>, 2: 569–70. Yarrell noted that the convolution of the trachea was not always present in younger birds. In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 2: 60 n. 46, CD cited Blyth on the convolution of the trachea in spoonbills.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f36">The genus <hi rend="italic">Palamedea</hi> (now <hi rend="italic">Anhima</hi>) has one species, <hi rend="italic">Anhima cornuta</hi>, the horned screamer. <hi rend="italic">Anseranas melanoleuca</hi>, the semipalmated goose, is now <hi rend="italic">A. semipalmata</hi>, the magpie goose). Blyth had referred to the feet of these birds in his letter of 19 February 1867 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 15).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f37"><hi rend="italic">Phoenicopterus</hi> is the genus of flamingos.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>