<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5397">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From J. V. Carus   11 February 1867</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">8689</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2006">2006</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5397 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5397.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5397.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="15">15</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp, encl 3pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 161: 55, 57</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>161: 55, 57</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_849.xml">Carus, J. V.</persName>
                <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                <date when="1867-02-11">11 Feb 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Sends CD an English translation of his preface to the revised German edition of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> and asks his opinion of it.</p>  
<p>Asks CD where he might get a specimen of <hi rend="italic">Eozoon</hi>.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">Eozoon</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">English</term>
                <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">queries / requests</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">specimens / samples</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>39, Elstertrasse, Leipzig.</placeName>
                    <date>Feb<hi rend="superscript">ry</hi> 11. 1867</date>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I hereby send you the preface (very hastily translated) which I intend to give to the new edition of the translation.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I prefer to give this instead of any other additions or notes partly from the reasons given in the very preface, partly because I don’t think the book itself the right place for any lengthy discussion.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> You would oblige me very much indeed, if you were to give me your opinion quite frankly. As I didn’t as yet send it to Stuttgart and the print of the text has scarcely begun (I saw the corrections of the three first sheets) it is plenty of time to make any alterations you should think fair or proper.<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>The chief part of the work, the revision and correction of the book is done; now it depends on Schweizerbart to bring it out quickly. I am sorry he will bring it out in parts.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But as this is a matter of business I cannot meddle with it.</p>
<p>Could you give me perhaps a direction where I could get a specimen of the Eozoon?<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
<p>Believe me | My dear Sir | yours very sincerely, | J. Victor Carus</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
        <div type="enclosure" subtype="other">
      
          <div type="transcription">
                     
<p><hi rend="underline">Preface of the editor.</hi></p>
<p>When I was asked to lead a new edition of the translation of Darwin’s book on the origin of species through the press I had first to complain that Bronn couldn’t do it himself any more. Now it was not only the piety owing to the dead which made it a duty for me to revise Bronn’s work, it was especially the conscience of deep obligation under which German Science stands to the late Bronn and which could not but be augmented by his introduction of the book on the origin of species to the public at large, that I welcomed the opportunity of continuing a task begun by him   My first aim could only be, to correct the errors and mistakes left unnoticed here and there, and above all to insert the many important additions of the author, which are to be found in the new english edition, into this German. Of these I may mention the detailed accounts of dimorphic and trimorphic plants and animals, of mimetic butterflies, of hybridism and the sterility and fertility of hybrids and first crosses, of means of transport and so on</p>
<p>A singular difficulty arose to me from the publisher’s wish to put my name on the title. As I acknowledge the great merits of Bronn’s heartily and without any reserve, yet here only his relation to the contents of the book edited by him could lead me. His position to Darwin’s theory is quite different of mine. Bronn declares in his concluding remarks, which he even joins to the text of the work as a 15. chapter, that “he was not able, to follow the doctrine” (put down in the preceding fourteen chapters) and that he thinks it “more consistant, to” insist upon the old point of view (viz. the admission of wonders), though it is not to be maintained scientifically.”</p>
<p>So also his foot-notes are mostly debating. Now, the more I should think it unfair to fight against Bronn’s opposing notes by polemising additions (which I shouldn’t have done even without giving my name) the less it seems to me advisable, to append explanations or notes betraying doubt to a work equally excellent in its richness of details as in the acuteness of its combinations, and this the less as the development of the science of organic nature within the last ten’s of years tends always more pressingly to a view which now Darwin has brought into such masterly form   Therefore in accordance with the author I decided, to leave out Bronn’s additions. I have also resisted the temptation to append notes of my own, though I might have been led to do it, for instance with regard to the value of zoological characters, to the causes of the variability, but especially with regard to the methodological necessity of the admission of the spontaneous generation I give therefore Darwin’s book so as it is in its fourth english edition published towards the close of the past year with some corrections sent me by the author. For those and for many lights on moot or doubtful points I feel myself most obliged to him.</p>
<p>J.V.C.</p> 
                </div>
        
    </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note><hi rend="italic">Top of letter</hi>: ‘Eozoon’ <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi></note>
            </div>

            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">For the published preface (‘Vorrede des Herausgebers’), see Bronn and Carus trans. 1867, pp. v–vi.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">See enclosure. The first two German translations of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> included notes and an extra chapter (chapter 15) by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Heinrich Georg Bronn</ref> (Bronn trans. 1860 and 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">In the letter from <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4246.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">E. Schweizerbart’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</ref> (the publishing firm in Stuttgart) of 24 January 1867, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref> informed CD that he had sent the first part of Carus’s manuscript to the printer.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">On the publisher, see n. 3, above. Bronn and Carus trans. 1867 was not published in parts.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In 1864, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1264.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John William Dawson</ref> identified samples taken from pre-Silurian strata in eastern Canada as fossilised Foraminifera, single-celled protists with shells; he named the species <hi rend="italic">Eozoon canadense</hi>, the ‘Dawn animal from Canada’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1883.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dawson 1864</ref>). Further samples were sent to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_839.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Benjamin Carpenter</ref>, an expert on Foraminifera, who confirmed Dawson’s interpretation (Carpenter 1864). CD added information on the discovery of <hi rend="italic">Eozoon canadense</hi> to <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 371, as substantiating his claim, made in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, p. 307, that life existed before the Silurian period (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 13, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4794.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 25 March [1865]</ref>, n. 11, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1100.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Burkhardt 1988</ref>, pp. 43–5). See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 14, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5106.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 31 May [1866]</ref>. The interpretation of the samples as pre-Silurian fossils remained controversial, however (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1270.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Carpenter 1866</ref>, and King and Rowney 1866); and by the end of the century, comparisons with similar, more recent, formations indicated that the samples were mineral in origin (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6974.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Schopf 2000</ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>