<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2698">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">To H. G. Bronn   14 February [1860]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                <idno type="lognum">13106</idno>
                
                
                
                
                <date when="1993">1993</date>
            <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2698 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2698.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2698.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
                <biblScope unit="vol" n="08">8</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">2pp</note>
                <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 143: 148</bibl></relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">Natural History Museum, Library and Archives (General Library DC AL 1/7)</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="../repo/repo_288.xml">NHM</repository>
                        <collection>General Library</collection>
                        <idno>DC AL 1/7</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                    <placeName>Down</placeName>
                    <date when="1860-02-14">14 Feb [1860]</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_657.xml">Bronn, H. G.</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract> 
                <p>Thanks HGB for agreeing to superintend translation of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p> 
                <p>Comments on HGB’s review.</p>
                <p>Encloses corrections and preface for Schweizerbart. Discusses translation of term "natural selection".</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                    <term type="languages" ref="#">German</term>
                    <term type="rx" ref="#">Bronn, H. G. 1860b</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">assessments</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                    <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <div type="text">
                    <opener>
                        <placeName>Down Bromley Kent.</placeName>
                        <date>Feb. 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                        <salute>My dear &amp; much honoured Sir</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <div type="transcription">
                        
                        <p>I thank you cordially for your extreme kindness in superintending the Translation. I have mentioned this to some eminent scientific men, &amp; they all agree that you have done a noble &amp; generous service. If I am proved quite wrong, yet I comfort myself in thinking that my Book may do some good; as truth can only be known by rising victorious from every attack. I thank you, also, much for the Review, &amp; for the kind manner in which you speak of me.—<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I send with this letter some corrections &amp; additions to M. Scheweitzerbart &amp; a short Historical Preface.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I am not much acquainted with German Authors, as I read German very slowly; therefore I do not know whether any Germans have advocated similar views with mine; if they have, would you do me the favour to insert a foot=note to the Preface?<ref target="#foot.f4"/> M. Scheweitzerbart has now the Reprint ready for a Translator to begin.— Several scientific men have thought the term “Natural Selection” good, because its meaning is <hi rend="underline">not</hi> obvious, &amp; each man could not put on it his own interpretation, &amp; because it at once connects Variation under domestication &amp; nature.— Is there any analogous term used by German Breeders of animals?— “Adelung”,—ennobling—would perhaps be too metaphorical. It is folly in me, but I cannot help doubting, whether “Wahl der Lebens-weise” expresses my notion.— It leaves the impression on my mind of the Lamarckian doctrine (which I reject) of habits of life being all-important. Man has altered &amp; thus improved the English Race-Horse by <hi rend="underline">selecting</hi> successive fleeter individuals; &amp; I believe, owing to the struggle for existence, that similar <hi rend="underline">slight</hi> variations in a wild Horse, <hi rend="underline">if advantageous to it</hi>, would be <hi rend="underline">selected</hi> or <hi rend="underline">preserved</hi> by Nature: Hence Natural Selection.</p>
                        <p>But I apologise for troubling you with these remarks on the importance of choosing good German terms for “natural selection.”<ref target="#foot.f5"/></p>
                        <p>With my heart-felt thanks &amp; with sincere respect | I remain Dear Sir | Yours very sincerely | Charles Darwin.</p>
                        <p>I am <hi rend="underline">very much</hi> obliged for your “Stuffengang &amp;c”, which I am now reading:<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I wish I knew what was the authority for a Batrachian in the New Hebrides.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.00 very] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.00 foot=note] ‘foot’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.00 ready … begin 1.00] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.00 altered] <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘selected’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">1.00 <hi rend="underline">preserved</hi>] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘improQQQQ’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.00 German] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>
                
                
                
                
                
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            <div type="footnotes">
                <note xml:id="foot.f1">Dated by the reference to the German translation of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f2">Bronn 1860a. There is a copy of the review in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4245.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Christian Friedrich Schweizerbart</ref>, owner of the publishing firm E. Schweizerbart of Stuttgart, was the publisher of the German edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2687.xml" resp="#automat">letter to H. G. Bronn, 4 February [1860]</ref>). The historical preface that CD had composed for the authorised American edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol.8, Appendix IV) was also published in the German edition of 1860. It was subsequently expanded and included in the third English edition.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f4">Bronn did not follow CD’s suggestion, although he did include a footnote to the discussion of Étienne Geoffroy St Hilaire’s views on species (Bronn trans. 1860, p. 2 n.): <quote type="quote"> Bekanntlich kam er in der Akademie mehrmals zu heftigen Auftritten noch mit Cuvier, welcher die Beständigkeit der Species gegen ihn vertheidigte. D. Übers. [It is well known that on several occasions in the academy he had violent clashes with Cuvier, who defended against him the view of the constancy of species. The translator.] </quote> In the historical sketch included in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6016.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 3d ed.</ref>, CD cited the German naturalists <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4200.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Hermann Schaaffhausen</ref>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_225.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Ernst von Baer</ref>, and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_731.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Karl Friedrich Burdach</ref> as having expressed views on species change. In a note (p. xviii), he added to these <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4842.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Franz Unger</ref>, Joseph Wilhelm Eduard d’Alton, and Lorenz Oken on the basis of references given in Bronn 1858b.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, Bronn had referred to natural selection as ‘Wahl der Lebens-Weise’ (Bronn 1860a, p. 112). The term Bronn used in his translation was ‘natürliche Züchtung’.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f6">Bronn 1860b. There are two copies in the Darwin Pamphlet Collection–CUL, one of which is annotated.</note>
                <note xml:id="foot.f7">Bronn 1860b, p. 13 n. According to CD’s views on the colonisation of oceanic islands, it would be very difficult for frogs or their eggs, which are damaged by salt-water, to reach isolated areas such as the New Hebrides.</note>
            </div>        
                
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>