<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-2510">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To Charles Lyell   25 October [1859]</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">174</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1992">1992</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-2510 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2510.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-2510.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="07">7</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">8pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="copy" subtype="CUL"><bibl>CUL DAR 146: 214</bibl></relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 176</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 7: 357</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">American Philosophical Society (Mss.B.D25.174)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_13.xml">APS</repository>
                    <collection>Mss.B.D25.</collection>
                    <idno>174</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Ilkley</placeName>
                <date when="1859-10-25">25 Oct [1859]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Discusses P. S. Pallas’ theory of origin of domestic dog breeds. CD believes domestic dogs descended from more than one aboriginal wild species but ultimately "we believe all canine species have descended from one parent and the only question is whether the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> or only part of difference in our domestic breeds has arisen since man domesticated them".</p>  
<p>Races of man offer great difficulty. The doctrine of Pallas and Agassiz that there are several species "does not help <hi rend="doubleUnderline">us</hi>" in the least.</p>  
<p>Hopes Henry Holland will not review <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi>.</p>  
<p>CD’s and CL’s difference on "principle of improvement" and "power of adaptation" is profound. Improvement in breeds of cattle requires neither. Urges him to reread first four chapters of <hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> carefully. Natural selection is not to be contrasted with "improvement": every step involves improvement in relation to the conditions of life. There is no need for a "principle" to intervene.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">cattle</term>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">dog</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Origin</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_43">Agassiz, J. L. R.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_2337">Holland, Henry</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_3654">Pallas, P. S.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">aboriginal forms</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">adaptation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">breeding (artificial)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">climate and conditions</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">constant varieties, races</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">highness and lowness</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">human intervention</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">humanity</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">number of species</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">origin</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">reception of Darwinism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">selection</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wild vs domestic forms</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Wells Terrace | Ilkley, Otley | Yorkshire</placeName>
                    <date>Oct. 25.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Lyell</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>The doctrine of Pallas applied to our domestic breeds, we will say to Dogs, is as follows.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> He believes that man tamed a wolf in one country, the jackall in another, the fox in another &amp; so on with other species. He does not suppose that these wild species were more variable than others. He <hi rend="underline">hypothetically</hi> supposes that when long domesticated they lose their tendency to sterility when crossed with the other domesticated <hi rend="underline">species</hi>; &amp; by their crossing when domesticated he believes that all our domestic races have originated. He or his followers further believe that the crossing gives as a tendency to <hi rend="underline">new</hi> characters to arise, &amp; this is not a little hypothetical. The whole doctrine is very hypothetical.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> Yet I certainly believe (but cannot here give reasons) that the American domestic dogs have descended from at least 3 or 4 aboriginally distinct species, &amp; that European dogs probably from several other species. There truly is, as you say, “an uncomfortable vague-ness” in whole doctrine.</p>
<p>You will see that I have spoken cautiously on subject. It is a curious, but not important subject for us: <hi rend="doubleUnderline">we</hi> believe that all canine species have descended from one parent; &amp; the only question is whether the <hi rend="underline">whole</hi> or only a part of difference between our domestic breeds has arisen since man domesticated them. I do not see how the question concerns specific centres.— The importance of period of gest-ation, has, I think, been much exaggerated: there is <hi rend="doubleUnderline">great</hi> <hi rend="doubleUnderline">individual</hi> difference in the period in our improved cattle, &amp; by selection, a breed could in all probability be easily made with longer or shorter period.—</p>
<p>The Races of Man offer great difficulty: I do not think doctrine of Pallas, or that of Agassiz that there are several species of man, helps <hi rend="doubleUnderline">us</hi> in the least.—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> I fancy I have got some rays of light on subject; but mutiny in India stopped some important enquiries.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> Much too long a subject for letter. I will add I do not attribute much effect to climate &amp;c.—</p>
<p>I believe, as you will see when you reread, that some plants migrated through Tropical <hi rend="underline">lowlands</hi> during glacial period.</p>
<p>I am terribly lame with inflamed leg (what the Water-cure Doctors call a severe crisis)<ref target="#foot.f5"/> &amp; this makes my hand-writing rather worse even than usual.—</p>
<p>If my book is reviewed in Quarterly, how I hope that Sir. H. Holland will not be Reviewer: he is so presumptuous &amp; knows so little.<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>Our difference on “principle of improvement” &amp; “power of adaptation” is too profound for discussion by letter. If I am wrong, I am quite blind to my error. If I am right, our difference will be got over only by your rereading carefully &amp; reflecting on my first four chapters. I supplicate you to read these again carefully.— The so-called improvement of our short-horn cattle, pigeons &amp;c, does not presuppose or require any aboriginal “power of adaptation” or “principle of improvement”; it requires only diversified variability, &amp; man to select or take advantage of those modifications which are useful to him: so under nature any slight modification which <hi rend="underline">chances</hi> to arise &amp; is useful to any creature is selected or preserved in the struggle for life; any modification which is injurious is destroyed or rejected; any which is neither useful nor injurious will be left a fluctuating element.—</p>
<p>When you contrast natural selection &amp; “Improvement”, you seem always to overlook (for I do not see how you can deny) that every step in the natural selection of each species implies improvement in that species in relation to its conditions of life. No modification can be selected without it be an improvement or advantage. Improvement implies, I suppose, each form obtaining many parts or organs, all excellently adapted for their functions. As each species is improved, &amp; as the number of forms will have increased if we look to the whole course of time, the organic conditions of life for other forms will become more complex; &amp; there will be a necessity for other forms to become improved or they will be exterminated; and I can see no limit to this process of improvement without the intervention of any other &amp; direct principle of improvement. All this seems to me quite compatable with certain forms, fitted for simple conditions, remaining unaltered, or being degraded.</p>
<p>If I have a second Edit. I will reiterate, “Natural Selection, &amp; as a general consequence Natural Improvement”.—<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>As you go as far as you do, I begin strongly to think, judging from myself, that you will go much further. How slowly the older geologists admitted your grand views on existing geological causes of change!— If at any time you think I can answer any question, it is a real pleasure to me to write.—</p>
<p>Yours affect<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> | C. Darwin</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.6 when domesticated] <hi rend="italic">interl before del</hi> ‘&amp; by assumed hypothetical variability’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.6 that all] ‘that’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.10 (but cannot here give reasons)] <hi rend="italic">parentheses over commas</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">1.12 There … whole doctrine. 1.13] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.4 between] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘in’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.4 has] <hi rend="italic">over</hi> ‘have’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">2.5 the] <hi rend="italic">interl before del interl</hi> ‘whole’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">2.7 difference] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> <hi rend="italic">illeg</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">6.2 &amp; knows so little.] <hi rend="italic">added</hi>; ‘&amp;’ <hi rend="italic">over full stop</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n10">7.9 is useful] ‘is’ <hi rend="italic">above del</hi> ‘be’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n11">8.5 or advantage.] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The ‘doctrine’ referred to by CD was discussed in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 253–4. <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3654.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pyotr Simon Pallas</ref> believed that most domestic animals had descended from two or more aboriginal species that had since become mixed by interbreeding (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6162.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pallas 1780</ref>, pp. 84, 100).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">CD had studied Pallas’s writings in detail in 1840 and 1844. His notes on <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6162.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Pallas 1780</ref> are inDAR 196.5. See also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1202.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 6 October [1848]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_43.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Louis Agassiz</ref> was a leading advocate of polygenesis.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">CD’s precise reference here is unknown. For a number of years, he had been corresponding with various naturalists in India, particularly with <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Blyth</ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vols. 5 and 6). The great revolt of the Bengal Army in 1857 led to the transference of Indian government from the East India Company to the crown in 1858.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">CD was familiar with the wish of hydropathic doctors to induce a ‘crisis’, as this had been an important aspect of <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Manby Gully’s</ref> therapy at Malvern, which CD underwent in 1849. See <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3197.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Gully 1846</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2337.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Henry Holland</ref>, a noted physician and a distant relative of CD, frequently reviewed scientific works for the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi>. The periodical was published by John Murray, as was <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>. CD had complained to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> that Holland ‘does not know enough of Nat. Hist.’ following Holland’s review of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1571.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Coral reefs</hi></ref> (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 4, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-1082.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [18 April 1847]</ref>). Lyell wrote to Murray on 4 November 1859 (Murray Archives): ‘Sir H. Holland is talking much aboutC Darwins subject but no one who has not specially devoted himself to paleontology ought to review D’s work.’ In the event, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5128.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Samuel Wilberforce</ref> reviewed <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In his letter, Lyell apparently discussed a ‘principle of improvement’ as being one element of CD’s theory. Lyell had long been an opponent of the doctrine of progressive development in the world. There is no record of CD ever using Lyell’s phrase.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>