<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-4433">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles Wright to Asa Gray   20, 25, and 26 March and 1 April 1864</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">11133</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-4433 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4433.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-4433.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="12">12</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp † (by CD)</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 181: 163</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>181: 163</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_5253.xml">Wright, Charles</persName>
                <placeName>Retiro Cuba</placeName>
                
            <date when="1864-03-20">20 Mar 1864</date>
            <date when="1864-03-25">25 Mar 1864</date>
            <date when="1864-03-26">26 Mar 1864</date>
            <date when="1864-04-01">1 Apr 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1957.xml">Gray, Asa</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Describes the flower and mode of action of a particular orchid.</p> 
<p>Has been examining <hi rend="italic">Spiranthes</hi> and is experimenting to see whether insects are necessary for its fertilisation.</p>  
<p>It seems that <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi> is designed so as <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to be fertilised.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insects</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Oncidium</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">orchid</term>
                <term type="plants" ref="#">Spiranthes</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">experiment, scientific observation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fertilisation and generation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flora</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">flowers and buds</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">movements and habits of plants</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">plant physiology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                
                <term type="tag" ref="#design_in_nature">Darwin In Nature Design In Nature</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Retiro</placeName>
                    <date>March 20th 1864</date>
                    <salute>My Dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I received a few days ago yours of the 16th ult. containing Dr. Hooker’s note which I have answered so much at length that perhaps he’ll dub me a “<hi rend="underline">bore</hi>” but I felt that I could not well reply to his questions without doing so.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I shall trust to your kindness to forward it when you have occasion to write a line yourself.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> We are now about at the end of the dry season.<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The savanas are now newly burnt over &amp; yield nothing. Forest trees are changing their attire: some are flowering[.] Orchids &amp; Tillandsias begin to grow anew. I have at last found one (orchid) in some respects more remarkable than those so graphically described by Mr. Darwin—<ref target="#foot.f4"/> sorry I cant give you the name tho’ I believe it is in my collections<ref target="#foot.f5"/>   The stigmatic surfaces are very sticky &amp; are widely separated by the rostellum which projects downwards or even a little backwards if any thing but nearly parrallel with the column which is <hi rend="underline">thick</hi> &amp; short (proportionally)   The downward movement of the pollinia is almost instantaneous so that I extracted a number without discovering it till I did it under the microscope. Sometimes it is slower sometimes quicker (according to the age of the fl. or time of day?) but it always ends with a jerk through <formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></math></formula>–<formula><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></formula> of the arc of about 90°. After depression the disk &amp; pedicels are just like the fig. of Gymnadenia conopsea—Darwin, p. 80.<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I say pedicels, for in this case the pedicels are connate into a strap-shaped organ (white—the disk is brownish) to the tip of which the minute oval pollen masses are attached by a point nearly at right angles but diverging laterally so as better to enter the stigmatic cavities though they appear to me to be at last some what too close together for that. However they stick well when introduced into the same or another fl. And they are so firm that they either remain bodily or are drawn out again which however rarely happens according to the few trials I have made. The lip is furnished with two prominent tubercular crests between which the proboscis of the insect must pass to reach the nectar in the minute sack at its base.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Day after tomorrow I expect to go to the coast (south) for two or three or <hi rend="underline">more</hi> days if I find many things to collect   This is the season when the people eat fish (flesh being prohibited)<ref target="#foot.f8"/> &amp; a neighbor of friend Blain<ref target="#foot.f9"/> goes to improve the fiesta and make a little money by the sale of his “<hi rend="underline">catch</hi>” &amp; at the same time obey the precepts of his church &amp; the dictates of his conscience!!! He used to be engaged in the slave trade smuggling &amp; piracy a little I believe. I have long wanted to visit that coast for a short herborisation &amp; once knowing the way I can return if it promises much for another &amp; more favorable season of the year</p>
<p>It is pretty dry though the grass is not yet very short and a pretty good shower came the other night to give it a start. My horses are in good condition against the time when I shall want to set out on some long tour. I proposed to Gundlach a run to the north in the summer after making our excursion westward.<ref target="#foot.f10"/> He says he can’t go yet, but I am inclining more &amp; more to go it alone if he wont accompany me. I have twice traversed the western end of the island in the latter part of the year, &amp; after a spring excursion through the same places I might well afford to spend a few months visiting my friends &amp; equipping myself anew for another two or three years absence fr. home &amp; residence in the island. We have dates fr. New York on the 12th inst<ref target="#foot.f11"/> &amp; am beginning to fear that Mexico poor priest-ridden Mexico will have just cause to laugh at us. The war seems to be degenerating into a systematic practice of pillage &amp; devastation to end perhaps in one of vengeance &amp; retaliation<ref target="#foot.f12"/></p>
<p>In my last excursion of about 25 sp. of shells collected in a season unfavorable 8 are new species</p>
<p>I examined again our little Spiranthes.<ref target="#foot.f13"/> From the flowers just opened the pollinia come out best. Those of older flowers wont stick but they project far over the stigma &amp; being powdery or at least friable it is not unlikely either that the pollen falls naturally onto the stigma or that the upper edge of it unites with the loosened pollen in some way or that minute insects crawling over it may carry some of it to the stigmatic surface. However it may be some have the pollinia removed others close up &amp; retain them in place while all or nearly all set their fruits.</p>
<p>Don José<ref target="#foot.f14"/> has covered a spike of buds of the plant I first mentioned to test the matter of fertilization &amp; see if insects are absolutely necessary to insure seed from that orchid</p>
<p>25th. I didnt go to the coast. Our fisher friend sent word that he had sickness in his family &amp; couldnt leave. So I went into the hills picking up mosses Lichens &amp;c. Got one new Rubiaceæ—a Bertiera probably. &amp; some fruiting orchids.</p>
<p>26th. I have just examined an oncidium—the largest if I mistake not in the island on one scape or panicle I counted more than 200 fl. The mechanism is plain   The object is that it shall <hi rend="underline">not</hi> be fertilized—and it isn’t   I have never seen a fr. &amp; Don José says the same. It is common   The fl. spreads wide open has no nectary &amp; I dont know what an insect should visit it for. But suppose a bumble-bee should but his nose against the big disk it will stick there &amp; if he raises his head a very little the anther jumps off sometimes to a distance at other times still clasps the pollinia. Do you suppose that now these pitch forward in order to hit the next stigma he runs against? Not at all. They fall back over Mr. Bumble-bee’s knowledge-box &amp; if he goes to a thousand other flowers the pollen doesn’t reach a stigma with his good will. Let Mr Darwin explain this if he can.<ref target="#foot.f15"/></p>
<p>April 1. Suspecting I had drawn hasty conclusions from the above experiments, I last night extracted a large number of the pollinia &amp; left them till this morning when they had all undergone the movement of depression showing the correctness of Mr. Darwin’s observations.<ref target="#foot.f16"/> Today I expect to dispatch this which will go to Havana tomorrow probably</p>
<p>Yours ever | Charles Wright</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note>1.12 The downward … instantaneous 1.13] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi></note>
                <note>8.3 I have never … probably 9.5] <hi rend="italic">double scored pencil</hi><ref target="#foot.f17"/></note>
            </div>

            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">Transcripts of letters from Gray to Wright are in the Gray Herbarium archives, Harvard University; portions of their correspondence have been published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>. A letter from Wright to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref>, dated 16 March 1864, is in Supplementary foreign letters, vol. 218, doc. 364, Library and Archives, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, and is reprinted in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, pp. 2–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">The letters from Gray to Hooker are in the Director’s Correspondence, Library and Archives, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew. Much of Wright’s correspondence was forwarded through Gray, who also purchased his collections and sent him books and supplies (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2214.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Dupree 1959</ref>, pp. 165–6, 211, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, p. 20).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Wright had been collecting plants in Cuba since 1856. In March 1864, he was living at Retiro, a property of his friend <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_474.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">José Blain’s</ref> in Pinar del Rio, the westernmost province of Cuba (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, p. 37).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Wright refers to <hi rend="italic">Orchids.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">For information on Wright’s collections from Cuba, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, pp. 66–77 and Appendix 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 80.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">An excerpt of a <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Gray to Wright of 30 March 1864</ref> appears in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, p. 72: <quote type="quote"> Yes, all observations are important. I will send your notes to Darwin who has been so sick we gave him up. But now he is better. He, if well enough, will give some special directions for experiments. </quote> Only one query from CD to Wright has been found (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4511.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 28 May [1864]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4558.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Asa Gray, 11 July 1864</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">It was customary for Roman Catholics to abstain from meat during Lent, which in 1864 ended on 27 March.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">Blain’s neighbour has not been identified.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Johannes Christoph (Juan Cristóbal) Gundlach, a friend of Wright’s, was a well-known naturalist in Cuba (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, pp. 36–7, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5820.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">NDB</hi></ref>; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 7, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-2557.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from Richard Hill, 26 November 1859</ref> and n. 6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Wright arrived in New England in August 1864 and left for Cuba again in May 1865 (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, pp. 15, 37, and Appendix 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12">On the key role played by the Catholic church and the issue of church property in the civil and economic strife and foreign interventions in Mexico at this time, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_4410.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Knowlton 1976</ref>, pp. 129–48. Wright also refers to the on-going American Civil War.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f13">Wright’s <hi rend="italic">Spiranthes</hi> was probably a tropical or sub-tropical species. CD discussed <hi rend="italic">Spiranthes autumnalis</hi>, a British species, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, pp. 116–29, and in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 151 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 148). In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, pp. 106–15, CD discussed <hi rend="italic">S. autumnalis</hi> and an Australian <hi rend="italic">Spiranthes.</hi> He acknowledged Gray’s help with two North American species in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6010.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi></ref>, p. 123 n., and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 111 n.; see also <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 9, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Asa Gray, 17 September [1861]</ref> and n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f14"><ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_474.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">José Blain</ref> (see n. 3, above).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f15">An excerpt of a <ref target="" resp="#automat">letter from Gray to Wright of 18 April 1864</ref> (see n. 1, above) appears in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_3887.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Howard 1988</ref>, p. 72: <quote type="quote"> Tomorrow I shall mail that to Hooker and at the same time send on yours to me to Darwin tho’ the poor man is sick; it will enliven him. I suspect that he will say that <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi> (that won’t fertilize) is a male plant—its pollen fertilizing some other more feminine individual. Keep up obs. and soon I will tell you what Darwin says. </quote> See n. 16, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f16">CD recorded Wright’s initial conclusion that CD had made an error, and his later confirmation of the movement of pollinia that enabled the pollination of <hi rend="italic">Oncidium</hi> and many other orchids, in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2498.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">‘Fertilization of orchids’</ref>, p. 152 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1506.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Collected papers</hi></ref> 2: 149), and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6011.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi> 2d ed.</ref>, p. 156.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f17">In addition to CD’s pencil annotations, there are blue crayon annotations that appear to have been made by Gray to draw CD’s attention to particular sections of Wright’s letter: the fifth paragraph, from ‘it is not unlikely . . .’; the sixth paragraph; the eighth paragraph, from ‘I have never seen …’; and the ninth paragraph.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>