<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3968">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Bartholomew James Sulivan   4 February [1863]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">10812</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1999">1999</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3968 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3968.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3968.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">7pp</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 177: 280</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>177: 280</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_4614.xml">Sulivan, B. J.</persName>
                <placeName>Board of Trade</placeName>
                <date when="1863-02-04">4 Feb [1863]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Thinks he may be appointed Commodore commanding the Squadron on the west coast of S. America. Wishes to leave England for his health’s sake.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">coast, west</term>
                <term type="health" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#">commodore of squadron</term>
                <term type="places" ref="#">America, S.</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">descent</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geology</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">negative attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">transmutation</term>
                <term type="social" ref="#">Other people</term>
                <term type="societal" ref="#">squadron</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName><hi rend="print">Board of Trade. S.W.</hi></placeName>
                    <date>Feby 4</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>You will I have no doubt be surprised when I tell you that it is most probable I shall shortly leave England as <hi rend="underline">Commodore</hi> to <hi rend="underline">command the Squadron</hi> on <hi rend="underline">West Coast</hi> of <hi rend="underline">S america</hi> <ref target="#foot.f2"/>   The Station being from <hi rend="underline">Equator</hi> to <hi rend="underline">Cape Horn</hi>. The Admiral taking the North Pacific— Will it not be singular if should once more go over our old ground—<ref target="#foot.f3"/> The fact is I have been for more than two months suffering from Bronchial complaint which though slight will not get better as every time it seems better I get a fresh cold. about six weeks since I was very unwell. I was saying at home that as it was the third winter I had been so frequently attacked this way I should have to avoid the winter in England—&amp; I wished there was any appointment in a good climate that I could get as it would set me up again as twice I had been set up by going to S america   But I knew of nothing likely and therefore we were seriously discussing my having to give up before next winter. The <hi rend="underline">very next day</hi> I saw in the paper that a Commodore <hi rend="underline">was to be sent to the Chili Station</hi>. It seemed of all things the very best as it would also enable me to serve my time for Active Flag, which next winter would be too late for.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> after hesitating for several days I found no one was nominated, so I went in for it—and at first thought it was quite settled, for Senior Naval Lord &amp; Private Secy—both nominated me for it to First Lord, which is generally conclusive,<ref target="#foot.f5"/> but they first postponed the app<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. to April on account of the financial years account preventing their doing it this year—and also to prepare a ship, and then they would not tell me if I were to go or not but I have heard some interest was rising for another— However as four admirals at adm<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> have concurred in telling 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Lord I have a stronger claim to it than any one, and as the Senior Naval Lord has told me what the limits of station are &amp; other particulars it ought to be pretty certain. I have also heard from several that it is said at admiralty I am to go: and so it rests till March.</p>
<p>I have not spoken about it outside Admiralty—for if I do not get it I would rather it was not generally known, so I only tell you for your private information that you may turn over in your all mind all the <hi rend="underline">Geological instructions</hi> you wish to give me. The ship will be “Curacoa” a Screw frigate, and if I go I shall probably go through Straits of M. and so see much of our old ground—<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>If they will give me leave my wife<ref target="#foot.f7"/> and girls will go with me as the Sea Voyage &amp; the climate of Valpo<ref target="#foot.f8"/> might do the girls much good.</p>
<p>I hope you are better now—&amp; that our talking so much did not do you any more than a Scrap of injury. I hear that Wickham and his family have not been well in France<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>with kind regards to all Your family believe me | Yours very sin<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> | B J Sulivan</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the reference to Sulivan’s visit to Down House in October 1862 (see n. 9, below).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Sulivan was a naval officer in the marine department at the Board of Trade (Sulivan ed. 1896, pp. 375, 379, and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2063.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">DNB</hi></ref>). A commodore is an officer intermediate in rank between a captain and an admiral.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">Sulivan was second lieutenant during the visit of HMS <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> to South America and during its surveying voyage of 1831–6 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2662.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Freeman 1978</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Sulivan was attempting to qualify for the active list of admirals (Sulivan ed. 1896, p. 377).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">The first lord of the admiralty was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4306.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward Adolphus Seymour Seymour</ref>, his private secretary was John Moore, and the senior naval lord was <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">William Hall Gage</ref> (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5816.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Navy list</hi></ref>, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6380.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Post Office London directory</hi></ref> 1863).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">Sulivan refers to the Straits of Magellan; the <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi> sailed through the Straits between 27 January and 13 February 1834, and between 25 May and 10 June 1834 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5784.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></ref>, Appendix, pp. 23–4, 29–30).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">Sulivan married Sophia Young in 1837 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1596.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">County families</hi></ref> 1871).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">The reference is to Valparaiso, Chile.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">On 21 October 1862, Sulivan, and two of the other officers who had served with CD on board HMS <hi rend="italic">Beagle</hi>, <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_3290.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Arthur Mellersh</ref> and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_5114.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">John Clements Wickham</ref>, visited Down House. CD suffered ill health following the visit (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 10, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3775.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from B. J. Sulivan, 18 October [1862]</ref> and n. 1, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3779.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to John Lubbock, 23 October [1862]</ref>). Wickham had retired to the south of France; he died of a stroke on 6 January 1864 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_256.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Aust. dict. biog.</hi></ref>).</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>