<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-5024">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">From Charles Lyell   1 March 1866</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">19379</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-5024 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5024.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-5024.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="14">14</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">ML</hi> 2: 157</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 14</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">DAR 91: 89–90</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_106.xml">CUL</repository>
                    <collection>DAR</collection>
                    <idno>91: 89–90</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_3051.xml">Lyell, Charles</persName>
                <placeName>London, Harley St, 53</placeName>
                <date when="1866-03-01">1 Mar 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract>
            <p>Feels sure that at times the globe must have been superficially cooler. Believes CD will turn out right with regard to migration across the equator via mountain chains, while the tropical heat of certain lowlands was retained.</p>
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="geology" ref="#">globe, cooled</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geological time, epochs</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mineralogy, minerals</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">theory (including philosophy)</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">wind and weather</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>53 Harley Street</placeName>
                    <date>March 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>./66.</date>
                    <salute>My dear Darwin</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>Please sign the memorial &amp; return it by return of post as no time is to be lost.<ref target="#foot.f1"/> I have had Hooker’s letter copied.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> I feel sure that the whole globe must at times have been superficially cooler— Still I think that during extreme excentricity the sun would make great efforts to compensate in perihelion for the chill of a long winter in aphelion in one hemisphere &amp; a cool summer in the other—<ref target="#foot.f3"/></p>
<p>I think you will turn out to be right in regard to meridianal lines of mountain chains by which the migrations across the equator took place while the was contemporaneous tropical heat of certain low lands, where plants requiring heat &amp; moisture were saved from extinction, by the heat of the earth’s surface, which was stored up in perihelion being prevented from radiating off freely into space by a blanket of aqueous vapour caused by the melting of ice &amp; snow.<ref target="#foot.f4"/> But though I am inclined to profit by Croll’s maximum excentricity for the glacial period, I consider it quite subordinate to geographical causes or the relative position of land &amp; sea &amp; the abnormal excess of land in polar regions.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> It is a vast subject &amp; if one applies to the astronomer there is no end to the number of uncertain data which it has never been worth their while to calculate for their own purposes. The worst of all the uncertainties is that which relates to the temperature of space<ref target="#foot.f6"/></p>
<p>believe me | ever most truly yrs | Cha Lyell</p> 
                </div>
            </div>

            
            
            
            
            
            
        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The memorial has not been identified, but may be that submitted by CD and others to W. E. Gladstone, 14 May 1866 (see this volume).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2">Lyell refers to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5013.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 21 February 1866</ref>. CD had forwarded part of the letter to Lyell, having been told by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_2357.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Joseph Dalton Hooker</ref> that Lyell wished to see it (see <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, [26 or 27 February 1866]</ref>, and <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [28 February 1866]</ref> and n. 3).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">For CD’s belief that the entire earth was cooler during the glacial period, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 12. Hooker had disagreed with CD on this and related topics in his letter to CD of 21 February 1866. The effects on global climate of aphelion and perihelion, eccentricity of the earth’s orbit, and other astronomical phenomena are discussed in chapter 13 of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1867–8</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">Lyell refers to CD’s argument in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, pp. 377–8, that temperate plants may have crossed through the tropical regions near the equator during a glacial period by means of mountain ranges, which would have remained cooler, while tropical plants were preserved in the greater heat of the low-lying areas. This would account for the existence of similar species in both the northern and southern temperate zones. For some years, Hooker challenged CD on the problem of the survival of tropical plants in ‘so very cool a greenhouse’ as would be required to allow temperate plants to cross the equator, suggesting that the distribution of plants and animals could be better explained by land-bridges and continental extension (see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1581.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi></ref> vol. 11, <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4024.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 5 March [1863]</ref> and n. 17). In the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, CD admitted that the survival of tropical species was a difficulty for his theory (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 450–1), but this text was not retained in later editions (see Peckham ed. 1959, pp. 599–603). CD later explained the survival of tropical plants according to <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_1127.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">James Croll’s</ref> theory of ice ages that alternated between hemispheres, and during which the temperature of the non-glaciated hemisphere rose (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6018.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 5th ed.</ref>, pp. 450–61; see also n. 5, below). Lyell, however, had invoked alternate meridional belts of cooler and warmer temperature to explain the survival of species during the glacial period (C. Lyell 1863, pp. 366–7).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">Croll had recently published a paper relating the occurrence of ice ages to the eccentricity of the earth’s orbit and to the longitude of the perihelion (Croll 1866a). For more on changes in global temperature, including the significance of Croll’s work to CD’s theory of the migration of plants during the glacial period, see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-4999.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to Charles Lyell, 7 February [1866]</ref> and n. 12, and the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5013.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from J. D. Hooker, 21 February 1866</ref> and n. 10; see also the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [28 February 1866]</ref> and n. 7. Lyell explained former changes in climate in relation to geographical and astronomical causes in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_5032.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">C. Lyell 1867–8</ref>, chapters 12 and 13, respectively. For a summary of Lyell’s position on former climate changes, see <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6035.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Ospovat 1977</ref> and <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_2543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Fleming 1998</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">CD wrote of uncertainties about the temperature of space, in the light of recent contributions by physicists and astronomers to the understanding of glaciation, in the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-5020.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, [28 February 1866]</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>