<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tei_math.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="DCP-LETT-3816">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="main_title">To H. W. Bates   20 November [1862]<ref target="#foot.f1"/></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Darwin Correspondence Project</authority>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
            <idno type="lognum">1534</idno>
            
            
            
            
            <date when="1997">1997</date>
        <availability xml:id="rights" status="restricted"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">DCP-LETT-3816 by <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk">The Darwin Correspondence Project</ref> is licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ref>. Based on a work at <ref target="https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3816.xml">https://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/letter/?docId=letters/DCP-LETT-3816.xml</ref>.</licence></availability>
</publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin</title>
            <biblScope unit="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note type="physdesc" n="ALS">4pp</note>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">LL</hi> 2: 391;</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl>Stecher (1969): 36</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="publication">
                <bibl> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> 10: 539</bibl>
            </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl type="provenance">Cleveland Health Sciences Library (Robert M. Stecher collection)</bibl>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository key="../repo/repo_93.xml">Cleveland</repository>
                </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_1.xml">Darwin, C. R.</persName>
                <placeName>Down</placeName>
                <date when="1862-11-20">20 Nov [1862]</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
                <persName key="../nameregs/nameregs_317.xml">Bates, H. W.</persName>
            </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <abstract> 
<p>Just finished HWB’s paper ["Contributions to an insect fauna of the Amazon valley", <hi rend="italic">Trans. Linn. Soc. Lond.</hi> 23 (1862): 495–566], one of the most remarkable he has ever read. Found mimetic cases and connection of facts marvellous. Finds equally important the facts on variation and segregation of complete and semi-complete species. Questions whether insect mimicry is not due to small size and defencelessness. Criticises title of paper. Mentions that Wallace will appreciate it.</p> 
        </abstract>
        <textClass>
            <keywords>
                <term type="animals" ref="#">insect</term>
                <term type="it" ref="#">Trans. Linn. Soc. Lond.</term>
                <term type="people" ref="#subject_4935">Wallace, A. R.</term>
                <term type="rx" ref="#">Bates, H. W. 1861</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">fauna</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">geographical distribution</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">mimicry</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">physical ‘external’ characters</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">positive attitude/assessment</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">relation of organism to organism</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">species, speciation</term>
                <term type="scientific_terms" ref="#">variation</term>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="transcribed">Transcribed by <name xml:id="dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="initialProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="secondProofCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="footnoted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="reviewed">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="editorResponseCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="finalProofreadCompleted">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" status="copyedited">Transcribed by <name sameAs="#dcp">Darwin Correspondence Project</name></change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="letter" status="released">Transcription cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12" type="footnotes" status="released">Footnotes cleared for online release</change>
        <change when="2016-07-12">Converted to TEI P5 by <name xml:id="mjhawkins">Michael Hawkins</name></change>
        <change when="2022-08-16">Automatic links added to bibliographical references in footnotes by <name xml:id="automat">Michael Hawkins</name>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
        
        <div type="letter">
            <div type="text">
                <opener>
                    <placeName>Down Bromley Kent</placeName>
                    <date>Nov. 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                    <salute>Dear Bates</salute>
                </opener>
                <div type="transcription">
                     
<p>I have just finished after several reads your Paper.<ref target="#foot.f2"/> In my opinion it is one of the most remarkable &amp; admirable papers I ever read in my life. The mimetic cases are truly marvellous &amp; you connect excellently a host of analogous facts. The illustrations are beautiful &amp; seem very well chosen; but it would have saved the reader not a little trouble, if the name of each had been engraved below each separate figure;<ref target="#foot.f3"/> no doubt this would have put the engraver<ref target="#foot.f4"/> into fits, as it would have destroyed beauty of Plate. I am not at all surprised at such a paper having consumed much time. I rejoice that I passed over whole subject in the Origin, for I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have made a precious mess of it.<ref target="#foot.f5"/> You have most clearly stated &amp; solved a wonderful problem.—</p>
<p>No doubt with most people this will be the cream of the paper; but I am not sure that all your facts &amp; reasoning on variation &amp; on the segregation of complete &amp; semi-complete species is not really more, or at least as valuable a part.—<ref target="#foot.f6"/> I never conceived the process nearly so clearly before; one feels present at the creation of new forms.— I wish, however, you had enlarged a little more on the pairing of similar varieties; a rather more numerous body of facts seems here wanted.<ref target="#foot.f7"/></p>
<p>Then again what a host of curious miscellaneous observations there are,—as on related sexual &amp; individual variability you give; these will some day, if I live, be a treasure to me.—<ref target="#foot.f8"/></p>
<p>With respect to mimetic resemblance being so common with insects; do you not think it may be connected with their small size; they cannot defend themselves;— they cannot escape by flight at least from Birds; therefore they escape by trickery &amp; deception?<ref target="#foot.f9"/></p>
<p>I have one serious criticism to make &amp; that is about title of paper; I cannot but think that you ought to have called prominent attention in it to the mimetic resemblances.—<ref target="#foot.f10"/> Your paper is too good to be largely appreciated by the mob of naturalists without souls; but rely on it, that it will have <hi rend="underline">lasting</hi> value, &amp; I cordially congratulate you on your first great work. You will find, I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. think, that Wallace will fully appreciate it.—<ref target="#foot.f11"/></p>
<p>How gets on your Book?—<ref target="#foot.f12"/> Keep your spirits up. A Book is no light labour. I have been better lately &amp; working hard; but my health is very indifferent. How is your health?</p>
<p>Believe me Dear Bates | Yours very sincerely | Ch. Darwin</p>
<p>Excuse my poor M.S. paper.—</p> 
                </div>
            </div>
                <div type="tnotes">
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n1">1.4 the] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n2">1.5 the] <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n3">1.8 passed] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘slurred’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n4">2.2 on the] ‘on’ <hi rend="italic">added</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n5">2.5 enlarged] <hi rend="italic">after del</hi> ‘g’</note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n6">2.6 a rather] ‘a’ <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n7">3.1 miscellaneous] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n8">3.1 there are] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                    <note xml:id="tnote.n9">3.2 be] <hi rend="italic">interl</hi></note>
                </div>

        </div>

        

        

        <div type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="foot.f1">The year is established by the relationship to the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3825.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. W. Bates, 24 November 1862</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f2"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref> appeared in the third part of volume 23 of the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Linnean Society of London</hi>, which was published on 13 November 1862 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6543.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Raphael 1970</ref>); there is a copy of this part of the journal in the Darwin Library–CUL, in which Bates’s paper is heavily annotated.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f3">The two colour plates of Amazonian mimetic butterflies published in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref> (plates LV and LVI), were keyed by numbers to identifications and descriptions at the end of the paper (pp. 564–6). CD added the species names to the figures in his copy of the paper.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f4">The plates were drawn and engraved by <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4038.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Edward W. Robinson</ref>, a noted entomological artist.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f5">In his paper, Bates invoked the theory of natural selection to account for the phenomenon of mimicry in Amazonian butterflies, arguing that the case offered ‘a most beautiful proof of the truth of the theory’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>, p. 513). CD included a summary of Bates’s findings in the fourth edition of <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6014.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi></ref>, published in 1866 (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, pp. 502–6).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f6">In the introduction to his paper, Bates argued that ‘many of the now distinct species of <hi rend="italic">Heliconidæ</hi> have arisen from local varieties, segregated from the variations of preexisting widely disseminated species’ (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>, p. 501). In particular, he noted that in some species the varieties presented ‘all the different grades between simple individual differences and well-marked local varieties or races, which latter cannot be distinguished from true species, when two or more of them are found coexisting in the same locality without intercrossing’. For the details of these cases, Bates referred the reader to his systematic descriptions of the various species (pp. 515–64). See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3812.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 18 [November 1862]</ref> and n. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f7">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>, p. 501, Bates stated: <quote type="quote"> The process of the creation of a new species I believe to be accelerated in the <hi rend="italic">Ithomiæ</hi> and allied genera by the strong tendency of the insects, when pairing, to select none but their exact counterparts: this also enables a number of very closely allied ones to exist together, or the representative forms to live side by side on the confines of their areas, without amalgamating. </quote> In his copy of the paper, CD wrote at this point ‘What proof?’, but added ‘See further on’. Bates’s reply has not been found, but see the <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3861.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to H. W. Bates, 15 December [1862]</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f8">See, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>, p. 502. CD frequently cited Bates’s work in his account of sexual selection in insects in <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_1966.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Descent</hi></ref> 1: 309–15 and 341–423; however, he did not cite this paper.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f9">In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>, p. 507, Bates noted: <quote type="quote"> It may be asked, why are mimetic analogies so numerous and amazingly exact in insects, whilst so rare and vague in the higher animals? The only answer that I can suggest is, that insects have perhaps attained a higher degree of specialization, after their type, than most other classes: this seems to be shown by the perfection of their adaptive structures and instincts. </quote> In <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_6017.xml" resp="#mjhawkins"><hi rend="italic">Origin</hi> 4th ed.</ref>, p. 506, following his discussion of Bates’s work on mimicry, CD suggested that the ‘much greater frequency of mockery with insects than with other animals’ was ‘probably the consequence of their small size’, and continued: <quote type="quote"> insects cannot defend themselves, excepting indeed the kinds that sting, and I have never heard of an instance of these mocking other insects, though they are mocked: insects cannot escape by flight from the larger animals; hence they are reduced, like most weak creatures, to trickery and dissimulation. </quote></note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f10">Bates’s paper was entitled: ‘Contributions to an insect fauna of the Amazon Valley. <hi rend="italic">Lepidoptera</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Heliconidæ</hi>.’ See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3812.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter to J. D. Hooker, 18 [November 1862]</ref> and n. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f11">Bates and <ref target="../nameregs/nameregs_4935.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Alfred Russel Wallace</ref> were close friends, and had travelled together to South America in 1848 (see, for example, <ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_8126.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Wallace 1905</ref>). In his paper, Bates cited an instance of bird mimicry communicated to him by Wallace (<ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_446.xml" resp="#automat" cert="low">Bates 1862a</ref>, p. 507 n.).</note>
            <note xml:id="foot.f12"><ref target="../bibliographies/bibl_447.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">Bates 1863</ref>. See also <ref target="./DCP-LETT-3771.xml" resp="#mjhawkins">letter from H. W. Bates, 17 October 1862</ref>.</note>
        </div>        
            
    </body>
    </text>
</TEI>